<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the quality of further education and skills training"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64041</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-specific-learner-groups"/>
    <title>24+ advanced learning loans: specific learner groups</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Research on a proposal for learners aged 24 and above, studying at level 3 and above, to pay higher contributions towards costs.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports research findings on the government’s proposal for adults aged 24 and above, who study for qualifications at level 3 and above, to make greater contributions to the costs of their learning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government proposes to remove grant funding for these further education learners and courses. This will allow the government to focus investment on younger and lower-qualified learners who are less likely to invest in themselves. Instead, the government will provide income-contingent loans to cover the resulting upfront costs, in line with its principles of promoting fairness and personal responsibility. These 24+ Advanced Learning Loans will be made available to new learners from the 2013/14 academic year, with the first full year expected to be the 2014/15 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS carried out an impact assessment to show the economic costs and benefits of this proposal, and an equality impact assessment to look at how the proposal will affect different types of learners. This report explores these assessments, and looks at how learners are likely to respond to the 24+ Advanced Learning Loans proposal, and how its impact on their decisions and behaviours could be minimised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research provides a greater understanding of four specific learner groups: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;those aged 40+, and particularly those out of work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those with mental or physical disabilities or learning difficulties have particular needs regarding communication and information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those seeking to take up Advanced/Higher Apprentices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Muslim learners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This research indicated that most learner groups are unlikely to be put off by the loans proposition, provided it is communicated effectively. It also highlighted groups which are likely to face specific issues and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS research report no.100.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60884</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-graduate-apprenticeships-for-the-professions-introduced"/>
    <title>Press Release: Graduate apprenticeships for the professions introduced</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graduate and post-graduate level apprenticeships will soon be available in subjects including law, accountancy and advanced engineering, Skills Minister Matthew Hancock announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next year, changes to the Specification of Apprentices Standards for England (SASE) will mean that level six and seven apprenticeships – equivalent to bachelors and masters degree level – are available for the first time, making vocational learning an attractive alternative to the traditional higher education route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are already a number of these top-level schemes in development, including in accountancy, law and human resources. BPP Law School is looking to develop a Legal Apprenticeship pathway which could be an alternative route to the legal profession and qualification as a solicitor. It is in discussion with the relevant regulatory body and sector skills council, Skills for Justice, to progress its proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister Matthew Hancock said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past, apprenticeships were restricted to only some trades, and some parts of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now we are introducing apprenticeships in all types of jobs, including a new route to the professions, to ensure everyone can reach their potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These new apprenticeships will help more young people to receive on-the-job training at top companies like BPP Law School, ensuring a vocational route to success in accounting, insurance, and the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director of BPP Professional Apprenticeships James Hammill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to improving social mobility and diversity in the work place by opening up some of the most prestigious professions and employers to school leavers as an alternative to the traditional route. Apprenticeships are an excellent way for employers to recruit talent early and design a structured training programme that incorporates technical learning as well as invaluable work based skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BPP Law School is based in eight UK cities: Birmingham, Bristol, Cambridge, Leeds, Liverpool, London, Manchester and Swindon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60891</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T11:17:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-regulatory-impact-assessment-annex-2-table"/>
    <title>24+ Advanced Learning Loans: regulatory impact assessment - Annex 2 table </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Further information on Advanced Learning Loans</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information on 24+ Advanced Learning Loans: regulatory impact assessment. Contains Annex 2 table.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60892</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:31:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-regulatory-impact-assessment-underlying-data"/>
    <title>24+ Advanced Learning Loans: regulatory impact assessment - underlying data </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>More information about 24+ Advanced Learning Loans. Includes underlying data.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information about 24+ Advanced Learning Loans. Includes regulatory impact assessment and underlying data &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60893</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:31:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-equality-impact-assessment-underlying-data"/>
    <title>24+ Advanced Learning Loans – equality impact assessment – underlying data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Contains information about 24+ Advanced Learning Loans, including underlying data.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More information about 24+ Advanced Learning Loans. Includes information on equality impact assessment and underlying data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60195</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluation-of-the-deepened-co-location-trials"/>
    <title>Evaluation of the deepened co-location trials</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 jobcentres that took part in joint location trials with Next Steps.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 98. Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 Jobcentres that took part in the joint location trials with Next Step (now known as the National Careers Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It highlights key issues arising from the research with a view to contributing to the success of the wider roll out of joint location in Jobcentres in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56468</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:47:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-monthly-briefing-edition-7-november-december-2012"/>
    <title>24+ advanced learning loans. Monthly briefing: edition 7 - November/December 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Monthly update to help colleges and training organisations prepare for the introduction of student loans. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monthly update to help colleges and training organisations prepare for the introduction of student loans. Produced jointly with the Skills Funding Agency, the Student Loans Company and HM Revenue and Customs. Explains how the loans work and the policy behind them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55331</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:21:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boosting-skills-and-jobs-on-the-south-coast"/>
    <title>Boosting skills and jobs on the south coast</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Following the Autumn Statement, Vince Cable visited Southampton to launch two schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable was in Southampton to launch two key schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment, following on from new investment launched in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;Chancellor’s Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He visited Eastleigh College to announce a new £550 million Further Education Capital Investment Fund to help improve college facilities across the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That investment  will be targeted towards colleges in the greatest need of help to improve facilities, improve efficiency and save money in the long term. Colleges will be able to apply for funding through the Skills Funding Agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extra £310 million for the Regional Growth Fund to create and safeguard jobs was also announced in the Autumn Statement.  To date, £2.4 billion has been conditionally offered to businesses and intermediaries up and down the country – creating jobs and boosting the local economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south coast has benefited from a number of different Regional Growth Fund projects and programmes. The Solent LEP has been awarded £2m from the Regional Growth Fund to roll out the second phase of the successful Bridging the Gap Funding programme to Southampton and the Isle of Wight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other beneficiaries of Regional Growth Fund awards for the area include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southampton City Council has been awarded a further £5.3 million Regional Growth Fund in support of the ‘Platform for Prosperity’ project bringing the total to £10.9 million. The project entails the improvement and upgrade of the road infrastructure outside Eastern Docks and is expected to create or safeguard over 800 jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cobra Precision Engineering and Elite Care Homes are two of the first recipients of £100,000 of phase one of the Solent LEPs Bridging the Gap award. The grant will leverage close to £600,000 additional private investment and create and safeguard 12 jobs at the two firms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Solent Future’s project is a £13m Regional Growth Fund money investment from Round 3. Part of the funding will be utilised to ensure a sustainable future for the Advanced Manufacturing skills in the Solent workforce. This will bring together leading businesses, colleges and Universities at a world-class training centre on the Solent Enterprise Zone. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Portsmouth Naval Base Property Trust in Portsmouth secured £1.23 million of Regional Growth Fund to support two projects within the Historic Dockyard at Portsmouth. 
£750,000 will be used to develop the Cell Block Enterprise project which will support enterprise skills development and provide access to early stage funding with mentoring managed by the University of Portsmouth. The project aims to create over 440 jobs in the supply chain. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£475,000 will contribute to the development of the International Boatbuilding Training College (IBTC) which combines heritage conservation with apprenticeships and other training to develop transferrable skills. The project has also had initial support from the Heritage Lottery Fund which could result in a final grant of £3.9 million grant to help support the development of heritage skills for the future. Both projects will have a ten year economic life cycle. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;LINKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Dec/autumn-statement-2012"&gt;BIS: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Vince-Cable-launches-schemes-for-skills-and-jobs-on-South-Coast-68482.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Vince Cable launches schemes for skills and jobs on South Coast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-550m-capital-investment-programme-will-transform-FE-colleges-68485.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New £550m capital investment programme will transform FE colleges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56073</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T10:47:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-funding-statement-2012-2015"/>
    <title>Skills funding statement 2012 - 2015</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Confirms the budget available for the 2013-14 financial year for the further education (FE) sector. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Confirms the budget available for the 2013-14 financial year for the further education (FE) sector. Includes information for the Skills Funding Agency to set provider allocations for the 2013/14 academic year. The government is focusing investment on high quality provision that delivers good value for money, and its focus will remain on young adults, the low skilled and those who are unemployed. See also and the FE colleges capital investment strategy (URN 12/1340).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56315</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T14:59:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluation-of-the-impact-of-capital-expenditure-in-further-education-fe-colleges"/>
    <title>Evaluation of the impact of capital expenditure in further education (FE) colleges</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report commissioned by BIS evaluate the impact of capital spending on key policy goals.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no.99. Report commissioned by BIS evaluate the impact of capital spending on key policy goals. Combines quantitative and qualitative research and builds on a previous study undertaken in 2008. Focuses on completed capital spending projects by FE colleges within England (total per college) between April 2001 and September 2011. Underlying data for tables and figure in this publication is available in a machine processable format: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/dataset/impact-of-capital-expenditure-in-further-education-colleges-evaluation"&gt;underlying data on the impact of capital expenditure in FE colleges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
