<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/preventing-conflict-in-fragile-states--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-conflict-in-fragile-states--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-conflict-in-fragile-states--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Preventing conflict in fragile states"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55967</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-to-contribute-funds-to-courts-in-sierra-leone-and-cambodia--2"/>
    <title>UK to contribute funds to Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on UK contributions to the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in a written ministerial statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce that in order to strengthen international justice and help secure accountability for some of the most horrific crimes against humanity in the last 50 years, the UK will make a voluntary contribution of £1,000,000 to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and a voluntary contribution of £600,000 to the international component of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s contribution will help ensure the Special Court for Sierra Leone is able to complete its work, and leave a lasting legacy for the people of Sierra Leone. On 30 May, the Court sentenced Charles Taylor, a former President of Liberia, to 50 years in jail for aiding and abetting war crimes. Taylor is the first former Head of State to be convicted by an international tribunal and the Court is currently hearing his appeal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia is delivering long awaited justice for millions of Cambodians through the trials of the most senior and responsible surviving members of the Pol Pot regime. The scale of the crimes committed and the number of victims makes it one of the most significant tribunals of its kind since Nuremberg. The Government’s contribution will help to prevent the collapse of the Court which has faced a significant shortfall in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International justice is central to foreign policy. It is essential for securing the rights of individuals and states, and for securing peace and reconciliation. Through the International Criminal Court, and the separate international tribunals, we are working to make clear that those responsible for the worst crimes will be held to account and that political leaders will not enjoy impunity. Our support to these institutions is an important element in our strategy to reduce conflict, promote stability and strengthen the rules based international system. In order to give Parliament a full accounting of this work we will, from this point forward, also provide an annual statement at the start of the financial year detailing our progress on this important issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55324</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:59:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office"/>
    <title>North Korean Ambassador summoned to Foreign and Commonwealth Office </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Under Secretary, Simon Fraser, today summoned the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea Ambassador in London, Mr Hyon Hak Bong, to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Fraser made clear to the Ambassador the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions. He stressed that the international community was united in their assessment that this launch, using ballistic missile technology, was a breach of UN Security Council Resolution 1874 and that it threatened regional stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He urged the DPRK to avoid further provocative action and take urgent steps to re-engage constructively with the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally he pointed out that instead of expecting international aid and assistance the DPRK could have spent the money used on this launch to bring food and modernisation to its people.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50193</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T09:23:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T09:23:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I strongly condemn the DPRK’s satellite launch today. This launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 as it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. This provocative act will increase tensions in the region. I deplore the fact that the DPRK has chosen to prioritise this launch over improving the livelihood of its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be summoning the DPRK Ambassador to the UK to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the UK will urgently consult partners in the United Nations Security Council on our response to this development. It is essential that the DPRK refrain from further provocative action and take constructive steps towards denuclearisation and lasting peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50188</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:58:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali"/>
    <title>UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister made his comments following the arrest late on 10 December of Malian Prime Minister Diarra in Bamako by armed men on behalf of the military junta and the subsequent forced resignation of the Prime Minister and his Cabinet earlier today. Mr Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the latest events in Bamako, and particularly by the intervention of the Malian military junta which has forced the resignation today of Prime Minister Diarra and his Cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali. The rapid appointment of a new government of national unity to take forward the political roadmap towards democratic elections and the reunification of Mali is critical to further progress. These events underline the need for coordinated international action, particularly with the United Nations, the African Union and ECOWAS, to achieve stability in Mali.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18382</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:40:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-mongolia-round-table-discussions-held-in-london"/>
    <title>UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions held in London</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 28 November, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire hosted Damba Gankhuyag, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Mongolia for the tenth UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks focused on commercial relations, foreign policy issues and defence cooperation, with the UK and Mongolia ultimately signing a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to increase defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU is aimed at supporting Mongolian defence reform, in light of its peacekeeping activities in UN operations and its recently joining the OSCE. Through modernising equipment, Mongolia hopes to become even more efficient in supporting international operations in less stable regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global partner, Mongolia is becoming ever closer to the UK, with increasing trade and cultural links. The Minister discussed how best to share the UK’s experience of cultivating and managing investment in both directions to improve bilateral trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks saw the UK and Mongolia strengthen their relationship, on the eve of celebrating the fiftieth Anniversary of diplomatic relations next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI hosted a business session in the afternoon, which was attended by a large number of business representatives discussing Mongolia’s extractive industries, mutually beneficial opportunities and Stock Exchange collaboration. The talks were concluded by a session on education cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the tenth UK-Mongolia Round Table. Held every two years, the talks form a key part of the UK – Mongolia relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35625</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-un-international-day-for-the-elimination-of-violence-against-women"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary marks UN International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Preventing and addressing sexual violence is essential to resolving conflicts and building sustainable peace. In our lifetimes millions of women, children and men have endured this horror.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must shatter the culture of impunity for those who use rape and sexual violence as a weapon of war and shift the balance of shame away from survivors to the perpetrators of this crime. This is a cause whose time has come, and it will be a major theme of the UK’s Presidency of the G8 next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By standing shoulder to shoulder with civil society, communities and international organisations I truly believe that we can confront and one day even end the use of sexual violence as a weapon of war.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35607</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-travelling-to-uganda-rwanda-and-the-democratic-republic-of-congo"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister travelling to Uganda, Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, is travelling to Uganda today. This is the first leg of an unscheduled three stop trip to the region, which will include visits to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit will serve to support international efforts to bring an end to the crisis currently engulfing Goma. During his trip, Minister Simmonds will be meeting with regional leaders to discuss the situation, including political efforts underway to resolve the crisis, and the humanitarian situation. He will be pressing key actors to use any influence they have to bring an end to the crisis and limit its impact on civilian populations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am travelling to the region at short notice to show that the UK is focused on the serious and urgent crisis unfolding in Goma and to show my support to the people of the DRC. I am deeply concerned by the current crisis and I urge the M23 to stop their offensive and for all external support to the M23 to cease.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On my visit I will be meeting with my counterparts from across the region and will call on all to find, first and foremost, a resolution that will swiftly end the immediate fighting and produce a sustainable long term plan that will ensure peace and stability for the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35584</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wilton-park-conference-on-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations"/>
    <title>Wilton Park conference on preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the Foreign Secretary will attend and deliver the keynote speech on the final afternoon of a Wilton Park Conference on “Preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his announcement in May that Britain would set up a specialist team of experts that could be deployed to conflict areas to support UN missions and local civil society to investigate allegations of sexual violence, gather evidence and help build the capabilities of other nations, the Foreign Secretary will today announce that the specialist team now consists of 70 people and is ready to deploy overseas in the near future.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those recruited for the team include police, lawyers, psychologists, doctors, forensic experts, gender-based violence experts and experts in the care and protection of survivors and witnesses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will also announce additional funding of more than £¼ million over a three year period to the UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations and the Department of Field Support to develop policies, guidance and training for use by UN peacekeepers as first responders to incidents of sexual violence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the conference, the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that a critical mass of public opinion has now begun to build up against the use of rape as a weapon of war in many countries. My experience as a politician leads me to believe that this is the moment to mobilise global public opinion and to rally the efforts of nations, in the same way that we have mustered the will to ban the use of landmines and cluster munitions, and are on the verge of securing an international Arms Trade Treaty. Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation. It is a cause whose time has come.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants at today’s conference are drawn from over 25 countries and include ministers and senior practitioners and experts.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference which includes sessions on the international normative framework; addressing impunity; early warning indicators; strengthening justice mechanisms; and communications, was also attended by the following:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mrs Zainab Bangura, UN Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margot Wallstrom, the former Special Representative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Madeleine Rees, Secretary-General of the Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serge Brammertz, a prosecutor from the ICTY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be working with Foreign Secretary Hague again on the United Kingdom’s initiative on Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict. In many conflicts, sexual violence is used as a tactic of war, intended to hurt not only a single individual, but their family, their community, their ethnic group. Today this  has almost become a rule rather than an exception, and we all must work together to combat the impunity and ensure justice for the victims.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/35444</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/confronting-rape-as-a-weapon-of-war-a-challenge-for-our-generation"/>
    <title>Confronting rape as a weapon of war: a challenge for our generation</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each generation faces its own challenges, and each can shape our world for the better.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our generation has the opportunity, and the responsibility, to confront the use of rape and sexual violence as a weapon of war.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our lifetimes millions of women, children and men have endured this horror, including in Rwanda, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Colombia, Uganda, Liberia and in Bosnia, where only twenty years ago, on European soil, rape camps were set up and tens of thousands of women subjected to sexual slavery and enforced pregnancy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that preventing and addressing sexual violence is vital to resolving conflicts and building sustainable peace. I see it as a vast international issue that national foreign policies have not yet adequately addressed. And I am convinced that we can actually do something more about it. That is why I am championing it as Foreign Secretary.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my Party was still in Opposition I met survivors of rape in refugee camps in Darfur and in Srebrenica. Last month I returned to Bosnia and spent time with female and male survivors in Sarajevo, and I recently shared a platform with people working with survivors of rape and torture in the DRC.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences brought home to me the sheer extent and intensity of the problem, the overwhelming lack of justice for survivors of wartime rape and sexual violence despite a huge amount of excellent work by grassroots organisations and NGOs, and the direct link that this has with peace and security today. Where there is no justice or dignity for survivors development is held back, and the seeds of future conflict are sown.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this subject with a good deal of humility, as a man, and as someone who has not experienced conflict first hand or worked with survivors. But I have been appalled by the toll sexual violence in conflict has on children. To take just one example, of the thousands of reported rapes in the DRC in one recent period, up to 50% of all survivors were under the age of 17, and 10% were under the age of 10.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been struck by the terrible life sentence of trauma, stigma and illness that follows in the wake of rape in war, and its impact on families and communities. This was illustrated to me by the fact that 67% of survivors in Rwanda were subsequently found to be HIV positive.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have been deeply affected by the knowledge that many victims never get the recognition or support they are entitled to, eking out a precarious existence in conflict zones with their abusers often still at large in their communities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a tendency in the past to regard sexual violence as an inevitable by-product of conflict, something that happens in the ‘fog of war’ when law and order breaks down.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, we have treated sexual violence either as an issue of marginal importance in peace agreements which often tend to exclude women, or to see it as a global problem that is too immense for us to do anything about it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has to change. We now know that rape and sexual violence is used as a deliberate weapon of war in the same way that guns and tanks are, to terrorise civilian populations, to humiliate, scar and destroy whole ethnic groups or religious or political opponents, cheaply, silently and devastatingly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simply accept that this is part of the cycle of war is to consign hundreds of thousands of innocent people to an appalling fate in the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am convinced from my own experiences as Foreign Secretary over the last two and a half years that our failure to confront this issue does play a part in emboldening those who are orchestrating atrocities today, including in Syria. Our efforts to prevent rape in war have to be as determined as our efforts to prevent conflict in the first place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just some of the reasons why this issue matters to me and has a direct bearing on foreign policy. But there are also two factors which explain why I think the conditions are right for a major new international initiative, and why I am personally optimistic about our chances.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that we have developed an impressive array of mechanisms at the UN and national level over the last decade, including UN Security Council Resolutions 1325, 1820, 1888 and 1960, the office of the UN Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict, the various UN teams of experts, new mechanisms to train peacekeepers, and National Action Plans on Women Peace and Security, which include protections for violence against women and girls. Our understanding of these issues has been transformed over the last decade and we have a far wider range of capabilities to bring to bear against this problem. In the United Kingdom we are determined to champion women’s rights in all the UN bodies, and to be vigilant and outspoken against any attempt to undermine the gains that have now been secured.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And second, I believe that a critical mass of public opinion has now begun to build up in many countries against the use of sexual violence in conflict. My experience as a politician leads me to believe that this is the moment to mobilise global public opinion and to rally the efforts of nations, in the same way that we have mustered the will to ban the use of landmines and cluster munitions, and are on the verge of securing an international Arms Trade Treaty. Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation. It is a cause whose time has come.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is overwhelmingly due to years of work by the UN and its agencies, by NGOs, the International Criminal Court and other international tribunals and brave survivors who have felt able to share their stories with a shocked world. I am also conscious that many other countries have shown leadership in this area, including many that have emerged from conflict themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also benefited greatly from the insights of filmmakers, who have shone a light on painful events and helped us to understand our responsibilities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such Director is Jasmila Zbani?, who allowed us to screen her film ‘Emma’s Story’ during this conference.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another is Angelina Jolie.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you will be familiar with her work as Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was my encounter earlier this year with her film In the Land of Blood and Honey that actually galvanised me into starting this new British initiative, and led to her joining me at our event in the Foreign Office in May when I announced it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very grateful to Angelina Jolie for her support for our efforts to combat the terrible suffering she depicted so powerfully in her film, and for joining us again today.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She assures me she is here to meet you and to listen to our discussion, but I also think she may also be checking up on whether we have lived up to our promises.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we are making some strong and encouraging progress with your help. And our ambition and resolve is even greater than when we first began this initiative, because of the overwhelmingly positive reception it has received around the world.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are focussing our efforts on accountability and justice, and on increasing the number of prosecutions for these crimes. This is the area where there is the most glaring lack of political will, where I believe governments like our own can make the most difference, and where we must act if we are to erode the culture of impunity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May I announced that Britain would set up a specialist team of experts that can be deployed to conflict areas to support UN missions and local civil society to investigate allegations of sexual violence, to gather evidence and to help build up the capabilities of other nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, six months later we have recruited 70 people for this team already, which includes police, lawyers, psychologists, doctors, forensic experts, gender-based violence experts and experts in the care and protection of survivors and witnesses. I will shortly be able to announce its first deployment which will begin before the end of this year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each deployment will be tailored to meet local needs and circumstances. The deployments will be based on in-depth assessments of national and international responses in that country to date and how the British team could reinforce or complement existing efforts, as well as consultations with the authorities in each country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also pledged six months ago that we would use our Presidency of the G8 in 2013 to secure new commitments from some of the world’s most powerful nations. Be in no doubt, we really mean business about this. By the time our Presidency actually starts in January, we will already have spent seven months building support for our objectives before we begin negotiations in earnest. My colleagues around the world know already that it will be one of my top priorities for the meeting of G8 Foreign Ministers in April.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have proposed new G8 partnerships with conflict-affected countries, and a new International Protocol on the investigation and documentation of sexual violence in conflict. I welcome the fact that Mr Brammertz flagged up this issue yesterday, when he said that we need a standardised set of guidelines for effective prosecutions. This would be a practical response to the need to improve the evidence base for prosecutions for sexual violence in conflict at the national and international level, and it would draw on existing advice and guidelines. We want any new Protocol to be of genuine value to national authorities in their efforts to seek prosecutions. If adopted, it could be used in training and capacity building programmes, ensuring an enduring legacy which we would hope to expand beyond the G8 over time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all these areas our Government is not looking to reinvent the wheel - but we are saying that we are prepared to put Britain’s shoulder to it as never before.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not want to duplicate or cut across the work that has been done by experts - but we do want to set an example to the world of what governments can do.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are one of the few countries in the world that can lead such an effort. We have a network of 260 diplomatic posts around the globe, one of the most extensive of any nation. We have one of the largest programmes of international development aid in the world. We are members of the United Nations Security Council, NATO, the EU and the Commonwealth as well as our G8 role, all of which gives us the ability - as well as the responsibility - to take this cause to many of the most influential multilateral bodies in the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have set up an excellent new team of Foreign Office officials led by Emma Hopkins to oversee all our efforts. She and her colleagues have already visited Japan, France, Germany, the US, Canada, China, South Korea and international human rights organisations in Geneva, The Hague and the European Union, to discuss our proposals and mobilise support for our G8 campaign. I think their work will become a model for how other Foreign Ministries can increase their capabilities in this area, particularly in the way it draws on wide expertise from DfID and the Home Office as well as the Foreign and Commonwealth Office itself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sign of our determination to reinforce and not duplicate existing efforts, we are working closely with the UN Team of Exports on Rule of Law and Sexual Violence that supports the office of the UN Secretary-General’s Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict, Mrs Zainab Bangura.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July I announced that we have donated £1 million over two years to the ICC’s groundbreaking mechanism to help victims rebuild their lives, the Trust Fund for Victims. The projects the Fund supports in Uganda, DRC and elsewhere are based on the understanding that it is impossible fully to undo the damage caused by war crimes, including sexual violence. However it is possible to help empower survivors to rebuild their families and regain their place as contributing members of their society.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In New York in September I announced an increase in British support for the UN Special Representative’s work, with £1 million of funding over the next three years. I welcome the greater emphasis that she is placing on national ownership, leadership and responsibility. And I think we must also promote a more ‘strategic’ use of international effort to support UN work to combat impunity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am announcing today that we will contribute £375,000 over a three year period to the UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations and the Department of Field Support to develop policies, guidance and training for use by peacekeepers as first responders to incidents of sexual violence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are urging other countries to match our voluntary contributions in each of these areas. We will do all of these things and more, but of course we look to you to give us your help, advice, constructive criticism and support.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are among the world’s leading experts in the field of combating wartime rape and sexual violence, with deep knowledge and personal experience. I am extremely grateful to you all for travelling a long way to be here and for sharing your expertise with us, and I want to pay particular tribute to Special Representative Bangura and her predecessor Margot Wallstrom.&lt;br&gt;
We need your help to ensure that we have set the right level of ambition for the G8, to ensure that we are aiming high enough and that our proposals are drawn up to have the maximum possible impact.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already drawn five important conclusions from your discussions over the last two days.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, justice has got to be viewed in its fullest sense. It means many things to survivors, ranging from access to justice and effective remedy at the local and national level, reparation, medical care and support to rebuild lives, and it can also involve restorative justice and truth commissions as well as prosecutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we must conceptualise sexual violence in its broadest sense, in terms of women’s rights, education and participation. It is part of a much broader effort to address violence against women and girls and to empower women across society.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we need better coordination of current efforts, across the silos that can set in between our humanitarian, security and developmental efforts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, we have to build up national ownership by matching international efforts much more closely to national requirements and building up national capacity. In my mind this must include how we work to bridge the gap between international efforts and the grass roots organisations which work on the ground, understand the grain of the society, and have the trust of local people.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we need to shift the balance of shame away from survivors to the perpetrators of this crime. We need to break down the stigma by talking about it, which is something I am attempting to do as Foreign Secretary in my conversations around the world. And we have to recognise that unless we shift attitudes amongst men that rape is not a family matter, it is a violent crime, then the problem will persist.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am extremely grateful to you for taking part in this conference, and I will study your detailed recommendations. It is my sincere hope that you will continue to work with us over the coming year, giving us guidance and honest advice when you think we can do more. And I particularly hope you will feel able to work us with to build public momentum around our G8 campaign in 2013 and beyond, so that each country can feel the campaign in their own parliaments and media.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this will be our approach: increasing our own capabilities in the British Foreign Office, significantly increasing our support to UN efforts, raising the profile of the need to confront sexual violence in conflict in every way we can, and proposing new action that we hope will be adopted by many nations  in a new collective effort for our generation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been inspiring to meet many people around the world who share our sense of hope and ambition. On the rare occasion that I am met with a sceptical smile, I remind people of the 18th century slave trade. Although slavery is still with us in modern variants, our predecessors exploded the belief that slavery was in the natural order of things, and a problem too complex to be tackled. And I also remind people that even if our action only succeeds in making a difference at the margins of this vast problem, it could mean that thousands of vulnerable people are spared this appalling violation.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survivors I have met have made a great impression on me by their courage to speak about their experiences and to live, raise families and hold their heads high. By standing shoulder to shoulder with civil society, communities and international organisations I believe we can match the courage of these survivors with a new international resolve to confront and one day even end the use of sexual violence as a weapon of war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
