<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/leading-international-efforts-to-resolve-concerns-about-irans-nuclear-programme/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/leading-international-efforts-to-resolve-concerns-about-irans-nuclear-programme/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/leading-international-efforts-to-resolve-concerns-about-irans-nuclear-programme/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Leading international efforts to resolve concerns about Iran's nuclear programme"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27951</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-iaea-board-resolution-sends-clear-message-to-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister: "IAEA board resolution sends clear message to Iran"</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The resolution was sponsored by the five permanent members of the UN Security Council, plus Germany, (P5+1) and received overwhelming backing from the countries on the IAEA Board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the resolution Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the International Atomic Energy Agency’s Board of Governors’ Resolution adopted yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The IAEA’s latest report confirmed that Iran is expanding its uranium enrichment capacity in direct contravention of IAEA Board and Security Council resolutions, and that it is failing to cooperate with the Agency to address the possible military dimensions of its nuclear programme. These facts provide no assurance of Iran’s stated peaceful intentions. The overwhelming support for the IAEA Board’s Resolution yesterday sends a clear message to Iran about the international community’s determination that Iran must now urgently address the serious concerns about its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We seek a negotiated solution with Iran. The P5+1 continues to pursue negotiations with Iran in good faith. The onus is on Iran to take concrete steps to co-operate fully with the Agency and comply with all its international obligations.  Until it does, the international pressure on Iran will only increase.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46788</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-sanctions-on-iran-come-into-force"/>
    <title>EU sanctions on Iran come into force</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The toughest ever EU sanctions against Iran come into force today, drastically reducing the Iranian Government’s market for oil exports and constraining its ability to fund illegal proliferation activities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the latest diplomatic effort by the international community to intensify the pressure on the Iranian Government to negotiate seriously about its nuclear programme. The US introduced similar tough sanctions on Iran on 28 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent talks between Iran and negotiating powers in Moscow making little progress, the 27 member states of the EU last week agreed unanimously to bring in the oil ban without further delay.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restrictive sanctions are targeted at Iran’s nuclear programme, the people who run it and the money that funds it. Everyday goods such as food and medicines are excluded from sanctions to make sure that measures don’t target the Iranian people.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sanctions include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• an oil ban of Iranian crude oil starting on 1 July;&lt;br&gt;
• a ban on the provision of financial services related to the sale, purchase and transport of Iranian oil, including Protection and Indemnity insurance (P&amp;amp;I);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU has traditionally been a major importer of Iranian oil. In 2011, the EU accounted for approximately 23 per cent of Iran’s oil exports, or at least 585,000 barrels per day (source: IEA data). The phased introduction of the ban has given Member States adequate time to prepare, and for alternative oil suppliers to act to keep the market supplied. The embargo was agreed in January and the EU adopted the legal framework for it (EU Regulation 267/2012) in March. Member States are now ready to stop buying Iranian oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EU partners have been working closely with consumer and producer countries around the world to ensure that there is no shortage of oil to global markets and that other Iranian oil importers do not undermine the impact of the embargo. With the US, we are encouraging other non-EU countries who haven’t already done so to reduce or stop oil imports from Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The embargo and US National Defence Authorisation Act (NDAA) sanctions have caused Iranian oil exports to drop by around 1 million barrels per day, which in real terms means almost $8 billion in lost revenues every quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today unprecedented oil sanctions on Iran have come into force. These are the toughest measures the EU has adopted against Iran to date. They signal our clear determination to intensify the peaceful diplomatic pressure on the Iranian government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are seeking a diplomatic, negotiated settlement with Iran. We call on Iran to take concrete action to address international concerns about its nuclear programme. It is in the power of the Iranian leadership to end Iran’s current isolation, but unless they change course the pressure will only increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over the course of the next few weeks Iran faces a choice: it can continue to obfuscate and avoid the critical issues, incurring tough sanctions and increasing international isolation. Or it can begin to cooperate seriously by discussing the steps it is prepared to take on its nuclear programme, and seizing the opportunity to secure a more prosperous and peaceful future for the Iranian people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We urge the Iranian government to reflect seriously on its position and return to the negotiating table ready and willing to make diplomacy work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanctions against Iran are already having a significant impact on the Iranian economy.  The free market exchange rate has weakened and - though publicly the authorities remain in denial - inflation is widely reported to have picked up very sharply in recent months. Sanctions are also impacting the Government’s ability to move money and material in pursuit of proliferation sensitive activities. Iran is having difficulty finding buyers for its oil - with media reports that up to 14 Iranian oil tankers, capable of carrying 2 million barrels, are sitting stationary in the Persian Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the EU embargo, 10 other countries have reduced their imports of Iranian oil. Recent figures suggest that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• By 1 July, Iran’s oil exports are set to have reduced by up to 1 million barrels per day (40 per cent) from average 2011 levels (source: IEA June report);&lt;br&gt;
• China, India, Japan, South Korea, South Africa, Turkey, Taiwan, Sri Lanka, Singapore and Malaysia have already reduced Iranian oil imports significantly;&lt;br&gt;
• South Korea, a major importer who last year imported 87 million barrels of Iranian oil (source: IEA data), has said it will stop importing Iranian oil from 1 July;&lt;br&gt;
• China imported 556,000 bpd in 2011 (source: IEA data).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46787</id>
    <published>2012-06-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-eus-toughest-ever-sanctions-against-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes EU's 'toughest ever' sanctions against Iran</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the move, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today the EU has agreed that the oil ban against Iran will come into force as planned on the 1 July. This is an important step and one for which the UK Government has argued strongly. Alongside new US sanctions, which also come into force this week, these restrictive measures are the toughest ever adopted against the Iranian Government. They reflect the international community’s resolve, and our determination, to intensify the peaceful pressure on Iran until it starts to build confidence that its nuclear programme is purely peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Recent talks between the E3+3 and Iran on its nuclear programme were frank but difficult, with little progress made. Despite the negotiating powers’ best efforts in Baghdad and Moscow, the Iranian Government has so far failed to agree any concrete steps to address the international community’s serious concerns. It is not too late for Iran to give a more promising response to the offer of the E3+3, but they have not yet done so. The UK Government will argue for intensified sanctions over the coming months if there is no progress made in these negotiations.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46826</id>
    <published>2012-06-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-statement-on-conclusion-of-e3-3-talks"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary statement on conclusion of E3+3 talks</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the E3+3 talks concluded, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 approached the talks in Moscow ready to make progress. Our position was consistent, clear and reasonable. There was a detailed and frank exchange on our respective proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There remain significant differences on substance. We regret that Iran was not prepared to negotiate seriously on specific concerns of the international community - in particular regarding 20% enrichment. This is a missed opportunity to address the serious concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been unable to set another round of talks at this stage. However nuclear experts from both sides will meet to offer further clarity on technical issues, following which we will consider whether there is sufficient basis for further political talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 is united in reiterating that the onus is on Iran, which stands in contravention of six UNSCRs, to take concrete steps to reassure the international community about its intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran should not doubt our commitment to a peaceful, negotiated solution. But it should understand clearly that in order to achieve this it must be willing to take urgent, concrete steps to reassure the international community to which we will respond. Our door remains open for serious engagement and negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“EU oil sanctions will come into force on 1 July and until Iran chooses a different path we will work with partners across the world to intensify the pressure further”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46825</id>
    <published>2012-05-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-calls-on-iran-to-take-urgent-concrete-steps"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary calls on Iran to take “urgent, concrete steps”</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Talks between Iran and world powers in Baghdad have concluded today with limited progress. While there was serious discussion on the substance of Iran’s nuclear programme, including the key concerns around 20% enrichment, significant differences remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 went united and ready to take concrete steps to build confidence. In line with the reciprocal, step by step approach agreed at Istanbul we set out in detail the steps we hoped Iran would take and how we would respond. We are still waiting for Iran to engage fully on these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The clear and unified conclusion of the E3+3 was that urgent, concrete steps need to be taken by Iran to allow progress. If Iran fails to respond in a serious manner, they should be in no doubt that we will intensify the pressure from sanctions, including the embargo on oil imports already agreed, and will urge other nations to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we have confirmed at the conclusion of the talks in Baghdad today, we remain fully committed to the diplomatic process underway and to finding a peaceful, negotiated solution to the nuclear issue. We are making every effort to achieve this. But we must see significant progress from Iran at the next meeting in Moscow.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46824</id>
    <published>2012-05-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-iran-and-mepp-with-israeli-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses Iran and MEPP with Israeli Foreign Minister</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 22 May, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, welcomed Israeli Foreign Minister Avigdor Lieberman at the start of his two-day visit to the UK. The Ministers welcomed the growing strength of the bilateral relationship and efforts to deepen economic and hi-tech co-operation. They also discussed regional issues, including Iran and the Middle East Peace Process - including the importance of strengthening the Palestinian Authority. Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was pleased to welcome Foreign Minister Lieberman to the UK yesterday. We had a positive, wide-ranging meeting. In particular we discussed Iran and our shared determination to prevent Iran developing a nuclear weapon and the importance of Iran engaging meaningfully with the E3+3 in Baghdad to build confidence and help enable a peaceful resolution to the nuclear issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I made clear the UK’s concern about the current stalemate in the Middle East Peace Process, and our view that there is an urgent need for progress. I expressed the UK’s firm view that continued illegal Israeli settlement expansion in East Jerusalem and the West Bank is harming Israel’s international standing and endangering the two state solution. I reiterated our unswerving support for a lasting two state solution to the conflict that achieves a secure Israel alongside a sovereign and viable Palestinian State, based on the borders of 1967, with Jerusalem the future capital of both states, and a fair settlement for refugees, and our readiness to work with Israeli and Palestinian leaders to bring that about”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27518</id>
    <published>2012-04-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-comments-on-e3-3-talks-with-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary comments on E3+3 talks with Iran</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the outcome of the talks, he said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The six negotiating powers approached these talks determined to pursue a serious dialogue with Iran, and committed to finding a peaceful, negotiated solution to the nuclear issue. Today’s talks were a first step towards that objective, but there is still a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We look forward to the next round of talks. We now need agreement on urgent, practical steps to build confidence around the world that Iran will implement its international obligations and does not intend to build a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27515</id>
    <published>2012-04-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-talks-seeking-a-peaceful-and-negotiated-solution"/>
    <title>Iran talks: seeking a peaceful and negotiated solution</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 14 April, the international community meets in Istanbul for a new round of talks with Iran on its nuclear programme. As one of the six negotiating powers, we approach the negotiating table in the spirit of cooperation, ready and willing to make progress on an issue that has significant implications for the entire region. I urge Iran to seize this opportunity and demonstrate they are ready to talk meaningfully about our concerns.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I doubt anyone is unaware of the urgent need for these talks. The international community has serious and long-standing concerns about Iran’s nuclear programme, which the Iranian Government has failed to address for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran has repeatedly failed to comply with its obligations towards the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) and has failed to answer serious questions the IAEA has about possible military dimensions to its programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seriously concerned that Iran appears to be aiming to enrich far more uranium to nearly 20% than they would need for purely civilian purposes.&lt;br&gt;
We also know that Iran has a site near Qom which has tripled their capacity to enrich uranium to near 20%. This site has been built under a mountain and was never intended to be made public. Iranian secrecy around its nuclear programme only serves to deepen our concerns that they are trying to build a nuclear weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set alongside the regime’s support for violent groups in the region and brutal suppression of its own people, we are right to be concerned about how Iran would behave if it had a nuclear weapon and we are right to put pressure on the regime to comply with their international legal obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few months will see the introduction of the toughest sanctions yet on the Iranian regime. The EU and USA have both agreed sanctions affecting the purchase of Iranian oil. As a result, we have already seen countries around the world decreasing their dependence on Iranian oil. This has had a significant impact on the Iranian economy and has shocked the Iranian leadership. The pressure from oil sanctions will only increase over the coming months as more countries reduce their imports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sanctions are about encouraging the Iranian regime to come to the table, not about punishing the Iranian people. The Iranian regime should be in no doubt that we will keep up this pressure until we are confident their nuclear programme is purely peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside increasing the pressure on the regime to negotiate, we are working more widely to help reduce tensions in the region and support a nuclear weapons free region. We are working to promote a successful conference later this year on the creation of a Middle East Weapon of Mass Destruction (WMD) Free Zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our top diplomats meet in Istanbul today, we are serious in our willingness to engage with Iran. But we go into these talks with our eyes open. The story from previous talks has been depressingly familiar - Iranian posturing, delaying tactics, and in the end a failure to negotiate in good faith. If Iran offers nothing but preconditions that ignore six UN Security Council resolutions, the result will be decreased confidence from the international community and another lost opportunity for a diplomatic solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have no hidden agenda on this issue. We are not seeking regime change. What we want is a peaceful and negotiated solution. If Iran cooperates, our offer to provide help in a number of areas, including with the development of civil nuclear power stations, still stands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The onus is on Iran to prove to us it is serious this time. It is a welcome sign that Iran has said it is now willing to discuss the nuclear issue. This is a small shift that we want to test and explore. We hope these talks will be the start of a process of dialogue with a positive outcome. We enter into them in that spirit; the Iranians should too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was originally published in Al Hayat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46785</id>
    <published>2012-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-tough-eu-sanctions-on-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes tough EU sanctions on Iran</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the sanctions, the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today the EU has brought into force unprecedented sanctions against Iran, including an oil ban and freeze of assets held by the Central Bank of Iran. The message is clear. Iran cannot ignore the international community and should be in no doubt that we will ratchet up the pressure until it chooses a different path. I hope that Iran demonstrates it is willing to do so when it resumes talks with the E3+3 next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today the EU also agreed important measures to address the appalling human rights situation in Iran. I welcome the designation of prominent members of the judiciary and government, including some of the architects of repression, and the recognition that the Basij militia has been responsible for grave violations over many years. All those in Iran who continue to perpetrate human rights abuses should recognise that we will not tolerate impunity, nor stand idly by as the Iranian people’s rights are abused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have also further tightened controls to prevent any export of dual-use technical equipment and software that the Iranian regime might use to intercept or monitor communications. The Iranian people should be able to communicate freely instead of being denied their legitimate right to information. I call on Iran once again to meet its human rights obligations to its people.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27402</id>
    <published>2012-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-statement-on-e3-3-talks-with-iran--2"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary statement on E3+3 talks with Iran</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following Baroness Ashton’s announcement that the E3+3 (UK, US, France, Germany, Russia and China) have decided to resume talks with Iran on the nuclear issue, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, US, France, Germany, Russia and China have carefully considered Iran’s latest response to Baroness Ashton. We all agree that the international community should demonstrate its commitment to a diplomatic solution by acknowledging Iran’s agreement to meet, by testing its desire to talk and by offering it the opportunity to respond to our legitimate concerns about its nuclear intentions. It is time for Iran to choose a different path and to show the world that it wants a peaceful, negotiated solution to the nuclear issue.  It is for Iran to seize this opportunity and we urge it to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The onus will be on Iran to convince the international community that its nuclear programme is exclusively peaceful, by taking concrete actions. If it does so then we have always been ready to respond positively by offering assistance with the development of Iran’s civil nuclear power stations, and extending co-operation in other areas from political relations to economic development, as the E3+3 have consistently offered since 2008. Until those actions are taken we will not ease the international pressure on Iran.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
