<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/developing-a-new-high-speed-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/developing-a-new-high-speed-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/developing-a-new-high-speed-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Developing a new high speed rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-28T19:40:02+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15782</id>
    <published>2012-10-28T19:40:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-28T19:40:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/high-speed-rail-investing-in-britains-future-consultation"/>
    <title>High speed rail: investing in Britain's future consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a national high speed rail network offers a once-in-a-generation opportunity to transform the way we travel in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 28 February 2011 the government launched a national consultation, ‘High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future’. The consultation set out the government’s proposed strategy for a national high speed rail network for Britain and the route for an initial line between London and the West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation asked 7 questions, covering the government’s overall strategy, the proposed route for the London to West Midlands line, the environmental appraisal of this line, and options for supporting property owners affected by the proposals. The consultation closed on 29 July 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decisions"&gt;Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;‘High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future’ - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;‘High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future’ - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="decision-background-documents"&gt;Decision background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;: updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;: value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="consultation-responses"&gt;Consultation responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future’ consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="consultation-document"&gt;Consultation document&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/consultation-document"&gt;‘High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future’ consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="consultation-background-documents"&gt;Consultation background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-rail-alternatives-update"&gt;London to West Midlands rail alternatives - update of economic appraisal, 10 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/economic-case"&gt;Economic case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;: The Y network and London West Midlands, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/appraisal-sustainability"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; London to the West Midlands appraisal of sustainability, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/route-engineering-report"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; route engineering report, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/strategic-alternatives"&gt;Strategic alternatives to the proposed Y network, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-proposed-route-maps"&gt;Maps of the proposed route for consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/proposed-high-speed-rail-strategy-for-consultation"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; high speed rail background reports, 20 December 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="equality-impact-assessments"&gt;Equality impact assessments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/equality-impact-screening"&gt;‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future equality impact screening’, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;More about the consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13525</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T09:06:36+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-26T09:06:36+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/high-speed-two-exceptional-hardship-scheme-consultation"/>
    <title>High Speed Two - Exceptional Hardship Scheme Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultation document on a voluntary purchase scheme for property owners whose properties may be affected by any new high speed rail link between London and the West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the consultation on an Exceptional Hardship Scheme, the Secretary of State has confirmed that an Exceptional Hardship Scheme will be introduced, and that it will be open to applications from Friday 20 August. This section includes the written ministerial statement to Parliament, frequently asked questions and an analysis of the responses to the consultation. Further information please see &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/www.dft.gov.uk/pgr/rail/pi/highspeedrail/exceptionalhardshipscheme/analysisofresponses/"&gt;High Speed Two - Proposed Exceptional Hardship Scheme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadline for consultation responses on the Exceptional Hardship Scheme for a proposed high speed line from London to the West Midlands was been extended by four weeks to 17 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Transport has taken this decision in the light of representations arguing that ten weeks is not sufficient to allow all those with an interest to have the fullest possible opportunity to comment on these proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, and without prejudice to the outcome of the consultation, the Department for Transport will ensure that shadow arrangements are put in place so that, should a decision be taken to proceed with the scheme, applications can begin to be considered immediately. By bringing forward the timescale for applications in this way, this should help minimise uncertainty for those affected and ensure any payments can be made as quickly as possible wherever appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone whose application is considered under such shadow arrangements would also have a right of appeal once the formal scheme is up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printed copies (ISBN 9781848640795) of this publication and the High Speed Rail CD-ROM (product code HS2CD) can both be obtained from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/foi/dftps/howtoobtaindftpublications"&gt;Publications.&lt;/a&gt; The CD-ROM contains the command paper and all of the High Speed Two Ltd supporting documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13334</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T18:24:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/costs-of-hs2-spur-to-heathrow"/>
    <title>Costs of HS2 spur to Heathrow</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information response regarding costs of the High Speed 2 spur to Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15938</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:03:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/high-speed-two-property-and-compensation-for-london-west-midlands-video"/>
    <title>High Speed Two: Property and compensation for London - West Midlands video</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lZEuSlc-xzw&amp;amp;list=PL229C4FFECA41C8FD&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;feature=plpp_video"&gt;High Speed Two: Property and compensation for London - West Midlands video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will be a national high-speed rail network linking Birmingham, Manchester and Leeds with London and Heathrow. This video sets out the property and compensation proposals for the first stage of the network between London and the West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will bring transformational benefits to the UK: major investment; new jobs; regeneration in cities; improved connectivity, faster journeys and freeing up capacity on existing rail lines, which are becoming increasingly congested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But such a major project will also have environmental impacts and affect local property markets. The government has already worked hard to minimise the impact of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; on the landscape, protecting the countryside and local communities as far as possible by adding more tunnels and making changes to the proposed route between London and Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current law provides appropriate compensation for the vast majority of infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will be an exceptional construction project - the biggest seen in the UK since Victorian times. Because of the exceptional nature of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; we believe it is right to go above and beyond what is set out in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is being proposed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The six key elements of the government’s proposals to help those affected by &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-1-a-streamlined-advanced-purchase"&gt;Proposal 1: a streamlined advanced purchase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simplifies the compensation process for property owners in &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s safeguarded area; this is land that needs to be protected from any other conflicting developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-2-a-voluntary-purchase-scheme"&gt;Proposal 2: a voluntary purchase scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for rural areas where the line is not in deep bored tunnels. Property owners within 120 metres of either side of the line, but outside the safeguarded area, could ask the government to buy their property for its unblighted market value, that is what it would have been worth if there had been no plans for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-3-a-sale-and-rent-back-scheme"&gt;Proposal 3: a sale and rent-back scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would give greater flexibility for the home owners whose properties need to be demolished. They could sell their properties to the government, but remain living in them as tenants until the properties are required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-4-a-long-term-hardship-scheme"&gt;Proposal 4: a long term hardship scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would provide cover for properties beyond the voluntary purchase zone. It would help those who have a strong personal need to move but, because of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, cannot sell their home other than at a significant loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-5-properties-above-tunnels"&gt;Proposal 5: properties above tunnels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide confidence in properties above tunnels the Government will offer before and after surveys and settlement deeds and guarantee forever the rectification costs of any settlement or subsidence issues caused to properties by tunnelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="proposal-6-social-rented-housing"&gt;Proposal 6: Social rented housing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will work with local authorities, housing associations and affected tenants to develop a strategy to replace any social rented housing lost as a result of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s proposals are designed to ensure that property owners and occupiers receive as much certainty as possible, as early as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government would like your views on these proposals. For more information please visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details are contained in the government’s property and the consultation document are available at this web address [on screen]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copies of the consultation document can also be obtained free of charge by calling 0300 123 1102.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can respond to the consultation in a number of ways - online, with a response form, by post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any further queries you can email &lt;a href="mailto:HS2Enquiries@HS2.org.uk"&gt;HS2Enquiries@&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or call 020 7944 4908.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remember, The consultation closes on 31 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121025a"&gt;Government unveils generous &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; compensation package&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/mcloughlin-20121025a"&gt;High Speed Two - Assistance and compensation for home owners and occupiers on the London - West Midlands Route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15275</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T22:25:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/high-speed-two-assistance-and-compensation-for-home-owners-and-occupiers-on-the-london-west-midlands-route"/>
    <title>High Speed Two - assistance and compensation for home owners and occupiers on the London - West Midlands route</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In January the government announced that we would proceed with plans to build a high speed rail network linking London with Birmingham, Leeds and Manchester. High Speed Two (HS2) will have a transformative effect on Britain, bringing cities closer together and providing the new transport capacity we need to meet the challenges of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to drive forward with this vital national project. In doing so we need to provide support for those facing the disruption that the plans for the railway are causing, while also protecting the interests of tax-payers who will ultimately pay for compensation. We have been clear throughout that we are committed to providing appropriate compensation and assistance for those affected by the building of HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statutory system of compensation already provides fair compensation for the vast majority of infrastructure schemes. However, given the particular circumstances of HS2, in this case I believe it is right to go above and beyond what is required by law. Today I am launching a generous proposed compensation and support package for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals set out today all those living closest to the route of HS2, in the so-called ‘safeguarded area’, will be able to choose to sell their home to the government - whether it is required for construction or not - at any time after the HS2 route is safeguarded, which is currently expected to happen in Spring 2013. Those choosing to sell their homes will receive its full un-blighted value (that is, what the property would have been worth had there been no plans for HS2), a home loss payment of 10% of the value of the property (up to a maximum of £47,000) and be reimbursed for reasonable moving costs, including stamp duty on the purchase of a new property of equivalent value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rural areas we will establish a ‘voluntary purchase zone’, extending out from the boundary of the safeguarded area up to 120m either side of the line, within which homeowners will have the option to sell their homes to the government at their full unblighted value at any time after the HS2 route is safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those living beyond both the safeguarded area and voluntary purchase zone but who need to move house during the development of HS2 and find they are unable to sell their property, there will also be a ‘long term hardship scheme’ under which the government will buy the homes of successful applicants at their full unblighted value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, under the new ‘sale and rent’ back scheme, homeowners whose property will need to be acquired will have the option to sell their homes to the government early and stay in them as tenants until the properties are required for the railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the owners of properties above tunnels may also be concerned about the potential impact of HS2 and therefore we are bringing in a series of measures designed to provide confidence in these properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will work with local authorities, housing associations and affected tenants to agree a joint strategy to replace any social housing which is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must stress that we have already written directly to all those whose homes we currently expect to need to buy in order to build and operate HS2 on the London - West Midlands route. The wide-ranging proposals set out today reflect the significant nature of the concern that currently exists in the property markets near the HS2 line of route, they are not a reflection of what the government believes the long term impacts of HS2 will be. We fully expect that the impacts of HS2 will be considerably less than feared and that property prices will recover over time. However, we recognise that the current property markets near the HS2 line of route may not reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2 will be the backbone of a new transport system for the 21st century, offering the new railway capacity that our country will need to compete and grow. However, we fully recognise that the line will have unwelcome impacts on people living close to the route and I believe that this package of compensation demonstrates the strength of the government’s commitment to provide the right compensation and assistance to those affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the property consultation published today, we are also publishing a consultation on safeguarding directions for HS2. This will set out the proposed area of land considered necessary to protect the line of route from conflicting developments, that is to say planning permission being granted for developments on land that will be required for the construction or operation of HS2. This will also set the ‘safeguarded area’ within which compensation measures will apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both consultations will close on 31 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-property-compensation-london-west-midlands"&gt;High Speed Two: property and compensation for London - West Midlands video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20121025a/"&gt;Government unveils generous HS2 compensation package&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;*[HS2] High Speed 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14810</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:46:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-unveils-generous-hs2-compensation-package"/>
    <title>Government unveils generous HS2 compensation package</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Residents affected by the first phase of HS2 from London to the West Midlands will be offered a comprehensive package of compensation measures which go significantly beyond statutory requirements, the government confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2, a national high-speed rail network linking Birmingham, Manchester and Leeds with London and Heathrow, will transform the UK - bringing cities together, delivering jobs and growth, and providing a long-term solution to the capacity crunch facing the existing rail network. Stations will also be situated in the East Midlands and South Yorkshire, while high speed trains will continue on the existing rail network to serve destinations further north and into Scotland. The government has already consulted on the route of the first phase of the project to the West Midlands and the Transport Secretary will publish his preferred routes for the second phase of the scheme later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the government recognises the impact the project is having on property markets along the first phase of the route and, after careful consideration, has decided to go above and beyond what is required by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures proposed today go beyond the statutory requirements by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing a government commitment to buy any owner-occupied home in the ‘safeguarded area’ closest to the route - as set out in law, the government will then pay the full un-blighted value of the property, along with additional compensation of 10% up to a value of £47,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a ‘voluntary purchase zone’ immediately outside of the safeguarded area in rural areas, within which homeowners can sell their homes at their full un-blighted value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a long term hardship scheme to help those with a need to move during the development of HS2 but who are unable to sell their home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a sale and rent back scheme to give more flexibility to homeowners who wish to stay in properties which will ultimately be required to allow for construction work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a package of measures to provide clarity and reinforce confidence in properties above tunnels, including before and after surveys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a commitment to work with local authorities, housing associations and affected tenants to develop a strategy for replacing any lost social rented housing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HS2 will completely transform the UK. It will define our country, not just for the 21st century but beyond - linking our major cities in a way previous generations could only dream of.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;No major infrastructure project on this scale can be built without some impact on local communities, but I am determined to do everything I can to minimise the effect of HS2 on those closest to the line.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have developed the right compensation package, providing absolutely the right support for those affected, while at the same time protecting the interests of taxpayers. We have thought long and hard about this and the measures I have announced are fair and strike the right balance for local communities and the British taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compensation package announced today is comparable with the arrangements put in place for homeowners affected by the construction of HS1. It will now be subject to a period of consultation until 31 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the proposed compensation package, HS2 Ltd and the Department for Transport has also launched a three-month consultation aimed at local authorities on safeguarding the land needed in order to build and run the line between London and the West Midlands. Safeguarding is the technical term for the planning mechanism that protects large-scale public infrastructure projects from conflicting developments nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document &lt;a rel="external" href="http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/consultations/property-compensation-london-to-west-midlands"&gt;High Speed Two: Property and Compensation for London - West Midlands&lt;/a&gt; closes on 31 January 2013: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultation events for the property compensation consultation will take place along the line of route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/"&gt;high speed rail consultation website&lt;/a&gt; or by contacting the HS2 enquiries line on: 0207 944 4908.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="safeguarding-consultation"&gt;Safeguarding Consultation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document &lt;a rel="external" href="http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/consultations/safeguarding"&gt;High Speed Two: Safeguarding for London - West Midlands&lt;/a&gt; is available and closes on 31st January 2013: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is aimed at planning authorities. An email is being sent to local authorities, community forums and MPs inviting them to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further details on the compensation measures published today: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Streamlined system of advanced purchase within the safeguarded zone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under these measures, owner-occupiers of residential properties and owners of commercial properties (with a rateable value not exceeding £34,800) where some or all of the property is within the safeguarded area (usually 60 metres either side of the track) will be able to ask the government to purchase their property under compulsory terms at a time of their choosing after safeguarding directions are made (expected Spring 2013). This means they will receive the unblighted open market value of the property, a home loss payment (10% of the value of the property, up to £47,000) and disturbance costs (such as fees, removal costs and stamp duty on a new property of equivalent value).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government proposes that where the entirety of an eligible property is within the safeguarded area and the owner asks the government to purchase their property we will agree, whether it is actually required for the railway or not. We will also consider purchase requests where only part of a property is within the safeguarded zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streamlined system for voluntary purchase within a new voluntary purchase zone in rural areas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will also establish a new voluntary purchase zone outside of the immediate safeguarded zone within which owner-occupiers of residential property or owners of commercial property (with a rateable value not exceeding £34,800) will be also able to ask the government to purchase their property for its unblighted open market value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the impact of HS2 on the property market has been and is expected to continue to be greater in rural areas than in urban areas the Voluntary Purchase Zone will run from the M25 northwards to the south of the delta junction to Birmingham and to the north of the delta junction with the junction with the West Coast Main Line. The voluntary purchase zone will cover an area 120m either side of the line of route, except over bored tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hardship scheme for those beyond the safeguarded and voluntary purchase zones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those with a need to move during the development of HS2 but who are unable to sell their home despite being outside both the safeguarded area and the voluntary purchase zone will be able to apply to have the government purchase their homes under a hardship scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sale and rent back scheme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will allow homeowners whose property will need to be demolished to sell their property to the government when they wish but remain in their homes as tenants until their land is actually needed for construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A series of measures designed to provide peace of mind for property owners above tunnels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing before and after surveys at government expense and a ‘settlement deed’ which will guarantee that HS2 would be liable for any damage caused by tunnelling, in perpetuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While the safeguarding consultation is aimed primarily at local authorities, individuals are welcome to contribute if they wish. However, if they are particularly interested in the proposed compensation arrangements for the impact safeguarding has on their home or property, they are encouraged to respond to the property and compensation consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-property-compensation-london-west-midlands"&gt;High Speed Two: Property and Compensation for London - West Midlands video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/mcloughlin-20121025a"&gt;High Speed Two - Assistance and compensation for home owners and occupiers on the London - West Midlands Route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hs2"&gt;High Speed Rail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the Government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/greening-20120110"&gt;High speed rail, written ministerial statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120110/"&gt;Britain to have new national high-speed rail network, press release, 10 January 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13228</id>
    <published>2012-09-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:44:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/high-speed-rail-investing-in-britain-s-future-consultation-summary-report-addendum-2"/>
    <title>High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report addendum 2</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 10 January 2012, the government announced its decision to develop a new national high speed rail network following the completion of a major public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 29 May, the consultation responses were published online. We have discovered, since then, that a small number of responses submitted online (722 of around 55,000 submitted in total) were not analysed fully by Dialogue by Design (DbyD) due to technical errors. For these responses, the answers to one or more of the seven consultation questions were omitted from DbyD’s analysis. In total, approximately 0.4% of answers provided to individual consultation questions were affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This addendum report is a supplementary analysis by DbyD of the seven hundred and twenty two (722) affected consultation responses submitted online. The report concludes that the affected responses ‘do not provide any information that was not already included in the previous Consultation Summary Report or would have made a difference to the substantive content or balance of that report’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport issued a statement about this to Parliament on 18 September 2012 explaining that the cause has been identified as technical errors in transferring data captured from online consultation responses to the consultation analysis database held by DbyD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those who submitted the responses affected have been contacted with details of their particular cases to notify them and apologise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="read-the-written-ministerial-statement"&gt;Read the written ministerial statement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/baker-20120918b"&gt;High Speed Rail: Phase 1 Consultation Update, written statement, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/high-speed-rail-addendum/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report addendum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the Government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the Government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: Update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13548</id>
    <published>2012-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T11:13:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hs2-and-landscape-costs"/>
    <title>HS2 and landscape costs</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Environmental Information Regulations (EIR) response regarding High Speed 2 and landscape costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13337</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T16:22:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hs2-and-social-media"/>
    <title>HS2 and social media</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of information response regarding documents relating to the use of Twitter, Facebook or other social media and HS2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13508</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T13:57:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hs2-and-social-media-further-documents"/>
    <title>HS2 and social media - further documents</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of information response following on from FOI response F0008958 concerning social media and HS2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
