<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Reducing the impact of regulation on business"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48216</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/10-point-plan-for-eu-smart-regulation"/>
    <title>10 point plan for EU smart regulation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Business, along with Ministers from 12 other Member States, jointly signed a ‘10 point plan for EU smart regulation’. Sent to Commission President Barroso on 19 November 2012, in advance of the Commission’s forthcoming Smart Reg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47196</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/call-for-evidence-on-the-governments-review-of-the-balance-of-competences-between-the-united-kingdom-and-the-european-union"/>
    <title>Call for evidence on the government's review of the balance of competences between the United Kingdom and the European Union</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/corporate/images/logos/balance-of-competencies.JPG?w=200&amp;amp;h=50&amp;amp;as=1" alt="Review of the Balance of Competences"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is carrying out a review of the balance of competences between the EU and the UK. This is an audit of what the EU does and how it affects the UK. You can read more about it on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/european-union/balance-of-competences-review/"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office’s web page on the balance of competences review&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have published our first &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/g/12-1278-government-review-balance-competences-united-kingdom-european-union-call.pdf"&gt;Call for Evidence on the Internal Market: Synoptic Review (PDF, 735 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;. The Synoptic report will cover the overall application and effect of the EU Internal Market. The result of the report will be a comprehensive , thorough and detailed analysis of the wider functioning of the Internal Market. It will determine how the so-called “Four Freedoms” operate together to create an efficient and operating Internal Market and ultimately what this means for the UK. We will subsequently be reviewing each of the “Four Freedoms” in turn in semesters 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to contribute to the review is asked to send their written views before 28 February 2013 to &lt;a href="mailto:balanceofcompetences@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;balanceofcompetences@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; or online at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/internalmarket"&gt;https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/internalmarket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our intention to publish evidence at the end of the review when the reports are published. In the meantime, the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills plans to use section 22 to exempt FOI requests around evidence received.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48187</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-copyright-licensing"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: copyright licensing</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to copyright licensing. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48188</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-debtor-petition-reform"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: debtor petition reform</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to reform of the process by which an individual may apply for his or her own bankruptcy. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48191</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-civil-liability-and-health-and-safety-at-work-regulations"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: civil liability and health and safety at work regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to addressing potential unfairness arising when an employer is found liable to pay compensation to an employee, despite having taken all reasonable steps to protect them. Explains&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48171</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-bill-policy-paper"/>
    <title>Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill: policy paper</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains why the Government is undertaking the measures contained in this Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill, and explains what each measure aims to achieve. Also provides more detail on the clauses of the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48159</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reform-of-the-process-by-which-debtors-apply-for-bankruptcy-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Reform of the process by which debtors apply for bankruptcy: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A final stage assessment of the impact for a bankruptcy petition reform measure to be included in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill. Aims to improve the accessibility of bankruptcy for debtors who may be discouraged from engaging in a court based&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48160</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-section-138-of-the-equality-act-2010-and-the-need-for-the-obtaining-information-question-and-answer-forms-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Review of section 138 of the Equality Act 2010 and the need for the obtaining information question and answer forms: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A final stage assessment of the impact for a obtaining information measure to be included in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill. Aims to reduce any regulatory burden on employers that may be imposed as a result of the power to prescribe forms, whic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48161</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-err-bill-final-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Enterprise and Regulatory Reform (ERR) Bill: final impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Final stage impact assessment that summarises the cumulative effects of the proposed policies in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill. See also the accompanying impact assessments specifying the full intervention rationale, option appraisal, cost-ben&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
