<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-trade/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-trade/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-trade/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making it easier to trade"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47198</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/street-trading-and-pedlary-laws-a-joint-consultation-on-draft-regulations-to-repeal-the-pedlars-acts-uk-wide-and-make-changes-to-the-street-trading-legislation-in-england-wales-and-northern-ireland"/>
    <title>Street Trading and Pedlary Laws: A joint consultation on draft regulations to repeal the Pedlars Acts (UK wide) and make changes to the street trading legislation in England, Wales and Northern Ireland</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-to-consultation"&gt;Background to consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/11-542-street-trading-pedlar-laws-government-response.pdf"&gt;Government Response&lt;/a&gt; to the street trading and pedlary consultation, the Governments interpretation of compliance with the Directive developed in the course of the evaluation of the Directive amongst Member States. The consensus now is that the retail sale of goods is generally a service activity within the scope of the Directive and since pedlars and street traders are engaged in the retail sale of goods it has been concluded that changes are required to both of these regimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="purpose-of-consultation"&gt;Purpose of consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the consultation is to ensure that the street trading and pedlary regimes comply fully with the requirements of the Services Directive.   The UK Government and the Northern Ireland Executive are seeking views from stakeholders in relation to the repeal of the Pedlars Acts and changes to their respective street trading regimes. The Scottish Government is only seeking views in relation to the repeal of the Pedlars Acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="areas-for-consultation"&gt;Areas for consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public views are being sought specifically in the following areas: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repeal of the UK wide Pedlars Acts 1871 and 1881.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A new, clear and up to date definition of what behaviour constitutes acting as a pedlar for the purposes of the pedlar exemption under the street trading regimes of England, Wales and Northern Ireland.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes to Schedule 4 to the Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1982 to ensure compliance with the Services Directive - (the street trading regime of England and Wales).  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes to the Northern Ireland (Street Trading) Act 2001 to ensure compliance with the Services Directive.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-605-street-trading-compliance-with-services-directive-consultation.pdf"&gt;Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive. A joint consultation on the draft regulations - repeal of the Pedlars Acts (UK-wide), and changes to street trading legislation in England and Wales and Northern Ireland (PDF, 470 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-605rf-street-trading-compliance-with-services-directive-form.doc"&gt;Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive consultation - response form for England and Wales only (DOC, 151 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-606-street-trading-compliance-with-services-directive-impact.pdf"&gt;Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive impact assessment (PDF, 189 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48230</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-trading-and-pedlar-laws-compliance-with-the-european-services-directive-a-joint-consultation-on-the-draft-regulations-repeal-of-the-pedlars-acts-uk-wide-and-changes-to-street-trading-legislation-in-england-and-wales-and-northern-ireland"/>
    <title>Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive. A joint consultation on the draft regulations - repeal of the Pedlars Acts (UK-wide), and changes to street trading legislation in England and Wales and Northern Ireland</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses by 15 February 2013. Consultation seeking views on draft regulations to amend national street trading legislation for England and Wales and for Northern Ireland. Also covers proposals to repeal the Pedlars Act 1871 and 1881 for the whole of the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48231</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-trading-and-pedlary-laws-compliance-with-the-requirements-of-the-european-services-directive-response-form-for-england-and-wales-only"/>
    <title>Street trading and pedlary laws: compliance with the requirements of the European Services Directive. Response form for England and Wales only</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses by 15 February 2013. Template for responses to the consultation on draft regulations to amend national street trading legislation and proposals to repeal the Pedlars Act (URN 12/605).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48232</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-trading-and-pedlar-laws-compliance-with-the-european-services-directive-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive. Impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of draft regulations for the street trading regime and proposals to repeal the Pedlars Act. Aims to bring UK legislation in line with the European Services Directive (2006/123/EC) requirements. Also seeks to maintain a balance between&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48105</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-guidance-for-foreign-exchange-providers-compliance-with-consumer-protection-legislation"/>
    <title>BIS guidance for foreign exchange providers: compliance with consumer protection legislation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance for businesses on the Price Indications (Bureaux de Change (No.2) Regulations 1992, and applying the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 to foreign exchange providers. Gives supplementary guidance for providers of foreign exc&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48120</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/estate-agents-market-regulatory-reform-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Estate agents market regulatory reform: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of proposals to make regulation in the estate agency sector proportionate and targeted to the risk involved in the particular service being offered. See the related consultations on the Estate Agents Act (URN 12/931) and Property Misde&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48072</id>
    <published>2012-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-regulatory-framework-for-home-buying-and-selling-government-response-to-consultations-on-the-estate-agents-act-and-the-property-misdescriptions-act"/>
    <title>The regulatory framework for home buying and selling: government response to consultations on the Estate Agents Act and the Property Misdescriptions Act</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government response to consultations on the Estate Agents Act (URN 12/931) and the Property Misdescriptions Act (11/505) on proposals to make regulation in the estate agency sector proportionate and targeted to the risk involved in the particular serv&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45710</id>
    <published>2012-06-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/encouraging-new-business-models-amending-the-estate-agents-act-1979"/>
    <title>Encouraging new business models: amending the Estate Agents Act 1979</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respond by 10 August 2012. Informal consultation that seeks views on a proposal to amend section 1 of the Estate Agents Act 1979. The proposal aims to help businesses to innovate and grow and allow new business models to emerge while ensuring that consumer protection is not unduly compromised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45714</id>
    <published>2012-05-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/sunday-trading-during-the-2012-london-olympic-and-paralympic-games-assessment"/>
    <title>Sunday trading during the 2012 London Olympic and Paralympic Games: assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the evidence on the impact of options on the temporary suspension of Sunday Trading restrictions during the Olympic Games and Paralympic Games: 22 July to 9 September 2012. Includes an equality impact assessment. See also the guidance on the effect of the Act on the existing right of shop workers to opt out URN 12/764.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18380</id>
    <published>2012-05-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sunday-trading-laws-relaxed-for-olympics"/>
    <title>Sunday trading laws relaxed for Olympics</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bill means that shops with a relevant floor area of more than 280 square metres will not be subject to current Sunday trading restrictions during the Games.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suspension will only be for eight Sundays, from 22 July to the end of the Paralympic Games on 9 September. After this period the current Sunday trading restrictions will apply again.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Mark Prisk said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will be a fantastic opportunity to showcase, not just London, but the whole of the country to the rest of the world and provide a boost for the economy, sales and employment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Retail workers will keep all their legal protections, such as the right to opt-out of Sunday working, but many will want to take the opportunity to work extra or different hours. I want employers to work with their staff so that we can all make the most of the Olympics.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to make it clear that this is a temporary measure and not a test case for a permanent relaxation of the rules in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the full &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Sunday-Trading-Bill-receives-Royal-Assent-for-Olympic-Games-67966.aspx"&gt;press notice: Sunday trading Bill receives Royal Assent for Olympic Games&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further information on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/consumer-issues/buying-and-selling/sunday-trading"&gt;Sunday trading during the London Olympic Games and Paralympic Games&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/Employment/Employees/WorkingHoursAndTimeOff/DG_10028516"&gt;Guidance for workers on Sunday work and the temporary changes from DirectGov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/detail?itemId=1073792308&amp;amp;r.i=1073792311&amp;amp;r.l1=1073858787&amp;amp;r.l2=1073858926&amp;amp;r.l3=1074014429&amp;amp;r.s=sc&amp;amp;r.t=RESOURCES&amp;amp;type=RESOURCES"&gt;Guidance for employers on Sunday working from Business Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
