<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making transport more accessible to all"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10529</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T17:06:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/grant-funding-paid-to-mobility-centres"/>
    <title>Grant funding paid to mobility centres</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s (&lt;abbr title="The Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) response to Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request F0007301: Grant funding paid to mobility centres&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10635</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T16:26:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/blue-badge-scheme-contract"/>
    <title>Blue badge scheme contract</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s (DfT’s) response to Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request F0007842: Blue Badge scheme contract.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13159</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T17:36:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-27-september-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 27 September 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has published the following Transport Statistics on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/reported-road-casualties-great-britain-annual-report-2011"&gt;‘Reported road casualties Great Britain: 2011 Annual Report’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/public-attitudes-towards-train-services"&gt;public attitudes towards train services: Results from the April 2012 Opinions Survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/blue-badge-scheme-statistics-2011-12"&gt;Blue badge scheme statistics 2011/12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details on all &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13295</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T09:47:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/blue-badge-scheme-statistics-2011-12"/>
    <title>Blue badge scheme statistics: 2011/12</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents information on parking badges for disabled people (“Blue Badges”) in England in 2011/12, including numbers of valid badges on issue, and the number issued in the 2011/12 financial year. The data are derived from the Department’s annual survey of local authorities issuing Blue Badges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On 31 March 2012, the estimated number of valid Blue Badges held was 2.62 million, a decrease of 1.1 per cent from the revised figure of 2.65 million for the previous year, which was the highest annual figure recorded. This is the first year to experience a decline since 1997.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Of this total, 37 per cent were issued under the ‘without further assessment’ criteria, 62 per cent were issued under the ‘subject to further assessment’ criteria and 1 per cent were issued to organisations. These proportions have remained broadly similar since 1997.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 31 March 2012, 5.0 per cent of the English population held a valid Blue Badge, a decrease of 0.1 percentage points from 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2011/12, the estimated number of Blue Badges issued in England was 905 thousand, a decrease of 3.4 per cent from the previous year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The overall reduction in number of badges held between 2011 and 2012 has been driven by a decline of 4.3 per cent in the number of badges issued under the ‘subject to further assessment’ criteria in the last year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="technical-information"&gt;Technical information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on blue badge statistics, including the pre-release access list, and related technical documentation &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats?cachebust=1351690624&amp;amp;preview=8996#disabled-parking-badges-statistics"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:parking.data@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;parking.data@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone: 020 7944 3094&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12215</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T10:31:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-planning-policy-evaluation-and-future-directions"/>
    <title>Accessibility planning policy: Evaluation and future directions</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is an evaluation of the processes and impacts of Accessibility Planning Policy in relation to the development and delivery of local authorities’ Accessibility Planning Strategies, submitted as part of the 2006-2011 Local Transport Plans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14939</id>
    <published>2012-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-17T11:18:33+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-study-offers-bus-pass-holders-a-third-off-train-travel"/>
    <title>New study offers bus pass holders a third off train travel</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Older and disabled people with bus passes will be able to get a third off train travel as part of a twelve-month experiment announced by Rail Minister Norman Baker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial is being launched on Sunday to encourage more older and disabled people to use trains, and means concessionary bus pass holders will be able to claim discounted fares on two test routes without purchasing an annual Senior Railcard, which costs £28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is being rolled out by First Great Western and will apply to standard off-peak fares between Worcester and Swindon via Stroud, and between Westbury and Weymouth. The department will be assessing the trial keenly to see if a wider and more permanent application might be merited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is great news for bus pass holders and hopefully they will take full advantage of the discounts on offer through this innovative scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everybody is feeling the squeeze at the moment and this trial will help older and disabled people save money while travelling on these two important railway lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The railways are not only a crucial part of our country’s economic growth but they also provide a valuable link for families and friends. I am confident this scheme will help bolster those links and provide real benefits to those who need it most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Campaigning groups including the National Pensioner’s Convention and the National Federation of Occupational Pensioners have previously lobbied for concessionary bus passes to be used as a senior railcard, and believe it will lead to higher numbers of older and disabled people purchasing rail tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will work with First Great Western to examine the commercial viability of the scheme with a final report due in November next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Hopwood, First Great Western Managing Director, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First Great Western is privileged to provide services to some of the country’s leading destinations and our branch lines to Worcester and Weymouth are symbolic of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to be able to take part in this trial, which should help improve access for senior citizens and people with disabilities to the services that we offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The aim of the study is to provide the DfT with robust information to inform Train Operating Companies (TOCs) and the Association of Train Operating Companies (ATOC) on the commercial viability of extending some of the privileges associated with the Senior and Disabled Railcard to all holders of English National Concessionary travel passes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FGW will carry out a discount scheme over the course of one year offering holders of concessionary travel passes a 34% discount on standard class tickets at off-peak times (after 9.30am and before 11pm on weekday, all day on weekends and bank holidays) on the test areas of the rail network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The study will report quarterly on a quantitative assessment of the changes in peak and off-peak patronage amongst older and disabled customers that result from the discount scheme being available. Comparisons, where appropriate will be made to First Great Western’s continual customer research study; Customer Satisfaction Monitor (CSM).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DfT is due a final research report from FGW in November 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15982</id>
    <published>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:35:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hemel-hempstead-station"/>
    <title>Hemel Hempstead station</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of information response (F0009111) regarding accessibility at Hemel Hempstead station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/dft-f0009111.pdf"&gt;Freedom of information response letter regarding accessibility at Hemel Hempstead station&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/annex-a-stations-update20120401.pdf"&gt;Annex A: stations update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/annex-b-option-selection-report.pdf"&gt;Annex B: option selection report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/email-correspondence.pdf"&gt;Email correspondence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/hemel-photo-plan.pdf"&gt;Hemel Hempstead plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/hemel-photos.zip"&gt;Hemel Hempstead photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105134522/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/foi/dft-f0009111/further-email-correspondence.pdf"&gt;Further email correspondence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13142</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:18:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-statistics-2011"/>
    <title>Accessibility statistics: 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents information on accessibility statistics for England for 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility statistics provide a local-level measure of the availability of transport to key services (covering food stores, education, health care, town centres and employment centres) for the populations who use them. They are widely used in accessibility planning by local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in travel times and accessibility can be caused by three factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the number and location of service destinations;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the quality of the service destinations datasets;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and road / travel factors (such as public transport timetables, road layout and congestion).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In most the cases changes in the first two factors (i.e. relating to the number and location of destinations and data quality) will have a greater affect on average travel times than changes in timetables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release provides a summary of the statistics at national and regional level. The full set of results, including figures at Local Authority and Lower Super Output Area level, are available in separate files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The average minimum travel time to the seven key services (excluding town centres) was 14 minutes by public transport/walking, 9 minutes by cycling and 6 minutes by car. These times were 0.55 minutes longer than in 2010 for public transport/walking and around 0.2 minutes longer than in 2010 for both cycling and by car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average of key services excluding town centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As in previous years, hospitals had the longest average minimum travel times of the seven key services in 2011 with average minimum travel times of 30 minutes by public transport/walking, 21 minutes by cycling and 9 minutes by driving. Primary schools and foods stores were the most accessible services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users in urban areas could access key services by public transport/walking, on average, in 12 minutes compared with 22 minutes in rural areas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proportion of users able to access key services by public transport/walking in a ‘reasonable’ time was highest for employment centres (81%). The lowest was for hospitals (29%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall access to key services by public transport/walking within a ‘reasonable’ time was greatest in London and lowest in the East of England.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:subnational.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;subnational.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone: 020 7944 4139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12904</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-18T11:22:25+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-12-july-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 12 July 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has published the following transport statistics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120820032214/http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/accessibility-statistics-2011/"&gt;accessibility statistics: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8815</id>
    <published>2012-07-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/personal-independence-payment-and-eligibility-for-a-blue-badge"/>
    <title>Personal Independence Payment and eligibility for a Blue Badge</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a consultation document about the government’s changes to welfare reform and the effect they will have on eligibility for a Disabled Person’s Parking Permit, or Blue Badge. The consultation closes on Tuesday 2 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120709a/"&gt;Blue Badge consultation opens, 9 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/baker-20120709a/"&gt;Personal Independence Payment and eligibility for a Blue Badge, statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 9 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
