<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-transport-more-accessible-to-all/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making transport more accessible to all"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55970</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-for-everyone"/>
    <title>Transport for everyone </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker is calling on operators and local authorities to work with government to put accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help them to do this, the Department for Transport has published 2 action plans which set out priorities, as well as highlighting areas where action is in the pipeline or already underway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Transport for everyone’ outlines how operators, local councils and the Department can help to make it easier for people using public transport – particularly those with disabilities - to get to where they need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action plan builds on the success achieved in improving accessibility on public transport during the Olympics and Paralympics. At the heart of the plan is the importance of improving door-to-door journeys rather than addressing issues in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s equality action plan looks at how we can encourage a more inclusive transport network and underlines the importance of ensuring that policy makers at all levels are alive to the particular needs and concerns of different groups in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include affordability issues for young people and pensioners and the ability for all people to travel in safety and free from harassment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good transport system allows people to access jobs, opportunities and vital services - it needs to work for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the concerns that specific groups of people have about public transport and so we have pulled together ideas from across the transport sector on how these concerns can be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The action plans will help policy makers, as well as transport operators, to tackle problems head on and - more importantly - to level the playing field for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Sayce OBE, Disability Rights UK Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An accessible transport infrastructure is essential for what Disability Rights UK wants to achieve – disabled people playing a full and equal part in society. Over the past 20 years we have come a long way as our practical guide ‘Doing transport differently’ shows but there are still too many attitudinal, communication and physical barriers facing disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Action plan’ is a step change towards making further progress. We welcome the commitment that the Department for Transport will continue to work in partnership with disabled people and our organisations to ensure the most effective steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Accessibility action plan’ builds on the transport successes of the Olympic and Paralympic Games and aims to create a long lasting legacy of improved access and information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Olympic and Paralympic Games, public transport operators carried thousands of spectators with disabilities and work was done to ensure that the travelling public had easy access to information. One of the aims of the ‘Accessibility action plan’ will be to build on the Games Spectator Journey Planner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new planner would cover a wider geographical area and more types of transport as well as being made accessible to people with visual impairments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other measures outlined in the plan include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considering where £100 million of extra funding might be best spent in the long term to improve accessibility of railway stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible further amendments to the Blue Badge scheme to tackle abuse and fraud in this area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building on guidance for mobility scooters and powered wheelchairs to encourage training for those using this equipment &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Equality action plan’ sets out in one place what the department is doing to ensure people from all parts of society have the option to use public transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points addressed in the plan include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessibility to public transport for young people, older people and those living in rural areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety and personal security for women travellers, particularly at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling hate crime and bullying on buses and other public transport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promoting employment of under-represented groups within the transport industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both documents include lists of issues and the actions that have been, or will be, taken to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Accessibility action plan’&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;‘Equality action plan’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the interests of transparency and to enable as many people as possible to have their say, the ‘Equality action plan’ will be open for comment until 15 February. These will feed in to a final version of the document which will be published in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55866</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/accessibility-action-plan-and-equality-action-plan"/>
    <title>Accessibility action plan and equality action plan</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today pleased to be publishing the department’s accessibility action plan &lt;a href="/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Transport for Everyone: an action plan to improve accessibility for all’&lt;/a&gt;, and, for comment, a draft &lt;a href="/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;equality action plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has already been achieved in making transport more accessible, and the accessibility action plan seeks to address the challenges that remain. In doing so, we also want to draw on the success of the Olympic and Paralympic Games which demonstrated what can be done to provide those using our public transport system with a positive experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility action plan focuses not only on improving physical accessibility, but also on providing better information for the traveller, and on improving attitudes and behaviour, especially towards disabled passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying our priorities in the action plan, we have worked with a large number of representative organisations, individuals, transport operators and local authorities. I am grateful for the support and input that they have provided.  We want transport to be accessible by all and the plan moves us further towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equality action plan presents some of the activities we are undertaking to meet our duties under the equalities legislation, and provides an initial set of priorities for promoting equality and well-being, based on the evidence we have gathered and the engagement we have already had with transport organisations and other interested parties. We are seeking comments on this initial draft and will publish a final version following further engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54962</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:34:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"/>
    <title>Accessibility action plan</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This accessibility action plan identifies the department’s priorities for improving disabled people’s experience of public transport by building on the success of the Olympic and Paralympic Games.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is planning to implement in the next spending review period and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10529</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T17:06:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/grant-funding-paid-to-mobility-centres"/>
    <title>Grant funding paid to mobility centres</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s (&lt;abbr title="The Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) response to Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request F0007301: Grant funding paid to mobility centres&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10635</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T16:26:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/blue-badge-scheme-contract"/>
    <title>Blue badge scheme contract</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s (DfT’s) response to Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request F0007842: Blue Badge scheme contract.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16659</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T16:18:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-rail-accessibility-group"/>
    <title>National Rail Accessibility Group</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W5qB6WoTYXQ&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA" title="National Rail Accessibility Group"&gt;National Rail Accessibility Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sorry that I am unable to be with you in person today but at least I can be with you virtually. I am sure that this new group will help in improving access to our rail network, something that the government takes very seriously.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that you will be receiving a debrief from the train operators, following their sterling performance during this summer’s Olympic and Paralympic Games. Following this excellent result we need to consider what lessons can be learned for the everyday running of network, as we welcome ever increasing numbers of passengers, including those with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am sure you are all aware, we have continued with our vital Access for All programme. This £370 million programme will see accessible routes installed at more than 150 stations by 2015. More than 1,000 stations have already benefitted from smaller scale access improvements delivered under the Small Schemes element of Access for All and last year we announced a further £37.5 million in a new mid-tier fund that will benefit around 160 stations, including more than 30 accessible routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our view the programme has been a great success and that is why we therefore recently announced a further £100 million to extend it through to 2019.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will soon begin working with Network Rail to identify stations for the extended programme, ensuring value for money by targeting busier stations, but also seeking the views of train operators and local authorities on their priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel, work is proceeding to make all trains fully accessible by 2020. The government has been working hard with industry and stakeholders for over five years to make sure everyone knows what work needs to take place and passengers are already seeing the benefits, eight years ahead of the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 5,700 fully accessible train carriages are already in service – this represents over 48% of all vehicles on the national rail network. And Thameslink, IEP and Crossrail will provide 2,400 more new fully accessible vehicles by the end of 2019. We mustn’t forget either that all older trains now provide some access features, such as priority seating or passenger information systems, even if they don’t yet fully meet all the standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this progress, we recognise that there is still much work to do to make rail travel as seamless as possible. A key to this is the new Passenger Assist booking system, which I believe you’ll be hearing about today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this new group as a welcome means of exchanging experiences, ideas and best practice between rail users and providers, and wish it much success. I look forward to receiving updates of your work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13159</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T17:36:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-27-september-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 27 September 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has published the following Transport Statistics on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/reported-road-casualties-great-britain-annual-report-2011"&gt;‘Reported road casualties Great Britain: 2011 Annual Report’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/public-attitudes-towards-train-services"&gt;public attitudes towards train services: Results from the April 2012 Opinions Survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/releases/blue-badge-scheme-statistics-2011-12"&gt;Blue badge scheme statistics 2011/12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details on all &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12215</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T10:31:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-planning-policy-evaluation-and-future-directions"/>
    <title>Accessibility planning policy: Evaluation and future directions</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is an evaluation of the processes and impacts of Accessibility Planning Policy in relation to the development and delivery of local authorities’ Accessibility Planning Strategies, submitted as part of the 2006-2011 Local Transport Plans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14939</id>
    <published>2012-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-17T11:18:33+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-study-offers-bus-pass-holders-a-third-off-train-travel"/>
    <title>New study offers bus pass holders a third off train travel</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Older and disabled people with bus passes will be able to get a third off train travel as part of a twelve-month experiment announced by Rail Minister Norman Baker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial is being launched on Sunday to encourage more older and disabled people to use trains, and means concessionary bus pass holders will be able to claim discounted fares on two test routes without purchasing an annual Senior Railcard, which costs £28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is being rolled out by First Great Western and will apply to standard off-peak fares between Worcester and Swindon via Stroud, and between Westbury and Weymouth. The department will be assessing the trial keenly to see if a wider and more permanent application might be merited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is great news for bus pass holders and hopefully they will take full advantage of the discounts on offer through this innovative scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everybody is feeling the squeeze at the moment and this trial will help older and disabled people save money while travelling on these two important railway lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The railways are not only a crucial part of our country’s economic growth but they also provide a valuable link for families and friends. I am confident this scheme will help bolster those links and provide real benefits to those who need it most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Campaigning groups including the National Pensioner’s Convention and the National Federation of Occupational Pensioners have previously lobbied for concessionary bus passes to be used as a senior railcard, and believe it will lead to higher numbers of older and disabled people purchasing rail tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will work with First Great Western to examine the commercial viability of the scheme with a final report due in November next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Hopwood, First Great Western Managing Director, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First Great Western is privileged to provide services to some of the country’s leading destinations and our branch lines to Worcester and Weymouth are symbolic of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to be able to take part in this trial, which should help improve access for senior citizens and people with disabilities to the services that we offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The aim of the study is to provide the DfT with robust information to inform Train Operating Companies (TOCs) and the Association of Train Operating Companies (ATOC) on the commercial viability of extending some of the privileges associated with the Senior and Disabled Railcard to all holders of English National Concessionary travel passes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FGW will carry out a discount scheme over the course of one year offering holders of concessionary travel passes a 34% discount on standard class tickets at off-peak times (after 9.30am and before 11pm on weekday, all day on weekends and bank holidays) on the test areas of the rail network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The study will report quarterly on a quantitative assessment of the changes in peak and off-peak patronage amongst older and disabled customers that result from the discount scheme being available. Comparisons, where appropriate will be made to First Great Western’s continual customer research study; Customer Satisfaction Monitor (CSM).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DfT is due a final research report from FGW in November 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
