<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting fire and rescue authorities to reduce the number and impact of fires"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56532</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-fire-chief-to-lead-efficiency-review-of-fire-and-rescue"/>
    <title>Government fire chief to lead efficiency review of fire and rescue</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the public sector deficit, the government has protected fire and rescue authority funding. Some reduction was unavoidable but it was back-loaded so sensible savings could be made without impacting the service the public gets. Overall, fire and rescue authority spending power reductions - which takes into account grants from central government and council tax, was limited to 2.2% in 2011-12 and 0.5% in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is to be conducted by former firefighter and out-going government Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, in the new year. The review will seek to identify ways fire and rescue authorities can pinpoint savings and improvements without reducing the quality life-saving services that the country’s fire firefighters are known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many authorities have begun making efficiencies, but there is more that can be done to be more transparent about spending or introduce joint working with other emergency services liked shared senior management structures, improved procurement practices and better use of estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths and incidents are at an all time low. Over the last decade attendance at incidences has fallen by 39% and attendance at fires by 48%. The review will help today’s fire service reflect that change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conducting the review, Sir Ken Knight will talk to key partners to help develop his findings including the Local Government Association, Fire Sector Federation, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association and the Fire Brigades Union, as well as individual authorities and other emergency services. The report is expected to be completed in the spring of 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We all recognise our firefighters perform an incredibly important public service. That is why spending for fire and rescue authorities, like other blue light services, has been protected. But we cannot escape the reality that every bit of the public sector has to help reduce the deficit we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Public safety is always our first concern and this review will make sure no stone has been left unturned in the quest for the most efficient and effective front-line fire service there can be. I know Sir Ken is passionate about the quality of fire and rescue services and he will bring an enormous amount of experience and knowledge to the task.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With over 40 years in the fire service, I know firefighters care deeply about public safety and want to provide the best possible service, but we need to make sure that service is as effective and efficient as possible. Many authorities have made great strides already, but there is much more that can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This review is a real opportunity to get to grips with what is happening on the ground, to highlight best practice and make sure that every option for efficient working is being explored. I will be talking to firefighters, fire authorities and union reps about how we can get there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review the ways in which fire and rescue authorities may deliver further efficiencies and operational improvements without reducing the quality of front-line services to the public. The review will examine options for savings both within and beyond the current Spending Review period, including through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefighter training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flexible staffing and crewing arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of retained firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaboration with emergency services and other organisations on service delivery and estates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing of senior staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;locally led mergers and operational collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new fire-fighting technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventative approaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with local businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conducting this review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir Ken Knight will talk to key organisations in the fire sector, including the Local Government Association, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association, the Fire Brigades Union, the Fire Sector Federation, individual fire and rescue authorities and others who Sir Ken deems relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Ken will undertake up to 10 visits to a representative range of fire and rescue authorities, including those covering urban and rural areas, and those constituted as metropolitan, county and combined authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department will provide Sir Ken with analytical support, in particular in looking at examples of efficiencies from outside of the fire sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will take into account the findings of previous reviews and reports and their recommendations, including the 2002 ‘Independent Review of the Fire Service’ (the Bain Report), the Audit Commission’s 2008 ‘Community Safety National Report’, ‘Rising to the Challenge’, the 2010 Fire Futures review, and the 2011/2012 ‘Independent Review of Police Officer’ and ‘Staff Remuneration and Conditions’ (the Winsor Reports).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="timeline"&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Announce review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December 2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct field work and analysis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January to March 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Write and present report to DCLG ministers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spring 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact-details-for-responses"&gt;Contact details for responses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sir-ken-knight-biography"&gt;Sir Ken Knight biography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight has been the UK Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser for England since October 2007, advising ministers and senior officials on policy matters including the structure, organisation and performance of fire and rescue services and crucially, providing advice during major and catastrophic emergencies. He is also responsible for the enforcement Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005 in Crown premises in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56197</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/preferred-bidder-for-the-fire-service-college-confirmed"/>
    <title>Preferred bidder for the Fire Service College confirmed</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire minister said he was happy that the proposed sale of the college to Capita would achieve value for money for the public purse and secure the future of the college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that we are making real progress in securing the future of such an important facility. It is vital for the development of the Fire Service College that we put it on a sound footing, giving the private sector a chance to provide innovation and investment that will guarantee the future of a world-class asset.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure best value for money for taxpayers and enable the college to continue in its role, a number of conditions will be imposed on the proposed sale. These include commitments that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the college be preserved as a national training centre for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will continue to offer wider national resilience and emergency services training and exercises&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;government permission will be required if Capita wish to sell the incident ground&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councillor Kay Hammond, Chair of the Local Government Association’s fire services management committee, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is good news that government has listened to the views of the sector about the future of the Fire Service College and that it now looks set to get the outside investment it so badly needs. The Local Government Association and fire authorities will be keen to work with the future owners to help them transform the college into a first-class training facility fit for firefighters in the 21st century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association President, Vij Randeniya, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Chief Fire Officers’ Association welcomes the news that Capita has been selected. It has been a long and intensive process and we are glad that there is now clarity for the Fire Service College. We look forward to working closely with Capita to ensure that the very best provision is available for UK fire and rescue services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government now looks forward to holding constructive discussions with Capita to ensure that the transition from public to private sector is as smooth as possible and expects to complete the sale early in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Service College is a trading fund and executive agency of the department. Since becoming a trading fund in 1992, it has never been able to pay a dividend out of operating profits. The government’s response to Fire Futures on 12 April 2011 concluded that the college could achieve its full potential only if there was greater involvement from other sectors in its ownership, operation and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Options project considered 4 options for the future of the college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the status quo: the college remains as a trading fund of the department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a government owned contractor operated model: the assets remain under government ownership but management of the college is taken over by a private sector company under a long term contract, together with the staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disposal as a going concern: the college is sold to a private sector company who would continue to operate the college as a training centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closure: the college’s activities cease, staff are made redundant and the site is sold for an alternative use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the 4 options showed disposal as a going concern to be the best option, and the only one which both removes from government ongoing financial risks of ownership of the college and preserves a national training college for the fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers announced on 22 March 2012 that the Fire Service College would be sold as a going concern to a private sector company to continue operating as a training centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale process was launched on 10 April 2012 and the due diligence phase concluded in October with the receipt of final bids. Best and final offers were received in November. The aim is to complete the sale in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56085</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-10-2012-immediate"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 10/2012 immediate</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 is issued for the immediate attention of fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the announcement of the preferred bidder for the Fire Service College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17621</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T10:24:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-28-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 28/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consultation on proposed increases to employee pension contribution rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;departmental response to the consultation on amendments to the new Firefighters’ Pension Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update on the funding arrangements for localising support for council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government’s policy statement on business rates retention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of operational guidance and generic risk assessments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17112</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-5-7-incidents-involving-explosives"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 5.7: incidents involving explosives</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 5.7 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to incidents involving ‘commercial’ explosives, while in manufacture, storage or transportation. It does not cover improvised explosive devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in November 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16920</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T12:36:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-reforms"/>
    <title>Firefighters’ pension scheme reforms</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides details of the firefighters’ pension scheme from 2015. It relates to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-heads-of-agreement"&gt;heads
of agreement&lt;/a&gt; on the core parameters for reforms to the firefighters’ pension scheme that was published by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 9 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16737</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T16:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hazardous-materials-operational-guidance-for-the-fire-and-rescue-service"/>
    <title>Hazardous materials: operational guidance for the fire and rescue service</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides comprehensive yet flexible guidance that can be adapted to the nature, scale and requirements of the incident. It consolidates the content of over 500 items of previously published subject related documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16085</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:54:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/asian-fire-service-association-afsa-conference"/>
    <title>Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be invited to speak here today and to see so many others here to support you. I understand that this is the fifth AFSA national conference, and my predecessor Bob Neill has spoken at the last 2. I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Bob, who has a deep understanding of the issues you face, as well as a great knowledge of the sector. I know that Bob, when he was Fire Minister, greatly valued the close and positive relationship he had with AFSA. I very much hope to be able to continue that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-afsa"&gt;The importance of AFSA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of groups such as AFSA cannot be underestimated. You provide a forum for people to come together to discuss key concerns, to support each other’s development, and provide an opportunity for challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of challenge, AFSA continues to perform a vital role in terms of ensuring that equality, diversity and fairness are mainstreamed in the Fire and Rescue Service. Events such as this provide excellent opportunities for the exchange of ideas, and for lively debate. I know that a regional AFSA group has been set up here in the West Midlands, supporting professional development and progression, sharing learning experiences, building a solid network of mutual support for employees, and supporting charities and fundraising. All of this shows the excellent work that the association is doing both at the national and local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="promoting-equality-and-diversity"&gt;Promoting equality and diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that Sir Graham Meldrum, when he was Chief Fire Officer in the West Midlands and again as Chief Inspector of Her Majesty’s Fire Service Inspectorate did a great amount of work to promote equality and diversity in the service, and this excellent work has been carried on by Vij as Chief Fire Officer of the West Midlands, and in his presidency of the Chief Fire Officers Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to say, on a personal note, that I am deeply committed to advancing equality of opportunity to one and all, not only in the fire and rescue service, but also in the communities they live in and serve. I am also of the firm conviction that this is best driven locally. And I say this because I want each fire and rescue authority to be responsible for reaching out to minority groups, and ensuring that they recognise that the service is for them - not as an add on - but for them along with everyone else in the community. I want fire and rescue services to go out into their communities, find the right people, engage with them and draw them into the heart of the fire and rescue service family. I want the entire community to be so integrated into the fire and rescue service that we no longer have to think in terms of equality and diversity - it will just happen automatically. I know that this is at the core of what AFSA is working for, and you have my full support in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt, a lot is already happening, and I would like to highlight some of the work going on here in the West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service. They have Welcome to the West Midlands, an education programme for new migrants to promote safety, well being, community understanding and citizenship. This has been developed in consultation with migrants to meet the information gap which can occur when someone arrives in this country. The West Midlands also has active employee engagement through the local AFSA group, working with them to target under represented operational and support staff to develop essential skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my short time as Fire Minister I have been very impressed by the wide range of local initiatives such as these, which not only reach out to the under represented, but also to the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, the fire service is leading a community project with the Asian Development Association of Bury. This project, which provided employment opportunities for local people, has already seen the production of a fire safety video that can be heard in eight of Manchester’s most commonly used languages. It will be the main communication tool used in community education sessions, facilitated by fire and rescue service volunteers recruited by the association. There will also be a series of workshops for the &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; business community designed to raise awareness of how the fire and rescue service can help them meet their responsibilities under the Fire Safety Order. This project will be rolled out across all of Manchester’s ten metropolitan boroughs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage young people from a community they have previously found hard to reach, and to respect religious beliefs, they have established a cadet scheme in Hyde for young women from the Bangladeshi community, and they are hoping to use this as a model to engage many ethnic communities in similar activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is being driven forward at the local level - not by central target or quotas, but by responding to the demands of their local communities. And to be able to respond to these, each fire and rescue service needs to make full use of the human resources at their disposal - and to do this equality and diversity has to be at the core of any organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to delivering the best service to the local community is to have a diverse, representative workforce, equipped to understand and meet the needs of those it serves and capable of delivering a first class service to everyone. This will also support the service’s aim to create a better understanding of its preventative role and of the support and advice it is able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire service must ensure that every employee is valued; that there truly is equality of opportunity for all, and that the working culture is such that unfair discrimination, unacceptable behaviour, bullying and harassment are not tolerated. I strongly believe that the fire and rescue service has gone a long way to achieve this goal and together with partners like AFSA they can continue to work to create an even more open and inclusive service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-kills"&gt;Fire Kills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also like to take this opportunity to thank AFSA for your continued support of the Fire Kills campaign. The Fire Kills campaign has had a focus on &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; groups since 2005 - and for good reason. Research has shown that certain &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; communities are at a potentially greater risk from fire. Smoke alarm ownership amongst Asian communities is ten per cent lower than the national average.  Recent analysis of accidental dwelling fire victim profiles has suggested that Asian communities are potentially more vulnerable than African communities. This has led to our 2012 campaign focussing solely on the Bangladeshi and Pakistani communities. With smoke alarm ownership levels lower in these communities the primary message will be on the importance of working smoke alarms. Two bursts of advertising will run - one which began this week, and another in March 2013. The new campaign will focus on blessings. As you know blessing of wellbeing, health and a long life are delivered on important occasions in these communities. The new campaign will encourage people to make their blessings count - ‘when you give a blessing, make it count: test your smoke alarm’. There will be radio advertising to demonstrate the fire consequences of not having a working smoke alarm, linking it back to a blessing that was given. I have no doubt that this campaign, targeted primarily at first generation Pakistani and Bangladeshi communities, will be a powerful tool for you and all those in fire and rescue services seeking to reduce deaths and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-position"&gt;Economic position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of this conference is ‘advancing equality during austerity’. I think that it is important to note that there are signs of improvement in the economy. Jobs are being created, manufacturing and exports have grown as a share of our economy, our trade with vibrant, emerging economies such as China and Brazil is improving, and the world is once again investing in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we face many challenges. The debts built up over many years will take time to work our way through, not helped by a decline in our competitiveness which was effectively masked by unsustainable borrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to cut the national deficit, fire and rescue, as a frontline emergency service, has been given funding protection with reductions back-loaded to give more time for sensible savings to be made, and reductions applied to fire and rescue authorities have been less than those applied to local authorities in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been heartened to hear how many fire and rescue authorities have risen to the challenges that the spending review has posed. However, I know some of you have concerns that fire and rescue services may disproportionately reduce funding on equality and diversity activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this is not the case. But if you see this happening, then you must speak up. It is vital that fire and rescue services do not make decisions that will impact on their ability to deliver on their statutory duties as required under the Equality Act 2010, and transparency and accountability are at the heart of our approach towards local government generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing I would like to thank you once again for giving me this opportunity to speak to you today. I do hope that your organisation goes from strength to strength, and that you remain and important and influential voice in the British fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to extend my congratulations to all the award winners who will be honoured at this evening’s event, well done, keep up the good work and have a great night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17643</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T10:23:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-27-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 27/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for November 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recruitment of a new Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recruitment of 2 fire and rescue secondees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consultation on ‘Improving Local Government Transparency’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;announcement of a third year of council tax freeze for 2013-14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transitional grant for localising support for Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
