<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting fire and rescue authorities to reduce the number and impact of fires"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T10:44:03+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64195</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T10:44:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-29-2013"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 29/2013</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for January 2013 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;announcement of the operational efficiencies review led by Sir Ken Knight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fire capital bidding outcome for 2013 to 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;control centre buildings update&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of a new protective security strategy, framework and toolkit &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56832</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-protective-security-strategy-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue protective security strategy 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy is a refresh of the 2009 protective security strategy for fire and rescue authorities. It outlines 6 key deliverables to enhance protective security for fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57434</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/policy-on-protecting-personal-and-other-sensitive-information-in-fire-and-rescue-incident-and-casualty-data"/>
    <title>Policy on protecting personal and other sensitive information in fire and rescue incident and casualty data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This document summarises issues relating to data protection of fire and rescue incident records.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue services across Great Britain record details of all incidents attended and of casualties. A national database is populated from these and this contains details as described in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/incident-recording-system-for-fire-and-rescue-authorities"&gt;Incident recording system for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document summarises issues relating to data protection of fire and rescue incident records, and how these are managed in the context of the production of statistical outputs and access to record-level data sets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56532</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-fire-chief-to-lead-efficiency-review-of-fire-and-rescue"/>
    <title>Government fire chief to lead efficiency review of fire and rescue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An expert led review into the operational efficiency of the services delivered by fire and rescue authorities in England was announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the public sector deficit, the government has protected fire and rescue authority funding. Some reduction was unavoidable but it was back-loaded so sensible savings could be made without impacting the service the public gets. Overall, fire and rescue authority spending power reductions - which takes into account grants from central government and council tax, was limited to 2.2% in 2011-12 and 0.5% in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is to be conducted by former firefighter and out-going government Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, in the new year. The review will seek to identify ways fire and rescue authorities can pinpoint savings and improvements without reducing the quality life-saving services that the country’s fire firefighters are known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many authorities have begun making efficiencies, but there is more that can be done to be more transparent about spending or introduce joint working with other emergency services liked shared senior management structures, improved procurement practices and better use of estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths and incidents are at an all time low. Over the last decade attendance at incidences has fallen by 39% and attendance at fires by 48%. The review will help today’s fire service reflect that change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conducting the review, Sir Ken Knight will talk to key partners to help develop his findings including the Local Government Association, Fire Sector Federation, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association and the Fire Brigades Union, as well as individual authorities and other emergency services. The report is expected to be completed in the spring of 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We all recognise our firefighters perform an incredibly important public service. That is why spending for fire and rescue authorities, like other blue light services, has been protected. But we cannot escape the reality that every bit of the public sector has to help reduce the deficit we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Public safety is always our first concern and this review will make sure no stone has been left unturned in the quest for the most efficient and effective front-line fire service there can be. I know Sir Ken is passionate about the quality of fire and rescue services and he will bring an enormous amount of experience and knowledge to the task.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With over 40 years in the fire service, I know firefighters care deeply about public safety and want to provide the best possible service, but we need to make sure that service is as effective and efficient as possible. Many authorities have made great strides already, but there is much more that can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This review is a real opportunity to get to grips with what is happening on the ground, to highlight best practice and make sure that every option for efficient working is being explored. I will be talking to firefighters, fire authorities and union reps about how we can get there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review the ways in which fire and rescue authorities may deliver further efficiencies and operational improvements without reducing the quality of front-line services to the public. The review will examine options for savings both within and beyond the current Spending Review period, including through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefighter training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flexible staffing and crewing arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of retained firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaboration with emergency services and other organisations on service delivery and estates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing of senior staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;locally led mergers and operational collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new fire-fighting technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventative approaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with local businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conducting this review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir Ken Knight will talk to key organisations in the fire sector, including the Local Government Association, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association, the Fire Brigades Union, the Fire Sector Federation, individual fire and rescue authorities and others who Sir Ken deems relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Ken will undertake up to 10 visits to a representative range of fire and rescue authorities, including those covering urban and rural areas, and those constituted as metropolitan, county and combined authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department will provide Sir Ken with analytical support, in particular in looking at examples of efficiencies from outside of the fire sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will take into account the findings of previous reviews and reports and their recommendations, including the 2002 ‘Independent Review of the Fire Service’ (the Bain Report), the Audit Commission’s 2008 ‘Community Safety National Report’, ‘Rising to the Challenge’, the 2010 Fire Futures review, and the 2011/2012 ‘Independent Review of Police Officer’ and ‘Staff Remuneration and Conditions’ (the Winsor Reports).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="timeline"&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Announce review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December 2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct field work and analysis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January to March 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Write and present report to DCLG ministers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spring 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact-details-for-responses"&gt;Contact details for responses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sir-ken-knight-biography"&gt;Sir Ken Knight biography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight has been the UK Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser for England since October 2007, advising ministers and senior officials on policy matters including the structure, organisation and performance of fire and rescue services and crucially, providing advice during major and catastrophic emergencies. He is also responsible for the enforcement Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005 in Crown premises in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56197</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/preferred-bidder-for-the-fire-service-college-confirmed"/>
    <title>Preferred bidder for the Fire Service College confirmed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Fire minister Brandon Lewis has announced Capita as the preferred bidder for the purchase of the Fire Service College.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire minister said he was happy that the proposed sale of the college to Capita would achieve value for money for the public purse and secure the future of the college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that we are making real progress in securing the future of such an important facility. It is vital for the development of the Fire Service College that we put it on a sound footing, giving the private sector a chance to provide innovation and investment that will guarantee the future of a world-class asset.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure best value for money for taxpayers and enable the college to continue in its role, a number of conditions will be imposed on the proposed sale. These include commitments that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the college be preserved as a national training centre for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will continue to offer wider national resilience and emergency services training and exercises&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;government permission will be required if Capita wish to sell the incident ground&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councillor Kay Hammond, Chair of the Local Government Association’s fire services management committee, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is good news that government has listened to the views of the sector about the future of the Fire Service College and that it now looks set to get the outside investment it so badly needs. The Local Government Association and fire authorities will be keen to work with the future owners to help them transform the college into a first-class training facility fit for firefighters in the 21st century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association President, Vij Randeniya, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Chief Fire Officers’ Association welcomes the news that Capita has been selected. It has been a long and intensive process and we are glad that there is now clarity for the Fire Service College. We look forward to working closely with Capita to ensure that the very best provision is available for UK fire and rescue services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government now looks forward to holding constructive discussions with Capita to ensure that the transition from public to private sector is as smooth as possible and expects to complete the sale early in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Service College is a trading fund and executive agency of the department. Since becoming a trading fund in 1992, it has never been able to pay a dividend out of operating profits. The government’s response to Fire Futures on 12 April 2011 concluded that the college could achieve its full potential only if there was greater involvement from other sectors in its ownership, operation and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Options project considered 4 options for the future of the college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the status quo: the college remains as a trading fund of the department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a government owned contractor operated model: the assets remain under government ownership but management of the college is taken over by a private sector company under a long term contract, together with the staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disposal as a going concern: the college is sold to a private sector company who would continue to operate the college as a training centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closure: the college’s activities cease, staff are made redundant and the site is sold for an alternative use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the 4 options showed disposal as a going concern to be the best option, and the only one which both removes from government ongoing financial risks of ownership of the college and preserves a national training college for the fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers announced on 22 March 2012 that the Fire Service College would be sold as a going concern to a private sector company to continue operating as a training centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale process was launched on 10 April 2012 and the due diligence phase concluded in October with the receipt of final bids. Best and final offers were received in November. The aim is to complete the sale in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56085</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-10-2012-immediate"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 10/2012 immediate</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 is issued for the immediate attention of fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the announcement of the preferred bidder for the Fire Service College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/62269</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:30:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-statistics-great-britain-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Fire statistics Great Britain 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Data on incidents attended by fire and rescue services across Great Britain.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annual bulletin presenting detailed statistics on fires, casualties and false alarms attended by fire and rescue services across Great Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulletin includes analysis of the causes of fires, casualties and smoke alarms ownership and function. Trends over time are shown, together with a breakdown of incidents by type of property and geographical location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17621</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T10:24:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-28-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 28/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consultation on proposed increases to employee pension contribution rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;departmental response to the consultation on amendments to the new Firefighters’ Pension Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update on the funding arrangements for localising support for council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government’s policy statement on business rates retention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of operational guidance and generic risk assessments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/62735</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T09:43:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-schemes-membership-data-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Firefighters' pension schemes membership data England, 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Membership information on firefighters’ pension schemes in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release provides membership information on the firefighters’ pension schemes submitted by all 46 fire authorities in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescues from lifts and escalators to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
