<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Establishing stability in Afghanistan"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T10:53:03+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56544</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:53:03+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:53:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-nato-support-crucial-to-building-afghan-forces"/>
    <title>Liam Fox: NATO support crucial to building Afghan forces</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He confirmed Afghanistan as the highest foreign policy priority of the new British Coalition Government, and the top priority for the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the last day of his first NATO meeting in Brussels, Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Government supports both the mission and the counter-insurgency strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I encourage allies to demonstrate strategic patience and give time for the counter-insurgency strategy to work, but stress the need to be able to show significant progress, consolidating ISAF’s hold in central Helmand, and accelerating the training of the Afghan security forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to step up our approach to communicating the vital importance of the mission in Afghanistan. We need to produce a stronger narrative alongside the political leadership we are providing to ensure that our troops get the support they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that the NATO Training Mission is key to ISAF’s strategy for transition, to ensure the Afghans can take the lead in securing their own country in future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General McChrystal told this meeting that the Afghan National Security Forces [ANSF] are making quick progress in terms of training, but we still have some way to go in terms of improving the Afghan National Police and getting the numbers and quality of training up to the level we require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the vital role of the training mission. We will assess whether we can contribute more and urge others to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let me be direct: we are aware of the difficulties that some countries face in sending combat troops - politically and even constitutionally. However, there is no excuse for any country here not to send trainers to the Afghan mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we fail in the NATO Training Mission it will signify a lack of political will and a failure of moral resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to ensure we can build up that critical mass of the ANSF, so that when we do leave Afghanistan, we leave behind a secure country, and not a security vacuum. There is a moral duty on every member of NATO to contribute to that training mission, and that’s the message I give to our NATO partners today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5594/Liam_Fox-_NATO_support_crucial_to_building_Afghan_forces_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels [Picture: NATO, 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox welcomed progress that is beginning to be made on planning for transition, in advance of the Kabul Conference in July:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important to ensure that both ISAF contributors and the Government of Afghanistan are involved in developing the plan for transition and that the process should be transparent, allowing ISAF partners to communicate progress towards transition to domestic audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Security criteria should be the most important in assessing readiness for transition. Though some level of governance and development is essential for delivering security, we must not set the bar too high. Governance and development efforts will continue through and beyond transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also reaffirmed that NATO remains the most important strategic relationship for the United Kingdom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NATO is the core of the security and defence of all its members, on both sides of the Atlantic. It is the UK’s instrument of first resort for collective security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why NATO remains so important and so successful is its ability to change as risks and threats evolve. Afghanistan is one example of a task that would have been inconceivable a decade ago. Then the alliance was being told to go out of area or out of business. Today, it is very much in business but facing even greater challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that NATO has primacy in terms of Europe’s security and the starting point should be that the EU only acts militarily when NATO cannot or chooses not to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I recognise, of course, that there will be occasions when it is appropriate for the EU to intervene but the EU should avoid duplicating the functions NATO already performs and the capabilities it already possesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In today’s economic climate, the last thing any Defence Minister needs to put to his or her Finance Minister or Generals is a case for militarily unnecessary duplication. NATO and the EU need the strongest possible links and what matters most is what works best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox expressed concern over the state of NATO’s finances but said that he was encouraged by the Secretary General’s report to members which made it clear that much has been done to bring these under proper control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During two days of meetings in NATO Headquarters, Defence Ministers discussed NATO reform, resources, capabilities and missile defence, and met in ISAF and KFOR formats to discuss Afghanistan and Kosovo. There were also meetings of the NATO-Ukraine Commission, the NATO-Georgia Commission and the Nuclear Planning Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the margins of the formal meetings, Dr Fox met the NATO Secretary General and the Defence Ministers of the Czech Republic, Estonia, Norway, Denmark, Poland, the Netherlands, France, Afghanistan, Canada, Turkey, Portugal, Latvia, Australia, the United States and Hungary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56704</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:33:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/scots-guards-home-after-handover-to-afghan-forces"/>
    <title>Scots Guards home after handover to Afghan forces</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 50 Guardsmen from the Right Flank of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23989.aspx" title="1st Battalion Scots Guards"&gt;1st Battalion Scots Guards&lt;/a&gt; have returned to their barracks in Catterick, North Yorkshire, as the checkpoints they manned have been closed and the Afghan National Civil Order Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt;) are now taking responsibility for security in Helmand’s Upper Gereshk Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scots Guards are serving with Task Force Helmand, currently led by the British Army’s &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, known as ‘The Black Rats’, and the Right Flank form part of the first 500 British troops to be sent home from Afghanistan as announced by the Prime Minister last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The troops were based at Checkpoints ‘Barcha’ and ‘Pan Kalay’ and Observation Post ‘Tegha’ in the Upper Gereshk Valley - the northernmost area of operations for Task Force Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guardsmen have been working alongside the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt; to bring security and allow freedom of movement for traffic on Route 611, the main road between Sangin and Gereshk, but that job has been successfully handed over to the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Sayed Farid, the new Afghan Commander from the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s 5th Brigade taking over from the Scots Guards in Pan Kalay, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe all the Afghan forces are now well-equipped, well-armed and ready to take on the security of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since we have been here we have some really good relations with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="Afghanistan International Security Assistance Force"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; forces. They have really helped us out. We are only sad because our friends are leaving. They did their part of the job and we did ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Guardsman Alan Primrose " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5529/AMOCCCT-2012-240-295g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Guardsman Alan Primrose on board an RAF C-17 Globemaster aircraft at Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Platoon Commander Second Lieutenant James Westlake, attached to the Right Flank from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24680.aspx" title="Honourable Artillery Company"&gt;Honourable Artillery Company&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was quite apparent to everyone in the platoon, not just higher up, that the job is done. The time is right to be going back and the Afghan forces in those locations are ready to take over - there is just not a job for us to do by staying there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So everybody is satisfied that it is a job well done and, once you take that into account, everybody is looking forward to getting back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The checkpoints and observation post are the first on the main 611 highway in Task Force Helmand’s area of operations to be closed. During the closure process, the facilities were removed and the bases reduced to a more basic level for the few troops that remained until the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follwing some leave, the Scots Guards will be responsible for providing support to the battle groups deploying to Afghanistan in April 2013, when the Guardsmen will be reunited with the rest of the battalion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister announced last year that 500 British personnel would be withdrawn from Afghanistan by the end of 2012, reflecting the continuing progress in Helmand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown is consistent with the process of transition to Afghan forces agreed by &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; nations at Lisbon in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has emphasised the UK’s commitment to Afghanistan for the long term, pledging £70 million per annum in funding for the Afghan security forces, in addition to the taking the lead in setting up an Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy in Kabul after the combat mission ends in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56573</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:19:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/soldiers-offer-ground-expertise-to-aerial-assets-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Soldiers offer ground expertise to aerial assets in Afghanistan </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Army &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/equipment/aircraft/1531.aspx" title="Apache"&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt; helicopters are often called upon to neutralise enemy threats, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; plays an equally important role with their impressive fleet of fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fearsome aerial assets fly out of Kandahar and, although the pilots and support crew are based well outside &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/" title="British Army"&gt;Army&lt;/a&gt; circles, they have direct access to all things green courtesy of skilled ground liaison officers (GLOs) who are embedded within their squadrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such personnel act as a link between the 2 Services to ensure those in the air have a clear understanding of the situation below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/tornado.cfm" title="Tornado GR4"&gt;Tornado&lt;/a&gt; Force’s War Week exercise at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/" title="RAF Marham"&gt;RAF Marham&lt;/a&gt;, Captain James Perring of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/24651.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about taking everything that is happening on the ground and translating that into basic speak for the aircrew. They have no idea about the situation on the ground so we talk them through the process. I get involved with anything that is Army-related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to give as much information as possible so when they are up in the sky they know where people are and what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring is now on a four-month deployment with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/9squadron.cfm" title="9 Squadron"&gt;9 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; in Afghanistan and the serviceman was quick to highlight the differences between his roles with the RAF and Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ground Liaison Officer"&gt;GLO&lt;/abbr&gt; is a posting I applied for and is something completely different. I had no idea or appreciation of how air assets work so it has given me great insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is going to be an interesting tour and in a way I will have a greater understanding of the bigger picture in Afghanistan compared to spending 6 months on foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5427/tornadosg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring joined the Tornado Force for the War Week exercise at RAF Marham [Picture: Graeme Main, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working with the RAF has been a bit of a culture shock. Sometimes the bureaucracy can be frustrating but it works for them and it is like that for a reason. It has been hard to adjust but there are positives to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring was not the only soldier involved in War Week. Major Jeremy Higgins of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/23445.aspx" title="Royal Artillery"&gt;Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, a reservist who is a director for Cross Country Trains, was also on hand to offer expert advice and guidance from an Army perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise is designed to test personnel on the scenarios they are likely to face in theatre and the officer was determined to add as much realism as possible. Major Higgins said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to ensure the aircrew get the training they need ahead of the deployment, while tying in with other agencies such as forward air controllers. It is about orchestrating different elements in the air and on the ground so when the jets go out they get the training they require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will be talking to troops in the field beforehand, asking what they need and what they are trying to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The aircrew also highlight the areas they want to work on, such as night missions, and the soldiers come up with different scenarios for them. Effectively we have two serials feeding into one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a close link between the two forces, GLOs are mindful of not overloading their airborne colleagues with unfamiliar Army tactics and thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just UK personnel who benefit from the support offered by the Tornado crews. Major Higgins explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Preparing a Tornado for take off" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5428/tornados3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;RAF personnel preparing a Tornado for take off at Kandahar Airfield (library image) [Picture: Corporal Andy Benson RAF, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It can be quite challenging as we cover the whole of Afghanistan and can be allocated anywhere. It is an international role and we have to get information from soldiers who do not have English as their first language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We give the aircrews some situational awareness and that can be quite important due to the various forces we work with. They have different kit, depending on what they are doing, so a footprint of life on the ground is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Toyota Hilux with guys in the back could be perceived as being the enemy, but it may also be local allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about adding value in any way we can. We may be asked simple questions or ones that completely floor us. We interact with land troops to get a picture of what they want from the fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand for aerial assets is inevitably strong as soldiers maintain the Army’s operational tempo and such requests mean the RAF are on high alert during the training cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Lisa Foy, the acting officer in command of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/aboutus/opswg.cfm" title="RAF Marham - Operations Wing"&gt;RAF Marham’s Operations Wing&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is always more demand than we can meet but we strive to match the requirements from Land whenever possible. We want to benefit the personnel on exercise while training the Tornado crews as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise that the Force needs to train with soldiers and War Week is the perfect opportunity to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A lot of 9 Squadron’s training during this phase has been provided by the Army, and GLOs are critical in bringing everything together. Our expertise is in the air and these guys form a crucial link with the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report by Richard Long is taken from the December 2012 edition of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/soldier-magazine/soldier-magazine.aspx" title="Soldier magazine"&gt;Soldier&lt;/a&gt; - the magazine of the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56728</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:23:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:23:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-the-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet the Millies heroes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the rest of this week we’ll be bringing you interviews with some of the winners and their celebrity presenters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="true-grit-award"&gt;True Grit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wounded in a Taliban blast, hero soldier Corporal Oliver Kennedy battled through his own pain to help injured comrades. Corporal Kennedy, from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23994.aspx" title="The Princess of   Wales's Royal Regiment"&gt;Princess of Wales’s Royal Regiment&lt;/a&gt;, suffered deep shrapnel wounds when his platoon was hit in October 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He credited his training for ‘kicking in’ and he was quickly back on his feet pulling the wounded to safety. His actions, later described as ‘exemplary’, saw two men survive their life-threatening injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David Jason and ‘Spooks’ star Hermione Norris handed the True Grit Award to Corporal Kennedy who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;II just cracked on and carried on. I was shocked to win as my category was so strong and was lost for words but I’m so honoured to be nominated let alone win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backstage at the ceremony, Hermione Norris told Corporal Kennedy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s so admirable what you do to keep us safe and often goes unnoticed. It’s a huge privilege to be here to say thank you, show respect and celebrate what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hermione added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I find it overwhelming. I know quite a few people in the Army who have young families and the sacrifice that they make, the danger that they face and the humility of humanity to keep us all safe just takes my breath away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David Jason said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We know so little about the day-to-day work that these men and women do but it’s so important. I doubt that Mr and Mrs Average ever think about what these guys and girls do on our behalf but, without them, we’d be speaking German!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="most-outstanding-airman-award"&gt;Most Outstanding Airman Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christine Bleakley, Sergeant Roy Geddes and Frank Lampard" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4692/millies4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;From left: TV presenter Christine Bleakley, Sergeant Roy Geddes with his Outstanding Airman Award and Chelsea footballer Frank Lampard [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a Taliban death squad breached the walls of Camp Bastion, it was Sergeant Roy Geddes who led the defence. His heroic charge of the base is now dubbed the ‘Battle of Bastion’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Geddes from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/squadrons/51_sqn_history.cfm" title="51 Squadron Royal Air Force Regiment"&gt;51 Squadron Royal Air Force Regiment&lt;/a&gt; in Moray, led a band of men in September when 15 insurgents blew their way into the base, where Prince Harry was based at the time, killing 2 US Marines and destroying 6 US Harriers. Despite getting a painful lump of shrapnel in his knee, Sergeant Geddes fought on until the base was safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Geddes received the Most Outstanding Airman Award from TV presenter Christine Bleakley and Chelsea footballer Frank Lampard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second year running, Premiership and England star Frank joined the judges’ panel and had the tough task of helping to select the winners. He said that when he read the airman’s citation, he was instantly struck by his ‘quick-thinking’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Groups need leaders and Roy was certainly a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christine added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Roy is an extraordinary character, very unassuming, but when you hear the tale that he has to tell, you can’t quite believe it. He’s a very special man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look out for more Millies winners over the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56723</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-help-train-latest-batch-of-afghan-police-officers"/>
    <title>Royal Marines help train Afghan police</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trainees spent their final week of instruction receiving expert tuition on 40 Commando’s ranges at ‘HMS Price’, the hub of the Marines’ operation in Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dozen policemen graduated from the three-week course at a ceremony at District Police Headquarters in Gereshk attended by both their Afghan Uniform Police instructors and their International Security Assistance Force mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like other nations, Afghanistan has various police forces fulfilling various functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan Uniform Police, easily recognisable in Afghanistan by their gun-metal-blue uniforms, are the national law enforcement agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan Local Police, or &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt;, wear a khaki uniform and are a local police force drawn from the immediate area - much like community support officers in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Lee Piper, the &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt; Liaison Officer with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/40-Commando" title="40 Commando Royal Marines"&gt;40 Commando&lt;/a&gt;, explained the role of the newly-qualified officers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Afghan police training in Helmand" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4961/Afghan_police_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Afghan police training in Helmand [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These 12 Afghan Local Policemen completing training improves security because it will basically provide security for the local villagers. They have intimate knowledge of the local area for the Afghan National Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second graduation ceremony in the past month. Captain Kristian Hansen, the Afghan National Security Forces Development Officer with the Danish Army based at HMS Price, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It shows that training of the local police has come a long way. It’s now organised and taking place on a regular basis thus making the &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt; a better and more coherent security force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly-graduated officers will now man checkpoints in the south of the Nahr-e Saraj district of central Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their presence in the area is key to the improving security situation in the area, allowing British forces to hand over security responsibility for the area to the Afghan National Security Forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/55122</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:02:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-ministry-of-counter-narcotics-national-drug-control-strategy"/>
    <title>Afghanistan Ministry of Counter-Narcotics' National Drug Control Strategy </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the Afghan Government in implementing its National Drug Control Strategy. It is a comprehensive approach which covers a range of activities to counter the drugs trade. These include building government institutions and law enforcement capacity, targeted eradication programmes and the development of alternative livelihoods, information and education campaigns and engagement with countries in the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the attached updated five-year strategy for tackling the illicit drug problem in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/54865</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:52:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/government-publishes-afghanistan-progress-report"/>
    <title>Government publishes Afghanistan progress report </title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a written statement to parliament the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform the House that the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, together with the Ministry of Defence and the Department for International Development, is today publishing the twenty second progress report on developments in Afghanistan since November 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 9 October the UN Security Council adopted resolution 2069 (2012) extending the authorisation of the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan (ISAF) by a further year. The resolution provided a 12 month roll-over of the Chapter VII authorisation, with an unqualified “all necessary measures” provision. It also incorporated NATO Chicago Summit commitments to support the training, equipping, financing and capability development of the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF) up to and beyond 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Afghanistan held the first meeting of the Afghanistan-UK Joint Commission chaired by Afghanistan’s Deputy Foreign Minister Jawed Ludin and Baroness Warsi to review implementation of the Enduring Strategic Partnership document signed by President Karzai and the Prime Minister in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 25 October the International Development Committee (IDC) published its Afghanistan: Progress and Prospects after 2014 report. The Government welcomes this report. The Department for International Development will shortly publish a formal response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 31 October the Afghan Independent Election Commission (IEC) publicly announced that 5 April 2014 would be the date for the next Presidential Election in Afghanistan. The Provincial Council elections, postponed from 2013, will also take place on 5 April. As part of this announcement, the IEC published an ambitious timeline for the full electoral processes. Although the timeline as it stands does not cover the Parliamentary elections due in 2015, it effectively meets the Afghan commitment at the Tokyo Development Conference to produce a timeline by early 2013. An implementation plan is set to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October typically marks the end of the so called Afghan Summer fighting season. This time is used by insurgents to recuperate and plan. Overall the levels of violence are likely to decline, and in accordance with seasonal norms, we can expect the character of operations to change during the winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four members of UK Armed Forces lost their lives while deployed on operations in Afghanistan in October. The two separate incidents that caused these deaths were assessed to be the result of insider attacks. We take these attacks and their causes extremely seriously and we continue to work at the highest level to reduce the risk of insider attacks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of Afghanistan continued to progress plans for the privatisation of the New Kabul Bank. The first in a series of investor road shows took place in October. A road show in Dubai is planned for November. Tenders are being managed by the Afghan Ministry of Finance, Central Bank, and the Cabinet. The process aims to attract high quality investors. The New Kabul Bank is a commercially viable bank, with 550 million USD of deposits and over 100 branches across Afghanistan. As one of the largest banks in Afghanistan, its survival is important for economic development and jobs. The UK is supporting the Afghan Government with the sale of the Bank, thus promoting a transparent and effective process.&lt;br&gt;
I am placing the report in the Library of the House. It will also be published on the Foreign and Commonwealth Office website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-progress-reports" title="Afghanistan Progress Reports"&gt;Monthly progress reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British Embassy in Afghanistan &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinafghanistan.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Afghanistan"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54831</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:20:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-progress-reports"/>
    <title>Afghanistan: Progress reports</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary updates Parliament with a progress report every month as part of his commitment to keep Parliament regularly informed on developments in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/48782</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:40:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:40:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/light-dragoons-receive-afghanistan-medals"/>
    <title>Light Dragoons receive Afghanistan medals</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The medal parade was the last in a series of events marking the end off the Regiment’s deployment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Colonel of the Regiment, Major General Andrew Stewart, presented the campaign medals to the soldiers who have conducted homecoming parades in recent weeks in Barnsley, Newcastle and Dereham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicknamed ‘England’s Northern Cavalry’ this was the Regiment’s fourth tour of Afghanistan, having had Squadrons deployed in 2006, 2007 and 2009. Although a very successful tour, it was not without sacrifice and The Light Dragoons will always remember all those who died including Sergeant Lee Davidson who was Killed in Action on 9 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/26876.aspx" title="The Light Dragoons"&gt;The Light Dragoons&lt;/a&gt; have undertaken a number of different roles in Afghanistan. The soldiers from A Squadron acted as the eyes and ears of the Brigade. They also provided route security for convoys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D Squadron delivered training and mentoring support to the Afghan National Police Force and were later augmented by members of A Squadron. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Light Dragoons march through Dereham" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2654/16x-2012-119-0070g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The streets of Dereham came to a standstill on Wednesday 5 December as residents and businesses welcomed members of The Light Dragoons home from Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their fellow Light Dragoons sister unit, B Squadron, were The Brigade Reconnaissance Force (&lt;abbr title="Brigade Reconnaissance Force"&gt;BRF&lt;/abbr&gt;) who acted on military intelligence to remove key insurgency equipment and personnel from the area of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trooper Phil Burt and Sergeant Richardson who were part of the &lt;abbr title="Brigade Reconnaissance Force"&gt;BRF&lt;/abbr&gt; discovered a 50 calibre machine gun during one of their operations. Sgt Richardson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were preparing to clear a series of compounds when we saw a disturbance on the ground. The machine gun, nicknamed a Sushka, was covered with a sheet in a trench. It had been well maintained and had a box of ammo with it, so for us it was a great find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their six-month tour The Light Dragoons carried out some 248 operations, searched 1,700 Afghan compounds and discovered over three tonnes of Homemade Explosives and significant quantities of other bomb making equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the UK, C Squadron was the Rear Operations Group, ensuring that the families remaining behind were given the very best welfare support and ensuring that individual soldiers were fully prepared to deploy if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Large crowds in Derehm welcome The Light Dragoons " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2655/16x-2012-119-0013g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Large crowds, including family and friends of many of those marching, lined the route [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week the Regiment brought Central Norfolk to a standstill when thousands of people gathered on the streets of Dereham to welcome them home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shops closed and business came to a stand still as crowds, six people deep in places, waved flags and cheered as the proud soldiers marched through the streets. The Light Dragoons have been based in Swanton Morley near Dereham for the past 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the parade the Regiment attended a thanksgiving service at St Nicholas Church. Trooper Craig Hoe from Hull said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have had wonderful support at all of our homecoming parades. It’s great to know we have such support from the local community here where we are based and also back home in our recruiting areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The medal parade was also great; it has to the next best thing after my Pass Off Parade. I’m now looking forward to having some time off and enjoying some of my mam’s cooking. I’ve really missed that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/43712</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T16:09:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prince-of-wales-welcomes-homes-welsh-guards-from-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prince of Wales welcomes homes Welsh Guards from Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.princeofwales.gov.uk/" title="The Prince of Wales"&gt;The Prince of Wales&lt;/a&gt;, who is Colonel of the Welsh Guards, visited the battalion at Cavalry Barracks in Hounslow to present Operational Service Medals and meet battalion members and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 350 members of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/10757.aspx" title="1st Battalion Welsh Guards"&gt;1st Battalion Welsh Guards&lt;/a&gt; lined up on parade to be greeted by their Colonel, who welcomed them home and congratulated them on their achievements on Operation HERRICK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battalion served in Afghanistan from March to October 2012, carrying out a range of duties in various locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, the Prince also presented Elizabeth Crosses in a private ceremony to the families of those killed in Afghanistan. Tragically, 3 members of the battalion were killed in action, as well as 2 attached personnel, one of them from the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanking the Prince for his close interest in the battalion and taking the time to visit them, Commanding Officer Lieutenant Colonel Dino Bossi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1746/LOND-2012-244-127.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales welcomes home members of the 1st Battalion Welsh Guards from their recent tour of Afghanistan [Picture: Sergeant Adrian Harlen, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are enormously pleased and proud to have our Colonel, His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales, with us today to present the hard-won Afghanistan medals to the battalion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very fortunate to maintain such close links with His Royal Highness and grateful for the support and assistance he was able to give us while we were away, especially his care and attention towards our bereaved families and those of us who were wounded in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is a fitting culmination to our HERRICK 16 experience and one that will be remembered by the battalion and our families for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Thursday’s medal parade followed a ‘welcome home’ reception 2 days before when, following a march through Hounslow, the battalion was hosted by the London Borough of Hounslow, led by the Leader of the Council, Councillor Jagdish Sharma. The battalion has also recently exercised their Freedom of Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
