<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Establishing stability in Afghanistan"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60310</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/david-cameron-visits-troops-in-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>David Cameron visits troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Prime Minister praised armed forces success during visit to Camp Bastion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister flew into Afghanistan yesterday morning, 20 December. He visited Camp Bastion, where he met with military commanders before joining troops for an early Christmas dinner and a carol service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s visit came a day after he told &lt;abbr title="Members of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Parliament that troop numbers will almost halve to around 5,200 by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron meets troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5805/PMmeetstroops.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;David Cameron visits Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told journalists on the trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is still a difficult and dangerous place but we’ve made real progress. It is tough, it is difficult, and we’ve paid a high price but their efforts have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander Task Force Helmand, reiterated confidence in the growing capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is now absolutely appropriate we hand more and more control over to the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Cameron met troops who he praised for their service in Afghanistan and thanked them for making the country “prouder than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a message to the armed forces, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well it is a good time to come to Afghanistan and say a really big thank you to our troops for everything they do, and particularly at Christmas time when they’re away from loved ones.  But I think it’s an opportunity to say to all our forces all over the world…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You make us incredibly proud; we’re always proud of you, and this year perhaps prouder than ever for your extraordinary work in Afghanistan, for the amazing things you do over the whole of Africa to keep us safe from terrorism and piracy, for the extraordinary things you did at the Olympics where the military stepped up, put a smiling face on the greatest show on earth, won a lot of medals too and made the country very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military really are the best of the best and we can’t thank them enough for what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60044</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-announces-reduction-in-uk-troop-numbers-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prime Minister announces reduction in UK troop numbers in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK force levels in Afghanistan are to reduce to around 5,200 by the end of 2013, the Prime Minister announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="Number 10"&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt; told &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/" title="UK Parliament"&gt;Parliament&lt;/a&gt; that UK forces would shift from mentoring Afghan troops at battalion level to brigade level next year. This reflects the progress made in Helmand and the increasing ability and confidence of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;) to lead security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown, agreed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-security-council" title="National Security Council"&gt;National Security Council&lt;/a&gt; this week, is in line and consistent with both UK military advice and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;North Atlantic Treaty Organization&lt;/a&gt; strategy agreed at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/events_66529.htm" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization Summit, Lisbon 2010"&gt;Lisbon Summit in 2010&lt;/a&gt;, under which &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) forces continue to operate across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK forces will end combat operations by the end of 2014. It is part of transition to an enduring commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement comes as the previously announced reduction of UK force levels from 9,500 to 9,000 is being achieved with service personnel due to arrive home in time for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed work on how force levels will reduce in 2013 is ongoing and will be conducted in line with operational requirements and the transition process which remains on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Afghan forces increasingly take the lead, UK combat operations will give way to an increasing focus on training and advising. By the end of 2013, it is expected that UK forces will not routinely need to mentor Afghan forces below brigade level, allowing the reduction in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real progress being made on the ground in Helmand province will allow us, on current planning, to reduce British troops to around 5,200 by the end of 2013. This is a direct result of the success of the Afghan National Security Forces in assuming a lead role in delivering security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The phased process of transition of security responsibility agreed at the Lisbon Summit is well advanced and on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have consistently said that there will not be a cliff-edge reduction in troop numbers at the end of 2014. This gradual drawdown is firmly in line with the planning of our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; partners and the advice of military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces will continue to operate alongside their Afghan counterparts, albeit in lower numbers, until our combat operations cease at the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There remain huge challenges ahead for the Afghan people. Our combat mission is drawing to a close, but our commitment to the Afghan people is long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Afghan National Army" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5775/JMOCCCT-2012-014_Op_Horhari_Afghan_004.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Afghan National Army take part in an operation in Helmand province (stock image) [Picture: Sergeant Steve Blake RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir David Richards, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Army and Police have greatly improved in the past years. Their capability has increased so that today they enjoy the trust of some 84 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As they develop, and in agreement with the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, the efforts of our Armed Forces will continue to shift from a combat role to one that focuses on training, advice and assistance. That will allow us to make appropriate and measured reductions in our force levels in line with the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; plan and our Chicago commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These drawdown plans are based on military advice and following discussion with General Allen [Commander &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces]. I am confident that the progress we have seen in Helmand and across Afghanistan can be maintained and that we can complete the tasks we have been set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be in the position where we are now able to commit to reducing UK force levels to around 5,200 by the end of next year is testament to the professionalism and courage of those personnel who have served, and continue to serve, in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We must remember that the UK’s commitment to the operation in Afghanistan will continue beyond the end of 2014 as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/" title="Department for International Development"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [Department for International Development] and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign Office&lt;/a&gt; continue to build the government and nation while the UK’s pledge to support the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, including training the military’s officers, will be ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significant progress in Afghanistan continues with 75% of the Afghan population now being secured by the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; and at least 80% of all patrols being &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;-led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 80 UK bases at the start of the HERRICK 16 deployment this April, only 32 remain active with the others having been handed over to Afghan forces or closed. Afghan National Army numbers in Helmand province now stand at about 18,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56544</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:53:03+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:53:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-nato-support-crucial-to-building-afghan-forces"/>
    <title>Liam Fox: NATO support crucial to building Afghan forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Secretary of State for Defence, Dr Liam Fox, has welcomed the rapid progress in training the Afghan National Security Forces, and the role of the NATO Training Mission in Afghanistan, but insisted that NATO allies still need to up their game.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He confirmed Afghanistan as the highest foreign policy priority of the new British Coalition Government, and the top priority for the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the last day of his first NATO meeting in Brussels, Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Government supports both the mission and the counter-insurgency strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I encourage allies to demonstrate strategic patience and give time for the counter-insurgency strategy to work, but stress the need to be able to show significant progress, consolidating ISAF’s hold in central Helmand, and accelerating the training of the Afghan security forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to step up our approach to communicating the vital importance of the mission in Afghanistan. We need to produce a stronger narrative alongside the political leadership we are providing to ensure that our troops get the support they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that the NATO Training Mission is key to ISAF’s strategy for transition, to ensure the Afghans can take the lead in securing their own country in future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General McChrystal told this meeting that the Afghan National Security Forces [ANSF] are making quick progress in terms of training, but we still have some way to go in terms of improving the Afghan National Police and getting the numbers and quality of training up to the level we require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the vital role of the training mission. We will assess whether we can contribute more and urge others to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let me be direct: we are aware of the difficulties that some countries face in sending combat troops - politically and even constitutionally. However, there is no excuse for any country here not to send trainers to the Afghan mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we fail in the NATO Training Mission it will signify a lack of political will and a failure of moral resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to ensure we can build up that critical mass of the ANSF, so that when we do leave Afghanistan, we leave behind a secure country, and not a security vacuum. There is a moral duty on every member of NATO to contribute to that training mission, and that’s the message I give to our NATO partners today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5594/Liam_Fox-_NATO_support_crucial_to_building_Afghan_forces_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels [Picture: NATO, 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox welcomed progress that is beginning to be made on planning for transition, in advance of the Kabul Conference in July:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important to ensure that both ISAF contributors and the Government of Afghanistan are involved in developing the plan for transition and that the process should be transparent, allowing ISAF partners to communicate progress towards transition to domestic audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Security criteria should be the most important in assessing readiness for transition. Though some level of governance and development is essential for delivering security, we must not set the bar too high. Governance and development efforts will continue through and beyond transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also reaffirmed that NATO remains the most important strategic relationship for the United Kingdom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NATO is the core of the security and defence of all its members, on both sides of the Atlantic. It is the UK’s instrument of first resort for collective security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why NATO remains so important and so successful is its ability to change as risks and threats evolve. Afghanistan is one example of a task that would have been inconceivable a decade ago. Then the alliance was being told to go out of area or out of business. Today, it is very much in business but facing even greater challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that NATO has primacy in terms of Europe’s security and the starting point should be that the EU only acts militarily when NATO cannot or chooses not to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I recognise, of course, that there will be occasions when it is appropriate for the EU to intervene but the EU should avoid duplicating the functions NATO already performs and the capabilities it already possesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In today’s economic climate, the last thing any Defence Minister needs to put to his or her Finance Minister or Generals is a case for militarily unnecessary duplication. NATO and the EU need the strongest possible links and what matters most is what works best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox expressed concern over the state of NATO’s finances but said that he was encouraged by the Secretary General’s report to members which made it clear that much has been done to bring these under proper control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During two days of meetings in NATO Headquarters, Defence Ministers discussed NATO reform, resources, capabilities and missile defence, and met in ISAF and KFOR formats to discuss Afghanistan and Kosovo. There were also meetings of the NATO-Ukraine Commission, the NATO-Georgia Commission and the Nuclear Planning Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the margins of the formal meetings, Dr Fox met the NATO Secretary General and the Defence Ministers of the Czech Republic, Estonia, Norway, Denmark, Poland, the Netherlands, France, Afghanistan, Canada, Turkey, Portugal, Latvia, Australia, the United States and Hungary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56704</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:33:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/scots-guards-home-after-handover-to-afghan-forces"/>
    <title>Scots Guards home after handover to Afghan forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Soldiers from the Scots Guards have returned home from Afghanistan after handing security in their area of Helmand over to Afghan forces.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 50 Guardsmen from the Right Flank of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23989.aspx" title="1st Battalion Scots Guards"&gt;1st Battalion Scots Guards&lt;/a&gt; have returned to their barracks in Catterick, North Yorkshire, as the checkpoints they manned have been closed and the Afghan National Civil Order Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt;) are now taking responsibility for security in Helmand’s Upper Gereshk Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scots Guards are serving with Task Force Helmand, currently led by the British Army’s &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, known as ‘The Black Rats’, and the Right Flank form part of the first 500 British troops to be sent home from Afghanistan as announced by the Prime Minister last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The troops were based at Checkpoints ‘Barcha’ and ‘Pan Kalay’ and Observation Post ‘Tegha’ in the Upper Gereshk Valley - the northernmost area of operations for Task Force Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guardsmen have been working alongside the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt; to bring security and allow freedom of movement for traffic on Route 611, the main road between Sangin and Gereshk, but that job has been successfully handed over to the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Sayed Farid, the new Afghan Commander from the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Civil Order Police"&gt;ANCOP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s 5th Brigade taking over from the Scots Guards in Pan Kalay, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe all the Afghan forces are now well-equipped, well-armed and ready to take on the security of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since we have been here we have some really good relations with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="Afghanistan International Security Assistance Force"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; forces. They have really helped us out. We are only sad because our friends are leaving. They did their part of the job and we did ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Guardsman Alan Primrose " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5529/AMOCCCT-2012-240-295g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Guardsman Alan Primrose on board an RAF C-17 Globemaster aircraft at Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Platoon Commander Second Lieutenant James Westlake, attached to the Right Flank from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24680.aspx" title="Honourable Artillery Company"&gt;Honourable Artillery Company&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was quite apparent to everyone in the platoon, not just higher up, that the job is done. The time is right to be going back and the Afghan forces in those locations are ready to take over - there is just not a job for us to do by staying there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So everybody is satisfied that it is a job well done and, once you take that into account, everybody is looking forward to getting back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The checkpoints and observation post are the first on the main 611 highway in Task Force Helmand’s area of operations to be closed. During the closure process, the facilities were removed and the bases reduced to a more basic level for the few troops that remained until the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follwing some leave, the Scots Guards will be responsible for providing support to the battle groups deploying to Afghanistan in April 2013, when the Guardsmen will be reunited with the rest of the battalion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister announced last year that 500 British personnel would be withdrawn from Afghanistan by the end of 2012, reflecting the continuing progress in Helmand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown is consistent with the process of transition to Afghan forces agreed by &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; nations at Lisbon in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has emphasised the UK’s commitment to Afghanistan for the long term, pledging £70 million per annum in funding for the Afghan security forces, in addition to the taking the lead in setting up an Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy in Kabul after the combat mission ends in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56573</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:19:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/soldiers-offer-ground-expertise-to-aerial-assets-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Soldiers offer ground expertise to aerial assets in Afghanistan </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>When ground troops find themselves in trouble on the front line they have the reassurance of knowing that help is invariably close at hand.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Army &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/equipment/aircraft/1531.aspx" title="Apache"&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt; helicopters are often called upon to neutralise enemy threats, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; plays an equally important role with their impressive fleet of fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fearsome aerial assets fly out of Kandahar and, although the pilots and support crew are based well outside &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/" title="British Army"&gt;Army&lt;/a&gt; circles, they have direct access to all things green courtesy of skilled ground liaison officers (GLOs) who are embedded within their squadrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such personnel act as a link between the 2 Services to ensure those in the air have a clear understanding of the situation below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/tornado.cfm" title="Tornado GR4"&gt;Tornado&lt;/a&gt; Force’s War Week exercise at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/" title="RAF Marham"&gt;RAF Marham&lt;/a&gt;, Captain James Perring of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/24651.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about taking everything that is happening on the ground and translating that into basic speak for the aircrew. They have no idea about the situation on the ground so we talk them through the process. I get involved with anything that is Army-related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to give as much information as possible so when they are up in the sky they know where people are and what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring is now on a four-month deployment with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/9squadron.cfm" title="9 Squadron"&gt;9 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; in Afghanistan and the serviceman was quick to highlight the differences between his roles with the RAF and Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ground Liaison Officer"&gt;GLO&lt;/abbr&gt; is a posting I applied for and is something completely different. I had no idea or appreciation of how air assets work so it has given me great insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is going to be an interesting tour and in a way I will have a greater understanding of the bigger picture in Afghanistan compared to spending 6 months on foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5427/tornadosg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Major Jeremy Higgins (left) and Captain James Perring joined the Tornado Force for the War Week exercise at RAF Marham [Picture: Graeme Main, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working with the RAF has been a bit of a culture shock. Sometimes the bureaucracy can be frustrating but it works for them and it is like that for a reason. It has been hard to adjust but there are positives to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Perring was not the only soldier involved in War Week. Major Jeremy Higgins of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/23445.aspx" title="Royal Artillery"&gt;Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, a reservist who is a director for Cross Country Trains, was also on hand to offer expert advice and guidance from an Army perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise is designed to test personnel on the scenarios they are likely to face in theatre and the officer was determined to add as much realism as possible. Major Higgins said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are trying to ensure the aircrew get the training they need ahead of the deployment, while tying in with other agencies such as forward air controllers. It is about orchestrating different elements in the air and on the ground so when the jets go out they get the training they require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will be talking to troops in the field beforehand, asking what they need and what they are trying to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The aircrew also highlight the areas they want to work on, such as night missions, and the soldiers come up with different scenarios for them. Effectively we have two serials feeding into one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a close link between the two forces, GLOs are mindful of not overloading their airborne colleagues with unfamiliar Army tactics and thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just UK personnel who benefit from the support offered by the Tornado crews. Major Higgins explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Preparing a Tornado for take off" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5428/tornados3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;RAF personnel preparing a Tornado for take off at Kandahar Airfield (library image) [Picture: Corporal Andy Benson RAF, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It can be quite challenging as we cover the whole of Afghanistan and can be allocated anywhere. It is an international role and we have to get information from soldiers who do not have English as their first language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We give the aircrews some situational awareness and that can be quite important due to the various forces we work with. They have different kit, depending on what they are doing, so a footprint of life on the ground is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Toyota Hilux with guys in the back could be perceived as being the enemy, but it may also be local allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our role is about adding value in any way we can. We may be asked simple questions or ones that completely floor us. We interact with land troops to get a picture of what they want from the fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand for aerial assets is inevitably strong as soldiers maintain the Army’s operational tempo and such requests mean the RAF are on high alert during the training cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Lisa Foy, the acting officer in command of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/aboutus/opswg.cfm" title="RAF Marham - Operations Wing"&gt;RAF Marham’s Operations Wing&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is always more demand than we can meet but we strive to match the requirements from Land whenever possible. We want to benefit the personnel on exercise while training the Tornado crews as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise that the Force needs to train with soldiers and War Week is the perfect opportunity to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A lot of 9 Squadron’s training during this phase has been provided by the Army, and GLOs are critical in bringing everything together. Our expertise is in the air and these guys form a crucial link with the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report by Richard Long is taken from the December 2012 edition of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/soldier-magazine/soldier-magazine.aspx" title="Soldier magazine"&gt;Soldier&lt;/a&gt; - the magazine of the British Army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56728</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:23:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:23:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-the-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet the Millies heroes</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Last week, The Sun newspaper honoured courageous servicemen and women at its fifth annual Military Awards ceremony.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the rest of this week we’ll be bringing you interviews with some of the winners and their celebrity presenters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="true-grit-award"&gt;True Grit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wounded in a Taliban blast, hero soldier Corporal Oliver Kennedy battled through his own pain to help injured comrades. Corporal Kennedy, from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23994.aspx" title="The Princess of   Wales's Royal Regiment"&gt;Princess of Wales’s Royal Regiment&lt;/a&gt;, suffered deep shrapnel wounds when his platoon was hit in October 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He credited his training for ‘kicking in’ and he was quickly back on his feet pulling the wounded to safety. His actions, later described as ‘exemplary’, saw two men survive their life-threatening injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David Jason and ‘Spooks’ star Hermione Norris handed the True Grit Award to Corporal Kennedy who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;II just cracked on and carried on. I was shocked to win as my category was so strong and was lost for words but I’m so honoured to be nominated let alone win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backstage at the ceremony, Hermione Norris told Corporal Kennedy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s so admirable what you do to keep us safe and often goes unnoticed. It’s a huge privilege to be here to say thank you, show respect and celebrate what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hermione added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I find it overwhelming. I know quite a few people in the Army who have young families and the sacrifice that they make, the danger that they face and the humility of humanity to keep us all safe just takes my breath away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David Jason said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We know so little about the day-to-day work that these men and women do but it’s so important. I doubt that Mr and Mrs Average ever think about what these guys and girls do on our behalf but, without them, we’d be speaking German!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="most-outstanding-airman-award"&gt;Most Outstanding Airman Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christine Bleakley, Sergeant Roy Geddes and Frank Lampard" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4692/millies4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;From left: TV presenter Christine Bleakley, Sergeant Roy Geddes with his Outstanding Airman Award and Chelsea footballer Frank Lampard [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a Taliban death squad breached the walls of Camp Bastion, it was Sergeant Roy Geddes who led the defence. His heroic charge of the base is now dubbed the ‘Battle of Bastion’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Geddes from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/squadrons/51_sqn_history.cfm" title="51 Squadron Royal Air Force Regiment"&gt;51 Squadron Royal Air Force Regiment&lt;/a&gt; in Moray, led a band of men in September when 15 insurgents blew their way into the base, where Prince Harry was based at the time, killing 2 US Marines and destroying 6 US Harriers. Despite getting a painful lump of shrapnel in his knee, Sergeant Geddes fought on until the base was safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Geddes received the Most Outstanding Airman Award from TV presenter Christine Bleakley and Chelsea footballer Frank Lampard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second year running, Premiership and England star Frank joined the judges’ panel and had the tough task of helping to select the winners. He said that when he read the airman’s citation, he was instantly struck by his ‘quick-thinking’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Groups need leaders and Roy was certainly a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christine added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Roy is an extraordinary character, very unassuming, but when you hear the tale that he has to tell, you can’t quite believe it. He’s a very special man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look out for more Millies winners over the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56723</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-help-train-latest-batch-of-afghan-police-officers"/>
    <title>Royal Marines help train Afghan police</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Marines have helped the latest batch of Afghan police officers complete their training in Helmand.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trainees spent their final week of instruction receiving expert tuition on 40 Commando’s ranges at ‘HMS Price’, the hub of the Marines’ operation in Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dozen policemen graduated from the three-week course at a ceremony at District Police Headquarters in Gereshk attended by both their Afghan Uniform Police instructors and their International Security Assistance Force mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like other nations, Afghanistan has various police forces fulfilling various functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan Uniform Police, easily recognisable in Afghanistan by their gun-metal-blue uniforms, are the national law enforcement agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan Local Police, or &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt;, wear a khaki uniform and are a local police force drawn from the immediate area - much like community support officers in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Lee Piper, the &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt; Liaison Officer with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/40-Commando" title="40 Commando Royal Marines"&gt;40 Commando&lt;/a&gt;, explained the role of the newly-qualified officers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Afghan police training in Helmand" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4961/Afghan_police_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Afghan police training in Helmand [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These 12 Afghan Local Policemen completing training improves security because it will basically provide security for the local villagers. They have intimate knowledge of the local area for the Afghan National Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second graduation ceremony in the past month. Captain Kristian Hansen, the Afghan National Security Forces Development Officer with the Danish Army based at HMS Price, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It shows that training of the local police has come a long way. It’s now organised and taking place on a regular basis thus making the &lt;abbr title="Afghan Local Police"&gt;ALP&lt;/abbr&gt; a better and more coherent security force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly-graduated officers will now man checkpoints in the south of the Nahr-e Saraj district of central Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their presence in the area is key to the improving security situation in the area, allowing British forces to hand over security responsibility for the area to the Afghan National Security Forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/55791</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:30:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-progress-reports"/>
    <title>Afghanistan: Progress reports</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary's monthly updates to Parliament on developments in Afghanistan.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary updates Parliament with a progress report every month as part of his commitment to keep Parliament regularly informed on developments in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/55122</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:02:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-ministry-of-counter-narcotics-national-drug-control-strategy"/>
    <title>Afghanistan Ministry of Counter-Narcotics' National Drug Control Strategy </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the Afghan Government in implementing its National Drug Control Strategy. It is a comprehensive approach which covers a range of activities to counter the drugs trade. These include building government institutions and law enforcement capacity, targeted eradication programmes and the development of alternative livelihoods, information and education campaigns and engagement with countries in the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the attached updated five-year strategy for tackling the illicit drug problem in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
