<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Helping troubled families turn their lives around"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56690</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/louise-casey-calls-for-family-intervention-approach"/>
    <title>Louise Casey calls for family intervention approach</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The head of the Troubled Families programme has endorsed family intervention as the most effective way to turn problem families around and help them get on in life.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a look at the academic evidence, alongside consultation with practitioners and families themselves, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/louise-casey"&gt;Louise Casey&lt;/a&gt; today published a new report that shows the life-changing results that good family intervention can have on even the most challenging households, along with a guide to best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;‘Working with Troubled Families’ report&lt;/a&gt; outlines that family intervention reduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involvement in anti-social behaviour by 59%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;involvement in crime by 45%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truancy, exclusion, bad behaviour at school by 52%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also points to the 5 key features of effective family intervention being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated worker, dedicated to a family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ‘hands on’ support &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a persistent, assertive and challenging approach &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;considering the family as a whole - gathering the intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common purpose and agreed action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey is now calling on councils to review their own ways of working with troubled families and adopt these principles in order to ensure that the significant momentum that has built up behind the programme - with all eligible local authorities in England on board and committed to working with over 40,000 families in this financial year - continues in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to push on with this work and make further progress towards the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015, the Department for Communities and Local Government will also be holding a series of training academies for local authorities in the new year to help share best practice on family intervention and provide masterclasses from some of its leading exponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the government’s Troubled Families programme Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My last report was about listening to troubled families themselves and some of the stories from families were truly appalling. However these were families successfully going through family intervention and the results were impressive - so I wanted to ensure that this practice is adopted as widely as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This report makes a strong case about what works - family intervention that involves one dedicated worker for each family, providing tough but persistent challenge and support, has a dramatic impact, not just on the life chances of those within the families, but on the communities around them who suffer from the effects of truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This important piece of work is a crucial step towards building a wide campaign of support behind the work we are doing to break an inter-generational cycle of misery and failure with these families. It will put rocket boosters under the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around 120,000 troubled families by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Effective family intervention also demonstrates that savings can be made for taxpayers by putting families back on the right track for the long run, rather than wasting money on simply reacting to their problems. We must have aspiration for every family and this work will reach all corners of the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Clare Tickell, Chief Executive of Action for Children, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since developing the initial model, we’ve seen how family intervention can really help vulnerable families facing multiple difficulties in their lives. It works by forming effective relationships with families and building on their strengths. This timely guide is a welcome resource, which will help people understand the key features of the model, learn what really works and ensure that projects are delivered to a high quality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;Working with Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"&gt;Listening to Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, July 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All eligible local authorities are running troubled families programmes in their area and between them have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is today also publishing management information on the work of family intervention projects and services in England up to 31 March 2012. This reports the latest data at a national level for all participating family intervention services. It includes information on the families worked with and the percentage of families considered to have a successful outcome in relation to family functioning and risk, crime/ anti-social behaviour, health and education/ employment. This data was collected by the National Centre for Social Research (NatCen) which ran a secure web-based information system into which family intervention project staff recorded details of the families they worked with between 2007-2012. It can be found at Annex B of the ‘Working With Troubled Families’ report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56541</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"/>
    <title>Working with Troubled Families: a guide to evidence and good practice</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities and their partners on how to work with troubled families.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a tool to help local authorities and their partners, who have asked for guidance on how best to work with troubled families, and for the evidence about family intervention to be brought together in one place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report looks at academic evidence, local evaluations of practice, what practitioners have told us works in their services and what families tell us makes this work different and successful for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14067</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/troubled-families-case-studies"/>
    <title>Troubled families case studies</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This document describes how families were helped in Sheffield, Bradford, Lancashire, Leeds and Norfolk. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work with family intervention projects can make a significant difference to families’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14717</id>
    <published>2012-10-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/troubled-families-programme-on-track"/>
    <title>Troubled families programme on track</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has today announced that the Government’s Troubled Families initiative is on track, with councils committed to start working with more than a third of families in the first year of a three-year programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge enthusiasm has been shown for the scheme - with all 152 upper-tier local authorities in England on board - and momentum is now building, with families beginning to be identified and worked with, staff appointed and services expanded in order to get children back into school, reduce youth crime and anti-social behaviour and put adults on a path back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles today confirmed that over 40,000 claims have been made for up-front ‘attachment fees’ worth over £100million as part of the groundbreaking payment-by-results programme. This means that - working with local authorities and other agencies - the Department for Communities and Local Government remains on schedule to meet the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that this programme is progressing so quickly as it is crucial to turning around the lives of families that have been untouched by the State for a generation or more and turning around communities that are blighted by the problems these families cause.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Up-front ‘attachment fees’ allow local services to be expanded and transformed in order to provide the joined-up and challenging approach we know is needed with these families, so it is good news that the Government has already paid out over £100million to allow this work to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However under our payment-by-results programme full payment will not be made unless and until our goals of reducing truancy, youth crime, anti-social behaviour and unemployment have been achieved, as well as reducing the costs these families cause to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the deal with local authorities, Government will pay councils up to £4,000 per eligible family if they reduce truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour or put parents back into work. The Government’s £448million three-year budget is drawn from across seven departments in a bid to join up local services dealing with these families on the frontline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Press Notice applies to England.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local authorities have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has paid out £111,577,600 in the first round of payment-by-results attachment fees, which will allow local authorities to move quickly to reorganise services and start working with families.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full details of the Troubled Families payment-by-results framework can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/troubledfamiliesframework"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/troubledfamiliesframework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As part of the framework all upper-tier authorities have agreed the number of families they will work with over the three years of the programme and in claiming attachment fees have now committed to the number they will begin work with in the current financial year. This represents a large increase in the scale of activity being undertaken and most of the work is expected to commence in the latter part of the year to allow for the necessary expansion of services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14701</id>
    <published>2012-09-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-and-louise-casey-address-troubled-families-co-ordinators"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles and Louise Casey address troubled families co-ordinators</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has told troubled families co-ordinators that they are at the vanguard of a revolution in social policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government on Tuesday brought co-ordinators from all 152 upper-tier local authorities in England to London for a major national conference on delivering the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families in the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2219460.jpg" alt=""&gt;Louise Casey and Eric Pickles speaking to troubled families co-ordinators&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosted by head of the troubled families programme Louise Casey, the conference looked at ways of working with some of the hardest to reach families in the country in order to reduce youth crime and anti-social behaviour, get children off the streets and into school; and put adults on a path back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Secretary of State Eric Pickles told the co-ordinators that David Cameron “is obsessed by this issue”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What I’m keen on - where you have small numbers of families ruining areas and estates - is not just saving money but saving people - these are lives unfulfilled. You coordinators are going to do challenging work. You will be my revolutionaries! You will be looking at problems of the household as a whole, not as individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Across the political spectrum there is angst and guilt at not having dealt with this before. But where it is really working we are already seeing results. But I’m in a hurry. And that’s because we need momentum. So that we can show the sceptics that there is another way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funded by DCLG, co-ordinators will oversee each upper-tier authority’s troubled families programme and targets, bringing local agencies such as health, housing, social services, education and the police together on the ground in order to tackle problems in a joined-up way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her keynote speech to the conference, Louise Casey called on co-ordinators to be assertive, authoritative and challenging, and argued that the fate of the programme was in their hands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve given quite a lot of speeches since I took this job in December, but I have to say that this is the most important speech, to the most important audience so far. That is because I’ve made a huge commitment - to turn around the lives of 120,000 families - and you are the people who will determine whether that commitment is fulfilled and ultimately whether the troubled families programme succeeds or fails. This is a job that, for all of us, is not for the faint hearted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As troubled families co-ordinators you will be at the forefront of this push to bring about real change in families’ lives - the ambition being that their children will be going to school, they won’t be committing crime and anti-social behaviour and they will no longer be costing vast amounts of money in everything from noise complaints to police call outs and care proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We can all see that something needs to give and we need to do things differently. We have to reduce the vast amounts we are spending right across public services on these families. Something has to give in terms of changing these families’ lives, but something also has to give if we’re going to reduce the resources these families absorb from your purse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2052185?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2052185?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14649</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/report-highlights-chaos-of-troubled-families-lives"/>
    <title>Report highlights chaos of troubled families' lives</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey CB has published a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/listeningtroubledfamilies"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; highlighting the chaotic personal histories of the kinds of families who will be targeted as part of the Government’s commitment to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report details stark real-life accounts from families, with experiences often passed from generation to generation, such as domestic and sexual abuse, teenage pregnancies, poor parenting, social care interventions, police call outs and educational failure. It also contains Louise Casey’s early conclusions that a whole-family approach is often best for dealing with multiple and inter-linked problems; rather than approaches that deal with single problems or single individuals within a household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key recurring themes highlighted in the report include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dysfunctional and unstable family structures;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;History repeating itself within families and between generations;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extended family and antisocial networks within communities which reinforce destructive behaviour; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The need for one assertive family worker who offers practical help and support but also sanction in dealing with families.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Head of Troubled Families Policy Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am not making excuses for any family failing to send their kids to school or causing trouble in their community. However unless we really understand what it is about these families that means they behave in this way, we can’t start to turn their lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Conducting these interviews has been an eye-opening experience - to hear first hand about the lives these families lead and the legacy of trouble that’s often been passed down to them. It’s clearer than ever to me now that we cannot go on allowing families to fail their children; none of the parents I spoke to wanted their children to repeat a life of chaos and trouble, but often they couldn’t see how to put things right by themselves - they needed practical and persistent help to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome this report as it provides a real insight into these families’ dysfunctional lives and highlights the urgent need to turn them around. The Troubled Families team in my department are not just sitting in an office in Whitehall telling local authorities what to do but seeking to gain a true understanding of the challenges they face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Troubled Families programme the Department for Communities and Local Government will pay upper-tier local authorities up to £4,000 per eligible family on a payment-by-results basis if they reduce truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour or put parents back into work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s £448m three-year budget is drawn from across seven departments in a bid to join up local services dealing with these families on the frontline. All 152 upper-tier authorities in England have committed to engaging in the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This News Release covers England.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listening to Troubled Families: A report by Louise Casey CB&lt;/em&gt; can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/listeningtroubledfamilies"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/listeningtroubledfamilies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reporting to Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government Eric Pickles, Louise Casey was tasked by the Prime Minister in November 2011 with leading local authorities to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Troubled Families are eligible for this programme if they have children regularly absent or excluded from school; cause high levels of youth crime and/or anti-social behaviour; claim out-of-work benefits; and/or incur high costs for local public services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turning a family around is defined as: Achieving more than 85 per cent attendance and fewer than three exclusions from school for children; A 60 per cent reduction in anti-social behaviour across the whole family and a 33 per cent reduction in youth offending; and progress towards work for adults such as enrolment in the Work Programme or the European Social Fund provision for troubled families; or one adult in the family moving off benefits and into work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Families were interviewed in person by Louise Casey and were sourced by six Local Authorities and family intervention services across England.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11449</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:32:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"/>
    <title>Listening to troubled families</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey, head of the troubled families programme, interviewed 16 troubled families for this report that starkly describes the problems families face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of carrying out the interviews was to listen directly to families about their lives, the problems they have experienced and caused and to begin to understand the sort of help that will enable them to really change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14605</id>
    <published>2012-06-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-hails-100-troubled-families-take-up"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles hails 100% troubled families take-up</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has welcomed the news that every eligible council has agreed to run the Government’s Troubled Families programme in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overwhelmingly positive response from upper-tier local authorities in England means that the Department for Communities and Local Government is on track to meet the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families in the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils have welcomed the payment by results model launched in March 2012 to get children off the streets and back into school; reduce youth crime and anti-social behaviour; and put adults on a path back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is great news that every upper-tier authority has agreed to run this programme in their area. The fast and unanimous level of take-up shows that the Government has got the confidence of local councils that together we can tackle a problem that councils have long grappled with. We cannot go on spending so much taxpayers’ money on such a small amount of families without turning their lives around once and for all. This programme is a unique opportunity to do so and I am delighted that every council has opted in.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We now have an opportunity to offer real and lasting change for these families and the communities around them. Everyone will benefit from getting kids off the streets and into school; getting parents off benefits and into work; and cutting youth crime and anti-social behaviour. But it is also right that we will only pay councils in full if they deliver the results that we require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that these families put a £9 billion drain on public spending, amounting to £75,000 per family per year, with £8 billion of this spent on reacting to, rather than getting to the root causes of their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s £448 million three-year budget is drawn from across seven departments in a bid to join up local services dealing with these families on the frontline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This press release covers England.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Framework Document for Troubled Families Funding can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/troubledfamiliesframework"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/communities/troubledfamiliesframework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The payment by results outcomes are:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;more than 85 per cent attendance in schools and fewer than three exclusions from school&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a 60 per cent reduction in anti-social behaviour across the whole family&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and a 33 per cent reduction in youth offending
Payment of £3,900 (in 2012/13)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;progress towards work such as referral and attachment to the Work Programme or the European Social Fund provision for troubled families
Payment of £100 (in 2012/13)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one adult in the family moving off benefits and into continuous work
Payment of £4,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local authorities and their partners are expected to make up the remaining 60 per cent of the average £10,000 cost of a successful family intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The funding provided under the Troubled Families payment by results arrangements will be available for five out of six troubled families in each upper-tier local authority. This is to minimise double payment for the same outcomes. Government funding has already been provided to support these remaining families. For example, the Department for Work and Pension’s £200 million+ European Social Fund provision, the Work Programme and existing government-funded Multi-Systemic Therapy pilots.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Troubled Families Team and the Department for Communities and Local Government will be joined on secondment by Robert McCulloch-Graham who is currently the Director of Children’s Services at the London Borough of Barnet. Robert will be starting at the Department on 18 June 2012 and will bring with him experience of working on early intervention for troubled families across Barnet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9286</id>
    <published>2012-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/downing-street-launch-for-troubled-families-scheme--2"/>
    <title>Downing Street launch for 'troubled families' scheme</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local authority leaders and frontline community workers were this week invited to a reception in Downing Street to mark the start of the Government’s groundbreaking initiative to turn around the lives of troubled families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron was in attendance along with Cabinet ministers including Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles, Work and Pensions Secretary Iain Duncan Smith and Home Secretary Theresa May, as well as Head of Troubled Families Policy Louise Casey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming guests to Number 10 the Prime Minister expressed his “passion” for the project which is turning around the lives of the 120,000 most challenging families in England in the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reception came on the day that the Department for Communities and Local Government launched its unique payment by results programme that will reward upper tier local authorities with up to £4,000 per family if they get children off the streets and into school; reduce youth crime and antisocial behaviour; and put parents on a path back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10 authorities with the largest amount of troubled families, amounting to a fifth of those that are being targeted, are all signed up to the £448 million scheme and ready to begin work in the new financial year with many more expected in the coming months. All 152 top-tier council chief executives were invited to the event along with new Troubled Families Co-ordinators and frontline workers from the public and voluntary sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told guests that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s great to have so many people here from local government and so many people from different organisations and institutes that care about families. Today we’re celebrating a step forward in the programme of trying to deal with the most troubled families, and that is producing the payment by results model to make money available for local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We all know there are some deeply troubled families in our country who are responsible for a huge amount of social problems, for themselves but also for the wider community - the children aren’t going to school, the parents aren’t in work, they are responsible for a huge amount of crime and antisocial behaviour, and they are deeply, deeply chaotic.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am very proud of the fact that this Government has decided to roll up its sleeves and really try and deal with these problems, it’s a hugely important area of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also speaking at the event, Communities Secretary Eric Pickles added that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve brought the Government together, but the most important thing is this: that we all in this room - whether you’re a politician, a chief executive, somebody from a charity - we have a real chance of turning these lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We talk about the money its costing, but it is a human waste. People on a system that’s leading nowhere, and we’ve got a chance to make a difference, and I am very much looking forward to working with all of you in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on the Government’s Troubled Families project is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2118082"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2118082&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15390</id>
    <published>2012-03-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-troubled-families-programme-financial-framework"/>
    <title>The troubled families programme: financial framework</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Information on the Troubled Families programme payment-by-results scheme for local authorities</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Troubled Families Financial Framework is a results-based funding scheme which provides details of the payment mechanism for local authorities to receive extra funding to deal with troubled families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aimed at local authorities, this document explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the process and criteria for drawing up the list of families who will be part of the programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;arrangements in regard to upfront payments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what local authorities would need to achieve with each family in order to claim the result-based payment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
