<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/bringing-people-together-in-strong-united-communities/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/bringing-people-together-in-strong-united-communities/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/bringing-people-together-in-strong-united-communities/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Bringing people together in strong, united communities"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16140</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/faith-minister-visits-temple-to-start-diwali-celebrations"/>
    <title>Faith Minister visits temple to start Diwali celebrations</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neasden Temple is the first traditional Hindu Mandir in Europe and the largest temple outside India. During her visit, the Faith and Communities Minister received a traditional welcome by the trustees of the temple and heard about their work before embarking on a tour of the building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She met volunteers and heard about the central role the temple plays within the local community and beyond - having attracted devotees and visitors from across the world since it opened in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was then invited to set off the spectacular fireworks display enjoyed by the thousands of people who had travelled to the temple to mark the beginning of Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every year I look forward to celebrating Diwali, the festival of lights, so it was a particular honour to mark it this year at the magnificent Neasden Temple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fascinating to hear about the central role the temple plays within the local community, from hosting school visits and organising charitable events - and how the Mandir has attracted devotees from all corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to the trustees and volunteers many hours of devotion and commitment and thank them for the warm hospitality I received during my visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632012718099/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14760</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-sends-her-best-wishes-on-diwali"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes on Diwali</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister, Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes to all of those celebrating Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As people celebrate this special time in communities across the country, I send my warmest wishes to you all for a peaceful and happy Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Diwali provides an important opportunity for prayer and reflection as the festival which celebrates the victory of good over evil and light over darkness. It is a time for family and friends, the reaffirmation of hope and renewed commitment to friendship and goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In celebrating Diwali we can appreciate the diversity that characterises this country and also recognise the common values of compassion, honesty and goodwill in which we can all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As communities across the country begin their celebrations, I am delighted to wish everyone a very happy Diwali and a prosperous new year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16083</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T20:07:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/an-integration-nation-breaking-down-the-barriers"/>
    <title>An integration nation: breaking down the barriers</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain wouldn’t be the place it is today without the contribution of people from ethnic minority backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the Commonwealth soldiers who served with the allies in the wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the immigrants, people like my dad, who came here to build up our industries in the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of our diverse communities contributing to every section of society today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of Mo Farah. Our national hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Mo crossed the finish line - twice - this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation got behind this London lad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one batted an eyelid over the fact that he was a Somali-born Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, this guy is British - very British.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he told one interviewer: “Look mate, this is where I grew up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is my country and when I put on my Great Britain vest I’m proud.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It said a lot about the diverse, integrated state of our country today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where everyone - black, white and brown - was proud to drape themselves in red, white and blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite great individual examples, there are still barriers to integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today this is more of a problem for us as a country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because today Britain is in a global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can’t just rely on Mo Farah to win this one for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a race that pits us against counties around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a huge challenge of global, economic competition that will determine our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have got a secret weapon to succeed in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The races from around the globe that make up Britain today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our diverse communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with links to places across the world, with business acumen and ideas, with cultural insight and experience and with endless untapped talent and networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s our duty - it’s crucial to our future - to unlock this potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it flies in the face of the survey in which 52% of people said that migrants in Britain were bad for our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I want to focus on what the barriers are to integration and how we can overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="barriers"&gt;Barriers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s look at the barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the things that stop people getting on with each other are the same as the things that stop them getting on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, integration and social mobility are inextricably linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ethnic minority groups have much lower levels of English than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15% of Bangladeshi and 12% of Pakistani women report having little or no English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research shows that English language is the second biggest predictor in occupational success, after qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And 60% of people believe that the biggest barrier to being integrated is not speaking the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to get on top of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution isn’t to throw money at translation and interpretation services or at teaching assistants for non-English speaking pupils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s helping more people to learn English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’m delighted at my department’s commitment to fund English language learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I want to see us go further, finding new and innovative ways to help people learn English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s a DVD at home, a CD in the car, a volunteer at the community centre, or an after-school club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because a common language is the fundamental basis of common understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just language that holds the key to integration. It’s also got to start in our schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were huge gaps in attainment on the basis of ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With British Caribbean, British Pakistani and British Roma children falling way behind the national average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means freeing up communities to start free schools in areas of deprivation, like the King’s Academy in Bradford, so that everyone, whatever their background, has access to the best schooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means supporting failing comprehensives to become Academies, so that hard done by catchment areas suddenly get the best facilities and the best chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also means changing the way we support and engage with different communities to bring them into the fold - not leave them out in the cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government has moved away from intervention on the basis of race towards increasing the impact of mainstream policies on minority communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backing mainstream organisations, like Youth United, which bring together people of all backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And championing National Citizens’ Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just funding national bodies, but also supporting local projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My good friend, the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government, Eric Pickles, has led the way in this endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spearheading the Big Lunch and the Bandstand Marathon, which have brought people together over food and music - shared experience in shared spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Championing A Year of Service and the Near Neighbours programme, which have united people of different faiths so they can make a difference, together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And driving forward the Localism Act, so people can bid to run local services and shape the areas in which they live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sends out a clear message to our BME communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer are you getting the crumbs off the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You now have a stake in the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="values"&gt;Values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, let’s look at our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people to integrate in our society, I think Britain needs to be better at asserting its values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2006, Tony Blair urged minority communities to adopt British values and to integrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he forgot to point out that Britain needs to be equally sure of its values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nation, we need to be stronger about asserting shared British principles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like freedom, fairness and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunity, aspiration and tolerance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing as you would be done by, being proud of the country in which you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we ask people to sign up to our values if we are not sure of them ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’ve been so outspoken on Britain remembering its Christian heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I went to the Vatican and called on Europe to assert its Christian identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Christian Britain was more sure of its own identity it would be less rejecting of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I believe this government’s pro-faith agenda has reflected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Britain, once again, growing confident of its Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I’ve been so outspoken on the need for schools to teach history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted that Michael Gove has put history at the heart of our curriculum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, as I’ve said for years, how can we know where we’re going if we don’t know where we come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not only must we assert our values - we must ensure those values are afforded to everyone, whatever their faith, colour or creed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long authorities have dismissed many of the more difficult issues facing minority communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some said “don’t meddle in these matters”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others steered well clear for fear of offending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been treating our communities like foreign embassies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where rules from abroad apply and wider society keeps well out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for too long, cultural sensitivities have often led our leaders to become morally blind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we’ve dealt with matters differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came to forced marriage, we said enough was enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the same with the issue of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a drug is harming a specific communities it’s not enough to say it’s part of their cultural practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s right to say they deserve the same protection from harmful drugs like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why for many years I have campaigned for the banning of khat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise we should come down equally hard on attitudes that can lead to tragic consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I spoke out on the issue of child sexual grooming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said that a small minority of predominantly Pakistani men thought women were second class citizens and white women were third class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if we shy away from the difficult issues in this country, however uncomfortable, we will never confront them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how can people integrate in a society when, in the name of cultural sensitivity, we continue to entrench barriers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="discrimination"&gt;Discrimination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, let’s look at discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discrimination, intolerance, prejudice and bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stamp these out if we want our society to be better integrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These un-British traits mean that at best some people feel they don’t belong and at worst their lives and livelihoods are under threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in 2010, we made it a requirement for all police forces to record anti-Semitic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are funding tighter security measures in Jewish faith schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We appointed the first UK Envoy for Post-Holocaust issues, Sir Andrew Burns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are funding the Holocaust Education Trust’s Lessons from Auschwitz project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And are committing further funds to the Holocaust Memorial Day Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more than that - we are now finally starting to tackle the more recent scourge of anti-Muslim hatred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we announced last week, we are funding the Measuring Anti-Muslim Attacks (MAMA) programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we established the Cross Government Anti-Muslim Hatred Group, allowing us to respond to the growing problem of Islamophobia, department by department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighting bigotry and intolerance is key to enable people to integrate, to participate and to reach their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-of-britain"&gt;Future of Britain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t afford to let people be held back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it by language, by education, by discrimination, by disengagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, Britain’s migrant communities are key to our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to sell Britain to the world than our diverse communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whose links extend from Ankara to Islamabad, from Shanghai to Saint-Lucia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to offer the world the products it wants?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Than the country that sells naan bread to India; canoes to the Eskimos; tacos to Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to rebalance our economy and accelerate our recovery?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Than some of our most can-do businessmen and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our diaspora communities and entrepreneurs hold the key to linking businesses across continents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Thatcher once said: “Britain is now, more than ever, a multicultural society: and I think that we are beginning to appreciate the challenges and opportunities for learning that this diversity offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new resilience derived from diversity can only strengthen Britain.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates show that our economy is missing out on £8.6 billion a year - probably more - from failing to fully empower people from ethnic minorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine what Britain could do if we unlocked all that untapped talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to break down these barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expose those opportunities and those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring people in from the sidelines, into the mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the young black British boy doesn’t think he’s more likely to fail at school and less likely to get on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But realises that he is not part of the problem, he’s part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron has called on us to become an aspiration nation if we want to win the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we also need to be an integration nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking away those barriers that stop people playing their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asserting shared British values – and affording everyone those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing discrimination, tackling bigotry and hatred, wherever they arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, unlocking the full talent of Britain’s diversity - a diversity which is so essential to our country’s future prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14281</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:39:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-congratulate-the-new-archbishop-of-canterbury"/>
    <title>Ministers congratulate the new Archbishop of Canterbury</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Congratulations to the Right Reverend Justin Welby on his appointment as Archbishop of Canterbury following Dr Rowan Williams’ decade of guidance and leadership for the Church of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Archbishop can offer a unique perspective as an ex-businessman, following many years experience in a commercial environment, and that of previously serving as a parish priest, Dean of Liverpool and Bishop of Durham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish him every success and know that, with the challenges that will come, he will draw upon his diverse experience and demonstrate dedication to the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Church of England plays a valued and important role in the culture and constitution of our nation and I very much look forward to meeting the Archbishop soon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to welcome the Right Reverend Justin Welby as the newly appointed Archbishop of Canterbury and would like to wish him well following Dr Rowan Williams’ successful decade as leader of the Anglican church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With experience of both the business and religious world, he can bring a wide range of skills to his new role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to meeting him and discussing the ways in which the government and the church can continue to work together to improve local communities and increase interactions across all religions.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13584</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:55:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-calls-on-mosques-to-encourage-hate-crime-reporting"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi calls on mosques to encourage hate crime reporting</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Senior Minister for Faith at the Department for Communities and Local Government is to write to all imams to urge them to do more to tackle the problem in their areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures show there have been nearly 500 recorded incidents of anti-Muslim attacks in England since a new government-funded helpline was established in February this year to monitor them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Baroness Warsi, who argued last year that Islamophobia had “passed the dinner table test”, believes that the real figure may be much higher, with victims feeling unsupported to come forward or believing that reporting will not be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the minister will say that mosques can play a crucial part in helping victims have confidence that attacks will be treated seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mosques can encourage members, through notices and talks, to report any incidents of hate crime,” she will say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just as important, the mosque’s management team can put in place a register to monitor incidents and arrange to communicate this information to the police in the first instance. I know that more mosques are already doing these things, but some mosques could do more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She will add that, as well as enabling more prosecutions, clear and accurate data can help build a case for stronger action to be taken by all authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For me, statistics are a vital first step to tackling this issue and engaging the relevant agencies to do more to persuade others of the seriousness of the problem and do more about it,” she will say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The data still needs to be validated, but early indications are that nearly 60% of reported religious hate crime in 2011 was directed at Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That shows the scale of the problem, but we need better reporting and recording and more community awareness to allow us to build up a complete picture.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14740</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eid-message-from-faith-minister-baroness-warsi"/>
    <title>Eid message from Faith Minister Baroness Warsi</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Foreign Office Minister and Minister for Faith and Communities, Baroness Warsi, has sent her best wishes to those celebrating Eid ul Adha this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I want to send my best wishes to Muslims in Britain and across the world who are celebrating the conclusion of the Hajj pilgrimage and the holy festival of Eid ul Adha.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Eid gives us a special opportunity to reflect on the links between our faiths, since Islam, Christianity and Judaism share a founding father, Abraham, whose selfless sacrifice we mark during this festival.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“It is also an occasion for us to give to others and consider those less fortunate than ourselves. Foremost on my mind this Eid will be those suffering in Syria; the people across the world who are persecuted for following their faith; and brave, young Malala Yousafzai, Pakistan’s inspirational campaigner.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Eid is a time for peace and happiness and I look forward to celebrating it both at home with my family and in Downing Street.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Eid Mubarak.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2220858.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14736</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-celebrates-harvest-festival-at-borough-market"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles celebrates Harvest Festival at Borough Market</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles on Sunday joined a multi-faith celebration of Harvest Festival at London’s Borough Market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2241741.jpg" alt="Eric Pickles speaking at the Harvest Festival"&gt;Eric Pickles at Borough Market harvest Festival&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event, held jointly with Southwark Cathedral, coincided with the Market’s annual ‘Apple Day’ and began with the Dean of Southwark, The Very Reverend Andrew Nunn, leading a procession from the Cathedral into the market. A short act of worship including hymns sung by the Borough Market Choir was followed by a collection of food and clothing donated to the local Manna Day Centre for the homeless and the ROBES winter shelter project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Throughout the year, Christian communities across the country help others through volunteering and supporting charities. These admirable activities are highlighted by the Government-backed ‘A Year of Service’ programme, where during Harvest Festival Christian communities are opening doors to other faiths and to the wider public. Whether it be raising funds for local charities or distributing food, every good deed serves to enrich and unify our communities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s Christian-led event was one of many social action activities taking place this month across the country to coincide with Harvest Festival and is part of ‘A Year of Service’ - the year-long Government-backed programme to highlight the substantial contributions made by faith groups and to introduce more people to multi-faith volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian communities throughout October are inviting people from offices, schools, youth groups and places of worship from other faiths to take part in volunteering-led activities including food collections, processions and organising multi-faith meals for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Archbishop of Canterbury, Dr Rowan Williams, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This year, the unique A Year of Service programme is encouraging members of different faith communities and people of no faith to come together to volunteer and help improve local neighbourhoods. In most churches, Harvest Festival is usually celebrated only amongst Christians but this year partnerships are developing between local mosques, synagogues, temples and gurdwaras in order to gather and distribute food. Initiatives like this can make a real difference in areas where neighbours of different faiths do not yet know each other and Harvest gives a good opportunity for them to work together to help the poorest people in their neighbourhood.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2096271.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2096271.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=122138" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14734</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-virgin-islands-flag-flies-at-eland-house"/>
    <title>British Virgin Islands flag flies at Eland House</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has raised the flag of the British Virgin Islands outside the Department for Communities and Local Government in Whitehall, London, to mark St Ursula’s Day - the patron saint of the Islands - and as part of the flag flying programme by the Department in this Jubilee year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, the Government published an Overseas Territories White Paper; one of the goals is to raise awareness in the United Kingdom of these British communities, lands and seas around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, Mr Pickles announced a relaxation of the rules relating to the flying of flags to make it easier for the public to fly a wider range of flags without the need for express consent which could cost up to £335. The changes will increase the number of flags that people can fly, promoting integration and community spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles has asked for the flags of the United Kingdom’s Overseas Territories - from Anguilla to the Turks and Caicos Islands - to be proudly flown by the Department as part of a formal recognition of the continued important and close relationship with the country. This follows from a programme of flying England’s county flags last year. The British Virgin Islands’ flag is being flown alongside the United Kingdom’s Union flag, which is flown all year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flags will be flown at appropriate times in the coming months to recognise national days of significance. Britain has 14 Overseas Territories which encompass over 600,000 square miles and are home to 260,000 people - more than Nottingham or Newcastle. The Department provides advice and guidance to Territory Governments in areas where it has relevant expertise - in particular planning, housing, and fire safety and rescue services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major tourist destination and economic centre, the British Virgin Islands consist of around sixty different islands which are home to just under 30,000 people. At the ceremony of hoisting the British Virgin Islands’ flag, Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m delighted to see the flag of the British Virgin Islands flying proudly outside my Department. British Overseas Territories play a vital role in our sense of national identity and the Government’s vision is for the Territories to be vibrant and flourishing communities, proudly retaining aspects of their British identity and generating wider opportunities for their people.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I look forward to seeing many more flags of the UK’s overseas territories flying in the coming months especially in this year of celebration.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14723</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/more-support-for-star-indian-chefs-of-the-future"/>
    <title>More support for star Indian chefs of the future</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today joined Britain’s leading Indian chefs and restaurateurs to launch a new scholarship programme for students to develop their careers in ‘high-end’ Asian cuisine and restaurant management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Led by the University of West London - one of five Centres of Excellence in Asian and Oriental cuisine - with the backing of the Department for Communities and Local Government and the financial support of Lord Noon, the programme underlines the importance of South Asian cuisine to the British economy and the need to develop highly-skilled British talent in a sector that has depended traditionally on attracting chefs from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and local Government has worked with Noon Products Ltd and the University to develop the degree course and in addition to learning advanced cooking techniques and management skills, scholarship students will also undertake work placements at top Asian restaurants. They will also be mentored by some of the country’s most talented chefs and restaurateurs including award-winning Atul Kochhar, Vivek Singh and Cyrus Todiwala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the University’s award winning London School of Hospitality and Tourism Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There was a time when, for most people, Asian cuisine meant a post-pub Friday-night curry. But not anymore. Our high-end Asian restaurants have been instrumental in changing the perception of Indian and Asian cuisine and many have reached for and been awarded Michelin stars, proving the nation’s favourite food is just as sophisticated as any other.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is an industry worth over £3billion to the economy and we are fully committed to supporting British talent, all the way through from our favourite local curry houses and takeaways right up to our world-leading restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We want to ensure employees have the right skills and that Britain remains one of the best places in the world for our chefs and managers to train. I thank Lord Noon for his generous financial support and look forward to others in the industry joining in to ensure that our young chefs get to the very top of their profession.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hoped that the scheme will be expanded to include additional students and further institutions in the future. To achieve this, The Department is also working alongside the newly created Asian Restaurant Skills Board headed by Iqbal Wahhab - founder of London’s Cinnamon Club and Roast restaurants. The Board will shortly be writing to potential donors who have a stake in the growth of the sector to seek their financial support for expanding the scholarship scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor David Foskett, Head of the University’s London School of Hospitality and Tourism, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is a unique and wonderful opportunity for students who are interested in South Asian culinary arts. This initiative from the Secretary of State is warmly welcomed and demonstrates the government’s commitment to this important sector of the economy. It also underlines the emerging importance of South Asian cuisine on the global stage and the learning and career opportunities now available to students.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=121572" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631781892779/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The University of West London is one of five Centres of Excellence in Asian and Oriental Cuisine set up to help the sector address the wider skills and labour market demand for chefs in Asian and Oriental restaurants and takeaways. The four other centres of Excellence are in existing colleges and universities - located in Leeds, Manchester, Birmingham and central London - will, in collaboration with employers, train people to become chefs within the Asian and Oriental sector. People 1st, the sector skills council for hospitality, is leading the implementation of this programme. This will involve recruiting young people on to a pre-employment training programme, which guarantees them an interview with prospective employers and a paid apprenticeship in Asian and Oriental cuisine. The apprenticeship programme involves four days’ work in a catering establishment and one day studying in the college. Successful completion of the apprenticeship will lead to a NVQ Diploma in Professional Cookery. Government funding is available for training apprentices - 100 per cent of training is covered for 16-18 year-olds, 50 per cent of training covered for 19+ year-olds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The London School of Hospitality and Tourism at the University of West London has been chosen to pilot the ‘high-end’ scholarship programme because of the high quality of teaching standards, links with industry, and specialist knowledge of culinary arts and south Asian cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Four ‘high-end’ scholarships worth £3,750 each have been made possible at the University with the support of the Department for Communities and Local Government and Noon Products Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14721</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/world-war-i-heroes-battlefield-tours-mean-children-will-remember-them"/>
    <title>World War I Heroes - battlefield tours mean children will remember them</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today announced a new flagship scheme to commemorate the 100th anniversary of World War I (WWI) and give thousands of schoolchildren the opportunity to visit the Great War battlefields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pupils and teachers from every maintained secondary school in England will have the chance to go on a tour of the great battlefields - such as the Somme, Verdun and Fromelles - and take part in remembrance ceremonies on the western front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World War I is already compulsory for children aged 11 to 14. This project - part of the Centenary Education Programme - will allow pupils to learn at first hand about the sacrifices made by the troops and the personal stories of those involved in the war effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Children who do not visit will also benefit when pupils and teachers who have taken part in the project pass on what they have learnt from their first-hand experience. This could involve establishing commemoration projects, like collecting photographs and uncovering local stories, in their schools and local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron made the announcement today as he set out the Government’s plans to mark the centenary of the start of the First World War in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the Imperial War Museum, an institution founded in 1917 to record the then still-continuing conflict, Mr Cameron said that he wanted to build a truly national commemoration, worthy of this historic centenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Wilfred Owen described World War I as the ‘winter of the world’. The sacrifices of our forefathers are our shared heritage and the centenary will be commemorated across the nation and around the globe. We will remember them. It is vital that we help educate the next generation about this important part of our history so that it is never forgotten and I am delighted that my Department is helping this to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education Secretary Michael Gove said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The men who gave their lives in the Great War will remain heroes forever. The last British Veteran has now died but their bravery and suffering must never be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This project will ensure that never happens by leaving a lasting legacy of this hugely significant period of our nation’s history and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Children will learn, at first hand, about the sacrifices made by individuals and communities to secure our nation and protect our liberty. This tangible experience will reinforce what they have learnt in the classroom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pat Barker, author of the &lt;em&gt;Regeneration&lt;/em&gt; trilogy of novels and a member of the centenary project advisory panel, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I have found it an incredibly moving and enlightening experience, especially the monument at Thiepval in Flanders and seeing the names of men who have no graves. I am sure that all children who go on these tours will benefit hugely.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hew Strachan, Chichele Professor of the History of War at Oxford University, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As with the Olympics, so with the centenary of the Great War: the commemoration must bequeath to future generations a legacy that equips them with a deeper understanding of the war, its many meanings and its truly global significance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will cost £5.3m, from 2013 to 2019. Half the money is coming from the Department for Education and half from the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A procurement process will be run to decide on a single tour operator before the visits start in spring 2014, running until spring 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Department for Education’s £15m investment in cultural education following the Henley Review, we are working with cultural education organisations, including Arts Council England and English Heritage, to develop proposals for schools to mark the commemoration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Cross Governmental Core Liaison Group was established in February to provide leadership, coordination and delivery on the Government’s WW1 activities during 2014-2018. Andrew Murrison chairs the Group (the Department for Culture Media and Sport provides the secretariat and coordinating role), which comprises:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Department for Education&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Department for Culture Media and Sport&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ministry of Defence&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imperial War Museum&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heritage Lottery Fund&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonwealth War Graves Commission&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BBC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An advisory panel of unremunerated senior figures headed by Dr Andrew Murrison, the Prime Minister’s Special Representative for the centenary project is about to be appointed. The board’s purpose will be to offer independent oversight of the UK’s preparations for the centenary, a link with institutions beyond government and the encouragement of private giving to centenary related initiatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
