<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving high streets and town centres"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17099</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T13:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-sets-out-government-support-for-lifeline-shops"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk sets out government support for "lifeline shops"</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the Association of Convenience Stores, Mr Prisk described them as a vital service for the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He warned against overlooking the crucial role the army of small shopkeepers across the country plays not only economically but also socially - offering a friendly face and social hub to local communities, and especially older people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister pointed to research suggesting that around a quarter of elderly people use their local shop, often a convenience store, every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convenience stores represent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;almost 40% of all rural shops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over a third of shops in urban areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a quarter of all shops in the suburbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the age of supermarkets and online retail it’s easy to forget that convenience stores make up more than quarter of all shops. Yet they are not just an important part of the economy. For many people their local shop is also a lifeline. Whether they’re used for daily supplies or the occasional pint of milk, they are an essential part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s why this government is introducing measures specifically designed to support convenience stores. That means reforming the planning system, easing the financial pressures with business rate support, and offering practical ways to attract new custom, all in order to keep this vital local resource intact.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-support-to-convenience-stores"&gt;Government support to convenience stores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk acknowledged the new economic challenges traditional shops now face, especially the changing way that people shop - whether online or in out-of-town retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he also highlighted some of the key actions the government is taking to help them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s work to cut the deficit by a quarter in 2 years, which has kept interest rates lower for longer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new changes to the planning system to ensure that existing town centres should be the first preference for new retail facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expert support and a multi-million pound fund for Portas Pilots and Town Team Partners will encourage strong and bold local leadership to create competitive high streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doubled small business rates relief and a 20% reduction of corporation tax are helping smaller firms manage their bills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a delayed business rate revaluation, providing a more stable business environment and preventing an increase in rates for around 800,000 premises &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to help town centres adapt to changing demands, making it easier to convert empty offices into homes and bringing people back into the town centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"&gt;speech to the Association of Convenience Stores&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17100</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T18:39:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"/>
    <title> Heart of the Community conference 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be able to join you at this, my third Association of Convenience Stores conference, though I don’t think that earns me a Crackerjack pen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to pay tribute to James Lowman and the work of the Association. Whilst we have not always agreed, I have always found James to be both persistent and effective, in putting your case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it was following talks with James that I pressed for, and secured, a 3 year moratorium for small shops from the tobacco display ban, (much to the chagrin of the supermarket groups!). This was partly because of the points James made on how a convenience store is run, so his knowledge is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tough-times"&gt;Tough times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I recognise as someone who has been involved with business, and the government recognises, that these are tough times for retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer incomes are under continuing pressure. The uncertainty in the Eurozone has prolonged the credit crunch. And of course there is increasing competition, which only squeezes your already tight margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, alongside the established competition from the supermarkets and out of town centres, we are also seeing a long term shift in consumer habits, as the online market grows. In fact, I was looking at the numbers and online sales have doubled in the last decade, to make up 10% of UK retail sales. That trend is only going to continue, and begs real challenges for all of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in consumer habits is not wholly bad for smaller bricks and mortar retailers. Indeed it has been shown to actively help specialists or those with a particular offer to reach much wider markets. But it means that the question for all retailers is no longer whether you should adapt your business, but how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a very important shift which we in government must respond to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="value-of-convenience-sector"&gt;Value of convenience sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In government, we recognise the economic worth of the retail sector, both by turnover and measured by the number and type of jobs. Retailing is, for example, one of the most important ‘first’ employers, with a third of all retail employees, aged under 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a social value in small shops, (and particularly in the convenience sector) which we should not ignore, as indeed your research has shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A local convenience store is often one of the few places, where people meet and talk today. In villages and on many estates, it’s you and it’s your staff who know the local community, (and make time to talk to the elderly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representing 40% of all rural shops (and a third of shops in our towns), it’s the convenience sector which is usually there for a whole range of customers - perhaps those who don’t have a car, for young families, and for the elderly. It’s not to say that you aren’t economically important, but I also recognise the social benefit of a diverse, convenience sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, both as a constituency MP and as a member of Parliament, as well as a user of my local convenience store, and on behalf of the many customers who rely on the service and care you and your staff provide, let me say thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-can-be-done-to-help"&gt;What can be done to help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former businessman, I understand that of course empathy doesn’t pay your bills, or help you compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I would like to do if I can, is explain what we’re doing in government to help business generally, and retailing in particular, to weather the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think it’s important that we have been able to keep interest rates lower for substantially longer, by cutting the financial deficit by a quarter. The fact that we’ve been able to do this over the last 2 and a half years is vital. Clearly, there’s a difference between what we the government and you as retailers can borrow, but if we had continued to borrow, interest rates would have soared, crippling businesses and families alike. We can all see what that means, when we look abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So low interest rates have helped. But the government has also acted to cut your costs. We have cut corporation tax rates to 24 pence for larger firms, and to 20 pence for smaller businesses. And we have reversed plans to increase National Insurance contributions, which would have hit jobs hard. The Association of Convenience Stores were amongst those who helped to make that point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we came into office, we also acted to help cut business rate bills. It’s why we extended and doubled the small business rates relief that’s helped thousands of small shops pay their bills, and it’s why we have now given councils new powers to discount rates, (funded locally), to help those firms which are struggling. It’s a new power, only a few months old, and only a few councils have taken it up. I am sure the association will want to change that. In fact, your own submission to the Treasury says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s there, now all they need to do is use it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, our financial room for manoeuvre is very limited but we are listening carefully to your concerns and will try and help where we can. However, as I’d like to remain a minister, I won’t pre-empt the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently we have delayed the planned revaluation from 2015 to 2017. This is an important issue. Let me explain our thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we know that the last thing businesses needed right now, is the uncertainty which a revaluation would create. You get your valuation, there’s the counter valuation, appeals which leads to 18 months of uncertainty. It isn’t the right time to be doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we looked carefully at the independent evidence produced by the Valuation Office Agency as to who the likely winners and losers would be. We were and you might be surprised by the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Valuation Office Agency’s analysis shows that some 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates bill, with roughly 300,000 benefitting. Indeed many of the businesses represented here would have seen big hikes, in some cases up to 28%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems counter-intuitive, but the reason for this, is that because the revaluation must be revenue neutral, to compensate for lower rateable values, the tax rate would have to increase by approximately 20%. As a result, many businesses whose rents have fallen by less than the national average, which is how it is balanced, would have seen business rate bill goes up from 2015. We have asked business to come in so that we can explain how this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we felt, on balance, that now is not the time to be making this revaluation and in doing so we believe we can help many businesses in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that for many people, they think, ‘my rents have gone up’ but because there are 2 elements to business rates it doesn’t quite work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="town-centres-need-to-compete"&gt;Town centres need to compete&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s not just individual shops that need help. It’s also the traditional high street and many of our town centres. And our role should not be not to protect, but to enable. To ensure that our high streets are able to adapt to changing markets and consumer habits, so you can compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why last year the Prime Minister asked Mary Portas to review what needs to be done, by government, by local authorities and by business itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has produced an excellent report and brought her typical real energy and a keen consumer eye to the towns wanting to pilot this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s actually happening on the ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, our Town Centres First policy is an important and explicit part of our new National Planning Policy Framework. What it means in practice is that town centres should be the first preference for new retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we want to reform, planning to help town centres adapt. This means making it easier for the conversion of redundant first floors into homes, and secondly to enable empty offices that can often blight some high streets to also be converted into homes. Both these measures will bring people back into the town centre, increase footfall and so help existing retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we believe that strong local leadership is vital if towns are to be renewed. That is the clear lesson from both the Portas pilots and what we see regularly from successful shopping centres, who manage the whole customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If struggling high streets and town centres are to compete, they need the right people to deal with the promotion, management and coordination of their ‘centre’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we announced last month the creation of over 320 town team partners, who will get the expert advice, mentoring and support they need, to get an effective business plan in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went to Deptford, where I met the leaders of their town team, who are using one-stop shops and community cafés to make the most of what they feel is their unique selling point - its significant cluster of local artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UuacApa2aUE"&gt;Deptford visit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They plan to bring benefits to the entire high street, install art in the high street and set up shops as galleries under the ‘Made in Deptford’ banner to bring more people in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a really encouraging visit and just shows what together local civic and business leaders working as a partnership can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="physical-change"&gt;Physical change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course if towns are to compete, they need to address other issues than those I mentioned: from actively promoting local markets; through to being innovative, when managing and charging for local parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, lets be honest many need to change their appearance. And getting empty shops occupied is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why my predecessor Grant Shapps provided a £10 million High Street Innovation Fund, specifically to help those areas with the worst levels of empty shops. We’re already starting to see this helping to bring run down shops back into use, with other businesses kicking off as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think we can do more. The pop up shop movement, which helps new businesses set up and sell, is a great idea. Its something I want to impress on both landlords and tenants, and see expand right across the country, not least as it helps new firms start and will generate additional footfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am in talks with the Pop Up Britain team, led by Emma Jones, to see how we in government can help promote pop up shops across the country, and I hope to have something positive to say about it very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-next-step"&gt;The next step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope you can see, as a government we believe that much can be done to help retailers and our town centres compete. But it has to be a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government, councils, businesses and local people (especially) need to be engaged and feel that they can make a difference. This involves a long term shift and short term squeeze. This won’t be easy and many towns will struggle, especially where that sense of collaboration is missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can be done. As the people in Deptford have shown, if there’s the right imagination, will and support our high streets can have a great future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be different to what went before, but it’s vital that once again our town centres regain their role, at the heart of our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14296</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:50:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-urges-shoppers-love-your-local-market"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk urges shoppers: "love your local market"</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk called on communities and budding entrepreneurs to back their local markets well into the New Year, as part of a wider effort to breathe new life into the nation’s high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister confirmed that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/" title="Love Your Local Market"&gt;Love Your Local Market&lt;/a&gt; campaign in 2013 will take place from 15 May, and will give aspiring retailers the chance to test out their ideas at their local markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Love Your Local Market campaign, new stallholders will be able to take advantage of a ‘Table for a Tenner’ deal - with some offering free pitches - at markets across the country, with many offering mentoring to those setting up shop for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make sure as many high streets as possible can take part, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/" title="National Association of British Market Authorities"&gt;National Association of British Market Authorities&lt;/a&gt; will hold a series of roadshows sharing ideas that councils and other market operators can take to make their events a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 400 local markets across the country were involved this summer, with a locally-defined programme of events designed to attract visitors into town centres and help new start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Markets can play an integral role in reviving our high streets, offering something new and exciting for shoppers in a way the Internet and out-of-town retail centres can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge traders and councils across the country to back this effective and important campaign, offer support to budding entrepreneurs looking to trade and Love Your Local Market.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Wilson, OBE, Chief Executive of the National Association of British Market Authorities, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Love Your Local Market and National Market Day provided a great impetus to the campaign to revitalise the high street and created an opportunity for almost 2000 people to sample market trading for the first time. We now want to build on this success and make LYLM 2013 bigger and better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Harrison, Chief Executive of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmtf.co.uk/" title="National Market Traders Association"&gt;National Market Traders’ Federation&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We, at the National Market Traders’ Federation, are happy to see this campaign running again for a second year, and are delighted to support it. We do hope it has an even bigger impact than the first event with regard to the encouragement of new start-up businesses within the industry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="following-up-on-a-successful-fortnight"&gt;Following up on a successful fortnight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows the success of the Love Your Local Markets event in June this year, which saw over 400 markets run over the dedicated 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this scheme:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;around 400 markets took part under the Love Your Local Markets banner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just under 2,000 new traders joined local markets during last year’s campaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over 3,000 ‘Tables for a Tenner’ and free pitches were offered - over half of which were taken up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Rogers, whose chocolate stall is now a regular fixture at Ludlow Market, with visitors now looking to buy her products online and making bookings for her to cater weddings and other events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obi Nwosu, who started selling during Love Your Local Market at Portobello in London, and now has stalls in six locations across the Capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Smith, who started his Natural Ingredients stall at Fleetwood Market earlier this year, but is now trading on every market day of the week, and sell into retail outlets including food halls and other local specialist markets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14739</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/more-green-flag-awards-for-great-local-parks"/>
    <title>More Green Flag Awards for great local parks</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Flag Awards - an annual ‘MOT’ inspection for parks on aspects like safety and cleanliness - are to continue as Communities Minister Don Foster announces that Keep Britain Tidy has been awarded the licence to run the scheme for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First launched in 1996 the scheme has rewarded thousands of flags over the years, with a record number 1,424 sites receiving the award this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As thousands of tourists during the Olympics saw for themselves we have some of the greatest parks in the world in this country and I want to keep the standard very high.  This is why the government is pleased to announce that Keep Britain Tidy will continue to run the scheme, awarding green flags to those parks that provide great spaces for local people.
&amp;gt; “Open spaces are essential in bringing people of all ages and backgrounds together, and are particularly important for the millions of people who do not have the luxury of their own garden to relax in or for their children to play in.  Green flags will continue to reward great parks across the country and challenge all the others to do even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as parks the green flag award scheme is open to any freely accessible public open space, including woodlands, nature reserves, allotments and cemeteries.  Judging is carried out by an army of volunteer judges and parks that receive lottery funding are required to achieve green flag status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking today at the UK Parks Summit in London, organised by the Heritage Lottery Fund and Big Lottery Fund, Don Foster is also welcoming additional lottery funding to support parks saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that £100million of extra lottery money will be going to support parks over the next three years, getting local people involved and protecting historic monuments.  With the continuing green flags scheme these new measures are a real boost for the country’s parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep Britain Tidy Chief Executive Phil Barton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On behalf of the partners involved I’d like to say how thrilled we are to have won the licence to run the Green Flag Awards for the next five years.
&amp;gt; “We know how important this scheme is to the army of professional men and women who manage our green spaces across the country. We also understand that, in these difficult financial times, these professionals are facing significant challenges.
&amp;gt; “It is only by working together that we can maintain the high standards set by the Green Flag Award and it is against this backdrop that we are delighted to be working with key partners who will help strengthen the scheme. Through this partnership, we will continue to spread best practice and raise the standard of our parks and green spaces.
&amp;gt; “The new partnership believes the Green Flag Award is a model of how, by sharing good practice and celebrating and rewarding quality, we can raise the standards of public space in the UK, providing a range of benefits for local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Jenny Abramsky, Chair of the Heritage Lottery Fund said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted the Minister has made this commitment to the future of the Green Flags Awards scheme as it plays a vital role in inspiring local authorities and community groups to maintain their parks. Since 1996, the Heritage Lottery Fund and Big Lottery Fund have jointly invested over £640million to transform over 700 public open spaces.  The continuation of the Award - which we regard as a mark of quality all parks we fund must meet - will help safeguard our past investment along with our new commitment of £100million over the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Ainsworth, Chair of the Big Lottery Fund said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is great news and encouraging evidence of the government’s commitment to the quality of places and spaces where people live, work and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep Britain Tidy has been running the Green Flag Award scheme since 2009, with the contract expiring this year.  DCLG advertised the opportunity to run the scheme under licence and invited bids during the summer.  We are today confirming Keep Britain Tidy has been successful in its bid to become the licence holder for the scheme over the next five years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14737</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-support-to-help-town-team-partners-transform-their-high-streets"/>
    <title>New support to help 'Town Team Partners' transform their high streets</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of towns across the country are being offered support that will help them revitalise their high streets, Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following applications by local MPs, over 300 Town Teams have signed up to become &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/townteampartners/"&gt;Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;, and will benefit from a package of support, which includes help from the Government as well as advice and support from leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Town Teams Partners will receive an immediate boost, with national event to be held in Birmingham tomorrow by the Association of Town Centre Managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the extra support would help the teams to strengthen their leadership on the ground, and enable them to try new ideas on their high streets to make them more attractive and competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="designs-for-deptford"&gt;Designs for Deptford&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mark the announcement the Minister visited Deptford, a successful applicant to become a Town Team Partner. The team have plans to use the creative buzz generated by local artists by installing their art works in the high street and in local shops - from boutiques to the local fishmongers -  all under the ‘Made in Deptford’ banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also saw the Deptford Project, a railway carriage that has been transformed into a cafe - a great example of how the Town Team Partner plans to transform the look of the high street and showcase local talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/UuacApa2aUE?rel=0;showinfo=0" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/word/2242676.doc"&gt;Town Team Partners - Transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;MS Word, 27 kb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s a real hunger in town centres across the country for them to be revitalised and remain attractive places to visit. So I’m delighted that from today over 300 Town Team Partners will begin to receive a package of support that helps them breathe new life into their high streets.
&amp;gt; “No one’s pretending that there’s a silver bullet for improving the performance of our town centres. Yet as I saw in Deptford: with this new support, and the opportunity to learn from each other, Town Teams can channel their energy and enthusiasm into promoting a more exciting and competitive offer on our high-streets, and help them thrive for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="package-of-support"&gt;Package of support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity to become a Town Team Partner received an overwhelming response from towns across the country, with hundreds of MPs submitting applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Town Team Partner will have access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;help to get started and become established in their town&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and secure support from industry experts and trade bodies&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice and support&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas, and&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list of Town Team Partners is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="high-street-x-factor"&gt;High Street x-factor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Town centres also have the opportunity to win the £1million &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prize will be shared among the high streets that show the greatest improvements. Towns will be judged by an independent expert panel, for the inventiveness of their schemes and evidence of their impact, such as increased footfall or turnover, or improved skills and employment levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towns will also need to explain how they plan to use their prize money to further support their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14724</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/heart-of-stoke-on-trent-set-for-dramatic-transformation"/>
    <title>Heart of Stoke-on-Trent set for dramatic transformation</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plans to transform the city of Stoke-on-Trent into a thriving and successful centre are well underway thanks to a fresh injection of funding and an ambitious vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements will help enhance the image and appeal of the city to businesses, attracting fresh inward investment and job opportunities, and also help join up other developments taking place around the city from the Central Business District through to the Mitchell Memorial Theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public realm improvements, supported by £2.1million from the European Regional Development Fund, which is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and matched by Stoke-on-Trent City Council, are part of a package of improvements to develop and upgrade the city centre - creating a legacy for local people and making it more attractive to potential new investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Baroness Hanham CBE said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To improve the overall perception and performance of an area you have to get the foundations right. Stoke-on-Trent city centre is in great need of regeneration to ensure its future is prosperous. This has already started with key developments taking place in city and I am delighted that we are able to offer funding support to activities which complement these developments. From new street furniture to landscaped areas the changes planned will help create an attractive, vibrant and welcoming environment.
&amp;gt; “As well as creating something special for local people, I also hope this investment will send a clear signal to private sector investors, helping to continue the much needed and on-going regeneration of the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents, workers and visitors alike will be able to enjoy newly landscaped public spaces and street furniture, creating an attractive environment. The improvements will focus on the areas of Tontine Street, Percy Street and Stafford Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Ruth Rosenau, Stoke-on-Trent City Council cabinet member for regeneration, planning and transport, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re delighted to mark the start of these long-awaited works. It’s a very exciting project. It will give the area a contemporary city style and feel, but retain its very special character and heritage.
&amp;gt; “The area will become much more attractive and provide a more welcoming shopping environment, with natural stone paving and granite benches with ceramic detailing, plus new lighting, signs and trees.
&amp;gt; “It’s around 25 years since work on this scale and quality was last done in the area so it’s literally getting its biggest makeover in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about activities set for Stoke-on-Trent, contact Ciara Hill in Stoke-on-Trent City Council Press Office on 01782 232130 or e-mail &lt;a href="mailto:ciara.hill@stoke.gov.uk"&gt;ciara.hill@stoke.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2236525.pdf"&gt;News Release - Heart of Stoke-on-Trent set for dramatic transformation&lt;/a&gt;
(PDF, 45 kb, 2 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is the managing authority for the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Programme which runs from 2007 to 2013. This is one of the funds established by the European Commission to help local areas stimulate their economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme has been allocated 400million euros to invest in projects which will support local businesses and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West Midlands the priority areas and themes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Innovation and Research and Development
**Increasing investment in research and development through helping businesses take forward new innovation, sharing of knowledge and developing and demonstrating new technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Enterprise Development
**Increasing business performance through supporting high growth businesses, improving resource efficiency, providing access to finance and developing a strong entrepreneurial culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Sustainable Urban Development
**Improving the performance of key urban areas through regenerating local areas, encouraging investment and new businesses, creating job opportunities and helping communities most in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Inter-Regional Activity
**Working with European partners to learn and improve, share and apply best practice and solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow us on Twitter at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/erdfwmnews"&gt;www.twitter.com/erdfwmnews&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Lynsey Cooke, Communications Manager on 0303 444 6587 or email &lt;a href="mailto:lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14708</id>
    <published>2012-09-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-in-buy-british-call"/>
    <title>Minister in 'Buy British' call</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Don Foster today encouraged the public to ‘Buy British’ and recognise the importance of home-grown produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster hailed the growth of the nation’s farmers’ markets in recent years but said more can be done to support both high streets and the agricultural economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Harvest festival approaches he pledged to make it a priority in his new role to build on the success of the Government’s Love Your Local Market campaign and back British products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster was speaking on a visit to Brighton farmers market during the ‘Organic September’ month organised by the National Farmers Retail and Markets Association and ahead of their annual conference in Harrogate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging the public to buy British produce from their local Farmers Market will not only benefit the country’s farmers but will also help regenerate high streets and town squares as they see an increase in footfall to surrounding shops and restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has been driving the regeneration and growth of the nation’s high streets through Portas Pilots, Enterprise Zones and by keeping business rates low for small business owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In my own town of Bath we are proud to have had the country’s first Farmers Market and their success continues to literally bring home the bacon for British Farmers and their produce. Markets are a British institution - the familiar cry of ‘pound for a pound’ echoing across town squares.
&amp;gt; “The Harvest festivals will be in full swing in the coming weeks and I’m encouraging the public to visit the nearest market this weekend and ‘Buy British’ - they’ll be impressed by the great value and great taste of the produce on offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631610585980/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Love Your Local Market and the National Markets Fortnight was celebrated in June 2012. Information can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/"&gt;www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The National Farmers and Retail and Markets Association conference takes place on 30th September 2012. More information can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.farma.org.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=104:farmers-market-conference-london-2012&amp;amp;catid=17&amp;amp;Itemid=176"&gt;Farma website&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14693</id>
    <published>2012-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/common-sense-planning-reform-to-create-more-homes-and-boost-the-high-street"/>
    <title>Common sense planning reform to create more homes and boost the high street</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has approved a new measure that will increase the number of homes in town centres and help increase footfall on high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New planning rights will allow more flats to be created above shops without the need for planning permission. Two flats will be allowed to be created in office or storage space under new permitted development rights coming into force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change further streamlines the planning system, making it easier, quicker and cheaper for people to create new homes in existing underused space. It has the potential to help increase the amount of affordable housing and ensures better use is made of existing developed land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relaxing planning restrictions on creating flats above shops can also help increase the vitality of town centres by increasing footfall and providing a boost to high street regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These are common sense planning reforms that will deliver more affordable homes in areas where there are good transport links whilst ensuring better use of existing developed land.
&amp;gt; “Cutting this red tape should be a shot in the arm for the high street increasing footfall and providing a boost to regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Greg Clark Mr Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government is determined to make the very best use of existing buildings to provide more homes as quickly and simply as possible. This change offers real potential to provide more affordable housing and give a much needed boost to our high streets.
&amp;gt; “Ensuring unused space above shops can be used in a better way is one of the many changes the Government has introduced to streamline the planning system and to cut unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already taken steps to improve the planning system through the National Planning Policy Framework and the Localism Act, which are already delivering results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also announced proposed measures to simplify the planning system further by making it easier to temporarily re-use some buildings without needing planning permission, streamlining the paper work needed for planning applications and speeding up planning appeal decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has also outlined a package of measures to help high streets reclaim their role at the heart of our communities. These include encouraging town centres to become Town Team partners to benefit from the support and advice available from the Government and leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The change in permitted development rights applies to A1 (retail units) and A2 (financial/professional services units) commercial properties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current legislation only allows for one flat to be created above a shop without the need for a planning application.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new permitted development rights will come into force on 1 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11802</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/our-town-first-future-high-street-x-fund-prospectus"/>
    <title>Our town first: future high street x-fund prospectus</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the Government’s response to the Portas Review, we announced a £1million Future High Street X- Fund, to reward those areas delivering the most effective and innovative plans to bring their town centres back to life. The £1million prize fund will recognise and reward locations who have undertaken the most outstanding transformations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prospectus provides details of the fund and how to make a nomination. The closing date for nominations is 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14691</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/put-our-towns-first-and-revive-the-nations-high-streets"/>
    <title>Put our towns first and revive the nation's high streets</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Town Team partners to benefit from multi-million pound support&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPs returning to Parliament next week can put their towns first by putting their local high streets forward for a package of Government support and help make them the beating hearts of their communities once again, Local Government Minister Grant Shapps said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2082239.jpg" alt="High Street Illustration (Dermott Flynn)"&gt;Illustration by Dermott Flynn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister urged MPs whose towns missed out in the Portas Pilot competition to apply now for their town centres to become &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/townteampartners/"&gt;Town Team partners&lt;/a&gt; and benefit from help available, including support from the Government and access to advice and support from leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also called on towns across the country to apply to be considered for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/x-fund/"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund&lt;/a&gt;. Those town centres that show they have made the greatest improvements will win a share of the £1million prize on offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having witnessed the overwhelming response from over 400 towns to our search for Portas Pilots, I’m determined that the energy and enthusiasm they displayed is not lost, and that every area has the opportunity to breathe new life into their high streets.
&amp;gt; “It’s time to put ‘Our Towns First’. That’s why today I’m calling on MPs to apply for their towns to become Town Team partners, so that communities can put their plans into action with the backing of retail experts as well as learning the lessons from other town teams from across the country.
&amp;gt; “And for those who make the greatest improvements to their high streets, I look forward to awarding them with a share of the £1million Future High Streets X-Fund so that they can continue their sterling work to bring their town centres back to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="no-high-street-left-behind"&gt;No high street left behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This package of support comes after an overwhelming response to the competition to find 27 Portas Pilots. With over 400 town teams submitting bids, Mr Shapps is clear that none will be left behind in the campaign to breathe new life into the nation’s high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those MPs that apply to be Town Team partners will be making a commitment for their town team to take forward key elements of their original plan for reviving their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In exchange, they will have access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management, as well as key informative events;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct mentoring and visits from a range of retail experts;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regular meetings with other Town Teams to share lessons learned, tips and ideas; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an online community to receive advice and information from retail experts; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Already Portas Pilots across the country are taking steps to bring their high streets back to life. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market Rasen’s Portas Pilot, who attracted 35 new traders to the town in July putting the ‘market’ back into Market Rasen and enticing thousands of new visitors into the town. Going forward, they are now looking to run their next BIG Market event on 1 September with the theme, ‘Say Goodbye to Summer’;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton’s Portas Pilot, who are already achieving their goal to connect local businesses to the range of events taking place in the local high street. For example, for the 25th anniversary of Stockton’s International Riverside Festival, local restaurants were offered their own gazebos, banners and leaflets to serve their food to visitors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dartford’s Portas Pilot, which has opened a community shop to be used by a range of community groups as a place to meet and socialise. The Pilot have also been generating more Sunday trading through a ‘My Sunday’ marketing campaign that promotes the towns businesses, market, parks and free parking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="future-high-street-x-fund-open-for-business"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund open for business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps also called for nominations for town centres to be considered for the £1million Future High Street X-Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prize will be shared among the high streets that show the greatest improvements. Towns will be judged by an independent expert panel, for the inventiveness of their schemes and the impacts they can evidence, such as increased footfall or turnover, or improved skills and employment levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towns will also need to explain how they plan to use their prize money to further support their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MPs representing towns whose Portas Pilots bids were unsuccessful will today receive an application form to put forward their towns to be Town Team Partners. The deadline for submitting forms is 16 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Town First: Future High Street X-Fund - Prospectus&lt;/em&gt; is published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/x-fundprospectus"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/x-fundprospectus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent expert panel of judges will include representatives from Alliance Boots, the Association of Town Centre Management, Civic Voice, Locality and Yellowdoor (Mary Portas’s retail and brand communication agency).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
