<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Boosting private sector employment in England"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:30+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18321</id>
    <published>2011-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/regional-growth-fund-to-help-small-businesses"/>
    <title>Regional Growth Fund to help small businesses</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Hundreds of small businesses will benefit from government investment of £95 million to help boost growth and rebalance the economy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funding is expected to create at least 4,000 jobs and unlock around £500 million of new investment by small and medium businesses (SMEs).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RBS, NatWest and HSBC have agreed to facilitate the distribution of the £95 million - which is part of the government’s Regional Growth Fund. RBS and NatWest will facilitate £70 million and HSBC will facilitate £25 million. The banks will not profit financially from the administration of these schemes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these schemes small businesses, which are unable to secure commercial funding for their project, have the potential to benefit from government support through the banks’ regional networks in order to make their project commercially viable. The schemes announced today will provide grants to support SMEs considering investing in new capital assets and creating new employment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Mark Prisk said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These schemes will directly help SMEs that want to invest and create new jobs. They will deliver a shot in the arm to local communities and help small businesses drive local growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“100 per cent of the RGF funding will be provided as grants to small businesses with the banks employing their regional networks to administer the schemes for free.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-features-of-the-rbs-natwest-and-hsbc-schemes"&gt;Key features of the RBS, NatWest and HSBC schemes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RBS and NatWest scheme is called the regional growth fund and will distribute £70 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HSBC scheme is called the Assisted Asset Purchase Scheme and will distribute £25 million.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The funding will support new job-creating investment by SMEs across England, in particular parts that have become over-dependent on the public sector. 100 per cent of the RGF funding will be provided as grants to SMEs with the banks employing their regional networks to administer the schemes on a pro-bono basis. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SMEs can qualify for a grant if they are going to invest in new capital assets, such as plant and machinery, and create new jobs - and cannot get normal bank finance. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grants of up to £500,000 will be awarded alongside the award of a new bank loan on commercial terms. &lt;br&gt;
To qualify for the NatWest and RBS scheme, SMEs need a turnover of less than £25 million. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To qualify for the HSBC scheme the SME will need a turnover of less than 50 million Euros. &lt;br&gt;
The banks will not earn any fees to administer the scheme. Interest earned on any funds held on the bank’s balance sheet must be used for beneficiary grants or returned to the government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s Regional Growth Fund is a £1.4 billion fund supporting projects that can create jobs, are based in areas dependent on the public sector and are supported by private sector investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421994&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Business Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Nov/sme-business-growth"&gt;New measures to help British businesses&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18322</id>
    <published>2011-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-measures-announced-to-boost-british-business"/>
    <title>New measures announced to boost British business</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government announces new measures to help small businesses grow and create jobs, export to new markets, secure finance and cut red tape.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron announced the the business growth package at the ‘Exporting for Growth’ and Fitness Finance conference that will benefit hundreds of small businesses. They include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Nov/regional-growth-fund-to-help-small-businesses"&gt;£95 million investment from the Regional Growth Fund.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Web Fuelled Business initiative, helping businesses exploit the potential of the internet. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Export Challenge, opening up new markets around the world. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Finance Fitness campaign, providing the support small businesses need to access finance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Follow the Exporting for Growth and Finance Fitness event live [link expired]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“British SMEs are already doing incredible things, but we urgently need more of them to follow that boldness. We need this to be a country where more people think ‘I can start my own business and I can sell to the world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our determination is to come through these difficult times stronger, to trade our way to growth and jobs. We need to show real optimism about the future, and we need to show real aggression about pursuing Britain’s interests in the world. The markets are there to be tapped; the deals are there to be done, the opportunities are there to be capitalised on. Now together we must seize them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the Prime Minister’s speech&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-business-growth-package"&gt;The business growth package&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£95 million of new Regional Growth Fund money has been allocated for SMEs who can’t access commercial funding. This is being directed to small businesses through RBS, Natwest and HSBC - and it is expected to unlock a further £500 million of investment. The fund uses the high street banks to provide finance for SMEs seeking to purchase assets and create employment, which are unable to secure commercial funding for their project. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From April 1st ‘one-click registration’ will go live, so that businesses can get online, register their business at Companies House, sign up for PAYE registration, Corporation Tax and Self Assessment all in one place. The ability to register for VAT will be added shortly after. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching the Web Fuelled Business initiative - the Department for Business is teaming up with founding Dragons’ Den panellist Doug Richard and Yell to get 3,500 businesses into workshops all over the country to ensure they are able to exploit the global opportunities offered by the internet. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching the National Export Challenge; a series of initiatives to give SMEs the knowledge they need to make the first steps to breaking into new markets. The national challenge will get business intermediaries to provide sector knowledge and support for SMEs. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching the ‘Open to Export’ web resource providing small businesses with professional export advice, hosted by Yell to allow UK firms to swap information and experiences directly. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching a new campaign promoting different sources of finance to SMEs and giving them the tools and advice to access the finance they need, including advice and best-practice guidance for SMEs and a new Finance Finder tool on the BusinessLink website. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new UKTI prize for the best export idea. This prize will run regionally and nationally. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new “how to” export guide which professional services companies can use with their own branding to issue in branches, to memberships and customers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Promoting British business to the many journalists and international business people passing through London during the Olympic Games by establishing the new British Business Embassy, based at Lancaster House. It is estimated this will achieve £700m in export sales as a result of games-time activity. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To support the growth of businesses in Tech City the Prime Minister announced the expansion of the Red Tape Challenge so that entrepreneurs and investors can tell the Government where rules and regulations get in the way of innovation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, not only are we able to announce substantial new measures to support businesses, but also to see the commitment of private sector firms and organisations to tackling the economic challenges we face. We want to reach and help the 80 per cent of SMEs who don’t seek external advice before applying for finance.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The small firms of today are Britain’s international success stories of our future and it is this success that will build the strong, balanced economy that will secure our economic prosperity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421992&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;BIS press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/home.html?guid=none"&gt;UKTI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18301</id>
    <published>2011-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/950-million-investment-to-boost-local-economies-and-jobs"/>
    <title>£950 million investment to boost local economies and jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The second round of the Government's Regional Growth Fund will help create and safeguard more than 200,000 jobs across England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 31 October Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg announced &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;the successful bids for the second round of the Government’s £1.4 billion Regional Growth Fund (RGF).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support 119 bids from businesses and local partnerships with projects to expand their operations, create new jobs and attract private investment. Discussions are ongoing with a further 10 bidders about their projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 201,000 jobs created or protected, around 37,000 will be directly created jobs, and more than 164,000 will be in the supply chain. The Government investment will support nearly £6 billion of private investment secured by the successful projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be able to announce this boost to business, which will jump start growth and create jobs that last in the places that really need it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This targeted support for businesses across the country allows them to expand and create jobs. It unlocks private sector investment - with at least £5 put in for every £1 of public money. People in the rest of Britain have been let down for far too long by governments in thrall to one Square Mile of it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The first pot of Regional Growth Fund money is already making a difference across the country - helping to rebalance our economy so that every region and sector benefits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-successful-bids"&gt;The successful bids&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful bids are subject to legal checks before they can be awarded their final allocation of funding. This will establish whether the Government is confident that the organisations can deliver on the proposals in the bid and be agreed through contract. The Government expects the money to start being passed on to the bidders in the spring.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the successful bids include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research and development project to investigate the introduction of a new engine into the Bentley model range with a focus on the Chinese market. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project to stimulate investment, employment and economic growth in Bradford city centre by incentivising investment in, and speeding up delivery of, Westfield Bradford and the Central Business District, complemented by wider public investment in city centre business rate relief. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of new kilns and firing methods using innovative sintering processes at Ceram Research Ltd, which can be scaled up for industrial use in ceramics industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to be doing all we can to enable businesses and organisations to create much needed jobs and inject private investment into the economy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have announced today that a further 119 projects will benefit from the fund, and expect to deliver a huge number of jobs across their businesses and in the supply chain.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a very significant boost to local communities, and the Regional Growth Fund will help businesses to drive local growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421806&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Read the press notice in full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund/successful-projects-list/summary-rgf-projects-round-2"&gt;Successful 2nd round bids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18303</id>
    <published>2011-10-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/huddersfield-factory-gears-up-for-green-growth"/>
    <title>Huddersfield factory gears up for green growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nick Clegg and Vince Cable announce £4.8 million of Regional Growth Funding for local businesses.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Huddersfield business David Brown Gear Systems has successfully secured £4.8 million of private sector and government funding from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund,&lt;/a&gt; Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg and Business Secretary Vince Cable announced during a visit to the business today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will help create around 80 new jobs at the David Brown factory thanks to the funding programme which sees government and the private sector working together to boost regional growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister and Business Secretary visited the factory today to sign the legal contracts that will deliver the money. This follows a period of strict checks by the company and the government to ensure the deal offers the best value for money for taxpayers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Not only is it great to be announcing new jobs here in Huddersfield today, but it’s fantastic that David Brown is using the Regional Growth Fund to scale its operations up and out into the new and growing ‘green’ market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Creating jobs and growth is our number one priority for Britain right now.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But it’s not enough just to get us back to where we were. There can be no forgotten areas of Britain. We need to rebalance the economy by supporting growth in every region and across a range of industries. That’s what the Regional Growth Fund is all about.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="innovative-manufacturing"&gt;Innovative manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.davidbrown.com/"&gt;David Brown Gear Systems,&lt;/a&gt; which is a leading manufacturer of gear systems including those for submarines and trains, will use the funding to extend its reach into the renewable energy market, stepping up production of special gears for wind turbines by creating a wind turbine research and development innovation centre. David Brown will be investing around £2.8 million in addition to the government funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable also visited the University of Huddersfield for the official opening of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epsrc.ac.uk/funding/centres/innovativemanufacturing/Pages/imrcadvancedmetrology.aspx"&gt;Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) Centre for Innovative Manufacturing in Advanced Metrology.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was established earlier this year when EPSRC awarded funding of £4.7 million to the University’s globally-renowned Centre for Precision Technologies. A consortium of leading UK firms and organisations including Rolls Royce and David Brown Gear Systems, contributed a further £3 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre has embarked on a five-year project bringing together leading researchers and businesses. The result will be that companies will be able to fit their existing machine tools with devices that ensure almost total accuracy during manufacture, saving money and improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a great boost to the economy in Huddersfield. The investment of £2 million announced today for David Brown and the support for the Centre of Innovative Manufacturing will help businesses in the area expand their capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Support of this kind is vital if we are to help businesses create jobs where they are most needed and lever in important private sector investment. I’m looking forward to making more announcements of this kind in the coming weeks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421590&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Read the press notice in full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/pm-4-5bn-uk-oil-and-gas/"&gt;PM gives go-ahead for £4.5bn oil and gas project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Oct/170-million-government-funding-for-manufacturing-research"&gt;£170 million boost for UK manufacturing research&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18278</id>
    <published>2011-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/judging-starts-on-regional-growth-fund-bids"/>
    <title>Judging starts on Regional Growth Fund bids</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BIS has received more than 490 bids competing for a share of £950 million from round 2 of the Regional Growth Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These bids were received in response to the second round of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;£1.4 billion fund,&lt;/a&gt; which is designed to encourage enterprise, growth and jobs in the private sector and support regions that are dependent on the public sector. The bids will compete for a share of £950 million. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund/successful-projects-list"&gt;Further details on regional spread and total value of the bids&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 492 bids, asking for £3.3 billion, are being assessed by the Independent Advisory Board, chaired by Lord Heseltine, over the summer. The board will then make recommendations to a board of ministers, led by Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg, which will make the final decisions as to which proposals should receive funding. It is expected that the successful bidders will be announced in the autumn.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 140 bids received for the North West - the highest of all the regions, which account for 28 per cent of all the bids received. More than 330 of the total number of bids received are bidding for between £1 million and £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This vital regional fund uses government investment and multiplies it to give a real boost to local businesses. Round one is already helping local economies across the country and has attracted £2.5 billion of private sector investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will directly create or protect over 27,000 jobs, and secure around a further 100,000 jobs on related supply chains and in local economies. We welcome the bids received for the second round, and hope we can do even more this time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allocation of funding each successful proposal will receive will be the minimum amount the proposal needs to get off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each bid must also demonstrate it is bringing in private sources of funding as well. The public investment in the first 50 successful bids is expected to secure a further £2.5 billion of private investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We knew from the road shows there was going to be a huge amount of interest in the second round of the Regional Growth Fund, and we have been overwhelmed by the volume of bids submitted.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is clearly a hunger for public support which will allow new and exciting projects to deliver jobs and growth in their local communities to get off the ground, and I’m pleased to see so many people wanting to be a part of this. We now face the difficult task of assessing each of these bids; we have a busy summer ahead of us!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420634&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18249</id>
    <published>2011-05-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/local-growth-moves-up-a-gear"/>
    <title>Local growth moves up a gear</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New measures to help local enterprise partnerships and further roadshows for the Regional Growth Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Mark Prisk has stepped up the drive to stimulate local economic growth, announcing a package with three measures to help &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/leps"&gt;local enterprise partnerships&lt;/a&gt; get up and running. He also met for the first time the South East Midlands local enterprise partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine also kicked off a series of road shows on Thursday 12 March to promote the second round of the Regional Growth Fund and encourage bidders to compete for a share of £950m.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-enterprise-partnerships"&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local enterprise partnerships (LEPs) are able to bid for a share of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/leps/lep-start-up-fund"&gt;one-off £5m start up fund&lt;/a&gt; until the end of June. The Government expects the fund to cover start up costs such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office rental and equipment. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Training. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engaging with the wider business community. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;LEPs that already have these functions in place will not be able to bid for a share of the fund. The bids need to demonstrate that they can bring in other sources of funding as well, and that they have a plan to become self-sustainable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LEPS can also access the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/leptoolbox"&gt;online Toolbox&lt;/a&gt;, which provides comprehensive information on economic development activity across government departments, and ideas for strong partnership and government working. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships will also be able to access information through the new BIS Local network which will be the first point of contact on any issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we are moving up a gear in promoting local growth. Over the last ten months, business and civic leaders have risen to the challenge and we now have 33 partnerships in place covering 92 per cent of all businesses in England.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The package of support opportunities I’ve announced today will help partnerships to translate their ideas and ambition into real action to help businesses in their areas and to unlock growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Mark Prisk meets with South East Midlands local enterprise partnership &lt;br&gt;
** &lt;br&gt;
Mark Prisk met with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.southeastmidlands.org.uk/"&gt;South East Midlands LEP&lt;/a&gt; at Bedford i-lab on Friday 13 May to hear about the partnership’s plans for appointing its board and the main objectives and priorities it hopes to address.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The partnership covers Bedford, Central Bedforshire, Luton, Milton Keynes, Aykesbury Vale, Cherwell, Dacorum, Northampton, Corby, Daventry, Kettering and South Northamptonshire.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South East Midlands LEP covers a population of 1.8 million people, and 76,000 active enterprises.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The representatives I met have exceptional local knowledge and we discussed their ideas for the future and how they will put their action plans into practice. I have every confidence that they will be a success and look forward to hearing more about their progress.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will continue to meet more partnerships across England in the coming weeks and months to hear about their concerns, their successes and most importantly how they plan to make a contribution to economic growth in their area.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419486&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Read the press notice&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first road show for the second round of bidding for the Regional Growth Fund took place in Margate on Thursday 12 March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/blog/2011/05/11/regional-growth-fund-blog-takes-off/"&gt;Read Sir Ian Wrigglesworth’s first post on the Regional Growth Fund blog;&lt;/a&gt; his personal take on the Fund and where he will talk about his experiences as he tours the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second round of the Regional Growth Fund opened to bids on April 12 and will close at midday on July 1. The second round will aim to allocate around £950m - the bulk of the £1.4bn fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Find out more details about the Regional Growth Fund, submitting a bid and future road shows.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine attended the event in Margate, and spoke about the importance of economic growth and the role of the Regional Growth Fund. He then took questions about the process of submitting high-quality bids that offer the potential to create new jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Regional Growth Fund was exceptionally popular in the first round, and we received many bids that demonstrated strategic thinking on how to create jobs and contribute to local economies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope businesses and public-private partnerships are inspired to think about innovative and creative ways of making a difference to growth and shaping their economic future, and that we will see results of this thinking when we are assessing bids.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The road shows are an excellent opportunity for potential bidders to find out more information about ensuring bids meet the objectives and criteria. I urge all those interested to ask questions, and get as much out of these events as possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419462&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice: Local growth moves up a gear as Business Minister announces growth package for local enterprise partnerships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419486&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice: Business Minister Mark Prisk has had his first meeting with the South East Midlands local enterprise partnership today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/leps/lep-start-up-fund"&gt;Guidance and Application details for the £5m Start Up fund.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://geocommons.com/maps/32888"&gt;Map of approved local enterprise partnerships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419444&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice: Lord Heseltine encourages business to bid for share of funding for jobs and growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/May/local-growth"&gt;Attending a RGF Roadshow&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18238</id>
    <published>2011-04-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/450m-investment-for-regional-jobs-and-growth"/>
    <title>£450M investment for regional jobs and growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The first round of the Regional Growth Fund (RGF) sees £450 million invested in businesses across Britain.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first round of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund (RGF) &lt;/a&gt;will see more public investment support 50 bids by companies and partnerships across Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They demonstrated how they would create jobs and a high level of economic growth in their local communities over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RGF is a £1.4bn fund which is designed to encourage enterprise, growth and jobs in the private sector and support areas and communities that are dependent on the public sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government expects over 27,000 jobs to be directly created and safeguarded, with close to a further 100,000 jobs in associated supply chains and local economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund#round2"&gt;The second round of the fund opens to bids today&lt;/a&gt;. This round will aim to allocate the remainder of nearly £1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announcing the successful bids, Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was bowled over by the quality of the bids. This money will now help create and safeguard jobs in some of the communities worst hit by the economic downturn.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today is a step towards rebalancing our economy away from an unhealthy overreliance on a small number of industries and a few areas. We need to spread opportunity across the whole country, drawing on our many talents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="results-of-the-1st-round"&gt;Results of the 1st round&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful bids include the development of a former eye hospital in Manchester into a biomedical centre of excellence; the construction of a manufacturing plant on Teesside to develop resins for food and drink packaging; development of a cutting edge factory &amp;amp; R&amp;amp;D laboratory for Holroyd Precision Ltd in Rochdale, and a proposal from General Motors to build the next-generation Vivaro van in Luton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Supporting job creation in the regions is vital if we are to drive growth in our local communities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have received a large number of ambitious and highly competitive bids to this first round of the Regional Growth Fund, which will help a number of businesses across the country to expand and create thousands of new jobs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Regional Growth Fund is a competitive fund and we wanted to see proposals that created jobs in the private sector, in areas of deprivation and that is at risk of suffering from public sector cuts. I’m confident that the successful bids we have chosen will deliver on this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419127&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Economic growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth/the-plan-for-growth"&gt;The Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18167</id>
    <published>2010-10-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-plan-for-local-growth"/>
    <title>New plan for local growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government has announced new plans to kick start local growth</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that there are now 39 Local Enterprise partnerships. See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/leps/statistics"&gt;LEPs: Coverage and statistics&lt;/a&gt; for details&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper published today sets out the Government’s role in empowering locally driven growth, encouraging business investment and promoting economic development. For local communities this means ensuring that everyone has access to opportunities that growth brings and everyone is able to fulfil their potential. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the White Paper it was announced that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twenty-four local enterprise partnerships proposals have been given the green light, in a landmark move that will see local business and civic leaders working together to drive sustainable economic growth and create new jobs in their communities. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The £1.4bn Regional Growth Fund will be open for business from today, as announced by the Deputy Prime Minister. This will support the creation of private sector jobs and will particularly support communities currently dependent on the public sector, helping them make the transition to private sector led growth and prosperity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/cm7961-local-growth-white-paper.pdf"&gt;To find out more about Government’s approach to sub-national Growth, download the White Paper. (PDF, 1.9 Mb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sets out the Government’s new approach on rebalancing the economy and helping drive sustainable growth by focusing on three key themes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shifting power to local communities and businesses, by creating dynamic local enterprise partnerships. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing confidence to invest. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focused investment, by tackling barriers to growth that the market will not address itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/growth"&gt;Find out more about the path to sustainable growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="section"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-enterprise-partnerships"&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who understand their economies best should lead their development and enable all places to fulfil their potential. In September the Government received 62 responses to its invitation to form local enterprise partnerships. Proposals covered every part of England outside London. Today 24 bids have been asked to progress their proposals to the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View a map of approved local enterprise partnerships &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://geocommons.com/maps/32888"&gt;View full map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was delighted that so many of the proposals for local enterprise partnerships showed real imagination and initiative and a genuine desire to drive local economic growth. I am pleased to announce that we are asking 24 of these partnerships to set up their boards and get to work.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The knowledge and expertise of the private sector, local authorities and their local communities will be crucial as we work to create a better environment for business and ensure that everyone has access to the opportunities that growth brings.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships not being approved today have been informed and given feedback on how to develop their proposals further. Revised proposals will be welcomed by Government as they become ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper also sets out the timetable and further criteria for the operation of the newly-launched £1.4bn &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;. The fund will provide focused investment for projects that offer significant potential for private sector-led economic growth and sustainable employment. &lt;strong&gt;First round bids for funding are requested by 21 January 2011&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine will Chair the Independent Advisory Panel, which will consider all bids submitted to the fund and make recommendations to Ministers on which to approve. Lord Heseltine will be supported by Deputy Chair, Sir Ian Wrigglesworth and a panel of academics, business and civic leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=416242&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/cm7961-local-growth-white-paper.pdf"&gt;Download the White Paper on sub-national Growth (PDF, 1.9 Mb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/u/10-1226-understanding-local-growth.pdf"&gt;Analytical paper on sub national growth&lt;/a&gt; - this paper sets out the latest analysis underpinning the Government’s approach to local growth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/growth"&gt;Setting out the path to sustainable growth &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development"&gt;Economic development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18110</id>
    <published>2010-06-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/budget-creates-conditions-for-enterprise-and-growth"/>
    <title>Budget creates conditions for enterprise and growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer has set out his Budget with a comprehensive five-year plan to rebuild the British economy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The plan sets out action to tackle the unprecedented budget deficit, introduce a fairer tax system, encourage enterprise and support long-term growth across the economy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor wants to support business and make the UK more competitive. This means giving businesses more freedom by reducing regulation and providing targeted tax breaks, while ensuring that the economic opportunities for businesses are shared more evenly throughout the UK’s regions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A major package of reforms to reduce corporation tax rates including a reduction in the main rate of corporation tax from 28 per cent to 24 per cent over the course of four financial years from April 2011 and reductions to the main and special rates of capital allowances from April 2012. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A reduction in the small profits rate from 21 per cent to 20 per cent from April 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A National Insurance Contributions (NICs) holiday for new businesses which start-up in certain areas of the UK over the next three years. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An increase in the Enterprise Finance Guarantee and the creation of a new Enterprise Capital Fund. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Regional Growth Fund in 2010-11 and 2012-13 to support increases in business employment and growth. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 10 per cent rate of capital gains tax for entrepreneurial business activities will be extended from the first £2 million to the first £5 million of qualifying gains made over a lifetime. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other BIS related measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A review of the employment laws, by each relevant Department that will start immediately, to ensure maximum flexibility, protect fairness and promote competition &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stripping back regulation and introducing sunset clauses on all new regulations &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultation on how to phase out the Default Retirement Age &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Injecting private capital into Royal Mail, including opportunities for employee ownership &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Release of spectrum to support super-fast mobile broadband services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examining options for realising value from the student loan portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable told Sky News:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The deficit has got to be dealt with through a combination of taxes, spending cuts and economic growth. Growth will not happen automatically. The Budget gives incentives to companies to take on new employees. When you ask businesspeople what they want, their first request is to sort out the public finances.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2010_june_budget.htm"&gt;Treasury budget pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/junebudget_press_notices.htm"&gt;Treasury press notices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/jun/22/budget-taxandspending"&gt;Vince Cable’s column in The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
