<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16667</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-performance-and-the-planning-guarantee"/>
    <title>Planning performance and the Planning Guarantee</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation links to the Government’s proposals, contained within Clause 1 of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, to introduce legislation to give applicants the choice of submitting planning applications direct to the secretary of state, where the local planning authority is underperforming.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on what measures to use to identify an authority’s performance, how to identify underperformance and how to identify improved performance and related measures to underpin the Planning Guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16257</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-review-of-planning-appeal-procedures"/>
    <title>Technical review of planning appeal procedures</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published: 1 November 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to make the planning appeals process faster and more transparent, improve consistency and certainty in decision taking timescales. The proposals will bring cost and time benefits for those appealing decisions and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:36:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14388</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation"/>
    <title>Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes changes to increase permitted development rights for extensions to homes and business premises in non-protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to amend the Town and Country Planning (General Permitted Development) Order 1995 to allow homeowners and businesses to make larger extensions to their homes and business premises without requiring a planning application, and to allow quicker installation of broadband infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please submit your views using the questionnaire below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16273</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13313</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:45:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-to-get-jobs-and-boosting-growth"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people to get jobs and boosting growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk and saw how local businesses and civic leaders are using government funding to help boost local development and deliver the government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an enterprise zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury enterprise zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the enterprise zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprise zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.
Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase, which would see the development of 1,500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough local enterprise partnerships have contributed £2 million each from the government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using enterprise zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16940</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T20:24:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-applications-in-england-april-to-june-2012"/>
    <title>Planning applications in England: April to June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on planning applications were released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority on 26 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the period April to June 2012 authorities undertaking district level planning in England:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;received 121,150 applications for planning permission, a decrease of 1% compared with the corresponding quarter in 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decided 110,500 planning applications, 1% higher than in the same quarter in the previous year &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;granted 90,200 permissions, 1% higher than in the same quarter in 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decided 2% fewer residential decisions compared to the June quarter 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the year ending June 2012, district-level planning authorities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;received 476,100 applications, a decrease of 1% on the year ending June 2011 figure &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decided 436,000 planning applications, a slight decrease on the year ending June 2011 figure &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;granted 355,200 permissions, a small increase compared to the figure for the year to June 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decided 57% of major applications in 13 weeks, 70% of minors and 82% of others in 8 weeks; this compares to 65% for majors, 74% for minors and 85% for others in the year ending June 2011. However, in the last quarter there has been an upturn in the proportion of major applications decided in 13 weeks, increasing from 53% to 60%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decided 1% fewer residential decisions compared to the year ending June 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also view the full set of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/live-tables-on-planning-application-statistics"&gt;live tables on planning application statistics&lt;/a&gt; on this site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16040</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-inspectorate-essential-to-new-planning-measures"/>
    <title>Planning Inspectorate essential to new planning measures</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government recently announced a number of new measures in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; to reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New planning measures will put the Planning Inspectorate centre stage in ensuring we have a swift and effective planning system that helps boost local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By expanding permitted development rights, cutting red tape and streamlining the planning process we can save householders money and help businesses create jobs and compete.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his first visit to the Inspectorate in Bristol on Thursday, the minister discussed the work of planning inspectors with Inspectorate Chief Executive Sir Michael Pitt and toured the National Infrastructure Division and Planning Appeals Division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14731</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-applicants-no-longer-face-threat-of-double-charging"/>
    <title>Planning applicants no longer face threat of double charging</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New changes to planning laws will ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged a costly planning levy for local infrastructure, Planning Minister Nick Boles has confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possible double charging has been identified by builders and developers as disproportionate and making key development and regeneration proposals unviable that would bring locally-supported homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposed change, applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents to make them feasible without having to pay another &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/planningandbuilding/planningsystem/communityinfrastructurelevy/"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading British developer Land Securities has announced it will proceed with an estimated £350million scheme that will deliver 2,500 jobs as a result of the proposed changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Stopping this unnecessary double charging is an important step in the Government’s bid to do all it can to get the economy growing by supporting locally-led sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is just one of many measures we have committed to in order to unblock barriers to growth and to make the planning system simpler and more effective.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy helps support growth by contributing to essential infrastructure.  Funds are raised from developers undertaking new building projects and can be used to fund a wide range of infrastructure that is needed as a result of development, including new or safer road schemes, flood defences, park improvements, green spaces and leisure centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft regulations laid in parliament - and soon to be debated - include measures to stop applicants being charged the levy twice, if they amend existing planning consents through Section 73 of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1956365.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1956365.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14730</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bill-to-boost-growth-and-infrastructure-goes-before-parliament"/>
    <title>Bill to boost growth and infrastructure goes before Parliament</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New legislation to support the aspirations of hard working people by reducing the bureaucratic barriers that stop British businesses from creating jobs has been introduced to Parliament today to support local jobs and local growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help the country compete on the global stage by setting out a comprehensive series of practical reforms to reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlocking thousands of new jobs and billions of new investment in energy projects helping keep the country’s lights on by allowing existing consents to be varied and releasing £160 million in new gas infrastructure;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a new optional ‘employee-owner’ status for companies to offer, giving workers a financial stake in their firm’s growth and success through tax-free shares;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preventing unexpected hikes in business rates on local firms over the next five years. Tax stability is vital as business rates are the third biggest outgoing for firms;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting building going on stalled housing sites, by allowing the reconsideration of economically unviable ‘Section 106’ agreements. This could release some of the 75,000 affordable and private homes currently stalled. Unrealistic conditions currently mean no development, no regeneration and no community benefits;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping remove red tape which hinders superfast broadband being rolled out to local homes and businesses, especially in rural Britain facing a ‘digital divide’;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cutting back the volume of paperwork which applicants have to submit with a planning application, which go over and above what is reasonably needed to properly inform decisions about the proposed development;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stopping misuse of town and village green applications to undermine planned development, whilst protecting its use to safeguard cherished community spaces and ensure the protection of genuine town and village greens;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementing the recommendations from the ‘Penfold’ review to remove other over-lapping development consent regimes, where multiple permissions from different government agencies are required on top of planning permission; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speeding up the planning system for large scale business and commercial projects. Where developers choose the fast-track route decisions will be taken in twelve months from the start of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government, Eric Pickles, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These common sense reforms will support local jobs and local firms. They complement the changes we are already delivered through the Localism Act, from streamlined planning guidance and, shortly, from the local retention of business rates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will boost investment and local economic growth. It removes confusing and overlapping red tape, whilst ensuring democratic checks and balances and environmental safeguards remain in place.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2238633.pdf"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill: Background notes&lt;/a&gt;
(PDF, 34 kb, 3 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
