<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15764</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/draft-national-planning-policy-framework"/>
    <title>Draft National Planning Policy Framework</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft National Planning Policy Framework was published for consultation. This is a key part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more accessible, and to promote sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15362</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-traveller-sites"/>
    <title>Planning for traveller sites</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation on the government’s draft planning policy for traveller sites ended on 3 August, and a new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be published as soon as possible, following due consideration of the consultation responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also consulting on the draft &lt;em&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/em&gt; until 17 October. As part of this consultation, we welcome views on the consistency of the draft Framework with the draft planning policy for traveller sites, and any other comments about the government’s plans to incorporate planning policy on traveller sites into the final National Planning Policy Framework. The new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be reviewed in the light of all comments received and incorporated into the final National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the consultation on the National Planning Policy Framework, the government would welcome responses to the following question:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12779</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-schools-development"/>
    <title>Planning for schools development</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation document invites views on the government’s proposals to make changes to the general permitted development order to give a permitted development right for change of use planning permission for schools development. The purpose of the proposals set out in this document is to support the Department for Education’s policy on new free schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12778</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-projects-development-consent-orders"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure projects: development consent orders</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation invites views on proposed procedures for revoking or making changes to a development consent order for a nationally significant infrastructure project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12774</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-application-fees"/>
    <title>Planning application fees</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper seeks views on proposed changes to the planning application fees regime which would decentralise responsibility for setting fees to local planning authorities. We also propose to allow authorities to charge for resubmitted applications and to set higher fees for retrospective applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals will help to reduce the subsidising of planning applications by local taxpayers. If accepted and approved by Parliament, the changes would be implemented from April 2011, with a 6-month transition period until October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12766</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/recognising-professional-architects-qualifications-across-the-eu"/>
    <title>Recognising professional architects' qualifications across the EU</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation looks at an amendment to the Architects Act 1997 (as amended) in relation to the mutual recognition of professional qualifications. These provisions set out how professionals can obtain recognition of their qualifications when moving between Nation States within the EU in order to support greater freedom of movement within the Single Market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Architects Act sets out the basic criteria for automatic recognition of qualifications for architects. The way in which this part of the Act is currently drafted could have the potential to give rise to conditions prejudicial to the automatic recognition of qualifications held by other EU nationals who are seeking to practice as architects in the UK and who would be entitled to practice as architects in their home nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12762</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changing-land-use-from-commercial-to-residential"/>
    <title>Changing land use from commercial to residential</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the government’s proposals to amend the &lt;em&gt;Town and Country Planning (General Permitted Development) Order 1995&lt;/em&gt;  to grant permitted development rights to changes of use from commercial to residential, ie to allow such changes of use without the need for planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12732</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/flag-flying-regulations"/>
    <title>Flag-flying regulations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to streamline the planning regulations that apply to flag-flying to cut bureaucracy and reduce or eliminate the cost of applying for consent. This discussion paper sets out proposals for possible change to secondary legislation in order to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes proposed in this document are aimed at finding a way of preserving and encouraging valued flag-flying traditions, while at the same time maintaining safeguards against the unregulated display of flags that could affect local amenity or cause offence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12720</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/pre-application-process-for-planning-applications"/>
    <title>Pre-application process for planning applications</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is the result of merging and expanding reworked versions of the Local Authority guidance and the pre-application consultation guidance. It covers all the main processes required by an applicant prior to the submission of an application, including the pre-application consultation, the environmental impact assessment and drafting a Development Consent Order, including clarity on the ability to use alternatives in a draft order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance also gives more specific advice about consultation for offshore wind developments where there is no obvious local authority to consult. In addition the guidance provides further clarity on the Rochdale Envelope in applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12721</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-projects-application-form-guidance"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure projects: application form guidance</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The application form guidance has been refreshed to bring it into line with the &lt;em&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/em&gt; and has been made more concise in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
