<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T15:15:06+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64958</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T15:15:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-on-the-pre-application-process-for-major-infrastructure-projects"/>
    <title>Guidance on the pre-application process for major infrastructure projects</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This guidance sets out the requirements and procedures for the pre-application process and consultation for major infrastructure projects.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is the result of merging and expanding reworked versions of the local authority guidance and the pre-application guidance that went out to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/pre-application-process-for-planning-applications"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; on 13 April 2012. By merging these, we are avoiding unnecessary repetition of the description of common processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new guidance sets out the necessary requirements and procedures and gives clarity on the scope and scale of the consultation required at the pre-application stage. It covers all the main processes required by an applicant prior to the submission of an application, including the pre-application consultation, Environmental Impact Assessment, Habitats Regulations Assessments, and advice on drafting a Development Consent Order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60871</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T12:58:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T12:58:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"/>
    <title>Changes to Temporary Stop Notices consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on proposals to improve councils' power to tackle unauthorised development.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation is on the proposal to revoke Statutory Instrument 2005/206 under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/206/contents/made"&gt;Town and Country Planning (Temporary Stop Notice)(England) Regulations 2005&lt;/a&gt;. The regulation currently restricts councils use of Temporary Stop Notices on unauthorised sites where a caravan is used as a main residence. This can discourage local councils from serving stop notices where it may be beneficial to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this consultation would give local councils greater freedom to make a decision on the basis of local circumstances and on whether serving Temporary Stop Notices in respect of caravans used as main residences is appropriate. It will remain for local councils to consider the consequences of taking enforcement action and whether the action is necessary and proportionate in the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60870</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T10:54:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T10:54:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/streamlining-information-requirements-for-planning-applications"/>
    <title>Streamlining information requirements for planning applications</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on proposed changes to reduce information requirements for planning applications.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out proposals relating to information requirements for planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These proposals include changes to secondary legislation on information requirements for outline planning applications, and a requirement that local authorities update their local lists of information requirements at least every 2 years. It also sets out proposed changes to the standard application form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60830</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-freedom-for-local-councils-to-prevent-unauthorised-traveller-sites--2"/>
    <title>Greater freedom for local councils to prevent unauthorised traveller sites</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposals to give councils more freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites have been published for consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be given greater freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites being set up and prevent long, drawn-out stalemates like Dale Farm, under proposals published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="temporary-stop-notices"&gt;Temporary Stop Notices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals would allow councils greater freedom to use temporary stop notices in relation to caravans that are in breach of planning control, and are used as a person’s main residence. This would be backed up with the potential for heavy fines of up to £20,000 on indictment or an unlimited fine on summary conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the current system councils are constrained as to when they can use these powers against caravans that are main residences, which can result in long delays and high costs to stop unauthorised development of this kind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long a small minority have abused the planning system, often at the expense of local communities who are forced to put up with unauthorised development in their area. This government believes in fair play, with everyone abiding by the same rules. These proposals will assist local councils in taking effective action against those who don’t.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-powers"&gt;Stronger powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporary Stop Notices enable councils to take action with immediate effect against unauthorised development without having to wait three days for a Stop Notice, or 28 days for an enforcement notice to come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to the outcome of the consultation, today’s proposals would remove restrictions on the use of temporary stop notices so councils can act quickly against new unauthorised sites, and save on the costs of enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60950</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:56:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"/>
    <title>Planning practice guidance should be simpler</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An external review of planning practice guidance has recommended rationalising advice and making it easier to use.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review group, led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system but did not review planning policy. They were not tasked with revaluating green belt policy or other countryside protections, which continue to be safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that the existing guidance is unwieldy in its current form and recommends that it be shorter but retain key elements, and be more accessible to be useful to everyone using the planning system. They stated that guidance is important to ensuring planning decisions are properly informed but should not place undue burdens on users of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that a vast range of materials are being considered guidance, and that ‘living documents’ intended to be updated on a regular basis had not been amended since publication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; to consider the group’s recommendations was launched today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is very clear that the old way of doing things is no longer fit for purpose. We have made recommendations for a modern web-based resource that is clear, up-to-date, coherent and easily usable, not just by planners and developers, but the public too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very grateful to the group for all the work they have done on this. We will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and I would urge other users of the planning system to have their say by responding to the consultation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group consists of Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones. They are sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;External review of government planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;Review of planning practice guidance - consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt;, Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60325</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:58:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"/>
    <title>External review of government planning practice guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Conclusions and recommendations of the review of planning guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"&gt;21 December 2012&lt;/a&gt; the government welcomed the report of the review of planning practice guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, and announced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;short consultation&lt;/a&gt; on the review group’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group’s report makes recommendations as to the scope and form of practice guidance that should be provided in future by government to support effective planning; what new or updated practice guidance should be published, with clear priorities; and what guidance should be cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60403</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:57:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"/>
    <title> Review of planning practice guidance</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on the conclusions and recommendations of the review of planning guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"&gt;21 December 2012&lt;/a&gt; the government welcomed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;report of the review of planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt; led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the review group’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17814</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/statutory-consultee-performance-and-award-of-costs"/>
    <title>Statutory consultee performance and award of costs</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Proposals to amend guidance on awards in appeals and other planning proceedings.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes to amend guidance in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/costs-awards-in-appeals-and-other-planning-proceedings-circular-03-2009"&gt;Circular 03/09: Costs Awards in Appeals and Other Planning Proceedings&lt;/a&gt; in relation to statutory consultees and their advice at appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also announced clarifications to the guidance in relation to local councils and their development plan, and in relation to ensuring evidence submitted at appeal is manifestly accurate and truthful. The government is also requiring the 5 main statutory bodies to report on, and be accountable for their performance on dealing with planning applications as part of their individual Improvement Plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of responses was published on 18 December 2012. The report above summarises the key issues raised and provides a revised addendum to circular 03/09.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles has announced a new multi-million pound cash boost to help more communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles has announced a major milestone in the transfer of power to local communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
