<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16962</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 6 September 2012, the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister set out a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;major package of reforms to housing and planning&lt;/a&gt; to help create conditions for economic growth. This announcement included a commitment to ‘work to extend the principle of a one-stop-shop for non-planning consents for major infrastructure’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this consultation is to seek views from interested bodies on what consents should be moved within the scope of an expanded ‘one stop shop’ for major infrastructure and on proposals for streamlining the current list of statutory consultees that developers are required to consult before applying for a development consent order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"&gt;extend the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16960</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To help speed up planning decisions for the most complex projects and to increase choice for developers, the government proposes to extend the scope of the Planning Act 2008 so that a wider range of development can be brought within the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime. This will allow developers of nationally significant business or commercial projects to apply to the Secretary of State for the option of using the streamlined planning regime set out in the Planning Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views about the proposal to extend the nationally significant infrastructure regime and, in particular, about the types and forms of business and commercial projects to be prescribed in regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"&gt;expand and improve the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16956</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:39:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/measures-to-reduce-bureaucratic-barriers-to-growth-and-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Measures to reduce bureaucratic barriers to growth and infrastructure</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;, currently being considered in Parliament, will help the country compete on the global stage by introducing a comprehensive series of practical reforms that will reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals in the Bill include reducing the number of different consents infrastructure developers require. The government is also consulting on a new streamlined ‘one-stop-shop’ service and on reducing the number of bodies developers need to consult on every application. The proposed reforms will deliver a swifter, more efficient planning process while ensuring interested parties can continue to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms will also open up the fast-track planning process used for nationally significant infrastructure projects to additional types of nationally significant development. It will be open for the first time to business and commercial projects that are important to delivering growth and prosperity and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new types of developments that could be considered under the nationally significant infrastructure system include: manufacturing and major tourism and leisure proposals, office development such as research and development facilities, and warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers would be allowed to request that their application for these nationally significant business projects be determined through the infrastructure planning system which ensures decisions are made within 12 months from the beginning of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations on these two proposed reforms to the major infrastructure planning process were issued today. (See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects"&gt;extending the regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents"&gt;expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital we secure investment in new nationally significant infrastructure and commercial development, and that quicker and better planning decisions are made, if we are to help boost the economy and create the new jobs we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning delays help no one. They bring uncertainty for local people and local firms and can deter new investment all together. By streamlining the planning process to make it quicker and easier for these national significant projects to be decided we can ensure sustainable development gets underway without delay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reforms have already given significant additional powers to councils and communities so they can decide on the scale and location of development in their areas. With this power comes a responsibility to ensure that local planning decisions are efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will also give planning applicants the ability to apply directly to the Planning Inspectorate where there is clear evidence that a council’s planning service is performing very poorly and failing to administer a proper service for both applicants and local residents.  A consultation recently published sets out how these proposals would work, including the basis for assessing performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16667</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-performance-and-the-planning-guarantee"/>
    <title>Planning performance and the Planning Guarantee</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation links to the Government’s proposals, contained within Clause 1 of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, to introduce legislation to give applicants the choice of submitting planning applications direct to the secretary of state, where the local planning authority is underperforming.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on what measures to use to identify an authority’s performance, how to identify underperformance and how to identify improved performance and related measures to underpin the Planning Guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16257</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-review-of-planning-appeal-procedures"/>
    <title>Technical review of planning appeal procedures</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published: 1 November 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to make the planning appeals process faster and more transparent, improve consistency and certainty in decision taking timescales. The proposals will bring cost and time benefits for those appealing decisions and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:36:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14388</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation"/>
    <title>Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes changes to increase permitted development rights for extensions to homes and business premises in non-protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to amend the Town and Country Planning (General Permitted Development) Order 1995 to allow homeowners and businesses to make larger extensions to their homes and business premises without requiring a planning application, and to allow quicker installation of broadband infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please submit your views using the questionnaire below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16273</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13313</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:45:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-to-get-jobs-and-boosting-growth"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people to get jobs and boosting growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk and saw how local businesses and civic leaders are using government funding to help boost local development and deliver the government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an enterprise zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury enterprise zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the enterprise zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprise zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.
Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase, which would see the development of 1,500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough local enterprise partnerships have contributed £2 million each from the government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using enterprise zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
