<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48186</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-competition-and-markets-authority"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: Competition and Markets Authority</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to the competition reform and the Competition and Markets Authority. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48085</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/research-project-on-the-impact-of-anti-dumping-investigations-on-uk-business-final-report"/>
    <title>Research project on the impact of anti-dumping investigations on UK business: final report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Report for BIS that analyses the impact of anti-dumping investigations and procedures on UK business. Based on a survey of  UK companies. See also URN 12/1021AN for a graphical representations of the data collected in the report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48086</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/research-project-on-the-impact-of-anti-dumping-investigations-on-uk-business-annex-2-eurostat-data"/>
    <title>Research project on the impact of anti-dumping investigations on UK business: annex 2 - Eurostat data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graphical representations of the data collected in the business surveys on the effect of anti-dumping investigations on UK business (URN 12/1021).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45390</id>
    <published>2012-05-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-competition-reform"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: competition reform</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in  the Enterprise &amp;amp; Regulatory Reform Bill relating to the competition reform and the Competition and Markets Authority. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45691</id>
    <published>2012-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-governments-policy-for-the-groceries-code-adjudicator"/>
    <title>The government's policy for the Groceries Code Adjudicator</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains the government’s policy relating to the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill that was introduced into the House of Lords on 10th May 2012. Sets out why the government proposes to set up the Groceries Code Adjudicator and explains what the Bill is seeking to achieve. The Bill aims to enhance protection for suppliers, through ensuring that large retailers treat them fairly by lawfully adhering to the Groceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47089</id>
    <published>2012-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-groceries-code-adjudicator"/>
    <title>New Groceries Code Adjudicator</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Bill to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets is published in the House of Lords.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 May 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The creation of a new Adjudicator will beef up protection for farmers and suppliers. It will ensure that large retailers treat them fairly by lawfully adhering to the Groceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, it will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrate disputes between retailers and suppliers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate confidential complaints from direct and indirect suppliers, whether in the UK or overseas, and from third parties, to end the ‘climate of fear’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hold to account retailers who break the rules by ‘naming and shaming’ or fining supermarkets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Norman Lamb said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The large supermarkets have a lot of buyer power, and with power come responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Supermarkets will still be able to secure the best deals and to pass the benefits on to consumers, but they should also treat farmers and suppliers fairly and lawfully. This means paying them on time or not being able to scrap arrangements with farmers and suppliers at the drop of a hat.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Free and fair competition is the key to a healthy market and by preventing retailers from transferring excessive risk to their suppliers we will support investment and innovation in the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the long-term, that’s in the best interests of everyone, especially the consumer.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill was introduced into Parliament on 10 May. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/groceriescodeadjudicator.html"&gt;Follow the progress of the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill on the Parliament website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="groceries-code-adjudicator-gca"&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator (GCA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new body is being established to enforce the Groceries Code after the Competition Commission identified competition issues in their 2008 market study. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular it concluded that the market dominance of big supermarkets led to some suppliers being treated unfairly in the UK and overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a retailer is found to have breached the Groceries Code then the Adjudicator would have wide ranging powers to effect remedies such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issuing recommendations to solve the dispute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naming and shaming the offenders by publishing information. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imposing fines (if the Secretary of State considers that the other solutions aren’t working and grants the Adjudicator this power).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-Groceries-Adjudicator-to-protect-suppliers-from-unfair-treatment-by-supermarkets-679e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New Groceries Adjudicator to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/market-studies/cc-market-investigation-on-the-uk-supply-of-groceries"&gt;Competition Commission Market Investigation on the Supply of Groceries in the UK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/food-farm/food/food-industry/"&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs - Food industry, supply chain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45486</id>
    <published>2012-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-block-exemption-regulation-introduction"/>
    <title>General Block Exemption Regulation: introduction</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance on how to use the EU’s General Block Exemption Regulation. This Regulation covers categories of state aid that are legal without needing to be pre-notified to the EU Commission. See URN 12/747 for guidance on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45510</id>
    <published>2012-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/state-aid-frequently-asked-questions"/>
    <title>State aid: frequently asked questions</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answers frequently asked questions about state aid rules. Includes basic and also more detailed information on state aid terminology. State aid occurs when an authority grants public resources to selected entities which are engaged in economic activities. See also URN 12/746 for guidance on the General Block Exemption Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45708</id>
    <published>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/anti-competitive-behaviour-consultation-on-reforming-sme-and-consumer-options"/>
    <title>Anti-competitive behaviour: consultation on reforming SME and consumer options</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respond by 24 July 2012. Consultation seeking views on how to empower consumers and small businesses to challenge anti-competitive behaviour and secure redress. The consultation looks at how to establish the Competition Appeal Tribunal (CAT) as a major venue for competition actions in the UK, and introduce an opt-out collective actions regime for competition law. It also covers measures to promote Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR), and to ensure private actions complement the public enforcement regime. See URN 12/743 for the related impact assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
