<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48186</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-competition-and-markets-authority"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: Competition and Markets Authority</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to the competition reform and the Competition and Markets Authority. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48085</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/research-project-on-the-impact-of-anti-dumping-investigations-on-uk-business-final-report"/>
    <title>Research project on the impact of anti-dumping investigations on UK business: final report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Report for BIS that analyses the impact of anti-dumping investigations and procedures on UK business. Based on a survey of  UK companies. See also URN 12/1021AN for a graphical representations of the data collected in the report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48086</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/research-project-on-the-impact-of-anti-dumping-investigations-on-uk-business-annex-2-eurostat-data"/>
    <title>Research project on the impact of anti-dumping investigations on UK business: annex 2 - Eurostat data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graphical representations of the data collected in the business surveys on the effect of anti-dumping investigations on UK business (URN 12/1021).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45390</id>
    <published>2012-05-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-competition-reform"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: competition reform</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in  the Enterprise &amp;amp; Regulatory Reform Bill relating to the competition reform and the Competition and Markets Authority. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45691</id>
    <published>2012-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-governments-policy-for-the-groceries-code-adjudicator"/>
    <title>The government's policy for the Groceries Code Adjudicator</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains the government’s policy relating to the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill that was introduced into the House of Lords on 10th May 2012. Sets out why the government proposes to set up the Groceries Code Adjudicator and explains what the Bill is seeking to achieve. The Bill aims to enhance protection for suppliers, through ensuring that large retailers treat them fairly by lawfully adhering to the Groceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47089</id>
    <published>2012-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-groceries-code-adjudicator"/>
    <title>New Groceries Code Adjudicator</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Bill to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets is published in the House of Lords.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 May 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The creation of a new Adjudicator will beef up protection for farmers and suppliers. It will ensure that large retailers treat them fairly by lawfully adhering to the Groceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, it will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrate disputes between retailers and suppliers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate confidential complaints from direct and indirect suppliers, whether in the UK or overseas, and from third parties, to end the ‘climate of fear’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hold to account retailers who break the rules by ‘naming and shaming’ or fining supermarkets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Norman Lamb said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The large supermarkets have a lot of buyer power, and with power come responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Supermarkets will still be able to secure the best deals and to pass the benefits on to consumers, but they should also treat farmers and suppliers fairly and lawfully. This means paying them on time or not being able to scrap arrangements with farmers and suppliers at the drop of a hat.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Free and fair competition is the key to a healthy market and by preventing retailers from transferring excessive risk to their suppliers we will support investment and innovation in the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the long-term, that’s in the best interests of everyone, especially the consumer.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill was introduced into Parliament on 10 May. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/groceriescodeadjudicator.html"&gt;Follow the progress of the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill on the Parliament website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="groceries-code-adjudicator-gca"&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator (GCA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new body is being established to enforce the Groceries Code after the Competition Commission identified competition issues in their 2008 market study. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular it concluded that the market dominance of big supermarkets led to some suppliers being treated unfairly in the UK and overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a retailer is found to have breached the Groceries Code then the Adjudicator would have wide ranging powers to effect remedies such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issuing recommendations to solve the dispute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naming and shaming the offenders by publishing information. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imposing fines (if the Secretary of State considers that the other solutions aren’t working and grants the Adjudicator this power).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-Groceries-Adjudicator-to-protect-suppliers-from-unfair-treatment-by-supermarkets-679e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New Groceries Adjudicator to protect suppliers from unfair treatment by supermarkets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/market-studies/cc-market-investigation-on-the-uk-supply-of-groceries"&gt;Competition Commission Market Investigation on the Supply of Groceries in the UK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/food-farm/food/food-industry/"&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs - Food industry, supply chain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45486</id>
    <published>2012-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-block-exemption-regulation-introduction"/>
    <title>General Block Exemption Regulation: introduction</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance on how to use the EU’s General Block Exemption Regulation. This Regulation covers categories of state aid that are legal without needing to be pre-notified to the EU Commission. See URN 12/747 for guidance on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45510</id>
    <published>2012-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/state-aid-frequently-asked-questions"/>
    <title>State aid: frequently asked questions</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answers frequently asked questions about state aid rules. Includes basic and also more detailed information on state aid terminology. State aid occurs when an authority grants public resources to selected entities which are engaged in economic activities. See also URN 12/746 for guidance on the General Block Exemption Regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45708</id>
    <published>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/anti-competitive-behaviour-consultation-on-reforming-sme-and-consumer-options"/>
    <title>Anti-competitive behaviour: consultation on reforming SME and consumer options</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respond by 24 July 2012. Consultation seeking views on how to empower consumers and small businesses to challenge anti-competitive behaviour and secure redress. The consultation looks at how to establish the Competition Appeal Tribunal (CAT) as a major venue for competition actions in the UK, and introduce an opt-out collective actions regime for competition law. It also covers measures to promote Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR), and to ensure private actions complement the public enforcement regime. See URN 12/743 for the related impact assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/45709</id>
    <published>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:27:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/anti-competitive-behaviour-impact-of-proposed-reforms-for-sme-and-consumer-options"/>
    <title>Anti-competitive behaviour: impact of proposed reforms for SME and consumer options</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the costs and benefits of proposals in the consultation on how to empower consumers and small businesses to challenge anti-competitive behaviour and secure redress (URN 12/742). Looks at the impact of four different options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
