<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting economic growth through local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16435</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T15:08:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-sees-west-midlands-newest-business-growth-projects"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles sees West Midlands' newest business growth projects</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local growth is flourishing in Aston and Wolverhampton as a result of locally directed government funding to create high-tech manufacturing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began his tour at the Sertec Group Holdings in Aston where he signed a contract for £2 million of Growing Places funding from the Greater Birmingham and Solihull local enterprise partnership. This will allow them to purchase new ground at the Aston Regional Investment site and improve its infrastructure connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sertec is looking to relocate to a new advanced manufacturing hub in Aston, 1 of 6 economic zones unveiled by Birmingham City Council. This new hub is phase one of Aston’s regional investment sites capable of delivering 3,000 jobs, 300,000 square feet of office or industrial space and bringing in over £30 million of private sector money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles inspected a subsidiary plant of Sertec also set to benefit. Presslite is a local family-run business that manufactures automotive parts for major car companies and employs 150 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Communities Secretary then travelled to the i54 enterprise zone near Wolverhampton where he met senior representatives from 3 companies. Moog, a high-tech aerospace business; Eurofins, a food testing laboratory; and Jaguar Land-Rover who will start building their new engine there creating at least 750 new jobs following their £355 million investment backed up by £10 million from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 3 firms were attracted by the low business rates, streamlined planning permissions within the enterprise zone as well as a £40 million joint investment from Wolverhampton City Council and Staffordshire County Council in a new junction off the M54 that will service the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are making decisions everyday to unlock much-needed local growth and give private sector companies every reason to invest and locate to their areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through our enterprise zones - like the i54 in Wolverhampton - and our Growing Places Fund - put to such good use in Aston - civic and businesses leaders in the West Midlands are helping create new jobs for their residents by bringing new firms to their local economy.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13313</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:45:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-to-get-jobs-and-boosting-growth"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people to get jobs and boosting growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk and saw how local businesses and civic leaders are using government funding to help boost local development and deliver the government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an enterprise zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury enterprise zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the enterprise zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprise zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.
Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase, which would see the development of 1,500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough local enterprise partnerships have contributed £2 million each from the government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using enterprise zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16134</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-get-jobs-and-growth-going"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people get jobs and growth going</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk today to see how local businesses and civic leaders are using Government funding to help boost local development and deliver the Government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an Enterprise Zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of Government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury Enterprise Zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the Enterprise Zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enterprise Zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase first which would see the development of 1500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the Government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the Government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough Local Enterprise Partnerships have contributed £2million each from the Government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Local Enterprise Partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using Enterprise Zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/3772</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T10:21:09+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T10:21:09+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/420-million-to-support-local-infrastructure"/>
    <title>£420 million to support local infrastructure</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-magic-ingredient"&gt;The ‘magic ingredient’&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week the Prime Minister gave a keynote speech where he set out a vision for this country’s infrastructure in the 21st century. He described new infrastructure as ‘the magic ingredient’ to long-term economic success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional £270 million is being made available through the growing places fund. Less than a week after the Budget this money is being allocated to local enterprise partnerships giving them and the market greater confidence to invest. This builds on the £500 million already allocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="growing-places-fund"&gt;Growing places fund&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing places fund provides local areas with up-front and flexible funding so they can quickly boost economic growth by getting the required infrastructure built to build new homes, create jobs and get stalled projects moving again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£12 million for Greater Manchester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£11 million for Leeds City region&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 million for Hertfordshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£6 million for Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;almost £7 million for the Heart of the South West local enterprise partnership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to £150 million will be available for large-scale infrastructure projects in core cities. This money will be financed through a scheme known as ‘tax increment financing type 2’, which lets local authorities borrow against future growth in business rates for 25 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on a competition for allocating funding will be announced in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We know that new infrastructure is one of the most important ways to get the economy going again, support new homes and create long-term jobs and growth. That is why last week government made over £400 million more available to communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The extra growing places fund money is available immediately so local enterprise partnerships can unlock sites for infrastructure development that support new homes and tax increment finance will give councils the means to raise their own finances over the longer term to back infrastructure projects themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Justine Greening said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport infrastructure projects are often the key to unlocking jobs and growth potential, where new link roads or junction improvements can be a catalyst for investment in new regeneration sites of homes and businesses that otherwise might not happen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Feedback from the first round of our funding is that lots of projects are transport focused which is why I am delighted to provide £150 million from my department towards the additional £270 million for the growing places fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/pm-speech-on-infrastructure/" title="Prime Minister's speech on infrastructure"&gt;Prime Minister’s speech on infrastructure.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lancashire Local enterprise partnership has approved its first 3 schemes to receive £7 million. These 3 schemes - Luneside East commercial development in Lancaster, Burnley Bridge business park, Edge Hill University expansion in Ormskirk - are ready to start work immediately, providing transport infrastructure and land remediation works creating 1,550 new jobs, with a further £95 million investment and creating 577 new homes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worcestershire local enterprise partnership has allocated £3.25 million of its growing places fund to 4 schemes which will create over 500 new jobs and lever in over £20 million of other investment. These schemes include Hoo Brook Link Road and groundwork and utilities infrastructure at Worcester University Park and mixed-use development around Worcestershire County Cricket ground.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2010-11/localgovernmentfinance.html" title="Local Government Finance Bill"&gt;Local Government Finance Bill&lt;/a&gt; takes forward proposals designed to encourage local economic growth, reduce the financial deficit and drive decentralisation of control over local government finance. This includes allowing for authorities to retain in full the rates growth in designated tax increment financing (TIF2) and enterprise zone areas. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/localgovernment/localgovernmentfinance/lgfinancebill/briefguide/" title="A brief guide to the Local Government Finance Bill"&gt;Read a brief guide to the bill.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A first wave of city deals has already started with England’s 8 largest cities outside London. These will give them the powers they need to attract private sector investment, create new jobs, and rebalance the economy. The cities are:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Leeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Liverpool&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Manchester&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Newcastle&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nottingham&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sheffield&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The additional growing places funding comes from various central government department underspends. The government has written to local enterprise partnerships this week setting out the allocation for 2012-13 and beyond as follows:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Local enterprise partnership&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Additional allocation&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Overall total&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;North Eastern Local Enterprise Partnership&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£ 8,198,503&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£25,253,169&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sheffield City Region&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,027,853&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£18,574,935&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Stoke and Staffordshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,721,421&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£11,462,668&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Greater Birmingham and Solihull&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,283,524&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£22,494,722&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hertfordshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,246,729&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£16,236,239&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cumbria&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,162,498&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,667,772&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lancashire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,286,494&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£19,378,944&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Greater Manchester&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£12,099,215&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£37,358,032&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Liverpool City Region&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,336,851&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£19,529,710&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cheshire and Warrington&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,257,719&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£13,159,667&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;York and North Yorkshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,043,369&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9,373,951&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leeds City Region&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£11,739,899&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£36,225,183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Humber&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,844,599&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£8,762,240&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leicester and Leicestershire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,343,040&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£13,405,370&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tees Valley&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,788,254&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£8,587,013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Marches Enterprise Partnership - Shropshire and Herefordshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,659,812&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£8,190,847&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lincolnshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,185,269&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9,801,076&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Derby, Derbyshire, Nottingham and Nottinghamshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£8,538,103&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£26,344,104&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black Country&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,701,565&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£14,488,451&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Worcestershire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,791,486&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,518,972&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Coventry and Warwickshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4,144,786&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£12,816,184&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South East Midlands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,070,478&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£18,759,514&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northamptonshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£1,915,237&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,910,558&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Buckinghamshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,029,024&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,276,294&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Greater Cambridge &amp;amp; Greater Peterborough&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,214,464&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£16,118,213&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New Anglia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,912,036&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£18,200,892&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South East&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£15,983,959&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£49,210,053&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Coast to Capital&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,674,599&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£23,699,125&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enterprise M3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£7,021,240&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£21,744,341&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Solent&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,865,727&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£18,110,320&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oxfordshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,925,449&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9,054,428&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thames Valley Berkshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,163,226&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£16,039,518&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gloucestershire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,751,807&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£8,498,295&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;West of England&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£5,527,958&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£17,107,499&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Swindon and Wiltshire&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,040,261&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9,386,900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dorset&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£3,126,241&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9,639,201&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Heart of the South West&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,978,179&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£21,488,660&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cornwall and the Isles of Scilly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2,072,352&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£6,365,681&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pan London&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£69,326,773&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£110,761,262&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TOTAL*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£270,000,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£730,000,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;*£460 million of the original allocation went to local enterprise partnerships in England. The additional funding brings the total for England to £730 million. The remainder of the original allocation of £500 million was allocated to the devolved administrations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14699</id>
    <published>2012-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/local-enterprise-partnerships-receive-boost"/>
    <title>Local enterprise partnerships receive boost</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government is today announcing core funding for Local Enterprise Partnerships (LEPs) to allow them to drive forward their growth priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships are central to the Government’s approach to driving local economic growth and for ensuring that every community is able to fulfil its potential. This offer of over £24million from Government could unlock up to £20million locally and will enable Local Enterprise Partnerships to deliver their local plans for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interim £5million funding package will be made available immediately for all Local Enterprise Partnerships to draw upon for the remainder of this financial year. This will be followed by up to £250,000 per Local Enterprise Partnership per year for the following two years. Where matched by funds locally the overall funding pot could equate up to £45million over this period. The central government funding will be provided on a 50/50 basis by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) and the Department for Communities and Local Government (DCLG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Today’s £25million boost will give Local Enterprise Partnerships the financial stability they need going forward, to build on their early successes and tailor the support they offer to local needs. If matched by local support, this could mean that up to £45million will be available to help Local Enterprise Partnerships turn their plans into jobs and growth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is crucial we arm Local Enterprise Partnerships with the tools and resources they need to play a prominent role in delivering growth and jobs for their communities. This funding will help Local Enterprise Partnerships plan for the long term and ensure they can remain locally-led instead of dependent on central government support.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We need to ensure Local Enterprise Partnerships remain voluntary business and civic partnerships so they are in the best possible position to deliver sustainable growth and job creation in their areas. Already we are seeing Local Enterprise Partnerships across England delivering innovative schemes in their communities. This financial support will help the partnerships to continue this work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships will be invited to bid for matched funding for 2013/14 and 2014/15, setting out how they would be able to offer a cash match from public or private resources. Details on the scope of the match will be discussed with Local Enterprise Partnerships shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government made £5million of core funding available to Local Enterprise Partnerships last year to help them start up and establish themselves through financial support for things such as board support, development of priorities and business engagement. This was followed by a further £4million to build capacity over a four year period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interim funding for 2012/13 is made up of £4,875,000 split equally between BIS and DCLG.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 2013/14 and 2014/15, matched funding will be offered of up to £250,000 per LEP per annum, with DCLG and BIS together contributing £10million per year. Local Enterprise Partnerships wishing to utilise this funding will be required to source match funding of equal value.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are 39 Local Enterprise Partnerships across England. Each Local Enterprise Partnership is made up of local businesses working in partnership with a combination of local authorities. Further details on Local Enterprise Partnerships and what they do is available on the BIS website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14658</id>
    <published>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-new-manufacturing-institute-with-3-5-million-boost"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens new manufacturing institute with £3.5 million boost</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today announced a £3.5million Government investment for manufacturing innovation at the opening of a new High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2189195.jpg" alt="Eric Pickles visiting the new manufacturing institute"&gt;The institute is close to the legendary Dagenham factory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Institute has been created in partnership with the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence and Ford Britain, who are investing a further £1.44million, and is located in a manufacturing heartland a short distance from the legendary Dagenham factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Institute will develop new and innovative ways to improve manufacturing techniques and increase productivity that will ensure Britain remains a top choice for investment. It is expected to generate £80million to the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Institute will develop state of the art virtual manufacturing systems to assist companies to develop and implement world leading manufacturing processes, which are often too costly for many organisations to design themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will bring together leading lights from the worlds of business, engineering and academia employing 22 researchers and PhD students to work alongside 6 Ford research staff to create programmes that will help develop the high skilled work force needed to operate such systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles was joined by Ford Britain Chairman Joe Greenwell, as well as Chief Executive Bill Williams and Chairman, Martin Broadhurst of the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence. They met engineers learning the skills to drive the industry forward in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This country and county has a proud history of manufacturing. By investing in high-tech skills and innovation we can help ensure that as well as being part of our past, quality manufacturing is part of our future.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“By promoting enterprise, pushing forward research, creating jobs and giving people more skills we are sending a powerful signal that Britain is a top choice for inward investment and with that bringing local growth back to communities.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is an Institute with a big ambition, to push back the frontiers of manufacturing, quicken production and reduce costs and bring benefits to business as well as the local area. It is a delight to open this new Institute and to pledge £3.5million of investment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“By bringing together the leading lights from business, academia and engineering the institute presents a wonderful opportunity to put Britain back at the forefront of manufacturing achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The Government is committed helping to stimulate local enterprise and help drive local growth investment in projects like this that not only boost businesses but bring about wider benefits to the local area. As the world’s eyes turn to this area in the coming weeks, this institute stands out as a beacon of the innovation in the manufacturing industry.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Greenwell, Ford of Britain chairman, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ford is delighted to be a founding partner in this exciting new initiative. The Institute will accelerate research and development in innovative manufacturing systems that will help underpin the future of the UK’s high value manufacturing sector. This complements the work that Ford is already doing in this area and also provides significant opportunities for supply chain partners.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Williams, CEO of the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The creation of the High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute is a bold step in further establishing the United Kingdom in its place of the premier league of manufacturing engineering excellence world-wide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157630744962904/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is contributing £3.5million over three years to the High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will be based at the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence (CEME) at Rainham, Essex. CEME is a registered charity that operates an industry-led education and business campus in the heart of the Thames Gateway. CEME was created in 2002 as part of the Government’s regeneration programme for the Thames Gateway region. It is a key catalyst for delivering growth in business and skills for the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute will focus on the discipline of Manufacturing Engineering. Manufacturing Engineering is the branch of engineering concerned with the efficient production of industrial goods. It includes the design of production plant equipment and processes. This is an activity common to all manufacturing sectors and is particularly relevant to high volume operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14650</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/enterprise-zones-website-will-help-businesses-grow"/>
    <title>Enterprise zones website will help businesses grow</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Government micro site will showcase the many business benefits of locating in one of England’s 24 Enterprise Zones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has launched a brand new micro site to promote Enterprise Zones across England. The site is designed as the first point of call for all budding entrepreneurs and businesses looking to grow and expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184519.jpg" alt="Enterpise Zones microsite"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The site helps businesses find a place to grow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By choosing to locate in one of the 24 zones which cover a variety of industry sectors, small start-ups and expanding businesses will benefit from a number of measures including discounted business rates, simplified planning procedures and business ready infrastructures including super fast broadband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has joined the Department for Business Innovation and Skills and UK Trade and Investment in the way it seeks to speak to businesses and entrepreneurs in order to attract inward investment to the UK. Enterprise Zones are a route to generating jobs and businesses, helping to rebalance the economy and drive local and national growth and enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;www.enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk
&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Follow&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/entzonesgov"&gt;@entzonesgov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184613.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184613.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14643</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lift-off-for-jobs-in-herefordshire"/>
    <title>Lift off for jobs in Herefordshire</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovative Enterprise Zone brings new investment to local area&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has praised the innovation and ‘can-do’ attitude of Hereford Enterprise Zone for teaming up with global aerospace companies to create local jobs and stimulate growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179557.jpg" alt="Hereford Enterprise Zone"&gt;Hereford Enterprise Zone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hereford Enterprise Zone has been promoting the strengths of the local area as a hotspot for high tech businesses investment, which includes immediate tax breaks for companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing the huge benefits available, two global Aerospace companies, Tbilisi Aerospace Manufacturing based in Georgia and MARKET-MATS from the Ukraine, recently announced ambitious plans to locate in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move signals a major step forward in development of the Hereford Enterprise Zone with the potential to create hundreds of new jobs, bring wider benefits to the local area and mark out Herefordshire and Britain as a great choice for businesses across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the Communities Secretary met with the Governor of Washington State, Christine Gregoire, representatives from Herefordshire Council and the Aerospace companies to welcome the planned investment into the Hereford Enterprise Zone and wider Herefordshire area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This agreement shows that our low tax, light-touch regulation Enterprise Zones and Herefordshire’s ‘can do’ ambitions are a great combination that business are eager to take advantage of - Tbilisi Aerospace Manufacturing and Market-Mats will bring new jobs to the area and energise the local economy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new generation of 24 Enterprise Zones with simplified planning rules, super-fast broadband and tax breaks for businesses, now span across England. The Zones are helping to create conditions to stimulate growth and have the potential to create tens of thousands of new jobs by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179536.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179536.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9047</id>
    <published>2012-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/10-million-investment-to-connect-northampton-enterprise-zone"/>
    <title>£10 million investment to connect Northampton enterprise zone</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Transport Secretary Justine Greening announced a £10 million boost for transport infrastructure in Northampton’s Enterprise Zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money is being invested in the development of the Castle Railway Station at the heart of Northampton Enterprise Zone. The new station will provide vital infrastructure capacity to support local plans for sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northampton Enterprise Zone is building on the areas strengths in advanced technologies, high performance engineering, and low carbon technology. With access to super fast broadband, up to 100 per cent business rates discounts and simplified planning process the Zone is already attracting big business hitters like Carlsberg, providing more jobs and boosting the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Northampton is using its Enterprise Zone to energise the local economy and boost business. As these new opportunities for innovation and enterprise open up it is vital the infrastructure is in place to match Northampton’s ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This £10 million for the Castle Railway station is another step forward in Northampton’s resurgence as a place where local communities thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minster Andrew Stunell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Improving the transport links to this ambitious area will help Northampton to unleash its potential as a centre for local growth and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Turning Castle Station into a key transport hub at the heart of the Enterprise Zone is just one more reason for business to invest in this area and bring new jobs and homes that will benefit the whole community.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with funding from Network Rail and Northamptonshire County Council the Government’s contribution will go towards phase one of the redevelopment scheme which includes a new station building and access to the platforms, which will be a major improvement for residents and visitors to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Northamptonshire Development Corporation, the agency driving regeneration in West Northamptonshire, can now look at how they can take forward subsequent phases of the redevelopment which will include a new larger car park and release of land for commercial opportunities close to the station.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/12569</id>
    <published>2012-04-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:37:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-enterprise-partnership-network-conference"/>
    <title>Local enterprise partnership network conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcript of the speech as delivered.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, thank you to David and the Network for the work they’ve done in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here in Royal Mint Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s a pity the money isn’t here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the Cabinet went on a visit to the actual Mint in Wales where we watched them mint coins for the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They told us that normally they would check our pockets for change in case we planned to walk off with any Olympics coins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since we were the Cabinet they’d let us off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, if anyone would like a few Olympics coins I’m ready to cut a reasonable deal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the health of the economy, just like the health of the body depends on good circulation. I know that Bob in his presentation this morning set out the scale of the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our currency it must flow to every corner of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As that great Elizabethan Sir Francis Bacon once said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Money is like muck, not good except it be spread.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means giving local areas the means to prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used to be good at this in days gone by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution was forged, not in the corridors of Whitehall, but the crucible of our local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arkwright’s first cotton mill in Derbyshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spinning and textiles in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron in Shropshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a great time it must have been with those pioneers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An age where competition between local areas sparked ideas and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaping and remaking our country into the world’s workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over the past hundred years or so we’ve seen Big Government in revolt (or revolting Big Government).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dead hand clawing back power and resource from any innovation that moved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government following after Government but the computer still saying no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast barrier of bureaucracy blocking up the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with local enterprise partnerships we’ve gone back to first principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving localities a real stake in the performance of their own economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating self-sustaining economies with local led growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working hand in glove with the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving back not just political but economic power to local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see where local enterprise partnerships fit into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, you’re leading the charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So two years on from your creation what’s happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I can see - plenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve seized the initiative and demonstrated local leadership over the Growing Places Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s where we’d like the future to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way these decisions used to be made was through civil servants and scoring systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers made decisions at the end of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’re saying there’s a better way of doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re giving you the power to get on with the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put money into local growth and local infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what’s happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hertfordshire Local Enterprise Partnership Board recently approved £11.5m for a range of projects that will bring a hospital, housing, offices and green spaces to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention a new stage for Elstree Studios - which brought us &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Indiana Jones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total we’re talking about 4,000 new jobs and 2,000 new homes by the time these projects are completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the South East partnership has already identified 10 projects with planning consent to receive £33m and create 28,000 jobs and 14,000 new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, over in Lancashire, they’ve approved three schemes which are ready to start work immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as Justine set out earlier - you know how to get the best bang for your buck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms that means 1,550 new jobs, a further £95m investment just short of 600 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to give a big hand to all those private sector lenders who’ve given their time to the enterprise cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your efforts are paying off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what’s so encouraging is the way that different areas are spurring each other on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coventry and Warwickshire Local Enterprise Partnership decided to encourage 100 companies to recruit 100 new apprentices in 100 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anything they can do Leeds can do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Leeds City Region Local Enterprise Partnership is aiming to get 1,000 companies to sign up to its 5-3-1 initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It brings skills, education, mentoring, work placements and apprenticeships to a local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’ll bet there’s someone here thinking a thousand? Only a thousand? I can do better than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, speaking as a Bradford man, I’m sure there’s even someone who can put one over on Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all means do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve no problem whatsoever with a bit of sibling rivalry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local people will be the winners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since we’re talking rewards let’s focus on the crown jewels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m referring, of course, to our Enterprise Zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing quite says we’re open for business than these hot houses of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I last looked there were 24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Hull to Hereford, Sheffield to the Solent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All with simplified planning rules, and 100 per cent relief for all new firms over five years and to be kitted out with super fast broadband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these tax breaks begin the moment a business moves onto the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve a zone in the Humber that could bring in more than 20,000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one in Tees Valley too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping us keep our place as a world leader in renewable energy, advanced manufacturing and digital sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention supporting up to 1,200 jobs by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on all day but now’s maybe not the time to pat yourselves on the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve a job to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go further faster we need to tear down the culture of delay in local government circles that’s paralysed action and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said last time I was here, I’m fed up with local organisations waiting for my permission to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be shy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t put your hand up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t faff about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ve found particularly refreshing about our local enterprise partnerships is the way they’re getting the public sector to just get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, Local Development Orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They let local authorities grant automatic planning permission for certain developments such as new industrial buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing the normal delay and costs of planning permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They give firms greater certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’ve no idea why only a handful were put in place in the seven years since they’ve been in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s anyone’s guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Enterprise Zones aren’t backwards in coming forwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re getting stuck in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two thirds of the Zones will have at least one of these orders in place by the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen orders have already been agreed, eight more have got through the consultation, a further 40 are in the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great Yarmouth and Lowestoft Enterprise Zone has a nice collection of development orders on the mantelpiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six at the last count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this hub of off shore wind farms, port logistics and engineering is putting its orders to good use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning them into new buildings, extensions, roads, telecommunications and low carbon energy installations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day I popped in to see one of the entrepreneurial companies who are benefiting from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SeaJacks build vessels for offshore wind farms in the North Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No idea how they do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just glad they’ve got the money to get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few folk think that doing things locally loses out a bit in terms of global prestige.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that’s stuff and nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re helping us gain a slice of the global pie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not over egging it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at global manufacturer X:Cel Superturn. It’s rapidly expanding its operation into the Sheffield City Region Enterprise Zone bringing £18 million with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese logistics firm Vantec, a subsidiary of Nissan, recently became the first overseas company to invest £24 million in an Enterprise Zone - taking advantage of Sunderland’s Enhanced Capital Allowances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These examples I think prove a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we need to give even more power to your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re about reforming business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing local areas to keep the proceeds of the wealth they create instead of handing it back to central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve published the National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development will now get the green light unless the harm outweighs the economic benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework is another example of our new approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve taken 1,000 pages of planning regulation down to less than 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given planning back to the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve made the point about how difficult it can be to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we’re doing something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that local enterprise partnerships alongside local authorities can create decent developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places where people can work and grow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am expecting to hear what’s going well and what’s getting in the way of you getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand today that you have shared stories of the good, bad and the ugly, for example: the good work that you have led to speed up planning locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ursula (Ursula Lidbetter - Chair, Greater Lincolnshire Local Enterprise Partnership) - I would like to hear more about what you have done to get planners and developers to agree investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denys (Denys Shortt - Chair, Coventry and Warwickshire Local Enterprise Partnership) - I know that my officials - including Bob - worked with you and transport officials to unlock a key development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex (Alex Pratt - Chair, Buckinghamshire Thames Valley Local Enterprise Partnership) - you have secured private sector resource to support the Buckinghamshire Thames Valley Local Enterprise Partnership. I would be interested in hearing what the local authorities are also doing to support you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must go further and faster - the scale of the challenge is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard today that because of local authority processes, one area took four months to procure a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would have been cheaper and easier to have trained a pigeon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything that takes four months to procure, tells you there is something wrong with the procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That it’s not fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally these processes are put together by people who don’t understand the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who are only interested in making sure nothing goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t be seduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re here to name and shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me let you into a secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a risk when we set up the local enterprise partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was against the normal way they do things from the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s basically because we didn’t want you to mimic or copy what had gone before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted you to bring that private sector vitality to the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage local authorities to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deliver the growth that makes a difference to our local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bet there are a few local organisations out there right now with their noses out of joint, uncomfortable with the way you’re pushing the boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to give you a considered view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re clearly doing something right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if there’s anyone who is refusing to play ball and help you to help your local communities let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, if there are local authorities out there that are refusing to pool their resources to support their partnership, I’ll be expecting answers - pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t be shy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see rules break them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are obstacles - go through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise the dead hand of Government will come up from the grave and pull you all down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take liberties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell us what you need to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all share the determination to act on behalf of our local communities, our local heartlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that that will help the money flow and the economy grow to the benefit of all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
