<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting economic growth through local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-06T10:22:27+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18802</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T10:22:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-investment-in-local-growth-to-continue"/>
    <title>Government investment in local growth to continue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor has announced a package of measures in his Autumn Statement that will help the department continue to boost local growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures will enable the country to build new homes, deliver key infrastructure and support vital jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new £474 million Local Infrastructure Fund that will support investment in key local projects will open up new development, including locally supported large housing sites and bring surplus public land back into use, delivering much needed new homes, businesses, infrastructure and local transport schemes. Plus a further £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures announced in the Autumn Statement and the September Housing and Planning package will support delivery of up to 120,000 homes. There will also be cash injections for local areas through a £1.5 billion borrowing arrangement for local enterprise partnerships and more money for the Regional Growth Fund. While small firms will continue to receive larger business rate tax breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-investment-in-local-infrastructure"&gt;New investment in local infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £225 million will be used to accelerate delivery of locally supported large housing sites, supporting around 50,000 homes. There are many locally supported large housing schemes in the development pipeline that can provide real benefits to local communities that are struggling to move forward because of the current economic circumstances. This fund will help unlock those stalled sites so they become shovel ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £190 million of the funding will be used to enable the quicker disposal of surplus public sector land for new homes. Alongside this, the Government will provide £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development. Government has identified enough land for over 106,000 homes and has already sold around 33,000. The Home and Communities Agency will become a single ‘shop window’ for land disposal so much needed homes can be built on these sites sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £60 million of this will be made available to support infrastructure in a limited number of enterprise zones. Building work has already begun on 20 zones and the majority have put in place simplified planning arrangements and secured private sector investment. The fund will help accelerate the infrastructure preparations so that new businesses can open and more new jobs are created as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from Lord Heseltine’s report which recommended devolution of more economic powers, local enterprise partnerships will be able to borrow up to £1.5 billion at cheap rates for nominated infrastructure projects. This puts partnerships and councils in much greater control over the levers of growth. They are already putting the Growing Places Fund to good use supporting 169 projects in the first 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will also pump an additional £350 million into the Regional Growth Fund, including a new £210 million to support jobs and growth across England - bringing the total fund to £2.6 billion. In addition, a new £170 million Department for Transport local transport pinch point fund, to unlock new development, homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="extra-support-for-business-continues"&gt;Extra support for business continues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to tackle the deficit there continues to be no real terms increases in business rates and inflation has fallen easing pressure further. The government will provide a further one year extension of the temporary doubling of small business rate relief to an estimated half a million business properties. In addition councils can now offer extra discounts to support local business and the 24 enterprise zones offer special 100% rate discounts to new firms that create local jobs. Postponing a revaluation will avoid local firms and local shops facing unexpected hikes in their business-rates bills over the next 5 years. Early estimates suggest that 800,000 premises faced a real-terms rise in their bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chancellor also announced a new temporary measure to extend the time period for the exemption from empty property rates, for newly built property for 18 months which will support construction. This will help promote regeneration and support high street renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="efficiency-savings-to-continue"&gt;Efficiency savings to continue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the government’s fiscal plans the new investment in the economy will, in part, be funded by some government departments’ resource budgets being reduced. The Department for Communites and Local Government has already become a smaller, streamlined, more flexible organisation. Its administration spending will reduce in real terms by 44% having reduced headcount by 37%. Arms length bodies have been reduced from 26 to 13 and the government office regions have been closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has been exempt from the reduction in 2013-2014 in recognition that local authorities are holding down budgets by comparable amounts by keeping council tax low in that year. This important concession will allow local authorities time in 2013-2014 to continue to protect frontline services by delivering reforms that will drive through further savings through transforming service delivery as demonstrated by the whole-place community budget pilots. Full details of local government funding for next year will be announced in the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement due later this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/54871</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:12:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012--2"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>What the Autumn Statement means for Business, Innovation and Skills.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to Parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £310 million, bringing the total available from April 2013 to £2.6 billion. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16508</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T16:16:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T16:16:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-sees-west-midlands-newest-business-growth-projects"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles sees West Midlands' newest business growth projects</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Communities Secretary Eric Pickles saw first hand today how local growth is flourishing in Aston and Wolverhampton.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local growth is flourishing in Aston and Wolverhampton as a result of locally directed government funding to create high-tech manufacturing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began his tour at the Sertec Group Holdings in Aston where he signed a contract for £2 million of Growing Places funding from the Greater Birmingham and Solihull local enterprise partnership. This will allow them to purchase new ground at the Aston Regional Investment site and improve its infrastructure connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sertec is looking to relocate to a new advanced manufacturing hub in Aston, 1 of 6 economic zones unveiled by Birmingham City Council. This new hub is phase one of Aston’s regional investment sites capable of delivering 3,000 jobs, 300,000 square feet of office or industrial space and bringing in over £30 million of private sector money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles inspected a subsidiary plant of Sertec also set to benefit. Presslite is a local family-run business that manufactures automotive parts for major car companies and employs 150 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Communities Secretary then travelled to the i54 enterprise zone near Wolverhampton where he met senior representatives from 3 companies. Moog, a high-tech aerospace business; Eurofins, a food testing laboratory; and Jaguar Land-Rover who will start building their new engine there creating at least 750 new jobs following their £355 million investment backed up by £10 million from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 3 firms were attracted by the low business rates, streamlined planning permissions within the enterprise zone as well as a £40 million joint investment from Wolverhampton City Council and Staffordshire County Council in a new junction off the M54 that will service the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are making decisions everyday to unlock much-needed local growth and give private sector companies every reason to invest and locate to their areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through our enterprise zones - like the i54 in Wolverhampton - and our Growing Places Fund - put to such good use in Aston - civic and businesses leaders in the West Midlands are helping create new jobs for their residents by bringing new firms to their local economy.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13313</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:45:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-to-get-jobs-and-boosting-growth"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people to get jobs and boosting growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk to see how local businesses are using government funding to help boost local development.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk and saw how local businesses and civic leaders are using government funding to help boost local development and deliver the government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an enterprise zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury enterprise zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the enterprise zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprise zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.
Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase, which would see the development of 1,500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough local enterprise partnerships have contributed £2 million each from the government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local enterprise partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using enterprise zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16134</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-plans-helping-local-people-get-jobs-and-growth-going"/>
    <title>Government plans helping local people get jobs and growth going</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles visited Cambridgeshire and Suffolk today to see how local businesses and civic leaders are using Government funding to help boost local development and deliver the Government’s drive for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst on the tour of the local area, Mr Pickles visited an Enterprise Zone, a previously stalled housing site and a high-tech research park to see the effects of Government investment delivered with a localist approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles began the day by opening a new training centre in the Alconbury Enterprise Zone, a former airfield and brownfield site. This new training centre will train hundreds of local people to further develop the site. Over the course of the development period, the Enterprise Zone will create in excess of  8,000 jobs in high-tech research, development and manufacturing. The site owners, Urban&amp;amp;Civic are working with JobCentre Plus, the local authority and local further education colleges to establish a jobs and skills ‘hub’ which will support local people into work with additional contractors and companies coming to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enterprise Zone has already delivered a simplified planning process that turned around consent for the marquee “incubator” building in just 36 days and using its business rate benefits has attracted high-tech research and development firm Enval to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uniquely, the zone will be rolled out alongside a wider residential development which could include 5,000 new homes, public transport infrastructure including guided busways and cycle networks; energy, water and waste infrastructure; community facilities including schools and a health centre; and 700 acres of landscaped green space with over half a million trees planted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his tour, he also visited the site of the Northstowe new town which will eventually provide around 10,000 new homes. Planning permission was recently given for the first phase first which would see the development of 1500 new homes. Mr Pickles reaffirmed the Government’s commitment to continuing to work with local partners to accelerate delivery and remove barriers to the establishment of this high quality new town. By unblocking the site, the Government has given a vital boost to local job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also paid a visit to the Haverhill Research Park and saw how the New Anglia and Greater Cambridgeshire Great Peterborough Local Enterprise Partnerships have contributed £2million each from the Government’s Growing Places Fund. The funding will enable the provision of infrastructure and site works to open up a 29.5 acre site that will create 350 homes, employment space, a hotel and leisure facilities which will establish 2000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships are unlocking much-needed local growth and providing strong local incentives for companies looking to invest. Using Enterprise Zones - like the one in Alconbury - and the Growing Places Fund, civic leaders and businesses are helping to create jobs, homes and leisure facilities that people need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There is huge potential in sites like Northstowe to boost local economies and we simply cannot afford to have them lying idle because of earlier agreements that are no longer viable. Britain is in a global race today with rising nations like China and Brazil. Countries like ours will only be able to compete if we make it easier for businesses to invest and quicker for infrastructure to get built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14699</id>
    <published>2012-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/local-enterprise-partnerships-receive-boost"/>
    <title>Local enterprise partnerships receive boost</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government is today announcing core funding for Local Enterprise Partnerships (LEPs) to allow them to drive forward their growth priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships are central to the Government’s approach to driving local economic growth and for ensuring that every community is able to fulfil its potential. This offer of over £24million from Government could unlock up to £20million locally and will enable Local Enterprise Partnerships to deliver their local plans for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interim £5million funding package will be made available immediately for all Local Enterprise Partnerships to draw upon for the remainder of this financial year. This will be followed by up to £250,000 per Local Enterprise Partnership per year for the following two years. Where matched by funds locally the overall funding pot could equate up to £45million over this period. The central government funding will be provided on a 50/50 basis by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) and the Department for Communities and Local Government (DCLG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s £25million boost will give Local Enterprise Partnerships the financial stability they need going forward, to build on their early successes and tailor the support they offer to local needs. If matched by local support, this could mean that up to £45million will be available to help Local Enterprise Partnerships turn their plans into jobs and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial we arm Local Enterprise Partnerships with the tools and resources they need to play a prominent role in delivering growth and jobs for their communities. This funding will help Local Enterprise Partnerships plan for the long term and ensure they can remain locally-led instead of dependent on central government support.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We need to ensure Local Enterprise Partnerships remain voluntary business and civic partnerships so they are in the best possible position to deliver sustainable growth and job creation in their areas. Already we are seeing Local Enterprise Partnerships across England delivering innovative schemes in their communities. This financial support will help the partnerships to continue this work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships will be invited to bid for matched funding for 2013/14 and 2014/15, setting out how they would be able to offer a cash match from public or private resources. Details on the scope of the match will be discussed with Local Enterprise Partnerships shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government made £5million of core funding available to Local Enterprise Partnerships last year to help them start up and establish themselves through financial support for things such as board support, development of priorities and business engagement. This was followed by a further £4million to build capacity over a four year period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interim funding for 2012/13 is made up of £4,875,000 split equally between BIS and DCLG.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 2013/14 and 2014/15, matched funding will be offered of up to £250,000 per LEP per annum, with DCLG and BIS together contributing £10million per year. Local Enterprise Partnerships wishing to utilise this funding will be required to source match funding of equal value.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are 39 Local Enterprise Partnerships across England. Each Local Enterprise Partnership is made up of local businesses working in partnership with a combination of local authorities. Further details on Local Enterprise Partnerships and what they do is available on the BIS website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14658</id>
    <published>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-new-manufacturing-institute-with-3-5-million-boost"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens new manufacturing institute with £3.5 million boost</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today announced a £3.5million Government investment for manufacturing innovation at the opening of a new High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2189195.jpg" alt="Eric Pickles visiting the new manufacturing institute"&gt;The institute is close to the legendary Dagenham factory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Institute has been created in partnership with the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence and Ford Britain, who are investing a further £1.44million, and is located in a manufacturing heartland a short distance from the legendary Dagenham factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Institute will develop new and innovative ways to improve manufacturing techniques and increase productivity that will ensure Britain remains a top choice for investment. It is expected to generate £80million to the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Institute will develop state of the art virtual manufacturing systems to assist companies to develop and implement world leading manufacturing processes, which are often too costly for many organisations to design themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will bring together leading lights from the worlds of business, engineering and academia employing 22 researchers and PhD students to work alongside 6 Ford research staff to create programmes that will help develop the high skilled work force needed to operate such systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles was joined by Ford Britain Chairman Joe Greenwell, as well as Chief Executive Bill Williams and Chairman, Martin Broadhurst of the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence. They met engineers learning the skills to drive the industry forward in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This country and county has a proud history of manufacturing. By investing in high-tech skills and innovation we can help ensure that as well as being part of our past, quality manufacturing is part of our future.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;By promoting enterprise, pushing forward research, creating jobs and giving people more skills we are sending a powerful signal that Britain is a top choice for inward investment and with that bringing local growth back to communities.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This is an Institute with a big ambition, to push back the frontiers of manufacturing, quicken production and reduce costs and bring benefits to business as well as the local area. It is a delight to open this new Institute and to pledge £3.5million of investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By bringing together the leading lights from business, academia and engineering the institute presents a wonderful opportunity to put Britain back at the forefront of manufacturing achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Government is committed helping to stimulate local enterprise and help drive local growth investment in projects like this that not only boost businesses but bring about wider benefits to the local area. As the world’s eyes turn to this area in the coming weeks, this institute stands out as a beacon of the innovation in the manufacturing industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Greenwell, Ford of Britain chairman, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ford is delighted to be a founding partner in this exciting new initiative. The Institute will accelerate research and development in innovative manufacturing systems that will help underpin the future of the UK’s high value manufacturing sector. This complements the work that Ford is already doing in this area and also provides significant opportunities for supply chain partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Williams, CEO of the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The creation of the High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute is a bold step in further establishing the United Kingdom in its place of the premier league of manufacturing engineering excellence world-wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157630744962904/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is contributing £3.5million over three years to the High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will be based at the Centre for Engineering and Manufacturing Excellence (CEME) at Rainham, Essex. CEME is a registered charity that operates an industry-led education and business campus in the heart of the Thames Gateway. CEME was created in 2002 as part of the Government’s regeneration programme for the Thames Gateway region. It is a key catalyst for delivering growth in business and skills for the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The High Speed Sustainable Manufacturing Institute will focus on the discipline of Manufacturing Engineering. Manufacturing Engineering is the branch of engineering concerned with the efficient production of industrial goods. It includes the design of production plant equipment and processes. This is an activity common to all manufacturing sectors and is particularly relevant to high volume operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14650</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/enterprise-zones-website-will-help-businesses-grow"/>
    <title>Enterprise zones website will help businesses grow</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Government micro site will showcase the many business benefits of locating in one of England’s 24 Enterprise Zones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has launched a brand new micro site to promote Enterprise Zones across England. The site is designed as the first point of call for all budding entrepreneurs and businesses looking to grow and expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184519.jpg" alt="Enterpise Zones microsite"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The site helps businesses find a place to grow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By choosing to locate in one of the 24 zones which cover a variety of industry sectors, small start-ups and expanding businesses will benefit from a number of measures including discounted business rates, simplified planning procedures and business ready infrastructures including super fast broadband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has joined the Department for Business Innovation and Skills and UK Trade and Investment in the way it seeks to speak to businesses and entrepreneurs in order to attract inward investment to the UK. Enterprise Zones are a route to generating jobs and businesses, helping to rebalance the economy and drive local and national growth and enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;www.enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk
&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Follow&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/entzonesgov"&gt;@entzonesgov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184613.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2184613.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14643</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lift-off-for-jobs-in-herefordshire"/>
    <title>Lift off for jobs in Herefordshire</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovative Enterprise Zone brings new investment to local area&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles has praised the innovation and ‘can-do’ attitude of Hereford Enterprise Zone for teaming up with global aerospace companies to create local jobs and stimulate growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179557.jpg" alt="Hereford Enterprise Zone"&gt;Hereford Enterprise Zone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hereford Enterprise Zone has been promoting the strengths of the local area as a hotspot for high tech businesses investment, which includes immediate tax breaks for companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing the huge benefits available, two global Aerospace companies, Tbilisi Aerospace Manufacturing based in Georgia and MARKET-MATS from the Ukraine, recently announced ambitious plans to locate in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move signals a major step forward in development of the Hereford Enterprise Zone with the potential to create hundreds of new jobs, bring wider benefits to the local area and mark out Herefordshire and Britain as a great choice for businesses across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the Communities Secretary met with the Governor of Washington State, Christine Gregoire, representatives from Herefordshire Council and the Aerospace companies to welcome the planned investment into the Hereford Enterprise Zone and wider Herefordshire area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This agreement shows that our low tax, light-touch regulation Enterprise Zones and Herefordshire’s ‘can do’ ambitions are a great combination that business are eager to take advantage of - Tbilisi Aerospace Manufacturing and Market-Mats will bring new jobs to the area and energise the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new generation of 24 Enterprise Zones with simplified planning rules, super-fast broadband and tax breaks for businesses, now span across England. The Zones are helping to create conditions to stimulate growth and have the potential to create tens of thousands of new jobs by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179536.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2179536.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9047</id>
    <published>2012-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/10-million-investment-to-connect-northampton-enterprise-zone"/>
    <title>£10 million investment to connect Northampton enterprise zone</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Transport Secretary Justine Greening announced a £10 million boost for transport infrastructure in Northampton’s Enterprise Zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money is being invested in the development of the Castle Railway Station at the heart of Northampton Enterprise Zone. The new station will provide vital infrastructure capacity to support local plans for sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northampton Enterprise Zone is building on the areas strengths in advanced technologies, high performance engineering, and low carbon technology. With access to super fast broadband, up to 100 per cent business rates discounts and simplified planning process the Zone is already attracting big business hitters like Carlsberg, providing more jobs and boosting the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Northampton is using its Enterprise Zone to energise the local economy and boost business. As these new opportunities for innovation and enterprise open up it is vital the infrastructure is in place to match Northampton’s ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This £10 million for the Castle Railway station is another step forward in Northampton’s resurgence as a place where local communities thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minster Andrew Stunell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Improving the transport links to this ambitious area will help Northampton to unleash its potential as a centre for local growth and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Turning Castle Station into a key transport hub at the heart of the Enterprise Zone is just one more reason for business to invest in this area and bring new jobs and homes that will benefit the whole community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with funding from Network Rail and Northamptonshire County Council the Government’s contribution will go towards phase one of the redevelopment scheme which includes a new station building and access to the platforms, which will be a major improvement for residents and visitors to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Northamptonshire Development Corporation, the agency driving regeneration in West Northamptonshire, can now look at how they can take forward subsequent phases of the redevelopment which will include a new larger car park and release of land for commercial opportunities close to the station.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
