<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving people more power over what happens in their neighbourhood"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13413</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-it-easier-to-set-up-new-town-and-parish-councils-discussion-paper"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils: discussion paper</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils. This discussion paper presents a range of proposals that would help achieve this. We would like your views on these, as well as any other comments or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12768</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-right-to-challenge--2"/>
    <title>Community Right to Challenge</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the provisions being made by government in the Localism Bill to introduce a Community Right to Challenge. It seeks views on the detail of how the right will work in practice, which will be set out in regulations. It also invites views on what type of support and guidance should be provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12769</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-right-to-bid"/>
    <title>Community Right to Bid</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the provisions being made by government in the Localism Bill to assist community organisations who wish to purchase assets of community value. It seeks views on the detail of how the scheme should be delivered, which will be set out in regulations. It also invites views on what type of support and guidance should be provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12765</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/sustainable-communities-act-2007-regulations"/>
    <title>Sustainable Communities Act 2007 regulations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 December 2010 the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government issued a second invitation to local authorities under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007 (‘The Act’). He invited councils to consult people, ask them how they would like to see their local area improved and to take whatever action they see fit to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If councils, having consulted and reached agreement with their local communities, find that a bureaucratic barrier prevents them from taking action, they can submit a formal ‘proposal’ asking government to remove the barrier through the online portal at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). This portal is also open to anyone who wishes to ask the government to remove a barrier which is stopping local action. We would, for example, welcome requests to remove barriers from organisations such as town and parish councils, and County Associations of Parish Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act was amended in April 2010 to allow the procedures for receiving, considering and deciding proposals under the Act to be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act now allows the arrangements for the consideration of proposals submitted in response to the invitation to be set out in regulations, following a period of consultation. There will be no deadlines for the submission of proposals, which can now be submitted straight to the government at any time. Information on the action the government is taking on the proposals will be available online so that councils and communities can track progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act, and the proposed draft regulations set out in this consultation, is a means to hold government to account and ensure each proposal is given the fullest consideration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12755</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-use-of-restrictive-covenants-for-pubs"/>
    <title>The use of restrictive covenants for pubs</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation aims to establish an evidence base regarding the use of restrictive covenants which prevent pubs from being used as such once they are sold, and the impact that this has on local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responses to the consultation will be used by the government to help assess whether action needs to be undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12746</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/neighbourhood-planning-regulations--2"/>
    <title>Neighbourhood planning regulations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill leaves various procedural and technical requirements of the neighbourhood planning system to regulations. This consultation seeks views on whether the proposed neighbourhood planning regulations are fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12724</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-policy-statement-for-part-2-of-the-localism-act-2011"/>
    <title>Proposed policy statement for part 2 of the Localism Act 2011</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is on a proposed policy statement for Part 2 of the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act provides a substantial and lasting shift in power away from central government and towards local people. The government has given public authorities more powers and freedoms to conduct their business and deliver services to the public. This includes a major reduction in the ‘oversight’ role of central government. Public authorities must, therefore, accept responsibility for the consequences of their actions or omissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2 of the Localism Act is about incentivising public authorities to comply with European law, in order to avoid any financial sanctions in the first place. The proposed policy statement sets out a fair, proportionate and reasonable approach for the use of Part 2. The statement has been developed with the Local Government Association and the Greater London Authority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12710</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposals-from-town-and-parish-councils-under-the-sustainable-communities-act-2007"/>
    <title>Proposals from town and parish councils under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 December 2010 the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government issued a second invitation to local authorities under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007. He invited local authorities to consult people, ask them how they would like to see their local area improved and to take appropriate action to make it happen. The Localism Act has given them far more freedom and flexibility to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If local authorities, having consulted and reached agreement with their local communities, find that a bureaucratic barrier prevents them from taking action, they can submit a formal ‘proposal’ under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007 asking Government to remove the barrier through the online portal at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). This portal is also open to anyone who wishes to ask the government to remove a barrier which is stopping local action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation is seeking views on whether the existing arrangements for submitting barrier busting proposals are appropriate or whether town and parish councils should be able to submit proposals using the Sustainable Communities Act as well as local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14752</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress--2"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by Locality, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; Neighbourhood Planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and Town Halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality CEO Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ‘12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. Download an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localism-act-2011-overview" title="Localism Act 2011: overview"&gt;overview to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid" title="Community Right to Bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt; came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mycommunityrights.org.uk" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
