<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving people more power over what happens in their neighbourhood"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14752</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress--2"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by Locality, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; Neighbourhood Planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and Town Halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality CEO Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ‘12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. Download an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localism-act-2011-overview" title="Localism Act 2011: overview"&gt;overview to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid" title="Community Right to Bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt; came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mycommunityrights.org.uk" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12146</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T16:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/brandon-lewis-celebrates-with-locals-at-essexs-resident-run-pub"/>
    <title>Brandon Lewis celebrates with locals at Essex's 'resident run pub'</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2009 the local community deprived of their much loved local decided to take action and set about running it for themselves. They set up an action group and a team of enthusiastic local volunteers to restore the pub, staff the bar and get The Norton back in business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting the dedicated team of volunteers, the minister toasted the innovative community who have now set their ambitions higher with plans to buy the freehold so the community can claim a real stake in the pub by buying shares in the business. The Norton has already raised enough money for the deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community shares let local people take a more active in role in their communities. Members, as part-owners, have a direct say in their success and encourage people to play an active part in their future. Last month the department launched a new community shares unit that gives advice to residents on how they can claim an ownership stake in local assets and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community Pubs Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Norton is not just a cracking pub, a lively atmosphere and vital local business but it is a true example of a resident run pub run that is now firmly in the hands of the whole community. I wish it every success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The community of Cold Norton have shown just how determination and ambition can be used to safeguard treasured local facilities - not just so they can stay open, but so they can thrive and grow. It is exactly why we are pushing power away from Whitehall and into the hands of local people who know what they want for their area.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Guppy Chairman at The Norton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Opening and operating a community pub has been hard work but generally fun, I believe Cold Norton is a much better place to live with a good friendly pub. It is not just about selling alcohol but the place has become a focal point for the whole village.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to see community pubs thriving everywhere and has introduced a series of measures to support them including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to introduce local business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood" title="Giving communities more say about what happens in their area"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, the department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13413</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-it-easier-to-set-up-new-town-and-parish-councils-discussion-paper"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils: discussion paper</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils. This discussion paper presents a range of proposals that would help achieve this. We would like your views on these, as well as any other comments or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14715</id>
    <published>2012-10-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-community-shares-to-boost-local-services"/>
    <title>New 'Community Shares' to boost local services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today launched a new Community Shares Unit to help local people claim a stake and become part owners of much loved local assets and services such as their community pub, football club or even in the generation of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community shares let local people to take a more active in role in their communities by giving members - as part-owners - a direct say in their success, encouraging them to play an active part in their future. Most investors buy shares to help achieve a social good, however if the enterprise is successful they may also benefit from dividend payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dividends can be paid in money, but also in kind, with cheaper energy, cut-price pints, and local, fairly-priced food as possible incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and run by Co-operatives UK and Locality - the country’s largest network of community led organisations - the new Community Shares Unit will enable more local enterprises to use share offers as a way of raising finance - in particular risk capital - to purchase buildings or get new projects up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the Community Development Finance Association annual conference, Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are shifting control away from Whitehall, handing communities the powers they need to run their own affairs.
&amp;gt; “Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground.
&amp;gt; “We want to create the conditions in which social investment and community finance can flourish to make this happen. This new unit will give them the helping hand they need to take full advantage of the opportunity to do things their way, in the best interests of their area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new unit aims to grow the community shares market with the ambition of launching over 200 share issues over the next three years. It will also offer guidance and advice to investors seeking to understand more about the market, and support community enterprises, with services such as checking offer documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Mayo, Secretary General of Co-operatives UK, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re seeing more and more communities taking things into their own hands. They are investing co-operatively in local enterprises themselves, whether that’s football or farming, retail or renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Rolo, Director of Innovation at Locality, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that the Department for Communities and Local Government is supporting one of the fastest growing areas of social investment. Community shares generate the right kind of finance and act as a powerful lever to access other funding, allowing communities to develop fully sustainable enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since 2009, 15,000 people have invested in over 100 community share issues, raising over £15million. To find out more on community shares and the new Unit visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityshares.org.uk/"&gt;www.communityshares.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last three years Co-operatives UK and Locality have undertaken a Government-funded research project examining the potential of community shares and bonds as a way to increase community empowerment and grow social enterprises and attract investment from non-government sources. It investigated how members of the public can invest in enterprises that serve a community purpose. Ten projects tested the idea, looking at barriers that could restrict their growth and how they can be overcome. These include community retail stores, renewable energy and a football club. The outcome of the action research project confirmed that community shares not only help communities access funding directly but are also a good lever for accessing complementary grant and loan funding. They provide a viable option to the undercapitalisation of the community sector. The Department are funding Co-operatives UK in association with Locality, over three years, to establish the Community Shares Unit. To find out more about locality please visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/"&gt;www.locality.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). To find out more about Co-operatives UK please visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;www.uk.coop&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Community share offers are proving a lifeline for communities across the country. For example, Community enterprise organisation Bath and West Community Energy have, since 2010, raised funding to bring alternative sources of energy to their community, including the installation of solar, photovoltaic, hydro and wind technologies. With nearly 200 members, Bath and West Community Energy have raised £722,000 through a community share offer, exceeding their share target.  This in turn has helped them to secure £1million loan finance to fund 12 of their projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act which was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. A plain English guide to the Localism Act is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month The Community Right to Bid came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Community Rights website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk"&gt;www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is also available on the My Community Rights website. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14712</id>
    <published>2012-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/handing-power-back-to-the-people-of-milton-keynes"/>
    <title>Handing power back to the people of Milton Keynes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Milton Keynes residents will be given a much greater say over the future development of their town under new proposals published today by Housing Minister Mark Prisk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its designation as a new town in 1967 Milton Keynes has been subject to central Government involvement either through the establishment of Development Corporations or, more recently, through the Milton Keynes Partnership Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But under new plans published for consultation today, those planning functions currently undertaken by the Homes and Communities Agency would be transferred to Milton Keynes Council. This would allow Milton Keynes Council the opportunity to plan development more strategically in their area and also allow local residents a greater say in how that land is developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For years, development control of Milton Keynes has been split between the locally elected council and a Government agency. Today’s proposals would shift power back to where it belongs - with the people who live in the area.
&amp;gt; “I look forward to hearing how Milton Keynes Council plans to work with local people to decide the future development of their town to secure its future for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homes and Communities Agency Chief Executive Pat Ritchie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency has been working closely with colleagues at the Department for Communities and Local Government and Milton Keynes Council for many months to facilitate this transfer which has now taken a significant step forward.
&amp;gt; “It is a great example of central and local government working together to help achieve and deliver local ambition. We will continue to work together to finalise the process which will enable Milton Keynes Council to fulfil their plans for growth and continue the excellent development work that has been carried out here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milton Keynes Chief Executive David Hill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘localisation’ of the Homes and Communities Agency’s roles and responsibilities in Milton Keynes and the transfer of its residual land assets to Milton Keynes Council will - for the first time in Milton Keynes’ history - mean that all the key mechanisms for shaping the way in which the city develops are in the hands of locally elected representatives.
&amp;gt; “That should give confidence to local residents that plans for future growth will be responsive to their views and aspirations. The transfer package has been supported by all the political groups on the council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion letter on the future of planning functions in Milton Keynes, is published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/hcamiltonkeynestransfer"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/hcamiltonkeynestransfer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deadline for responses is &lt;strong&gt;Monday 29 October&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14707</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-launches-new-stop-the-clock-power-to-save-local-treasures"/>
    <title>Minister launches new 'stop-the-clock' power to save local treasures</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today legally authorised new powers for communities to help prevent the rapid sell off of treasured community assets and buildings so they can be protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Bid, created in the historic Localism Act, comes in force tomorrow across the country so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities like post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to audience of local activists and parish councillors at the National Association of Local Councils conference, Mr Foster spoke of the Government’s continued desire to push power back into the hands of local people so they can decide what is important in their communities for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new right gives voluntary and community organisations and parish councils the opportunity to nominate an asset to be included on a list of ‘assets of community value’, pausing the sale of a successfully listed asset for six-months, giving communities the time to prepare a bid and get a business plan together. Previously the community had no opportunity or time to gather resources to bid to buy or take them over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For too long communities have been shut out, forced to watch from the sidelines as treasured local assets, vital in peoples daily lives, have been shut-down and sold on. We are determined to put an end to that and put people back at the centre of the future of their communities.
&amp;gt; “The Community Right to bid lets communities decide what’s important to them and ‘stop the clock’ on sales so they have them the time to get together a bid, put together a plan and ensure that prized local assets can live on, this time run by the local community for the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities are already showing their determination and appetite to get involved in saving and running local facilities and amenities and over 500 people are looking into using the Right to Bid in their community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Norden, local people formed a Trust to buy and refurbish the historic old library building and reopen it as a community facility. The group purchased the lease form the Local authority and since then the building has been transformed into a modern community hub and a doctors surgery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Cranleigh, the community is already planning to use the Community Right to Bid to return the first village hospital in the community back into the hands of the local people to provide support to the elderly in the community and ensure that the long history of the building as a community facility can continue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Bid, is just one of the Community Rights measures brought in by the Localism Act. In June, the Government announced a £30million package of specialist support to help communities take advantage of their new rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Bid was introduced by the Localism Act 2011 which was enacted on 15 November 2011. The Right to Bid comes into force on 19 September. A plain English guide to the Localism Act is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Community Rights website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk"&gt;www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is also available on the My Community Rights website. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mycommunityrights.org.uk"&gt;mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/&lt;/a&gt; (external link). &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11804</id>
    <published>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tenant-panels-and-empowerment-training-and-support-programme-prospectus"/>
    <title>Tenant panels and empowerment: training and support programme prospectus</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This prospectus invites applications from eligible organisations for grant funding to deliver a national programme for social tenants living in social housing that will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;encourage more tenant panels to challenge landlords, shape services and get involved in local decision making; and
empower tenants to engage with their landlord and take control of local services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11807</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/food-growing-case-studies"/>
    <title>Food growing: case studies</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The projects included in this document showcase best practice and the varied approaches that community groups have taken to getting land to use for their food growing projects. From space on housing estates now being run as a mini social enterprise, to derelict allotment land, every project shows that where community groups work together with their local authorities or other local landowners, great achievements can follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11292</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/openness-and-transparency-on-personal-interests-guidance-for-councillors"/>
    <title>Openness and transparency on personal interests: guidance for councillors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide gives basic practical information to councillors about how to be open and transparent about their personal interests. It is designed to help councillors, including parish councillors, now that new standards arrangements have been introduced by the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
