<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Protecting and developing the overseas territories"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56680</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-the-overseas-territories-and-overseas-territory-leaders-issue-joint-communique-following-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council agree joint communique</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council, chaired by Minister Simmonds and attended by Premiers, Chief Ministers and other elected representatives from Britain’s Overseas Territories, closed today with the agreement of a joint communiqué which sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the second day of the Council also saw the Prime Minister welcome Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said in his foreword in the White Paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom’s 14 Overseas Territories are an integral part of Britain’s life and history. This Government is ambitious for our Territories as we are ambitious for the United Kingdom.  We want to see our communities flourish in partnership, with strong and sustainable local economies. We see an important opportunity to set world standards in our stewardship of the extraordinary natural environments we have inherited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out a very positive vision for the Overseas Territories. This first meeting of the Joint Ministerial Council has helped us identify an ambitious list of priority areas for action, such as encouraging economic growth; protecting the environment and making government work better. We will work closely with the Territories in the coming year to achieve what we have together set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of my Ministerial colleagues from across Government took part in the Council this week, demonstrating that the UK Government as a whole is committed to supporting the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17809</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:37:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>UK and Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds, has opened the first annual Joint Ministerial Council, bringing together political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers to drive forward implementation of the vision and strategy set out in the June 2012 White Paper &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/overseas-territories/overseas-territories-white-paper/" title="Overseas Territotories White Paper"&gt;The Overseas Territories: Security, Success and Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council aims to agree priorities and plans for the UK and the Territories to work together on wide range of issues including: building successful and resilient economies; harnessing support from the Commonwealth and the EU; cherishing the environment and creating green growth; working together for better government; building stronger, healthier and safer communities; health; and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister will welcome elected leaders to Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister. Ministers and senior officials from wide range of UK Departments will take part in the Council, demonstrating the commitment from across government to working with the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the meeting Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to welcome elected leaders from the Overseas Territories to the Joint Ministerial Council. This is an opportunity for us to strengthen our work together to build flourishing communities, proudly retaining aspects of their British identity, creating new opportunities for young and future generations and protecting natural environments to the highest international standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year, we have demonstrated our commitment to preserving the astounding natural environment in the territories, by establishing a new Marine Protected Area in South Georgia &amp;amp; the South Sandwich Islands and launching Darwin Plus, the new Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16633</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:14:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-overseas-territories-security-success-and-sustainability"/>
    <title>The Overseas Territories: security, success and sustainability</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government published this white paper on the Overseas Territories on the 28 June 2012, setting out its overall approach. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35547</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/overseas-territories-flags-flown-for-the-first-time-in-parliament-square"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories flags flown for the first time in Parliament Square</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/foreignoffice/8138384167/"&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flags will fly throughout the visit of the President of the Republic of Indonesia, Dr Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono, who is in London until 2 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the occasion, Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am really pleased to see the flags of the Overseas Territories being flown on a state occasion in London. This brings representation of the Overseas Territories in line with the Commonwealth nations, which have long had their flags flown on such occasions. Flying these flags is a sign to the people in the Territories, and those in the UK, of our renewed commitment to the Territories, which was outlined in our recent White Paper. I hope that this will help raise the profile of the Overseas Territories in the UK and around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flags of the Overseas Territories will now be flown on state occasions in London, including Trooping the Colour and other ceremonial occasions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35512</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-launches-new-environment-and-climate-fund-for-the-uk-s-overseas-territories"/>
    <title>Government launches new environment and climate fund for the UK’s Overseas Territories</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Fund, which brings together funds from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, and Department for International Development, will disburse around £2 million per year dedicated to environmental and conservation projects in the UK’s Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories are home to many species and environments found nowhere else in the world - including an estimated 90% of the biodiversity found within the UK and Overseas Territories combined.  The unique environmental wealth of the Overseas Territories was highlighted in the recent UK Government White Paper on the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In welcoming the new Fund, Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an excellent example of how we are meeting our White Paper commitment to provide co-ordinated Government support to the Overseas Territories and a signal of how important we consider the environments of the Overseas Territories to be. I have high hopes that this Fund will lead to many innovative and creative projects which will result in better sustainable environmental management in the Overseas Territories”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the announcement on the creation of the new Fund, Dr Tim Stowe, the RSPB’s International Director, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is excellent news for Britain’s albatrosses, iguanas, whales, and elephant seals, and is a welcome announcement alongside the Government’s recently announced action plan for Overseas Territories biodiversity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Fund provides a simpler and more co-ordinated funding mechanism and will support a range of environment and climate-related issues to ensure long-term sustainable natural resource management in the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fund was launched today to coincide with the 11th meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity in Hyderabad, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the Fund, including details of how to apply, can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://darwin.defra.gov.uk/"&gt;Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35648</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-united-kingdom-restates-its-longstanding-commitment-to-the-people-of-gibraltar"/>
    <title>The United Kingdom restates its longstanding commitment to the people of Gibraltar</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland recalls its sovereignty over Gibraltar and the Territorial Waters surrounding it and reaffirms that as a separate territory, recognised by the United Nations and included since 1946 in its list of non-self governing territories, Gibraltar enjoys the individual and collective rights accorded by the UN Charter. The 2006 Gibraltar Constitution provides for a modern and mature relationship between Gibraltar and the UK. This description would not apply to any relationship based on colonialism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom restates its longstanding commitment to the people of Gibraltar that it will never enter into arrangements under which the people of Gibraltar would pass under the sovereignty of another State against their wishes. The United Kingdom also confirms that it will not enter into a process of sovereignty negotiations with which Gibraltar is not content.&lt;br&gt;
The United Kingdom notes that both it and Gibraltar desire to continue the Trilateral Forum for Dialogue, as the most credible, constructive and practical means of strengthening UK-Gibraltar-Spain relations for the benefit of all parties, but the United Kingdom recognises the Forum cannot continue in the absence of agreement between all parties to its resumption. The United Kingdom regrets the fact that the Government of Spain withdrew from those talks in 2011 and stands ready to explore new ways of taking forward dialogue and co-operation on issues of mutual importance by any means that fully reflect the interests, rights and responsibilities of the people of Gibraltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27929</id>
    <published>2012-09-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/overseas-territories-flags-flown-over-foreign-office"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories flags flown over Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;From now on, the flag of each UK Overseas Territory will be flown over the FCO one day every year, to mark a significant day in each of their respective histories.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lidington said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I send my greetings and best wishes to all Gibraltarians on Gibraltar National Day. It is a day to celebrate the people of Gibraltar, their community and identity. It is fitting that Gibraltar’s flag should be flown annually in London to mark this occasion.”      &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Simmonds said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased that the FCO is celebrating this new era of positive engagement between the UK and the Territories by flying their flags over our building in London. The Government is determined to show our commitment to this relationship in a year which has seen a number of important landmarks, including the publication of the White Paper.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 14 June, the flag of the Falkland Islands was flown over the FCO, 10 Downing Street and the Department for Communities and Local Government to commemorate the 30th Anniversary of the islands’ liberation. The flags of all Territories were flown as part of the Diamond Jubilee pageant and will be featured in future ceremonies of State.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27818</id>
    <published>2012-07-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/combating-illegal-fishing-in-the-southern-ocean"/>
    <title>Combating illegal fishing in the Southern Ocean</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK jointly convened and co-chaired a workshop in Cape Town, South Africa from 24 to 27 July, aimed at developing regional capacity to combat illegal fishing in Southern Ocean waters.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop, which was attended by representatives from 16 coastal African States as well as regional organisations, identified a range of practical controls that states could put in place within their ports to reduce illegal fishing activity. This was the second such workshop the UK has been involved in, and builds upon the progress that followed the first workshop, held in August 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop was jointly chaired by the FCO’s Polar Regions Unit and the South African Department of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, and was held under the auspices of CCAMLR (Commission for the Conservation of the Antarctic Marine Living Resources) and NEPAD (the African Union’s  New Partnership for Africa’s Development).   The event was supported by the UK, South Africa and Australia, and featured a wide range of experts and guest speakers, including the UN Food and Agriculture Organisation.  Like the 2010 conference, this event was primarily funded by CCAMLR, using proceeds the UK had donated from the sale of fish confiscated from an illegal vessel operating in the waters of the UK Overseas Territory of South Georgia &amp;amp; the South Sandwich Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On hearing of the successful conclusion of the workshop, Foreign Office Minister Henry Bellingham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m delighted that the UK has been able to contribute to this important work.  Illegal fishing is a major global problem: estimates suggest that in some areas illegal fishing accounts for up to 40% of all fish landed, and that the illegal fishing industry is worth up to £15billion annually.  This problem can only be tackled by the international community working together.  Initiatives such as this workshop play a vital role in facilitating the commitment and collaboration that are needed for an improved deterrence of illegal fishing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants in the workshop included representatives from: Benin, Cameroon, Comoros, Cote d’Ivoire, Gabon, Ghana, Kenya, Liberia, Mauritius, Mozambique, Namibia, Sao Tome &amp;amp; Principe, Sierra Leone, South Africa, Tanzania and Togo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=22712334"&gt;Read about the previous workshop, held in 2010.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27814</id>
    <published>2012-07-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/relations-between-the-uk-and-turks-caicos-islands"/>
    <title>Relations between the UK and Turks &amp; Caicos Islands</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was delighted to welcome Dr Ewing to the London Olympics and to the UK.  We had a good and constructive discussion about the financial and economic situation in TCI, the forthcoming elections, Dr Ewing’s vision for the future of the Islands, and the bilateral relationship between the UK and TCI.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I underlined that the UK remains committed to continuing our open dialogue with both TCI political parties and independent candidates, and to supporting the new Premier chosen by the people of the Turks and Caicos Islands in the November elections.  I look forward to continuing to build on these relationships in the run up to the polls.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47017</id>
    <published>2012-07-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/incursion-by-spanish-authorities-into-british-gibraltar-territorial-waters"/>
    <title>Incursion by Spanish authorities into British Gibraltar Territorial Waters</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reacting to a recent incursion by Spanish authorities into British Gibraltar territorial waters by the Spanish Guardia Civil on Friday, Mr Lidington said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked by the disgraceful behaviour of the Spanish Guardia Civil who detained two Gibraltarian British Nationals in British jurisdiction and transferred them to Spain.  The Government will be making it clear to Spain that such action, on the part of the law enforcement agencies of a EU Partner and NATO Ally, is intolerable and unlawful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The British Government remains confident of our Sovereignty of Gibraltar and British Gibraltar Territorial Waters.  Our position is clear.  The UK will never enter into arrangements under which the people of Gibraltar would pass under the sovereignty of another State against their wishes.  Furthermore, the UK will not enter into a process of sovereignty negotiations with which Gibraltar is not content.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
