<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting the Overseas Territories"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60181</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-court-of-human-rights-decision-on-chagossian-case"/>
    <title>European Court of Human Rights’ decision on Chagossian Case</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case concerns complaints made by the Chagos Islanders arising from the evacuation of the British Indian Ocean Territory between 1967 and 1973.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the end of this legal process, which has taken many years. We have made clear our regret for the wrongs done to the Chagossian people over forty years ago. Nevertheless, it was right for the Government to defend itself against this action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that this litigation is concluded, the Government will take stock of our policy towards the resettlement of the British Indian Ocean Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;), as we have always said we would. There are fundamental difficulties with resettlement in &lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;, but we will be as positive as possible in our engagement with Chagossian groups and all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Human Rights decision on application 35622/04: Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.echr.coe.int/ECHR/Homepage_EN" title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/59931</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T14:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories: Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chaired the first meeting of the Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council in London from 4-5 December. This Council brings together the political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers. It provides a forum for the exchange of views on political and constitutional issues and has a mandate to lead work to review and implement the strategy and commitments in the June 2012 White Paper The Overseas Territories: Security Success and Sustainability and to promote the security and good governance of the Territories and their sustainable economic and social development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council agreed a communiqué which identified priority issues and set out a comprehensive action plan for joint work. A copy of this communiqué has been laid in the Library of the House. The communiqué reflects the commitment of the governments of the Overseas Territories and the UK to work together to support economic growth and jobs; to protect the environment and create green growth; to harness effectively the support of the EU, the Commonwealth and other international organisations; and to deliver better government, better education and stronger, healthier and safer communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with our commitment in the White Paper we will report to Parliament on progress in implementing the commitments in the communiqué by territory governments and UK Departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual Joint Ministerial Council succeeds the Overseas Territories Consultative Council set up in 1999. It was attended this year by political leaders and representatives of the following Territories: Anguilla; Bermuda; the British Virgin Islands; the Cayman Islands; the Falkland Islands; Gibraltar; Montserrat; Pitcairn; St Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha; and the Turks and Caicos Islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 December the Prime Minister welcomed Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Overseas Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council" title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council-communique" title=" Joint Ministerial Council communique"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council communiqué&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57510</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:04:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth Land </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen visited the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office for the second time today, as the last official engagement of her Diamond Jubilee year. Her Majesty’s previous visit was in 1982 to mark the department’s bicentenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of the building, Foreign Secretary William Hague announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory had been named ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’ in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a mark of this country’s gratitude to The Queen for Her service, we are naming a part of the British Antarctic Territory in her honour as ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fitting tribute at the end of Her Majesty’s Diamond Jubilee year, and I am very proud to be able to announce it as she visits the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Territory is a unique and important member of the network of fourteen UK Overseas Territories. To be able to recognise the UK’s commitment to Antarctica with a permanent association with Her Majesty is a great honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area now to be known as Queen Elizabeth Land, which was previously unnamed, is around 169,000 square miles (437,000 sq km), making up just under a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory. This is almost twice the size of the UK, which stands at 94,000 square miles (244,000 sq km).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land is bounded on the North side by the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves, to the North East by Coats Land, on the East by Dronning Maud Land and extending on the West side to a line between the South Pole and Rutford Ice Stream, east of Constellation Inlet.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen has been on the throne for 60 of the 104 years since the UK claimed territory in Antarctica in 1908. This includes the entire time it has been known as the British Antarctic Territory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Queen Elizabeth Land" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5726/QEL-Antarctica-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Antarctic Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt;) extends from 20⁰ to 80⁰ West. It was claimed by the UK in 1908 and was the first official claim in Antarctica. It was designated officially as a separate Overseas Territory in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All claims to territory within Antarctica are held in abeyance under Article IV of the Antarctic Treaty, 1959, which neither confirms nor denies competing claims, but prevents new claims being made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name Queen Elizabeth Land will now be used on all British maps. Because of the unique status of Antarctica, which is covered by an international Treaty that suspends territorial sovereignty, it is for other countries to decide whether or not they will officially recognise this name.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place naming in &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaken on the basis that a currently unnamed area requires a name for scientific or logistical purposes. This approach is fully in line with the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions on names are made by the Commissioner of the British Antarctic Territory, who is based in London. The Commissioner takes advice on new names from the Antarctic Place Names Committee, which meets twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has no permanent population. British presence is maintained via three research stations operated by the British Antarctic Survey. The Territory itself is self-financing, investing modest receipts from stamp sales and the income tax from overwintering British scientists in environmental projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is not the first time that land in Antarctica has been named after The Queen. Princess Elizabeth Land in East Antarctica, which was discovered in 1931 by the Australian Sir Douglas Mawson, was named by him after Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth (now Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II). And in 2006, an unnamed mountain range in the Antarctic Peninsula was named The Princess Royal Range, in recognition of Her Royal Highness’s work to support environmental and heritage protection work in Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Foreign Secretary's speech"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s speech&lt;/a&gt; welcoming Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on supporting the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories" title="Supporting the Overseas Territories"&gt;Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57435</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:28:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office"/>
    <title>Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary announced that an area in the British Antarctic Territory has been named Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are all delighted to welcome you to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office for the final event of your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In a year in which millions of British people have been able to see you and cheer you, we are truly honoured here in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to have you here with us and to take our part in closing this magnificent period of celebration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is an opportunity for everyone here to show how proud they are to serve in your Majesty’s Diplomatic Service and in the Home Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And there are over 10,000 British and locally-engaged staff in our Embassies and High Commissions abroad who will be equally inspired by your visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You embody a life of service to our country, and a lifetime of diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have made over 260 official visits to 116 different countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Promoting reconciliation, as you did on your visit to West Germany in 1965, and to Japan in 1975;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving encouragement to nations after profound change, such as your visit to Russia in 1994 and to South Africa in 1995;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helping to heal the wounds of history and to make peace irreversible, as I saw myself during your truly historic State Visit to Ireland last year;
And all the time steadfastly uniting the Commonwealth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are deeply grateful to you, and to the 11 members of the Royal Family who have travelled to 29 countries and territories for your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, I am conscious that I am your twenty-second Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your wisdom and experience are an inspiration to all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are striving for excellence in all that we do in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our goal is to be the best Diplomatic Service in the world: helping British people overseas, supporting our economy, keeping our country secure, and upholding freedom and human rights at all times. We do this with your example always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we are renaming in your honour the newly-restored old Home Office Library, which now houses our historians and the Knowledge and Information Management team, which will be called the Diamond Jubilee Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I am delighted to announce that as a mark of our country’s gratitude to you, an area of the Antarctic 437,000 square kilometres in size, nearly twice the size of the United Kingdom and more than a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory, will be given a name for the very first time. From today, in your honour, it will be forever known as Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are proud to serve a Queen who has achieved so much for our nation and who embodies the ideals of public service that we cherish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we thank you for your visit; for this proud and happy occasion that we will all remember for the rest of our lives, and which will be recorded for our successors in the plaque you are unveiling today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank everyone here and all the staff of Foreign and Commonwealth Office, all over the world for all their hard work on behalf of our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And now your Majesty to commemorate your visit today I invite you to unveil the plaque marking your Diamond Jubilee Year.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5731/Queen_s-visit--final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title="Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56680</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-the-overseas-territories-and-overseas-territory-leaders-issue-joint-communique-following-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council agree joint communique</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council, chaired by Minister Simmonds and attended by Premiers, Chief Ministers and other elected representatives from Britain’s Overseas Territories, closed today with the agreement of a joint communiqué which sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the second day of the Council also saw the Prime Minister welcome Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said in his foreword in the White Paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom’s 14 Overseas Territories are an integral part of Britain’s life and history. This Government is ambitious for our Territories as we are ambitious for the United Kingdom.  We want to see our communities flourish in partnership, with strong and sustainable local economies. We see an important opportunity to set world standards in our stewardship of the extraordinary natural environments we have inherited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out a very positive vision for the Overseas Territories. This first meeting of the Joint Ministerial Council has helped us identify an ambitious list of priority areas for action, such as encouraging economic growth; protecting the environment and making government work better. We will work closely with the Territories in the coming year to achieve what we have together set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of my Ministerial colleagues from across Government took part in the Council this week, demonstrating that the UK Government as a whole is committed to supporting the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17809</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:37:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>UK and Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds, has opened the first annual Joint Ministerial Council, bringing together political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers to drive forward implementation of the vision and strategy set out in the June 2012 White Paper &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/overseas-territories/overseas-territories-white-paper/" title="Overseas Territotories White Paper"&gt;The Overseas Territories: Security, Success and Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council aims to agree priorities and plans for the UK and the Territories to work together on wide range of issues including: building successful and resilient economies; harnessing support from the Commonwealth and the EU; cherishing the environment and creating green growth; working together for better government; building stronger, healthier and safer communities; health; and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister will welcome elected leaders to Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister. Ministers and senior officials from wide range of UK Departments will take part in the Council, demonstrating the commitment from across government to working with the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the meeting Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to welcome elected leaders from the Overseas Territories to the Joint Ministerial Council. This is an opportunity for us to strengthen our work together to build flourishing communities, proudly retaining aspects of their British identity, creating new opportunities for young and future generations and protecting natural environments to the highest international standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year, we have demonstrated our commitment to preserving the astounding natural environment in the territories, by establishing a new Marine Protected Area in South Georgia &amp;amp; the South Sandwich Islands and launching Darwin Plus, the new Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59936</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T14:16:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council-communique"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council Communiqué</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This joint communiqué sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political leaders and representatives of the UK and the Overseas Territories, met in Lancaster House in London on 4-5 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They welcome the elections held in the Turks and Caicos Islands on 9 November, the restoration of democratically elected Government, and the participation of elected representatives in the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first meeting as the new Joint Ministerial Council which succeeds the Overseas Territories Consultative Councils. The Joint Ministerial Council will meet once a year at a mutually convenient time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16633</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:14:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-overseas-territories-security-success-and-sustainability"/>
    <title>The Overseas Territories: security, success and sustainability</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government published this white paper on the Overseas Territories on the 28 June 2012, setting out its overall approach. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35547</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/overseas-territories-flags-flown-for-the-first-time-in-parliament-square"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories flags flown for the first time in Parliament Square</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/foreignoffice/8138384167/"&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flags will fly throughout the visit of the President of the Republic of Indonesia, Dr Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono, who is in London until 2 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the occasion, Minister for the Overseas Territories, Mark Simmonds MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am really pleased to see the flags of the Overseas Territories being flown on a state occasion in London. This brings representation of the Overseas Territories in line with the Commonwealth nations, which have long had their flags flown on such occasions. Flying these flags is a sign to the people in the Territories, and those in the UK, of our renewed commitment to the Territories, which was outlined in our recent White Paper. I hope that this will help raise the profile of the Overseas Territories in the UK and around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flags of the Overseas Territories will now be flown on state occasions in London, including Trooping the Colour and other ceremonial occasions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35512</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-launches-new-environment-and-climate-fund-for-the-uk-s-overseas-territories"/>
    <title>Government launches new environment and climate fund for the UK’s Overseas Territories</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Fund, which brings together funds from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, and Department for International Development, will disburse around £2 million per year dedicated to environmental and conservation projects in the UK’s Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories are home to many species and environments found nowhere else in the world - including an estimated 90% of the biodiversity found within the UK and Overseas Territories combined.  The unique environmental wealth of the Overseas Territories was highlighted in the recent UK Government White Paper on the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In welcoming the new Fund, Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an excellent example of how we are meeting our White Paper commitment to provide co-ordinated Government support to the Overseas Territories and a signal of how important we consider the environments of the Overseas Territories to be. I have high hopes that this Fund will lead to many innovative and creative projects which will result in better sustainable environmental management in the Overseas Territories”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the announcement on the creation of the new Fund, Dr Tim Stowe, the RSPB’s International Director, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is excellent news for Britain’s albatrosses, iguanas, whales, and elephant seals, and is a welcome announcement alongside the Government’s recently announced action plan for Overseas Territories biodiversity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Fund provides a simpler and more co-ordinated funding mechanism and will support a range of environment and climate-related issues to ensure long-term sustainable natural resource management in the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fund was launched today to coincide with the 11th meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity in Hyderabad, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the Fund, including details of how to apply, can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://darwin.defra.gov.uk/"&gt;Defra website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
