<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Business and enterprise"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65670</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--107"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"&gt;updated parliament on the crisis in Syria&lt;/a&gt; and outlined further UK action for the coming weeks. He said: “Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;meeting organised by the UK this week,&lt;/a&gt; the Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt will &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"&gt;answer questions about the UK’s policy on Syria&lt;/a&gt; via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"&gt;Foreign Secretary met the Secretary General of the League of Arab States&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the Middle East Peace Process and Syria. Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Secretary said: “We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bahrain"&gt;Bahrain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt expressed dismay at the decision&lt;/a&gt;, saying: “I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pakistan"&gt;Pakistan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"&gt;condemned the brutal terrorist attacks in Quetta and Swat this week.&lt;/a&gt; He said: “The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="saudi-arabia"&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemned the beheading&lt;/a&gt; of a Sri Lankan national Rizana Nafeek and reiterated the UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"&gt;urged the Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of respected community leader Sombath Somphone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Baugh the British Ambassador to Somalia &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/mattbaugh/2013/01/09/somalia-a-new-years-resolution-together-into-2013/"&gt;blogged about how the changes of 2012 offer better prospects for improved stability in Somalia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We advised British nationals travelling in Australia to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"&gt;check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65618</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T12:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T12:21:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretary-william-hague-met-the-ethiopian-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary William Hague meets the Ethiopian Foreign Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary discusses human rights with the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary met the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros on 10 January. Dr Tedros also met the Minister of Africa, Mark Simmonds, and the Secretary of State for International Development, Justine Greening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary discussed a range of issues including the UK’s bilateral relationship with Ethiopia, regional security, commercial relations and counter-terrorism. The Foreign Secretary also underlined the importance the UK attaches to human rights and raised concerns over the sentences handed down under Ethiopia’s anti-terrorism laws.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office officials also attended a business roundtable chaired by Dr Tedros in the Ethiopian Embassy for existing and potential investors.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65653</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T12:05:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T12:05:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"/>
    <title>UK urge’s Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of community leader</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has expressed concern about the disappearance of community leader Sombath Somphone in Vientiane, Laos.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sombath Somphone founded the Participatory Development Training Center (PADETC) a non-profit private school in Vientiane and was awarded the Ramon Magsaysay award for his work promoting sustainable development in Laos. Sombath also worked with the UK to organise the Asia-Europe People’s Forum in October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on his recent disappearance Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely concerned by the disappearance of the respected NGO worker Sombath Somphone in Vientiane, who went missing on 15 December 2012. Sombath has played a crucial role, over many years, in  helping some of the poorest communities in Laos develop a stable means of income. He has proved a crucial partner in preparing and delivering with the UK a forum for young people in Laos last year. The UK Government strongly urges the Lao authorities to ensure a prompt, thorough and impartial investigation into Sombath’s disappearance, and to do all they can to ensure that Sombath is reunited with his family as matter of urgency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rmaf.org.ph/" title="http://www.rmaf.org.ph/"&gt;Ramon Magsaysay Award Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.padetc.org/" title="http://www.padetc.org/"&gt;Participatory Development Training Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.aepf.info/" title="http://www.aepf.info/"&gt;Asia-Europe People’s Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65301</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sweet-deal-for-growth-in-birmingham"/>
    <title>Sweet deal for growth in Birmingham</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A raft of initiatives to boost economic growth in Birmingham will be on the agenda today as Business Minister Michael Fallon visits the city to champion government support for the area’s economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will be putting the seal of approval to a new deal to cut red tape for Mondelez International, owner of the Cadbury’s brand which will reduce duplication and costs whilst maintaining high safety standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal, known as a primary authority partnership, means Birmingham City Council will provide advice to all of Mondelez International’s UK sites on regulations including food safety and hygiene and has already lead to Mondelez International cutting £250,000 in packaging costs alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Fallon will then visit Quality Plated Products (QPP), a manufacturing company in Great Barr who have been awarded a loan of £245,000 from the government’s Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative. The company uses a unique technology to supply metal plated plastic to the automotive industry. Thanks to the government support it will be increasing capacity, creating an additional 11 jobs and starting a new apprenticeship scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Birmingham has long been an engine of the country’s economy, and my tour around the city has shown that’s certainly the case today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is doing all it can to support the West Midlands; whether that’s direct support through our Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative to companies like QPP, rolling out ultra fast broadband, or helping household names like Cadbury by reducing the amount of red tape they have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By taking clear and decisive action and giving direct help to companies and regions they can realise their growth potential and compete in the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister’s tour will also see him visiting Aero Engine Controls, a leading aerospace and defence manufacturing company. This is part of a series visits today by Business Ministers to discuss how business and government can work more effectively together to tackle barriers to growth, boost exports and grow high value jobs in the UK. The Minister will also meet members of the Greater Birmingham and Solihull Local Enterprise Partnership to discuss their ‘Strategy for Growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships can be formed to cover key aspects of environmental health, trading standards and fire safety services, including health and safety, fair trading, food standards and product safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are now more than 600 businesses and 97 local authorities operating one or more of the 2,016 primary authority partnerships. The scheme covers more than 58,500 premises. 37% of businesses involved are SMEs. It was introduced in 2009 and is administered by the Better Regulation Delivery Office (BRDO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative is a national fund of up to £125m to create more competitive supply chains, sustain or create new employment opportunities, and create better synergies and sustained collaborative relationships throughout supply chains that participate in this initiative. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx"&gt;http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s industrial strategy is about looking to the future, presenting a long-term, whole of government approach to supporting British business, giving them the confidence they need to invest, hire staff and grow. Long-term strategies are being developed in partnership with industry in key sectors including aerospace, nuclear, and the information economy - the aerospace strategy will be published in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/61088</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge: Retail and Manufacturing Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The purpose of this consultation was to seek views on the amendment and removal of statutory instruments which were identified under the Retail and Manufacturing Red Tape Challenge spotlight process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s response to the consultation was published on the 16th July. This confirms the proposals we intend to take forward which include the revocation of the following measures on the 1st October 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imitation Dummies (Safety) Regulations 1993 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas cooking Appliances (Safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating Appliances (Fireguards) (Safety) Regulations 1991 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Catalytic Heaters (safety) Regulations 1984 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All-Terrain Motor Vehicle (safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking Utensils (Safety) Regulations 1972 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indication of Prices (Beds) Order 1978 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child Resistant Packaging and Tactile Danger Warning (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1992 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands for Carry-cots (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1996 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magnetic Toys (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second Government response was published on the 30th November. This confirms the amendment and revocation of the following regulations on the 6 April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61079</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/30-million-boost-as-start-up-loans-for-young-entrepreneurs-expanded"/>
    <title>£30 million boost as Start-Up Loans for young entrepreneurs expanded</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Thousands more young people have the opportunity to apply for government loans to turn their business ideas into reality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has today announced a boost to the government’s Start-Up loans scheme, with funding being increased by £30 million to £110 million over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also said that due to demand from those who had just missed out on the scheme, and the challenges faced to secure loans to start a business, the age limit for applying will now be extended from 24 to 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-Up Loans provide budding entrepreneurs a range of support to get their business idea off the ground, including access to a business mentor as well as funding in the region of £2,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 3000 people have applied or registered an interest in a Start-Up loan; when their business plan is robust and approved, applicants are able to access the financial support, with a repayment period of up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that the scheme has been live over £1.5 million worth of loans have been approved, helping over 460 new businesses get off the ground. Around 100 new businesses a week are expected to reach approval stage in January, with thousands more in the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Start-Up Loans scheme forms an integral part of the Business in You campaign, which encourages the start up and growth of new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startuploans.co.uk/"&gt;Visit the Start-Up Loans Company for more information and details on how to apply.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business"&gt;Tools and guidance for businesses on Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/start-up-loans-scheme-expanded/"&gt;Read the full story on the Number 10 website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
