<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Business and enterprise"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/59984</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:12:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:12:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>What the government is doing to reduce anti-competitive activities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets are the best way of making sure a country’s resources are put to their best use. They encourage enterprise and widen choice for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can develop in any economy. They can harm consumers and stifle innovation and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an anti-competitive activity would be when two companies agree to charge the same price for a similar product. This protects the companies’ profits but means consumers get less choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can be very bad for consumers. That’s why they have to be identified and stopped as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the government’s three growth objectives is that the UK should become the best place to start, finance and grow a business. Reforming and improving the laws on anti-competitive activities is a major part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-competition-law"&gt;Changing competition law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is reforming the laws that cover competition and anti-competitive activities in business, including those relating to mergers, markets and illegal activities such as price-fixing and cartels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also reforming the institutions that police competition and anti-competitive activities, and strengthening their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These laws, institutions and powers are collectively known as the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/processes-for-tackling-anti-competitive-activity--2"&gt;guide to the competition regime&lt;/a&gt; if you’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="competition-landscape"&gt;Competition landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re making changes to the organisations that deal with competition and anti-competitive activities in business. We’re doing this between now and the end of 2014. This work is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and competition landscape reforms."&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reforms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="setting-up-a-new-watchdog-for-the-grocery-industry"&gt;Setting up a new watchdog for the grocery industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re creating a new watchdog for the grocery industry. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/groceries-code-adjudicator" title="Groceries Code."&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt; will give suppliers, including farmers supplying the bigger supermarket chains, more protection against anti-competitive activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-legal-challenges-easier"&gt;Making legal challenges easier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to make it easier for consumers and small businesses to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/private-actions-pro-tem" title="Private Action."&gt;challenge anti-competitive behaviour&lt;/a&gt; by bringing a legal challenge (also known as a private action) against anti-competitive activities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-aid"&gt;State aid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re modernising the rules on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State aid is when a public body (such as a local authority) or publicly funded body (such as the Big Lottery) provides a business, charity or other organisation with financial help that could give them an advantage over another business. This kind of financial help is generally outlawed by the European treaty, as it’s an anti-competitive practice. State aid regulations set legal ways to give this kind of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"&gt;detailed guide on state aid&lt;/a&gt; for public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different rules - also covered in the detailed guide - apply to agriculture, aquaculture, fisheries, transport and maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK competition law has to comply with EU law. Article 101 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/antitrust/overview_en.html"&gt;Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU)&lt;/a&gt; bans any agreements between businesses ‘which have as their object… the prevention [or] restriction… of competition within the common market.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/59915</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T10:57:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"/>
    <title>Reducing the impact of regulation on business</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Cutting red tape, improving existing regulations and avoiding unnecessary new regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regulations are ineffective and unnecessary. Complying with them costs businesses time and money, and can restrict growth. Red tape can also make running charities and community groups more difficult than it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure all regulations are fair and effective. We want to strike the right balance between protecting people’s rights, health and safety and freeing them from unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure regulations in the UK are fair and effective, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;controlling the number of new regulations by &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;operating a ‘one in, two out’ rule for business regulation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/assessing-the-impact-of-new-regulation"&gt;assessing the impact of each regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reviewing-the-effectiveness-of-government-regulations"&gt;reviewing the effectiveness of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-regulation-for-small-businesses"&gt;reducing regulation for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/improving-enforcement-of-government-regulations"&gt;improving enforcement of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/using-alternatives-to-regulation-education-campaigns-economic-instruments"&gt;using alternatives to regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-the-cost-of-eu-regulation-on-uk-business"&gt;reducing the cost of EU regulation on UK business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We publish &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publication_filter_option=guidance&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=department-for-business-innovation-skills"&gt;guidance for all government policymakers&lt;/a&gt; to help design better regulations or find other options instead of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, regulations - and the inspections and bureaucracy that go with them - have piled up. Businesses say the amount of new regulation is one of their biggest problems, preventing them from growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2010, we said that we would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut red tape for businesses and individuals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not rely on rules and regulations by themselves to get things done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re running a series of reviews called ‘Focus on enforcement’ to get businesses’ views on how we could improve the way we enforce regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/"&gt;Have your say on how we enforce regulations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also running the Red Tape Challenge, asking businesses and the public which regulations they think could be removed or improved. See what businesses are saying: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Tell us which regulations you think should be removed or improved.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57424</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The government has today published new data detailing lending by specific banks through the Enterprise Finance Guarantee scheme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past 5 years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57077</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:38:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"/>
    <title>Update on Enterprise Finance Guarantee lending  </title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Minister for Business and Enterprise Rt Hon Michael Fallon on new data detailing lending by specific banks.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures by individual bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to ensuring that viable small and medium-size enterprises can obtain the finance they need for working capital and investment. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; plays an important part in this, with over 9,900 &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; being offered loans with a value in excess of £1 billion since May 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has made a number of important changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme during the last twelve months. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans are now available to an additional 3,800 businesses with an increase in the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million. The maximum £1 million lifetime scheme limit has been replaced by a rolling £1 million limit. We also raised by 7%, the level of lenders &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; annual loan portfolios to which the Government guarantee applies from 13% to 20%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was made to address the legitimate concern of lenders that they would breach their annual claim limit. In doing this, the Government committed to a more even share of the risk of default with the lenders, with the aim of removing that as a barrier to lending &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; is a demand led scheme, accounting for one to two per cent of overall &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; lending. While utilisation is directly linked to subdued demand for credit in the wider economy, overall &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending levels are disappointing. There have been some positive signs, with a number of the main banks increasing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending this financial year, albeit from a low level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that banks lend responsibly and make use of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; when it is appropriate to do so, but it is clear from the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures that a number of lenders could and should be doing more. The publication of individual bank &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures is intended to help achieve this. In parallel, we are exploring with the banks ways of flexing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; to address debt serviceability, which is the principal reason behind loan declines. Further detail will be provided in the New Year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, already publishes a wide range of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures, which are updated on a quarterly basis. Publication of individual &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures will further enhance this, allowing business customers to identify which banks are making most use of the scheme, and also enable participating lenders and new market entrants to identity new opportunities, thus increasing choice and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a further step towards greater transparency in bank lending, specifically to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"&gt;The full list of available &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60156</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T13:08:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"/>
    <title>Number and value of Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) scheme loans drawn.</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number and value of EFG loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/59955</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:04:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:04:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"/>
    <title>Making companies more accountable to shareholders and the public</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Making companies more accountable will make them more attractive to investors and make the public want to buy their products and services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shareholders and the public have lost confidence in the way companies are run and they believe that companies should be rewarded for success not failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making companies more accountable in how they work - and showing that they are improving - will increase investor and public confidence, making them more attractive to investors and giving the public more trust in their products and services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make companies more accountable to their shareholders and the public, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/improving-company-reporting"&gt;improving company reporting&lt;/a&gt; through a new law which changes how they write their reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/increasing-representation-on-boards-of-listed-companies"&gt;making company boards more representative of women&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing in legislation that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/giving-shareholders-more-power-to-link-pay-to-performance"&gt;gives shareholders more power to link pay to performance&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a national contact point at the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt;) where people or organisations can report UK multinationals they think may be breaking the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt; guidelines for trading abroad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Financial Reporting Council’s (&lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;) &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Corporate-Governance-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Corporate Governance Code&lt;/a&gt;, launched in 2010, sets out good principles for running a company board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Stewardship-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Stewardship Code&lt;/a&gt; makes investors more answerable to their clients and beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt; have a detailed explanation about why they are improving these codes and how they fit into government regulation in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/getattachment/1db9539d-9176-4546-91ee-828b7fd087a8/The-UK-Approach-to-Corporate-Governance.aspx"&gt;UK approach to corporate governance.&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2012 Kay Review of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/12-917-kay-review-of-equity-markets-final-report.pdf"&gt;Equity markets and long-term decision making&lt;/a&gt; Professor Kay examines how to improve the performance of UK companies, and provide returns to savers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121205150610/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/corporate-governance/kay-review"&gt;See the full background on the review, including responses to the call for evidence and the consultation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 22 November 2012 the government published its response &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=bis%20ensuring%20equity%20markets%20support%20long%20time%20growth&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;ved=0CC4QFjAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bis.gov.uk%2Fassets%2Fbiscore%2Fbusiness-law%2Fdocs%2Fe%2F12-1188-equity-markets-support-growth-response-to-kay-review.pdf&amp;amp;ei=Q6a_UIfZFZTM0AW414GIAQ&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFKxfouDderH7bnrYUmF_gWKCDeZQ"&gt;Ensuring equity markets support long-term growth&lt;/a&gt; welcoming the Kay Report and accepting Professor Kay’s analysis and conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56972</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:03:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-figures-show-government-is-winning-war-on-red-tape"/>
    <title>New figures show government is winning war on red tape</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Minister pledges tougher action to eliminate burdens on enterprise.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business will benefit from nearly £1 billion in reduced red tape costs thanks to government action, independent figures revealed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Statement of New Regulation reports that the overall closing balance for ‘One-in, One-out’, the government rule that dictates that every new cost on business must be balanced by an equivalent saving, is predicted to be around £836 million since January 2011. These figures are independently verified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the statement shows that the government expects to reduce the regulatory burden by around a further £83 million between January 2013 - when ‘One-in, One-Out’ is replaced by ‘One-in, Two-out’ - and June 2013.  Expected measures include reforms to environmental regulation, employment law and consumer law.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said that Whitehall is increasingly putting the needs of businesses centre stage, but vowed to go further and faster to roll back barriers to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every department is predicting either a zero balance or being in credit at the start of One-in, Two-out, showing that the de-regulatory agenda is having an impact right across Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the overwhelming majority of government measures affecting business are deregulatory, with only ten new items imposing new costs on business compared with 89 that will save money or will impose a zero net cost. The costs from the ‘ins’ (£6 million) are also dwarfed by the savings from the ‘outs’ (£89 million), giving a predicted net saving to business of £83 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent deregulatory measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;changes to modernise and simplify the registration of company charges, saving £21.9 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a series of changes to building regulations to reduce cost and complexity for industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less heavy-handed Health and Safety regulations for low-risk businesses including shop and offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improvements to speed up processes covering adoption and foster-carer eligibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government has a very simple objective: to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business.  This requires a fundamental culture change in Whitehall, so that new regulation is only imposed as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve made a promising start, but firms still struggle with excessive red tape.  We’ll now push departments to go further to bear down on costs imposed on business, and we’ll fight harder to get EU bureaucracy off the back of our entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time this Statement sets out EU measures that will be introduced during the reporting period, giving businesses time to prepare for these changes.   Fifty-seven EU measures are expected to be implemented into UK legislation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every six months the government publishes a Statement of New Regulation listing of all the regulations it plans to introduce and remove in the next six months, and showing the net direct costs to business. The Fifth Statement of New Regulation is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘One-in, One-out’ rule was introduced on 1 September 2010 and applies to regulations introduced from January 2011.  The rule prevents any government department introducing new regulation that will impose a direct net cost on business and voluntary organisations - unless the department can find savings by removing or modifying another regulation of an equivalent cost. ‘One-in, Two-out’ will also operate in this way, but the removal or modification must be of twice the equivalent cost. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like ‘One-in, One-out’ , ‘One-in, Two-Out’ will not apply to EU legislation unless it has been converted into UK law in a way that goes beyond minimum EU requirements, putting UK businesses at a disadvantage.  A number of other areas are exempt from the rule, including tax administration and civil emergencies regulation. More detail is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When developing a new regulatory or deregulatory proposal, each Government department must carry out an impact assessment. This includes estimating the likely cost to business. To ensure estimates are credible, the impact assessment is considered by an independent body, the Regulatory Policy Committee (RPC). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited, with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The government announced on 10 September 2012 that at least 3,000 of the regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. A second phase of the Red Tape Challenge will start in spring 2013.  More information on the Red Tape Challenge is avaiable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alongside the drive to remove superfluous regulation, government is working to ensure that necessary regulations on business are enforced more efficiently. Focus on Enforcement reviews are being carried out across a number of sectors where aspects of the enforcement regime may be imposing unnecessary burdens on business, making inefficient use of public sector resources or hampering economic growth.  At Autumn Statement, the government also announced a number of measures to tackle systemic issues, including the lack of consistent fees and charges and appeals mechanisms. The Focus on Enforcement website is available &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/iscuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
