<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Business and enterprise"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T12:04:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56815</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:04:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:04:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"/>
    <title>Making companies more accountable to shareholders and the public</title>
    <summary>Making companies more accountable will make them more attractive to investors and make the public want to buy their products and services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shareholders and the public have lost confidence in the way companies are run and they believe that companies should be rewarded for success not failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making companies more accountable in how they work - and showing that they are improving - will increase investor and public confidence, making them more attractive to investors and giving the public more trust in their products and services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make companies more accountable to their shareholders and the public, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/improving-company-reporting"&gt;improving company reporting&lt;/a&gt; through a new law which changes how they write their reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/increasing-representation-on-boards-of-listed-companies"&gt;making company boards more representative of women&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing in legislation that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/giving-shareholders-more-power-to-link-pay-to-performance"&gt;gives shareholders more power to link pay to performance&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a national contact point at the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt;) where people or organisations can report UK multinationals they think may be breaking the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt; guidelines for trading abroad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Financial Reporting Council’s (&lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Corporate-Governance-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Corporate Governance Code&lt;/a&gt;, launched in 2010, sets out good principles for running a company board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Stewardship-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Stewardship Code&lt;/a&gt; makes investors more answerable to their clients and beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt; have a detailed explanation about why they are improving these codes and how they fit into government regulation in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/getattachment/1db9539d-9176-4546-91ee-828b7fd087a8/The-UK-Approach-to-Corporate-Governance.aspx"&gt;UK approach to corporate governance.&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2012 Kay Review of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/12-917-kay-review-of-equity-markets-final-report.pdf"&gt;Equity markets and long-term decision making&lt;/a&gt; Professor Kay examines how to improve the performance of UK companies, and provide returns to savers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121205150610/http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/corporate-governance/kay-review"&gt;See the full background on the review, including responses to the call for evidence and the consultation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 22 November 2012 the government published its response &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=bis%20ensuring%20equity%20markets%20support%20long%20time%20growth&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;ved=0CC4QFjAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bis.gov.uk%2Fassets%2Fbiscore%2Fbusiness-law%2Fdocs%2Fe%2F12-1188-equity-markets-support-growth-response-to-kay-review.pdf&amp;amp;ei=Q6a_UIfZFZTM0AW414GIAQ&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFKxfouDderH7bnrYUmF_gWKCDeZQ"&gt;Ensuring equity markets support long-term growth&lt;/a&gt; welcoming the Kay Report and accepting Professor Kay’s analysis and conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56802</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:03:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:03:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-figures-show-government-is-winning-war-on-red-tape"/>
    <title>New figures show government is winning war on red tape</title>
    <summary>Business Minister pledges tougher action to eliminate burdens on enterprise</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business will benefit from nearly £1 billion in reduced red tape costs thanks to Government action, independent figures revealed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Statement of New Regulation reports that the overall closing balance for ‘One-in, One-out’, the Government rule that dictates that every new cost on business must be balanced by an equivalent saving, is predicted to be around £836 million since January 2011. These figures are independently verified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the statement shows that the Government expects to reduce the regulatory burden by around a further £83 million between January 2013 - when ‘One-in, One-Out’ is replaced by ‘One-in, Two-out’ - and June 2013.  Expected measures include reforms to environmental regulation, employment law and consumer law.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said that Whitehall is increasingly putting the needs of businesses centre stage, but vowed to go further and faster to roll back barriers to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every department is predicting either a zero balance or being in credit at the start of One-in, Two-out, showing that the de-regulatory agenda is having an impact right across Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the overwhelming majority of Government measures affecting business are deregulatory, with only ten new items imposing new costs on business compared with 89 that will save money or will impose a zero net cost. The costs from the ‘ins’ (£6 million) are also dwarfed by the savings from the ‘outs’ (£89 million), giving a predicted net saving to business of £83 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent deregulatory measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changes to modernise and simplify the registration of company charges, saving £21.9 million.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A series of changes to building regulations to reduce cost and complexity for industry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less heavy-handed Health and Safety regulations for low-risk businesses including shop and offices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvements to speed up processes covering adoption and foster-carer eligibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government has a very simple objective: to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business.  This requires a fundamental culture change in Whitehall, so that new regulation is only imposed as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve made a promising start, but firms still struggle with excessive red tape.  We’ll now push departments to go further to bear down on costs imposed on business, and we’ll fight harder to get EU bureaucracy off the back of our entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time this Statement sets out EU measures that will be introduced during the reporting period, giving businesses time to prepare for these changes.   Fifty-seven EU measures are expected to be implemented into UK legislation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every six months the government publishes a Statement of New Regulation listing of all the regulations it plans to introduce and remove in the next six months, and showing the net direct costs to business. The Fifth Statement of New Regulation is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘One-in, One-out’ rule was introduced on 1 September 2010 and applies to regulations introduced from January 2011.  The rule prevents any government department introducing new regulation that will impose a direct net cost on business and voluntary organisations - unless the department can find savings by removing or modifying another regulation of an equivalent cost. ‘One-in, Two-out’ will also operate in this way, but the removal or modification must be of twice the equivalent cost. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like ‘One-in, One-out’ , ‘One-in, Two-Out’ will not apply to EU legislation unless it has been converted into UK law in a way that goes beyond minimum EU requirements, putting UK businesses at a disadvantage.  A number of other areas are exempt from the rule, including tax administration and civil emergencies regulation. More detail is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When developing a new regulatory or deregulatory proposal, each Government department must carry out an impact assessment. This includes estimating the likely cost to business. To ensure estimates are credible, the impact assessment is considered by an independent body, the Regulatory Policy Committee (RPC). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited, with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The Government announced on 10 September 2012 that at least 3,000 of the regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. A second phase of the Red Tape Challenge will start in spring 2013.  More information on the Red Tape Challenge is avaiable &lt;a href="www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alongside the drive to remove superfluous regulation, Government is working to ensure that necessary regulations on business are enforced more efficiently. Focus on Enforcement reviews are being carried out across a number of sectors where aspects of the enforcement regime may be imposing unnecessary burdens on business, making inefficient use of public sector resources or hampering economic growth.  At Autumn Statement, the Government also announced a number of measures to tackle systemic issues, including the lack of consistent fees and charges and appeals mechanisms. The Focus on Enforcement website is available &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/iscuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56724</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:28:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:28:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"/>
    <title>Reducing the impact of regulation on business</title>
    <summary>Cutting red tape, improving existing regulations and avoiding unnecessary new regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regulations are ineffective and unnecessary. Complying with them costs businesses time and money, and can restrict growth. Red tape can also make running charities and community groups more difficult than it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure all regulations are fair and effective. We want to strike the right balance between protecting people’s rights, health and safety and freeing them from unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure regulations in the UK are fair and effective, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;controlling the number of new regulations by &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;operating a ‘one in, two out’ rule for business regulation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/assessing-the-impact-of-new-regulation"&gt;assessing the impact of each regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reviewing-the-effectiveness-of-government-regulations"&gt;reviewing the effectiveness of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-regulation-for-small-businesses"&gt;reducing regulation for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/improving-enforcement-of-government-regulations"&gt;improving enforcement of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/using-alternatives-to-regulation-education-campaigns-economic-instruments"&gt;using alternatives to regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-the-cost-of-eu-regulation-on-uk-business"&gt;reducing the cost of EU regulation on UK business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We publish &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publication_filter_option=guidance&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=department-for-business-innovation-skills"&gt;guidance for all government policymakers&lt;/a&gt; to help design better regulations or find other options instead of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, regulations - and the inspections and bureaucracy that go with them - have piled up. Businesses say the amount of new regulation is one of their biggest problems, preventing them from growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2010, we said that we would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut red tape for businesses and individuals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not rely on rules and regulations by themselves to get things done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re running a series of reviews called ‘Focus on enforcement’ to get businesses’ views on how we could improve the way we enforce regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/"&gt;Have your say on how we enforce regulations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also running the Red Tape Challenge, asking businesses and the public which regulations they think could be removed or improved. See what businesses are saying: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Tell us which regulations you think should be removed or improved.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56364</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:02:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dclg-statement-of-new-regulation-1-january-to-30-june-2013"/>
    <title>DCLG statement of new regulation - 1 January to 30 June 2013</title>
    <summary>Overview of regulations that are scheduled to be implemented or removed between 1 January and 30 June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The headline figures show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we are introducing 24 measures in this period, 20 of which are deregulatory measures that will reduce the burden on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;none of these measures will increase the regulatory burden on businesses, as they are all either deregulatory measures that will bring savings to business, or regulatory measures that have no cost to business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Regulatory Policy Committee have evaluated 5 of our measures and estimated that they will reduce the burden on business by £45.36 million per year. We expect this figure to rise considerably as our other measures are validated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56873</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:23:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/private-security-companies"/>
    <title>Private Security Companies</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the development of a regulatory system for private security companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aims to raise the global standards of private security companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) working in complex and high risk environments overseas. To this end, we have been working closely with interested partners, including industry and civil society, to establish a voluntary, independently audited and internationally recognised regulatory system that is practicable, effective and affordable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification to professional standards is the next step towards effective voluntary regulation. First the Government endorsed the Montreux Document in 2008, in which States commit to observe existing international legal obligations relevant to the operations of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in areas of armed conflict. Secondly, in 2010, an International Code of Conduct for Private Security Providers (&lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt;) was created. This provides a set of principles to guide companies. The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been signed by over 500 &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;, around a third of them British. We have reviewed options on setting new professional standards to make the Code effective. We now intend to issue an HMG publication specifying that ASIS PSC 1-2012 is the applicable standard for UK-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments on land overseas. I will place a copy of the publication in the libraries of both Houses. Companies, independent auditors and the UK Accreditation Service (&lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) will then take the further steps to enable auditing against these standards to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; mandated the development of auditable standards to ensure that signatory companies are implementing their commitments under the code. In response to this requirement, the international security trade association, ASIS, was funded by the Department of Defense to develop the standard – ‘PSC1’ – for the regulation of private security companies operating on land in complex environments overseas. This standard was drafted in a multinational and multi-stakeholder forum in which UK Government, UK industry and UK civil society fully participated.  It was published in March 2012 as an approved American National Standard and is the only standard currently available for companies operating in this field. &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; seeking certification in the UK to this new standard will have to be audited by independent third party auditors accredited by &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our trade association partners, the Security in Complex Environments Group, will, in consultation with Government, develop guidance to help British &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; meet the requirements of the new standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ambition is to have a single, internationally agreed standard and we therefore welcome the fact that PSC1 was recently submitted to the International Standards Organisation (ISO) to be considered for adoption as an international standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments. This process may take some time. We will review the need for a separate HMG publication of this standard once the ISO process has been completed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working with other States, industry and civil society internationally to ensure that there should be globally recognised standards and that UK companies are not unfairly disadvantaged by raising their standards. We expect that the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; governing board, when established, will advise that certification to the PSC 1 standard by suitably accredited independent auditors will meet the Code’s requirements for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to have auditable professional standards. We are still consulting with industry and civil society partners on what additional steps &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; might need to take to obtain full certification by the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; that they are meeting the Code’s principles but I can confirm that there will be no need for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to go through duplicate auditing procedures to become certified.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; was drafted with land-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in mind. However, since 2010 there has been a rapid rise in the number of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on anti-piracy operations at sea. Although many of the principles relating to &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on land and at sea are similar, there are important legal and practical differences. The Government is therefore also contributing to an international drafting process under the ISO for an equivalent professional standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in the maritime sector. A draft maritime standard was introduced at the International Maritime Organisation in late November. If and when this standard is adopted, &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will start the process of accrediting suitably qualified independent third party auditors to certify UK-based maritime &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity on the standards against which &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; should be audited is an important step forward in the drive to raise standards in this industry through voluntary action, but independently audited. It is also a practical illustration of the Government’s commitment to human rights and to working with business and civil society to find effective ways to implement our commitments even in the most challenging environments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56731</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:15:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-regulations-covering-january-to-june-2013"/>
    <title>BIS fifth statement of new regulation: regulations covering January to June 2013</title>
    <summary>Informs businesses and interested stakeholders of Department for Business domestic regulations that come into force between January and June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lists Department of Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) measures in scope of ‘One In, Two Out’ regulations to come into force from January to June 2013, to show how BIS is removing burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56721</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-sonr"/>
    <title>Fifth statement of new regulation (SONR)</title>
    <summary>An overview of regulations planned to be implemented or removed by government departments between 1 January and 30 June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides a forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect. The headline figures show that the sum total of Government deregulation by July 2013 is expected to reduce the annual cost to business by around £919 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <summary>New Innovation Vouchers for businesses who want to use public open data to develop new ideas, improve processes and target new markets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55880</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:10:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:10:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up and grow a business </title>
    <summary>Government support for small to medium sized businesses and start-ups - from finance to help and advice</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people feel that starting a business is not for them, either because they’re worried about finding funding and making money or because they don’t think they have the skills or experience needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, research shows that existing small and medium enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) can be put off growing their business because of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of access to finance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not being able to recruit people and lacking the right skills in new and existing staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;day-to-day cash flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-the-uk-an-easier-place-to-do-business"&gt;Making the UK an easier place to do business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/enabling-businesses-to-get-finance"&gt;providing funding and programmes to make loans available to more small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a scheme with the Bank of England to enable banks and building societies to borrow from them at cheaper rates so that they can then lend to small to medium businesses (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) at lower interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new business bank that will provide more funding to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support"&gt;providing funding and programmes to encourage private sector investment in small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with private sector investors to provide government and private sector money to invest in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investing in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; with government and private sector money through the Start-Up Loan Scheme, the Business Finance Partnership and Business Angel Co-Investment Fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/encouraging-a-more-entrepreneurial-society"&gt;funding and managing initiatives to encourage young people and give them the skills to set up their own business&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recruiting young business owners to volunteer as enterprise champions who will go into schools and talk to young people about running their own business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with schools and colleges to promote schemes such as ‘Tenner’ which gives £10 to each student to start a business and ‘Enterprise Village’ which helps schools to set up businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support--2"&gt;providing support and advice to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve launched websites that provide information to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; on how to run and grow their business – Business in You, GrowthAccelerator, Mentorsme and Manufacturing Advisory Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of private sector businesses in the UK increased to 4.8 million at the start of 2012 – a record high. Barclays estimate there were just under 500,000 business start-ups in England and Wales in 2011; also a record number and 12,700 (2.6%) more than in 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period about 500,000 businesses closed. Businesses have told us that they need access to finance and less red tape in order to keep running. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve developed our policies to support start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; so that they can continue to grow and make a contribution to the economy and so that they get access to finance and support that hasn’t been previously available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work closely with businesses, financial institutions and other government departments to help make sure the environment is right for UK businesses to start up, grow and succeed. Our work covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;Better regulations to make doing business easier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax – working with HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs who are introducing a range of measures to help start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; including a National Insurance holiday for the first year of employing people, reduced Corporation Tax and a Seed Enterprise Investment Scheme &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment"&gt;Exporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth"&gt;Innovation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56434</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-tackles-red-tape-head-on-with-package-of-measures"/>
    <title>Government tackles red tape head on with package of measures</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of the way that appeals are handled by regulators launched today is the first stage of a new wave of bureaucracy busting measures announced by the government, Business Minister Michael Fallon confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and other interested parties will have a chance to take part in a review of the effectiveness of appeals mechanisms operated by national and local regulators. The Focus on Enforcement Appeals Review will give those affected the opportunity to talk about their experiences of formal and informal appeals processes, and suggest how they could be made to work more effectively, providing a swifter route to resolution and better industry understanding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will also gather examples of approaches that have successfully helped businesses understand regulators’ decisions and meet their obligations more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have started a bonfire of excessive red tape, but I know that it is just as important that we look at the way that regulations are enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is room for far more effective enforcement which reduces the burden on business which stick to the rules.  Despite best efforts, sometimes things can go wrong – that has become clear from previous Focus on Enforcement Reviews. So I want to hear views on how we can improve the way appeals currently work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greater clarity and trust between regulators and businesses will lead to better enforcement of the law and higher standards across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest review follows a package of new measures announced at the Autumn Statement to tackle systemic problems with the way regulations are enforced and cut the unnecessary red tape and burdens that companies have to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a consultation on placing a legislative duty on non-economic regulators to have regard to growth and take into account the economic impacts of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new accounting system for regulators, so that in future regulators will have to publish impact assessments for prior consultation, scrutiny and challenge by industry, of the impacts of all changes in their activities that have a significant (positive and negative) financial impact on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consultation on an amended Regulators’ Compliance Code to ensure regulators are internally and geographically consistent, give consideration to earned recognition, and offer minimum service standards to those they regulate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government action to ensure regulators are transparent about the fees they charge and bear down on their costs and improve their efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also today, as part of the package the government announced plans to cut bureaucracy by widening the range of regulations included in the Primary Authority scheme. The plans would see the scheme covering age-related sales of gambling, the Housing Health and Safety Rating system for assessing potential hazards in dwellings, sun-bed tanning and Welsh regulations for single-use carrier bag charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships are reducing regulatory burdens for companies and allowing them to grow. It’s now time to extend the scope of the scheme to streamline the way regulators work with businesses, improve protections to the public and help local authorities to target their resources against rogue traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major business groups such as the CBI, British Retail Consortium and FSB are strongly in favour of Primary Authority and of its extension. The Trading Standards Institute and Chartered Institute of Environmental Health are also in favour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence arising from sector-specific Focus on Enforcement reviews has already indicated that businesses have concerns about how current appeals systems operate. These include confusing or multiple appeals mechanisms lack of transparency and in some cases resolution taking excessively long periods of time.   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The forthcoming review will invite evidence from all sectors of the economy and any regulatory regime. Appeals mechanisms for economic regulators are not included in the scope of this review. Interested parties can participate in the review of appeals at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year at Budget, the government announced a new approach to cutting red tape, looking at how rules are enforced, rather than the rules themselves. A series of Focus on Enforcement Reviews have shown that in addition to sector-specific issues, there are also systemic enforcement issues limiting industry that affect most if not all sectors. So, rather than tackling systemic issues case by case, the Government’s Autumn Statement package  aims to change the system, creating greater clarity and fairness for businesses while ensuring regulators focus their resources where they are needed most. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Primary Authority Scheme is run by the Better Regulation Delivery Office, an independent unit within the Business Innovation and Skills Department (BIS). See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are currently 602 businesses and 93 local authorities involved in Primary Authority partnerships, covering over 58,000 premises and over 1.57 million employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the scope of the scheme, or the list of regulations which can be covered by partnerships, can be achieved by secondary legislation. The consultation announced today runs until 24 January 2013 to allow feedback from stakeholders before secondary legislation is introduced into Parliament.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Housing Health and Safety Rating System (HHSRS) is a risk-based evaluation tool to help local authorities identify and protect against potential risks and hazards to health and safety from any deficiencies identified in dwellings. It was introduced under the Housing Act 2004 and applies to residential properties in England and Wales.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
