<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Business and enterprise"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <summary>New Innovation Vouchers for businesses who want to use public open data to develop new ideas, improve processes and target new markets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55880</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:10:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:10:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up and grow a business </title>
    <summary>Government support for small to medium sized businesses and start-ups - from finance to help and advice</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people feel that starting a business is not for them, either because they’re worried about finding funding and making money or because they don’t think they have the skills or experience needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, research shows that existing small and medium enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) can be put off growing their business because of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of access to finance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not being able to recruit people and lacking the right skills in new and existing staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;day-to-day cash flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-the-uk-an-easier-place-to-do-business"&gt;Making the UK an easier place to do business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/enabling-businesses-to-get-finance"&gt;providing funding and programmes to make loans available to more small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a scheme with the Bank of England to enable banks and building societies to borrow from them at cheaper rates so that they can then lend to small to medium businesses (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) at lower interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new business bank that will provide more funding to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support"&gt;providing funding and programmes to encourage private sector investment in small businesses&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with private sector investors to provide government and private sector money to invest in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investing in &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; with government and private sector money through the Start-Up Loan Scheme, the Business Finance Partnership and Business Angel Co-Investment Fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/encouraging-a-more-entrepreneurial-society"&gt;funding and managing initiatives to encourage young people and give them the skills to set up their own business&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recruiting young business owners to volunteer as enterprise champions who will go into schools and talk to young people about running their own business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with schools and colleges to promote schemes such as ‘Tenner’ which gives £10 to each student to start a business and ‘Enterprise Village’ which helps schools to set up businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/supporting-pages/helping-businesses-and-start-ups-get-advice-and-support--2"&gt;providing support and advice to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve launched websites that provide information to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; on how to run and grow their business – Business in You, GrowthAccelerator, Mentorsme and Manufacturing Advisory Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of private sector businesses in the UK increased to 4.8 million at the start of 2012 – a record high. Barclays estimate there were just under 500,000 business start-ups in England and Wales in 2011; also a record number and 12,700 (2.6%) more than in 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period about 500,000 businesses closed. Businesses have told us that they need access to finance and less red tape in order to keep running. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve developed our policies to support start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; so that they can continue to grow and make a contribution to the economy and so that they get access to finance and support that hasn’t been previously available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work closely with businesses, financial institutions and other government departments to help make sure the environment is right for UK businesses to start up, grow and succeed. Our work covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;Better regulations to make doing business easier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax – working with HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs who are introducing a range of measures to help start-ups and &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; including a National Insurance holiday for the first year of employing people, reduced Corporation Tax and a Seed Enterprise Investment Scheme &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment"&gt;Exporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth"&gt;Innovation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56434</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-tackles-red-tape-head-on-with-package-of-measures"/>
    <title>Government tackles red tape head on with package of measures</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of the way that appeals are handled by regulators launched today is the first stage of a new wave of bureaucracy busting measures announced by the government, Business Minister Michael Fallon confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and other interested parties will have a chance to take part in a review of the effectiveness of appeals mechanisms operated by national and local regulators. The Focus on Enforcement Appeals Review will give those affected the opportunity to talk about their experiences of formal and informal appeals processes, and suggest how they could be made to work more effectively, providing a swifter route to resolution and better industry understanding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will also gather examples of approaches that have successfully helped businesses understand regulators’ decisions and meet their obligations more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have started a bonfire of excessive red tape, but I know that it is just as important that we look at the way that regulations are enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is room for far more effective enforcement which reduces the burden on business which stick to the rules.  Despite best efforts, sometimes things can go wrong – that has become clear from previous Focus on Enforcement Reviews. So I want to hear views on how we can improve the way appeals currently work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greater clarity and trust between regulators and businesses will lead to better enforcement of the law and higher standards across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest review follows a package of new measures announced at the Autumn Statement to tackle systemic problems with the way regulations are enforced and cut the unnecessary red tape and burdens that companies have to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a consultation on placing a legislative duty on non-economic regulators to have regard to growth and take into account the economic impacts of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new accounting system for regulators, so that in future regulators will have to publish impact assessments for prior consultation, scrutiny and challenge by industry, of the impacts of all changes in their activities that have a significant (positive and negative) financial impact on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consultation on an amended Regulators’ Compliance Code to ensure regulators are internally and geographically consistent, give consideration to earned recognition, and offer minimum service standards to those they regulate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government action to ensure regulators are transparent about the fees they charge and bear down on their costs and improve their efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also today, as part of the package the government announced plans to cut bureaucracy by widening the range of regulations included in the Primary Authority scheme. The plans would see the scheme covering age-related sales of gambling, the Housing Health and Safety Rating system for assessing potential hazards in dwellings, sun-bed tanning and Welsh regulations for single-use carrier bag charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships are reducing regulatory burdens for companies and allowing them to grow. It’s now time to extend the scope of the scheme to streamline the way regulators work with businesses, improve protections to the public and help local authorities to target their resources against rogue traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major business groups such as the CBI, British Retail Consortium and FSB are strongly in favour of Primary Authority and of its extension. The Trading Standards Institute and Chartered Institute of Environmental Health are also in favour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence arising from sector-specific Focus on Enforcement reviews has already indicated that businesses have concerns about how current appeals systems operate. These include confusing or multiple appeals mechanisms lack of transparency and in some cases resolution taking excessively long periods of time.   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The forthcoming review will invite evidence from all sectors of the economy and any regulatory regime. Appeals mechanisms for economic regulators are not included in the scope of this review. Interested parties can participate in the review of appeals at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year at Budget, the government announced a new approach to cutting red tape, looking at how rules are enforced, rather than the rules themselves. A series of Focus on Enforcement Reviews have shown that in addition to sector-specific issues, there are also systemic enforcement issues limiting industry that affect most if not all sectors. So, rather than tackling systemic issues case by case, the Government’s Autumn Statement package  aims to change the system, creating greater clarity and fairness for businesses while ensuring regulators focus their resources where they are needed most. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Primary Authority Scheme is run by the Better Regulation Delivery Office, an independent unit within the Business Innovation and Skills Department (BIS). See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are currently 602 businesses and 93 local authorities involved in Primary Authority partnerships, covering over 58,000 premises and over 1.57 million employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the scope of the scheme, or the list of regulations which can be covered by partnerships, can be achieved by secondary legislation. The consultation announced today runs until 24 January 2013 to allow feedback from stakeholders before secondary legislation is introduced into Parliament.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Housing Health and Safety Rating System (HHSRS) is a risk-based evaluation tool to help local authorities identify and protect against potential risks and hazards to health and safety from any deficiencies identified in dwellings. It was introduced under the Housing Act 2004 and applies to residential properties in England and Wales.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56643</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:05:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-business-link-helpline"/>
    <title>Assessment of the Business Link helpline</title>
    <summary>Provides an early understanding of how effectively the Business Link helpline is performing. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether the Business Link helpline is performing effectively against its strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’, in which more businesses are assisted online rather than through other higher cost provision (for example face-to-face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the research has assessed the value of the service being provided to callers and how far actual demand has matched expectations. The findings are being used to help inform plans for continual improvement of the service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is based on interviews with helpline staff, analysis of monitoring data, call case studies and a customer survey that consisted of 657 telephone interviews that were completed with customers of the helpline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP led a trade mission to Burma earlier this week.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56633</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:06:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-online-business-support-offer-growth-and-improvement-service-my-new-business"/>
    <title>Assessment of the online business support offer: Growth and Improvement Service, My New Business</title>
    <summary>Assesses whether the new Business Link website services were performing effectively in their strategic role of digital transformation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether online business support services provided by Business Link have performed effectively against the strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’.  That is to successfully assist businesses through a website rather than through higher cost services (for example face to face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study also makes an early assessment of the value of the services provided to new users, with a focus on cost effectiveness and effective referral to other appropriate business support services in the public, private and third sectors. The support services include the comprehensive start-up service provided by My New Business, and online tools provided by the Growth Improvement Service, enabling businesses to identify and solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56450</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:55:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:55:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"/>
    <title>Reducing the impact of regulation on business</title>
    <summary>Cutting red tape, improving existing regulations and avoiding unnecessary new regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regulations are ineffective and unnecessary. Complying with them costs businesses time and money, and can restrict growth. Red tape can also make running charities and community groups more difficult than it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure all regulations are fair and effective. We want to strike the right balance between protecting people’s rights, health and safety and freeing them from unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure regulations in the UK are fair and effective, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;controlling the number of new regulations by &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;operating a ‘one in, two out’ rule for business regulation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/assessing-the-impact-of-new-regulation"&gt;assessing the impact of each regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reviewing-the-effectiveness-of-government-regulations"&gt;reviewing the effectiveness of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-regulation-for-small-businesses"&gt;reducing regulation for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/improving-enforcement-of-government-regulations"&gt;improving enforcement of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/using-alternatives-to-regulation-education-campaigns-economic-instruments"&gt;using alternatives to regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-the-cost-of-eu-regulation-on-uk-business"&gt;reducing the cost of EU regulation on UK business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We publish &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publication_filter_option=guidance&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=department-for-business-innovation-skills"&gt;guidance for all government policymakers&lt;/a&gt; to help design better regulations or find other options instead of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, regulations - and the inspections and bureaucracy that go with them - have piled up. Businesses say the amount of new regulation is one of their biggest problems, preventing them from growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2010, we said that we would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut red tape for businesses and individuals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not rely on rules and regulations by themselves to get things done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re running a series of reviews called ‘Focus on enforcement’ to get businesses’ views on how we could improve the way we enforce regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/"&gt;Have your say on how we enforce regulations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also running the Red Tape Challenge, asking businesses and the public which regulations they think could be removed or improved. See what businesses are saying: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Tell us which regulations you think should be removed or improved.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/39665</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services"/>
    <title>Ensuring the future of the universal postal service and Post Office network services</title>
    <summary>How the government is making sure there will always be a universal postal service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universal postal service - the six-day-a-week, one-price-goes-anywhere service to every address in the UK - is important for communities and the economy. The government needs to make sure the future of the service is secure and that everyone continues to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Post Office network is a unique national asset that provides convenient access to vital social and economic services to local communities across the UK. It needs to be maintained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wholly owns both Royal Mail Group Ltd (which provides the universal postal service in the UK) and Post Office Ltd (which runs the network of post offices). This shareholding is managed by the Shareholder Executive in the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;Attracting private capital into Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect the future of the universal postal service, we aim to end Royal Mail’s dependence on unpredictable funding from the taxpayer by attracting private capital into the company.  We intend to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;sell shares in Royal Mail&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;Funding and modernising the Post Office network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have committed £1.34 billion of funding for the network from financial year 2011 to 2012 to financial year 2014 to 2015. This will enable the Post Office to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;maintain and modernise its network&lt;/a&gt; to help safeguard its future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="separating-the-post-office-and-royal-mail"&gt;Separating the Post Office and Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Mail and the Post Office are different businesses, facing different challenges. In order to maintain the Post Office in public ownership and enable private sector investment in the Royal Mail letters and parcels business, we separated Post Office Ltd from Royal Mail Group Ltd in April 2012 to become a sister company of Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that the two companies will no longer work together. The Chief Executive of Royal Mail has called it “unthinkable” that there would not always be a strong relationship between Royal Mail and the Post Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure the continuation of their existing business relationship, at the time of separation, the management of Royal Mail and the Post Office put in place a commercial contract between the two parties (with the longest possible contract length permitted by law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-royal-mail-pensions"&gt;Funding Royal Mail pensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 1 April 2012 we transferred Royal Mail’s historic liabilities of around £40 billion from Royal Mail’s pension scheme to a new public sector scheme (the Royal Mail Statutory Pension Scheme, RMSPS) to be administered by the government.  At the same time around £28 billion of Royal Mail’s pension assets were transferred to government. The pension scheme left with Royal Mail was left with matching assets and liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-the-regulator"&gt;Changing the regulator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From October 2011 we transferred regulatory responsibility for the postal market from Postcomm to Ofcom, the regulator responsible for the wider communications sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012 Ofcom put in place new regulations for postal services for the next 7 years. Ofcom’s primary duty is to make sure there continues to be a universal postal service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/coalition-documents"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt; we said we would aim to inject private capital into Royal Mail, and explore opportunities for employee ownership. We also pledged to retain Post Office Ltd in public ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the request of the Business Secretary Vince Cable, Richard Hooper CBE, the former deputy chairman of Ofcom, updated his December 2008 report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file49389.pdf"&gt;Modernise or decline&lt;/a&gt; on the maintenance of the universal postal service in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hooper made three main recommendations in his September 2010 report, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/saving-the-royal-mails-universal-postal-service-in-the-digital-age-an-update-of-the-2008-independent-review"&gt;Saving the Royal Mail’s universal postal service in the digital age&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Royal Mail should have access to private sector capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its historic pension deficit should be resolved; its deficit of £8 billion sapped cash from the business, making it difficult to compete with other operators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way postal services are regulated needed to be better balanced so as to allow competition whilst ensuring the universal service remains available  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We agreed and introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; to implement the recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 we &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/post-office-mutualisation"&gt;consulted on the move towards an agreed model for a mutual Post Office&lt;/a&gt;. Our response to the consultation was published in July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two Acts specifically cover postal services in the UK:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;, which lifted restrictions on the ownership of Royal Mail, allowed for a future mutual ownership model for Post Office Limited (ie ownership across a mix of invested stakeholders, such as employees, subpostmasters and consumers, with no one party having an overall majority), enabled the transfer of the Royal Mail’s historic pension liabilities to government and put the framework in place to deliver a new regulatory regime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/26/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; - some of which was replaced or amended by the 2011 Act - has a number of important provisions still in force. These include provisions relating to offences in relation to the mail, the schemes (ie setting out details of services’ terms and conditions) of universal service providers, application of customs and excise legislation to postal packets, and financing and restructuring of the Royal Mail group of companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU Postal Services Directives require member states to ensure the provision of a universal postal service.  The requirements of the directives are implemented in UK law by the above Postal Services Acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/"&gt;Ofcom&lt;/a&gt; - the independent regulator and competition authority for the UK’s communications industries, and its responsibilities now include the postal sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consumerfocus.org.uk/"&gt;Consumer Focus&lt;/a&gt; - champions the needs of consumers, across markets, including the postal services sector, with a particular regard to the vulnerable, including those who have been or are about to be disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/15596</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2"/>
    <title>Modernising company law</title>
    <summary>The government wants to reduce the number of regulations that hold back businesses while protecting both workers and the public.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business regulations are necessary to protect the public and workers from safety risks and prevent pollution and environmental damage, but they can also stop businesses from reaching their potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to reduce the number of unnecessary regulations that hold back businesses while ensuring that both workers and the public are protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2/supporting-pages/simplifying-accounting-and-auditing-for-small-companies"&gt;simplifying accounting and auditing for small companies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2/supporting-pages/negotiating-with-the-eu-on-accounting-regulations"&gt;negotiating with the European Union to make accounting regulations more business friendly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of Companies Act 2006 was completed in October 2009 and made many changes to simplify and improve company law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a full consultation on reforming the UK system for registering company charges government has developed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/c/12-1025-companies-act-amendment-part-25-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;draft regulations with a view to amending Part 25 of the Companies Act 2006&lt;/a&gt;.  These regulations are due to be laid before Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55660</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"/>
    <title>Making companies more accountable to shareholders and the public</title>
    <summary>Making companies more accountable will make them more attractive to investors and make the public want to buy their products and services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shareholders and the public have lost confidence in the way companies are run and they believe that companies should be rewarded for success not failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making companies more accountable in how they work - and showing that they are improving - will increase investor and public confidence, making them more attractive to investors and giving the public more trust in their products and services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make companies more accountable to their shareholders and the public, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/improving-company-reporting"&gt;improving company reporting&lt;/a&gt; through a new law which changes how they write their reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/increasing-representation-on-boards-of-listed-companies"&gt;making company boards more representative of women&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing in legislation that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/supporting-pages/giving-shareholders-more-power-to-link-pay-to-performance"&gt;gives shareholders more power to link pay to performance&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a national contact point at the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt;) where people or organisations can report UK multinationals they think may be breaking the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt; guidelines for trading abroad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Financial Reporting Council’s (&lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Corporate-Governance-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Corporate Governance Code&lt;/a&gt;, launched in 2010, sets out good principles for running a company board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate-governance/UK-Stewardship-Code.aspx"&gt;UK Stewardship Code&lt;/a&gt; makes investors more answerable to their clients and beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Financial reporting Council"&gt;FRC&lt;/abbr&gt; have a detailed explanation about why they are improving these codes and how they fit into government regulation in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/getattachment/1db9539d-9176-4546-91ee-828b7fd087a8/The-UK-Approach-to-Corporate-Governance.aspx"&gt;UK approach to corporate governance.&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2012 Kay Review of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/12-917-kay-review-of-equity-markets-final-report.pdf"&gt;Equity markets and long-term decision making&lt;/a&gt; Professor Kay examines how to improve the performance of UK companies, and provide returns to savers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 22 November 2012 the government published its response &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=bis%20ensuring%20equity%20markets%20support%20long%20time%20growth&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;ved=0CC4QFjAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bis.gov.uk%2Fassets%2Fbiscore%2Fbusiness-law%2Fdocs%2Fe%2F12-1188-equity-markets-support-growth-response-to-kay-review.pdf&amp;amp;ei=Q6a_UIfZFZTM0AW414GIAQ&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFKxfouDderH7bnrYUmF_gWKCDeZQ"&gt;Ensuring equity markets support long-term growth&lt;/a&gt; welcoming the Kay Report and accepting Professor Kay’s analysis and conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
