<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/business-and-enterprise</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/business-and-enterprise.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Business and enterprise"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/61088</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge: Retail and Manufacturing Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The purpose of this consultation was to seek views on the amendment and removal of statutory instruments which were identified under the Retail and Manufacturing Red Tape Challenge spotlight process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s response to the consultation was published on the 16th July. This confirms the proposals we intend to take forward which include the revocation of the following measures on the 1st October 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imitation Dummies (Safety) Regulations 1993 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas cooking Appliances (Safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating Appliances (Fireguards) (Safety) Regulations 1991 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Catalytic Heaters (safety) Regulations 1984 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All-Terrain Motor Vehicle (safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking Utensils (Safety) Regulations 1972 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indication of Prices (Beds) Order 1978 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child Resistant Packaging and Tactile Danger Warning (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1992 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands for Carry-cots (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1996 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magnetic Toys (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second Government response was published on the 30th November. This confirms the amendment and revocation of the following regulations on the 6 April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61079</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/30-million-boost-as-start-up-loans-for-young-entrepreneurs-expanded"/>
    <title>£30 million boost as Start-Up Loans for young entrepreneurs expanded</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Thousands more young people have the opportunity to apply for government loans to turn their business ideas into reality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has today announced a boost to the government’s Start-Up loans scheme, with funding being increased by £30 million to £110 million over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also said that due to demand from those who had just missed out on the scheme, and the challenges faced to secure loans to start a business, the age limit for applying will now be extended from 24 to 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-Up Loans provide budding entrepreneurs a range of support to get their business idea off the ground, including access to a business mentor as well as funding in the region of £2,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 3000 people have applied or registered an interest in a Start-Up loan; when their business plan is robust and approved, applicants are able to access the financial support, with a repayment period of up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that the scheme has been live over £1.5 million worth of loans have been approved, helping over 460 new businesses get off the ground. Around 100 new businesses a week are expected to reach approval stage in January, with thousands more in the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Start-Up Loans scheme forms an integral part of the Business in You campaign, which encourages the start up and growth of new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startuploans.co.uk/"&gt;Visit the Start-Up Loans Company for more information and details on how to apply.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business"&gt;Tools and guidance for businesses on Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/start-up-loans-scheme-expanded/"&gt;Read the full story on the Number 10 website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60926</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T12:13:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T12:13:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/employee-ownership-and-share-buy-backs-consultation-on-implementation-of-nuttall-review-recommendations"/>
    <title>Employee Ownership and Share Buy Backs - Consultation on implementation of Nuttall Review recommendations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The Nuttall Review on Employee Ownership recommended (Recommendation V) that the Government should review and consult on changes to deregulate the conditions under which companies can: authorise share buy backs; finance share buy backs; and hold shares ‘in treasury’.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on deregulatory changes to the conditions under which companies can authorise and finance the repurchase of its own shares, and hold these shares once repurchased. The regulation of share buy backs is governed by the Companies Act 2006. Changes to these regulations, such as those proposed in this consultation would require changes via secondary legislation. The draft regulations attached below indicate how the government would implement these changes. Through this consultation we would also like to understand the implications for companies, employees, and other shareholders. In particular we wish to ensure there are no unintended consequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/59984</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:12:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:12:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>What the government is doing to reduce anti-competitive activities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets are the best way of making sure a country’s resources are put to their best use. They encourage enterprise and widen choice for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can develop in any economy. They can harm consumers and stifle innovation and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an anti-competitive activity would be when two companies agree to charge the same price for a similar product. This protects the companies’ profits but means consumers get less choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can be very bad for consumers. That’s why they have to be identified and stopped as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the government’s three growth objectives is that the UK should become the best place to start, finance and grow a business. Reforming and improving the laws on anti-competitive activities is a major part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-competition-law"&gt;Changing competition law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is reforming the laws that cover competition and anti-competitive activities in business, including those relating to mergers, markets and illegal activities such as price-fixing and cartels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also reforming the institutions that police competition and anti-competitive activities, and strengthening their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These laws, institutions and powers are collectively known as the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/processes-for-tackling-anti-competitive-activity--2"&gt;guide to the competition regime&lt;/a&gt; if you’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="competition-landscape"&gt;Competition landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re making changes to the organisations that deal with competition and anti-competitive activities in business. We’re doing this between now and the end of 2014. This work is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and competition landscape reforms."&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reforms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="setting-up-a-new-watchdog-for-the-grocery-industry"&gt;Setting up a new watchdog for the grocery industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re creating a new watchdog for the grocery industry. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/groceries-code-adjudicator" title="Groceries Code."&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt; will give suppliers, including farmers supplying the bigger supermarket chains, more protection against anti-competitive activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-legal-challenges-easier"&gt;Making legal challenges easier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to make it easier for consumers and small businesses to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/private-actions-pro-tem" title="Private Action."&gt;challenge anti-competitive behaviour&lt;/a&gt; by bringing a legal challenge (also known as a private action) against anti-competitive activities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-aid"&gt;State aid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re modernising the rules on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State aid is when a public body (such as a local authority) or publicly funded body (such as the Big Lottery) provides a business, charity or other organisation with financial help that could give them an advantage over another business. This kind of financial help is generally outlawed by the European treaty, as it’s an anti-competitive practice. State aid regulations set legal ways to give this kind of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"&gt;detailed guide on state aid&lt;/a&gt; for public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different rules - also covered in the detailed guide - apply to agriculture, aquaculture, fisheries, transport and maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK competition law has to comply with EU law. Article 101 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/antitrust/overview_en.html"&gt;Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU)&lt;/a&gt; bans any agreements between businesses ‘which have as their object… the prevention [or] restriction… of competition within the common market.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
