<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/climate-change</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Climate change"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17618</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T09:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/green-bus-fund-round-4"/>
    <title>Green Bus Fund round 4</title>
    <summary>Guidance and bidding documents for bus operators and local authorities to submit bids for the 4th round of the Green Bus Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Bus Fund supports bus companies and local authorities in England to help them buy new low carbon buses. Its main purpose is to support and speed up the introduction of hundreds of low carbon buses across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bidding guidance and documents are intended for bus operators and local authorities who want to submit bids for grant under the 4th round of the government’s Green Bus Fund. The bidding guidance explains the eligibility terms, the bidding process and how bids should be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17341</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T13:09:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the South West Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194318/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationswrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the South West regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S6 from the ‘Somerset and Exmoor National Park joint structure plan’ relating to the green belt in North East Somerset. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the coalition agreement to safeguard the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17304</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-green-belt-statistics-for-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Local authority green belt statistics for England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <summary>Statistics on designated green belt land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on the extent of the green belt in England were released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority on 30 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The extent of the designated green belt land in England in 2011/12 was estimated at 1,639,410 hectares, about 13% of the land area of England. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall there has been a decrease of 130 hectares from the revised 2010-11 green belt. This is due to three authorities who have adopted new plans in which they have changed the boundaries of the green belt. This represents a decrease of less than 0.01% per cent in the total green belt area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since these statistics were first compiled for 1997, there has been an increase in the area of green belt after taking account of the redesignation of some green belt as part of the New Forest National Park in 2005.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17243</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:33:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/town-and-country-planning-association-conference-speech"/>
    <title>Town and Country Planning Association conference speech</title>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Planning Minister Nick Boles about beautiful urban landscapes and affordable homes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;England is famous for the beauty of its landscapes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Yorkshire Dales to the South Hams, from the Weald of Kent to the Cumbrian Lakes, England glories in countryside of which generations of man and nature are joint authors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes - together with the greater drama of their Celtic cousins - that draw visitors to these islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes that our most popular institution and your sister organisation, the National Trust, was set up to preserve in perpetuity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of England is its finest asset and, for each of us, our most precious inheritance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative in both name and spirit, as a West Country boy and a Lincolnshire MP, as the son of a former director general of the National Trust and the brother of 1 of its conservation managers, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that nothing would do more to improve the health and happiness of the British people than if more of them got to spend more of their lives surrounded by beauty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty lifts, calms, excites, inspires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more intoxicating than any narcotic, more soothing than any therapy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Britain becomes more prosperous, we must insist that it becomes more beautiful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the beauty we seek, and the landscapes we treasure, are not only to be found in our open spaces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the loveliest scenery in Britain is to be found in our villages, cities and towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take you on a journey, which starts in my constituency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, the river Welland has snaked its way through the low contours of Lincolnshire from its source in Northamptonshire’s Hothorpe Hills.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enters Lincolnshire at the point where 4 counties meet and passes through countryside that is pleasant but hardly memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wandering painter or poet would not give this stretch of the Welland valley a second look, were it not for the landscape of Lincolnshire limestone that is the town of Stamford.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is not just 1 of England’s most beautiful towns; it is 1 of its finest bits of scenery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man-made. Built from stone and timber frames and slate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the aesthetic equal of our most splendid hills, lakes and rivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did this landscape come from?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it spring fully formed from the mind of some 17th century master planner, the brainchild of a Lincolnshire Haussman?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is, as the Royal Commission for Historic Monuments pronounced, ‘a town of discrete buildings’, each 1 unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earls of Exeter from nearby Burghley House provided long leases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the local community of wool, leather, cloth and hemp merchants, apothecaries and solicitors indulged themselves with a great variety of stone window surrounds, doorways, eaves, corner and chimney details.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did so within a broad set of rules set out in the London manuals of Rome educated James Gibbs but almost always used local architects and builders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford was the spontaneous product of human initiative, haphazardly executed and totally unplanned, motivated by the desire for profit, the love of God and that age-old urge that keeps makeover shows in business, the desire to make your house nicer than your neighbours’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop is north of the border, in Great Britain’s first New Town.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by contrast, was an example of municipal town planning at its boldest and most inspired.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the economic stagnation into which Edinburgh had slipped after the Act of Union, in 1752 the Provost, George Drummond, launched an architectural competition to design a new cityscape of wide streets, crescents and squares, featuring symmetrical terraces of town-houses as well as purpose-built shops and public gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-six year old James Craig won the competition and, in 4 stages between the 1760s and the 1850s, he, Robert Adam, William Chambers and William Playfair all stayed loyal to the original vision and developed their own variations on a Greek revival theme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In building their New Town, Edinburgh’s town councillors not only restored commercial and cultural vigour to Scotland’s capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also created 1 of the most beautiful landscapes in the British Isles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who can resist the melancholy charm of a walk in the rain around Charlotte Square and through Ainslie Place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would wager that the Facebook pages of recent visitors to Scotland contain at least as many photographs of Bute House and Moray Place as they do of Loch Lomond or Glencoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Stamford in the early 1600s, and in Edinburgh 150 later, beauty came about as a result of the natural human urge to get together with one’s neighbours to build a place in which it would be a pleasure to live and work, to raise a family and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same generous set of instincts that, another hundred and fifty years later, inspired Ebenezer Howard to build Letchworth Garden City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I am skating on very thin ice telling members of the Town and Country Planning Association anything about the Garden City movement, when your association was founded to promote just that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do want take a moment, as a layman, lacking all planning qualifications, to say why, like the Prime Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister, I believe that we have so much to learn from Ebenezer Howard and his garden cities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genius of Letchworth, like so many of the most appealing towns and cities, lies as much in the spaces between the buildings as in the buildings themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By resisting the temptation to cram as many houses as possible onto the available land and adopting their golden rule of twelve houses to the acre, Letchworth’s architects, Barry Parker and Raymond Unwin allowed room for the organic intermingling of nature and architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings are buttressed by front and back gardens, the roads are lined with broad verges and trees, the town is criss-crossed with footpaths and patchworked with allotments and parks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ebenezer Howard himself put it, “Parks and gardens, orchards and woods, are being planted in the midst of the busy life of the people, so that they can be enjoyed in the fullest measure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letchworth and the other garden cities work as living, breathing urban communities because, as an Ebenezer Howard put it, they combine “the advantages of the most energetic and active town life, with all the beauty and delight of the country.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way most English people want to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find a way to build places like this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has been holding us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only been planning minister for a few months but I have observed the debate about housing and planning for over ten years and I think I know what is wrong.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trapped in a vicious circle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at the new housing estates that have been bolted on to their towns and villages in recent decades and observe that few of them are beautiful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not to put too fine a point on it, many of them are pig-ugly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Harrisons Wharf in Purfleet that I visited last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure the flats inside are nice enough but they occupy an overbearing and unbroken slab of dismal brickwork that is an insult to the community it borders, cutting it off from a stretch of the River Thames which, in Victorian times, attracted day-trippers from London keen to take a pleasant walk along banks of the river.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since new housing estates are all too often soulless and formulaic, and those who will inhabit them will add to the pressure on local roads, primary school places and doctor’s appointments, existing residents oppose any proposal to build new houses on green field sites, even when the land is of low environmental quality.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities respond to the wishes of local voters by putting too few sites into their local plans. And this drives the cost of development land up to stratospheric levels (roughly £3 million an hectare in the South East and East of England by 2010.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers respond by stuffing as many units as they can onto any site and, in an attempt to make the properties affordable, skimp on room size, architectural features, vernacular materials, communal spaces and landscape design.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, because we don’t build beautifully, people don’t let us build much. And because we don’t build much, we can’t afford to build beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the coalition, and my personal mission as planning minister, is to help us break out of this vicious circle once and for all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get back on to that confident, progressive path, which created Stamford, Edinburgh New Town and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to build beautiful and affordable places once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have we done to bring this about? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles’ first step, in June 2010, was to scrap John Prescott’s blanket density target of 30 dwellings per hectare and to stop the garden grabbing that was destroying the precious green spaces that make Britain’s cities so pleasant to live in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government then embarked on a root and branch reform of the planning system and the creation of the National Planning Policy Framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mammoth task which had to be masterminded by a minister with a mammoth brain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my predecessor, Greg Clark, is blessed with exactly that - as well as the unfailing patience and politeness required to bring the good ship Reform to dock with most of those interested in planning and development still on board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Framework establishes a few clear principles, which it is now my job to drive through.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That local councils should take charge of development in their areas by drawing up local plans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that alongside the power to plan comes the responsibility to provide new houses to meet people’s aspirations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their local plans, councils must bring forward enough land to meet the objectively assessed housing needs of their area over the next 5 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they do so, they will be able to protect precious open spaces against speculative development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Secretary of State and I will back them to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they fail to take their responsibilities seriously, the presumption in favour of sustainable development will fill the vacuum and make the vital decisions that they are ducking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Framework, Grant Shapps introduced the New Homes Bonus, which gives local councils additional money for every new home for which they give planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in what I believe will turn out to be our most revolutionary step, the government launched neighbourhood planning through which villages, parishes and other neighbourhoods can take control of their future and decide for themselves how and where development should take place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be talking more about our ambitions for neighbourhood plans after the Autumn Statement.
So the government has acted to ensure that more land is brought forward for development and that local communities have an incentive to welcome new housing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now for planners, architects and developers, large and small, to seize the opportunity we have created and start designing beautiful places, which local people will welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, on the edge of Bishops Castle in Shropshire, Bob Tomlinson and Carole Salmon set out to create a new, contemporary village, a friendly place that people would want to live.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was The Wintles, 1 of the most exciting and enchanting collection of new houses anywhere in England.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses are all different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are unashamedly contemporary but incorporate vernacular features in a bold and imaginative way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a wide range of both natural and manufactured materials and make a priority of the spaces between the buildings (both private and communal) and the planting of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wintles did not get everything right first time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which experiment ever does?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not as integrated into the rest of Bishops Castle as some long-standing residents would like. And, to replicate it on a large scale, one would need to find a way to build houses that are just as beautiful and just as sustainable but cost less to build.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Bishops Castle I believe that the Living Village Trust created a model for our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which Ebenezer Howard would be proud.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which, once again, we build beautiful new urban landscapes full of affordable houses surrounded by green spaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be our goal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16388</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-west-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the West Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194311/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationwmrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the West Midlands regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16537</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T11:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-uk-bus-awards-lunch-speech"/>
    <title>2012 UK Bus Awards lunch speech</title>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also for inviting me along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pleasure to be here today at my third consecutive UK Bus Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s one for every Transport Secretary since I became a Minister at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I’m lucky enough to be sharing the stage with Jane (Jane Hill – BBC News).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A journalist and a newsreader, a TV anchor and a radio presenter - Jane is one of the country’s most familiar faces and familiar voices.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have it on good authority that Jane is a big fan of Radio 4’s “The Archers”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A drama come soap opera that seems to have been around forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters that not too many of the public would recognise in the street&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And people living in a make-believe world which critics claim bears little resemblance to everyday life in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say this all sounds a bit like the House of Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="speaking-up-for-the-bus-industry"&gt;Speaking up for the bus industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I hope I’ve not just been the consistent Ministerial face at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; - I’ve also tried to be a consistent voice when it comes to speaking up for the bus industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve said it before and I’ll keep on saying it - Britain’s buses matter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are a few familiar facts and figures that prove why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bus travel accounts for 63% of all public transport journeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last year in Great Britain buses clocked up 5.2 billion passenger journeys &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, as well as contributing more than £2 billion a year to the economy, the bus industry provides 124,000 direct jobs and supports an estimated 83,000 jobs through the supply chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buses also open up access to vital public services such as health and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, they provide a transport link between worker and workplace, with some two and a half million jobs accessed every day by bus, which is more than by all other forms of public transport combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, increasingly, buses are also helping to safeguard our environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, thanks to this government’s “&lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/background-to-the-green-bus-fund"&gt;Green Bus Fund&lt;/a&gt;” we’re seeing more and more low emission buses on our streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buses that emit around 30 per cent fewer greenhouse gas emissions than standard diesel buses and use around a third less fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And earlier this month I was pleased to announce an extra £20 million for what is now the 4th round of the Green Bus Fund, bringing the total support for this initiative to £95 million since its launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As highlighted in Greener Journey’s “Buses and Economic Growth Report” not only are buses the backbone of our public transport system, they can also boost economic growth and cut carbon by reducing congestion and replacing car journeys. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-industry-equal-to-testing-times"&gt;An industry equal to testing times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This then is an industry that makes a difference. But it’s also an industry that isn’t short of challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; and concessionary travel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; I of course recognise that the rate was cut by 20% from April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also think it’s worth remembering that the Government realised the importance of giving you plenty of time to get ready for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why we gave the bus market 18 months advance notice of the change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me say this on the issue of concessionary travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve made sure that bus operators will be reimbursed so that they are “no better and no worse off” by carrying concessionary passengers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because, we want the processes surrounding this to be as fair as possible, we’ve also speeded up the appeals mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I know that it’s not easy for operators right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluctuating fuel prices and the backdrop of a tough economic climate make these testing times for businesses and families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show bus patronage was down 0.3% in non-metropolitan areas and while this is unwelcoming it is far from the apocalypse scene commentators were predicting. Indeed overall, bus patronage across England rose by 0.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also pleased to see that 85% of bus passengers are satisfied with their service. And even in the area of lowest satisfaction it was still 79%. I haven’t seen the latest comparable figures for satisfaction with politicians and journalists but I’m told it’s not quite that high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, these may be testing times but, once again, the industry is showing itself to be equal to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="green-light-for-better-buses"&gt;Green Light for Better Buses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I sense a mood of quiet optimism that was especially tangible at the recent 2012 Euro Bus Expo, which I was delighted to open and where I was able to speak with many in the industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know that there is more to do. Now is not the time for the engine to tick over at the bus stop, we have to keep moving forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why earlier this year I set out my vision for buses in the &lt;a href="/government/publications/green-light-for-better-buses"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; policy document, “Green Light for Better Buses.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this report will help provide stability in the industry by reforming subsidy, improving competition and Incentivise partnership working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its heart is a shared vision for a bus service that is reliable and flexible, efficient and innovative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that offers competitive prices and smarter ticketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that gives taxpayers real value for money and passengers a travel option they want to use time and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that is successful and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that people want to use, not one they use because they have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="young-people"&gt;Young People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that one of the best ways to ensure success and sustainability over the long-term is to encourage much greater bus travel among that section of the market that is literally the future of the industry - young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a challenge that cannot be side-stepped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, just this month the Youth Select Committee published its report on “Transport and Young People.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That report called for the age at which young people start paying full fares to be set at 18 across England and for the introduction of a national concessionary scheme to provide a discounted bus travel card for those younger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I am looking at this report very seriously and I really do want to work with operators, and also local authorities, to improve the deal for our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as I said, this is a challenge we have to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also an opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s think about all the ways we can use bus services to help young people access employment and training opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make bus travel easy and attractive for young people by building on initiatives like CPT’s  (Confederation of Passenger Transport) excellent “Bus for Us” interactive website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that, since I launched it, over 80 of the UK’s bus operators are already signed up to “Bus for Us”  - equivalent to 85% of the bus market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to see all operators on board in the near future. There’s room on top for the rest. My message to the remaining 15% is “don’t miss the bus”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also be innovative about the fare deals and the discounts on offer to young people…and the great work done by Trent Barton in this area shows it can be done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s deliver some consistency too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, TCA- led youth concessions are offered in 28 TCAs outside London, and a commercial youth concession is available in 80 TCAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are some good things going on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is it that in some places there are no concessions at all? And how can it be that in one area a 16 year old might get free bus travel while, in another, a 14-year old pays full adult fare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s come together and work together to support our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, let’s win over the next generation of bus passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pay-tribute-to-all-the-nominees"&gt;Pay tribute to all the nominees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let me return to the reason why we are all here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I’m proud to be the bus champion in government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m also just as proud of the people and organisations working in the bus industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, this afternoon, we rightly take the time to recognise some of the brightest and the best in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty two categories in this year’s awards: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individuals and teams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local authorities and  operators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cities and shires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small projects and big projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All making today’s shortlist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all with something in common….excellence and achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, these awards show that the hallmarks of your industry are innovation, professionalism and sheer hard work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also show that, at its heart, your industry is all about people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can talk about investment. And we can debate the pros and cons of one policy versus another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when push comes to shove, it’s the people in the bus industry who make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference because they understand the needs of the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference because they want to provide a first class service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference by delivering real improvements on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who, and what, we are honouring today….and so I pay tribute to all of this year’s nominees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. They do say that making a speech is a bit like having a fight – any fool can start one, the real skill is knowing when and how to end it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I know you’re keen to get on with handing out those awards, so you’ll be pleased to hear that the “when” has arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for “how to end it” it simply remains for me to thank you for your hospitality, to thank you for listening and to wish all those waiting to hear if they’ve won the very best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you and hopefully I’ll see you all next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15105</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T12:52:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"/>
    <title>Low carbon bus calculator</title>
    <summary>This toolkit can be used to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (LCEB).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the benefits of purchasing a low carbon bus will be different for each operator and will depend on the way in which the bus in service is used. So, Department for Transport economists have produced a transparent, user-friendly toolkit to be used by bus operators and local authorities to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (&lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;). Your assessment should always compare the &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; to an equivalent diesel bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit allows you flexibility in changing the input assumptions to those most relevant to you. You will be able to assess the financial implications of purchasing a &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;, based on the fuel savings on offer (as advised by &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturers or experienced in trials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet tool is intended to provide indicative estimates only and &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; does not vouch for the accuracy of such estimates. Please note that the Department for Transport does not accept any liability for any decisions that may be taken on the basis of such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit will be routinely updated and refined. Details of any updates or changes that are made will be outlined in the ‘Intro’ worksheet of the toolkit. We therefore encourage you to visit this website regularly and download the toolkit to ensure you are using the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16656</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:54:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/suffolk-sustainable-transport-forum"/>
    <title>Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum</title>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jYG7r0lJIaE&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA" title="Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum"&gt;Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me to talk to your forum today. It seems fitting that I should be with you virtually to discuss our collective goals of creating growth whilst cutting carbon at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome the development of the Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum and the involvement of Hutchison Ports UK, BT and Suffolk County Council. This is a great example of joint working, both across business sectors and also between business and local government. I also understand that the New Anglia Local Enterprise Partnership is also working across the private and public sector on their Green Economy Pathfinder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low carbon transport plays a key role in the wider drive towards sustainable economic growth, this is as true on the local level as it is on the national and international level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we allocated a new £600 million Local Sustainable Transport funding for local projects which create growth and cut carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will be aware, Suffolk received £5 million for their Lowestoft Local Links project. This package includes improved pedestrian and cycle infrastructure, increased bus services, improvements to transport interchange hubs, enhanced travel planning provisions, and more. I was pleased to visit Lowestoft this time last year and get a sense of how this will be transforming access to and around the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also investing more widely in green public transport, for example through our national programme of rail electrification or the £30 million Green Bus Fund. Each year, every low-carbon bus outside London saves around 22 tonnes of CO2 compared with its diesel equivalent. Anglian Bus Ltd in Suffolk has been awarded £624,000 to fund 13 low carbon buses, and I look forward to seeing these roll out of the garages and on to the roads, they offer a more comfortable, more reliable and much greener experience for bus passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses have been closely involved in the planning and delivery of Local Sustainable Transport projects in Suffolk, and indeed across the 96 projects in 77 authorities that are going ahead because of the Fund.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses are doing this because they realise the benefits of an integrated transport system that allows easy access to workplaces; because of the reduced absenteeism that results from employees choosing a more active lifestyle; and because of the transformation of the local urban and rural environments that can result from an increased uptake of sustainable modes of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are also showing support by embracing alternatives to travel in their day-to-day office environments. Endorsing the use of technology, such as video speeches and teleconferencing, and supporting greater uptake of flexible working amongst staff can bring about an array of benefits. Reducing business flights and consolidating office space can lead to notable cost savings. And both research and experience have shown that employee productivity and wellbeing can be improved when we take a more flexible approach to the working day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympics proved a challenge and opportunity in this regard. Businesses and government understood that transport would be much busier than usual and that change was necessary. So employees came in to work and left for home earlier to escape the rush hour, they hopped on their bikes rather than hopping on the tube to escape the underground, or they stayed home and logged on rather than getting behind the wheel of a car, escaping the office altogether. The result was not just one of the most successful Games in history, but also one where transport was universally praised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the department is also investing more widely in transport infrastructure in the region, for example through the £22 million transport package for Ipswich. This is an innovative and exciting programme of work that will see Ipswich town centre become a thriving sustainable transport hub, and has the potential to transform the way people travel in and around Ipswich. Indeed, residents are already benefiting from new traffic management measures and cycle and pedestrian facilities, facilitating access to Suffolk College.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just about providing policies and funding for transport. We also need to invest in relationships. And that is why I  support fora like this which discuss common challenges, build partnerships,  share best practice and generate solutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thank you for inviting me, and good luck with your work. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16285</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/biofuels-the-renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-progress-on-adoption-and-the-next-generation"/>
    <title>Biofuels: the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation, progress on adoption and the next generation </title>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the Westminster Energy, Environment and Transport forum for inviting me to speak at your event this morning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to have the chance to talk to you about the possible next steps on biofuels policy. First though, I want to talk a bit about how we got to where we are today, and in particular about developments over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition government has stuck by its commitment to cut the carbon footprint of road transport by implementing measures which promote the use of renewable energy, including of course biofuels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concerted effort has not only contributed towards the European Renewable Energy Directive and Fuel Quality Directive targets, but also, in the case of sustainable biofuels, to our international obligations on climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took an important step towards the goal of truly sustainable biofuels when we implemented the transport elements of the Renewable Energy Directive last December. The introduction of mandatory sustainability criteria means that to benefit from incentives under the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) biofuels must now, with some exceptions, deliver greenhouse gas savings of at least 35% compared to fossil fuels. They also cannot be sourced from areas of high biodiversity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes we made to the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; last year also introduced double counting. This provides a further incentive for biofuels made from wastes and residues, in recognition that these feedstocks are unlikely to compete with food production or contribute to indirect land use change. In the first 4 years of the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;, the proportion of biofuels produced from wastes, rather than crops, increased from 12% to 49%.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am confident that we have already made significant progress towards ensuring that biofuels used in the UK are sustainable. Indeed, in my view it is imperative that the UK biofuel industry continues to invest and grow.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be able to open the Agri Energy biodiesel plant in Bootle in Liverpool this year….a large new investment that will see the collection of wastes turned into biodiesel.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it is vital that we keep seeing profitable investments like this which produce low carbon energy, provide jobs and help us to meet our ambitious carbon reduction targets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while biofuels should be a key means of achieving carbon reduction targets, we also know that some biofuels still carry sustainability risks. We remain very concerned that studies have demonstrated that some biofuels can even produce greater carbon emissions than fossil fuels, particularly when indirect land use change (or &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt;) is factored in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have consistently made clear at European level that &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt; needs to be addressed urgently to ensure that people can be confident that available biofuels mean genuine &lt;abbr title="greenhouse gas"&gt;GHG&lt;/abbr&gt; savings.  It is very much in the interests of the biofuel industry itself that we reach this point, and do so as soon as we can.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is helpful that the long awaited &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt; proposal was adopted and published by the European Commission last month. My officials and I are currently analysing the proposal and its implications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s proposal sets a 5% cap on the level of contribution food-crop-based feedstocks can make to our 10% &lt;abbr title="Renewable Energy Directive"&gt;RED&lt;/abbr&gt; transport target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal also includes additional support for advanced biofuels, seeking to encourage further development in feedstocks which do not compete for food, feed or land.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to ensure that we have a settled policy framework based on good scientific evidence, and I hope that these European developments can move towards this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime though, I genuinely do not believe that setting further short term interim targets can provide the clarity industry continues to demand.  It might give the veneer of certainty over a body of doubt.  Although I fully appreciate that industry needs clarity on future policy to plan investment, it is equally crucial that government’s policy achieves what it is meant to deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I have adopted a cautious approach in setting future biofuel targets within the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation.  Better in my view to go slower in a direction that is certain rather than to go fast and have to change direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been too many examples of government moving too quickly forward on a policy which they have later had to pull back on.  Furthermore, industry tells me that it is certainty they want, not an impression of certainty which turns out to be vacuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I can assure you that we will continue to investigate potentially helpful options, such as the advanced biofuels, which I believe offer a real opportunity for investment and growth for the whole economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the longer term the advancement of the biofuels industry will surely rely on the development and commercialisation of many of these new technologies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also interested in the potential to use biofuels in sectors where, at present, there are limited options to decarbonise…. such as in aviation and &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, I recognise the importance of biomethane made from waste as a sustainable renewable transport fuel, particularly in the heavy goods vehicle sector where there are real market barriers to uptake of low emission technologies such as hybrid, electric and gas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support the use of lower emission &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; technologies, the Department for Transport has made available over £11 million capital funding to trial low carbon lorries and their supporting infrastructure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 projects, trialling over 300 vehicles between them, will receive funding towards the cost of low emission &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; technologies.  The funding is also being used to help establish gas refuelling infrastructure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This initiative will increase the number of low carbon lorries on the road but it will also provide vital information on the performance of these vehicles in the real world….something that will help encourage wider uptake of lower carbon lorries and promote the use of biomethane as a sustainable fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also keen to develop this technology for buses, and am doing so through the Green Bus Fund.
Biofuels are of course just 1 part of a wider strategy to encourage growth and cut carbon.  For example, we are also committed to supporting the uptake of ultra low carbon vehicles in the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spending Review announced provision of over £400 million to support the development of the ultra low emission vehicle market work to 2015.  This support package includes funding;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for recharging infrastructure  schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote the uptake of ultra-low emission cars through the Plug-In Car and Van Grants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of £82 million to support for research and development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition UKH2Mobility was launched last January. This joint undertaking with key industry stakeholders will evaluate the potential for hydrogen as a fuel for ultra low carbon vehicles in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biofuels have become an important part of the UK economy, of our national infrastructure and of efforts to meet our international emission and energy targets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we are focused on ensuring that this national resource is used appropriately and that the full consequences of growing biofuels are considered and assessed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coalition government believes that it is possible both to safeguard the environment and support the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that these goals are not incompatible. Quite the reverse. They are in fact 2 sides of the same coin. You can cut carbon and boost growth and our work with biofuels is proof of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK biofuels industry continues to lead the world in sustainable and renewable fuels and I am proud of the efforts and achievements the industry has made so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain our lead in this industry and to address barriers to supply, we need to continue to work closely with suppliers and to listen to concerns raised about the social and environmental sustainability of biofuels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way not only will we get the best deal for the industry, the taxpayer and the consumer… we will get the right policies for our the transport sector, the economy and the environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16914</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:01:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:01:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment"/>
    <title>Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment</title>
    <summary>We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the environment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009 buildings accounted for about 43% of all the UK’s carbon emissions. Buildings and other developments can also damage the environment, through poor waste management or inefficient use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the natural and built environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have included policies in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to explain how developments should be planned to reduce carbon emissions and protect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce carbon emissions from buildings, we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are requiring local planning authorities to make sure that new developments are energy efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will require all new homes to be zero carbon from 2016 and are considering extending this to include all other buildings from 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/green_deal/green_deal.aspx" title="Green deal"&gt;green deal&lt;/a&gt; to enable people to pay for home improvements over time using savings on their regular energy bills &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have improved &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/energy-performance-of-buildings" title="Energy Performance Certificates"&gt;Energy Performance Certificates&lt;/a&gt; to make them more informative and user-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/code-for-sustainable-homes" title="Code for sustainable homes"&gt;Code for Sustainable Homes&lt;/a&gt; which provides a single national standard for the design and construction of sustainable new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect trees we have simplified the system for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/tree-preservation-orders" title="Tree preservation certificates"&gt;tree preservation orders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work with the 9 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/aggregate-working-parties" title="Aggregate working parties"&gt;aggregate working parties&lt;/a&gt; who provide technical advice about the supply and demand for aggregates such as sand, gravel and crushed rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is responsible for developing town and country planning policy and rules that affect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policies on planning and the environment are set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework-and-the-environment" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012 following extensive public consultation. The framework is an important part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more easy to understand, and to promote sustainable growth. It replaced and simplified a series of earlier planning policy statements and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the government’s policy to revoke existing regional strategies outside London. However, any final decision on this must take account of assessments of, and consultation on, the possible environmental effects. We are updating the earlier environmental reports and undertaking further consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/abolition-of-regional-strategies"&gt;written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt; made by Baroness Hanham on 25 July 2012 sets out the background and explains why the reports are being updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All EU member states must follow the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive. This requires that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all properties (homes, commercial and public buildings) must have an Energy Performance Certificate when sold, built or rented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger public buildings must display a Display Energy Certificate &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all air-conditioning systems over 12kW must be regularly inspected by an Energy Assessor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
