<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/climate-change</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Climate change"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T13:38:46+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56204</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:38:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change"/>
    <title>Taking international action to mitigate climate change</title>
    <summary>How we’re working with other countries to reduce global greenhouse gas emissions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the global average temperature rises more than 2°C above pre-industrial levels, significant negative impacts of climate change will be more likely and the cost of managing them will rise sharply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution led to an increase in greenhouse gas emissions caused by human activity. The Earth’s surface has consequently warmed by about 0.8°C since around 1900, with much of this warming occurring in the past 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have a 50% chance of keeping climate change to within 2°C of pre-industrial levels, global greenhouse gas emissions need to peak before 2020 and then decline steeply. The UK can’t make this happen on its own – the government has to work at an international level to make sure all countries do what is needed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/encouraging-the-eu-to-demonstrate-leadership-on-climate-change"&gt;encouraging the EU to demonstrate leadership on climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/international/negotiations/negotiations.aspx"&gt;negotiating for a comprehensive global climate change agreement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/What-we-do/Key-Issues/Climate-and-environment"&gt;reducing the impact of climate change in developing countries and the overseas territories&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing £2.9 billion through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/international-climate-fund-icf"&gt;International Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; to help developing countries mitigate and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financially supporting developing countries through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/reducing-emissions-from-deforestation-and-forest-degradation-redd"&gt;REDD+&lt;/a&gt; to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/leading-the-diplomatic-effort-to-mitigate-climate-change"&gt;leading the diplomatic effort to mitigate climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;evidence base to understand and predict climate change&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; that climate change is happening and mainly due to increasing greenhouse gases emitted as a result of human activity, the UN negotiated a treaty at its Conference on Environment and Development in 1992. This treaty is known as the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/2860.php"&gt;United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; and the UK is one of the 195 parties to it. Parties to the convention meet annually at the Conference of the Parties (&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-18-doha-2012"&gt;Conference of the Parties 18, Doha 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18 agreed to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;close 2 of the 3 parallel negotiating tracks so that future negotiations will all focus on the new agreement in 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a work plan for negotiation of a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/items/6240.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-17-durban-2011"&gt;Conference of the Parties 17, Durban 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17 agreed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/bodies/body/6645.php"&gt;Durban Platform for Enhanced Action&lt;/a&gt;, which aims to negotiate a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015 and increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide in 2012 a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establish a board for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/durban_nov_2011/session/6294.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-16-cancun-2010"&gt;Conference of the Parties 16, Cancun 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16 agreed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an overall 2°C target to limit temperature rise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to use the UN system to assess different countries’ actions against climate change &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on a system of measurement, reporting and verification to gauge how countries are meeting their promises to reduce greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to establish the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; and help developing countries access low carbon technology and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to halt, slow, and reverse the destruction of trees through the development of international rules and a monitoring system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/cancun_nov_2010/session/6254.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/essential_background/items/6031.php"&gt;Further information on earlier Conferences of Parties to the &lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16449</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/climate-public-private-partnership-cp3"/>
    <title>Climate Public Private Partnership (CP3)</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is helping to boost investment in climate projects in developing countries.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; will invest £130 million in 2 commercial private equity funds, which will aim to leverage private co-investment. These funds will be run on a strictly commercial basis by professional fund managers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an equity investment of £110 million, the project will include technical assistance to support the development of the project pipeline and facilitate pioneering projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Private-investment-to-help-tackle-climate-change/"&gt;Private investment to help tackle climate change press release.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/5720-business-case-for-icf-support-for-the-climate-publ.pdf"&gt;Business case for ICF support of the Climate Public Private Partnership.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16444</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/asian-development-bank-solar-loan-guarantee-facility"/>
    <title>Asian Development Bank Solar Loan Guarantee Facility</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is helping unlock India’s huge solar energy potential.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; contributed £6 million to this scheme, which works by offsetting part of the financing cost of using &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.adb.org/"&gt;Asian Development Bank (ADB)&lt;/a&gt; guarantees on commercial loans for small-scale solar plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected to stimulate an estimated £265 million of private sector investment in clean energy generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/4781-business-case-for-india-solar-power-generation-gua.pdf"&gt;Business case for India Solar Power Generation Guarantee Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16453</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/partnership-for-market-readiness-pmr"/>
    <title>Partnership for Market Readiness (PMR)</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is supporting the development of marketing mechanisms to help middle-income countries reduce greenhouse gas emissions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; has given £7 million to the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;, which is a grant-based trust fund that helps middle-income countries develop and pilot market-based policies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt; brings together policy makers from governments with experts and stakeholders to provide a platform for piloting these market-based policies. It builds on developing countries’ own mitigation priorities and recipient countries include Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Mexico, China, Indonesia, Thailand, Turkey and the Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thepmr.org/"&gt;More about the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/pn_036/pn_036.aspx"&gt;Press notice: UK government to support developing countries in reducing their carbon emissions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/internationalclimatechange/5528-icf-support-for-world-bank-partnership-for-market-.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Climate Fund"&gt;ICF&lt;/abbr&gt; support for World Bank’s Partnership for Market Readiness.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/48343</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy in force for the East of England).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/39671</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T17:19:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/energy-performance-of-buildings-directive-article-8-equivalence-uk-biennial-reports"/>
    <title>Energy Performance of Buildings Directive article 8 equivalence - UK biennial reports</title>
    <summary>Equivalence reports produced by the Building Research Establishment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive, published in January 2003, is designed to improve the energy efficiency of buildings across Europe. Article 8 of the Directive is specifically aimed at improving the performance of heating systems. The directive offers two alternatives for implementing article 8: option (a) which involves the implementation of an inspection regime; or option (b) which involves the provision of advice, but this option can also include ‘alternative solutions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has chosen to adopt option (b) and has prepared biennial Article 8 equivalence reports to demonstrate that this approach has an impact that is ‘broadly equivalent’ to that produced through the provisions of option (a).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reports were produced in January 2008 and November 2010 and we are publishing them in the interests of transparency and as part of our Freedom of Information commitment to publish the results of all commissioned research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17618</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T09:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/green-bus-fund-round-4"/>
    <title>Green Bus Fund round 4</title>
    <summary>Guidance and bidding documents for bus operators and local authorities to submit bids for the 4th round of the Green Bus Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Bus Fund supports bus companies and local authorities in England to help them buy new low carbon buses. Its main purpose is to support and speed up the introduction of hundreds of low carbon buses across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bidding guidance and documents are intended for bus operators and local authorities who want to submit bids for grant under the 4th round of the government’s Green Bus Fund. The bidding guidance explains the eligibility terms, the bidding process and how bids should be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17572</id>
    <published>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/zero-carbon-for-new-non-domestic-buildings"/>
    <title>Zero carbon for new non-domestic buildings</title>
    <summary>Consultation about working towards the government's ambition for all new non-domestic buildings to be zero carbon from 2019.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out proposals for working towards the government’s ambition that all new non-domestic buildings should be zero carbon from 2019, with the public sector leading the way from 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/32963</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-green-belt-statistics-for-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Local authority green belt statistics for England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <summary>Statistics on designated green belt land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on the extent of the green belt in England were released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority on 30 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The extent of the designated green belt land in England in 2011/12 was estimated at 1,639,410 hectares, about 13% of the land area of England. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall there has been a decrease of 130 hectares from the revised 2010-11 green belt. This is due to three authorities who have adopted new plans in which they have changed the boundaries of the green belt. This represents a decrease of less than 0.01% per cent in the total green belt area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since these statistics were first compiled for 1997, there has been an increase in the area of green belt after taking account of the redesignation of some green belt as part of the New Forest National Park in 2005.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17341</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T13:09:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the South West Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194318/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationswrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the South West regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S6 from the ‘Somerset and Exmoor National Park joint structure plan’ relating to the green belt in North East Somerset. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the coalition agreement to safeguard the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
