<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/climate-change</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/climate-change.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Climate change"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60040</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:34:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-our-buildings"/>
    <title>Recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings. The requirements of the Directive were implemented on a phased basis by the Energy Performance of Buildings (Certificates and Inspections) (England and Wales) Regulations 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key requirements were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be produced on the sale, rent or construction of a building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;display energy certificate to be produced and displayed in large public buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;air conditioning equipment above a certain size to be inspected regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes have been made to the regulations, to transpose the requirements of a recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive in England and Wales. The main requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013 and are summarised below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;property advertisements to include details of energy performance certificate rating where available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no longer a requirement to attach front page of the energy performance certificate to written material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extension of current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m².  Unlike buildings larger than 1,000m²,  display energy certificates for smaller public buildings will be valid for 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² where one has been previously issued&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidance documents have been revised to reflect the changes and can be viewed via the links above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new regulations consolidate all existing regulations which have been revoked. They are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/" title="legislation.gov.uk"&gt;legislation.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by The Right Honourable Don Foster MP on changes to the building regulations regime in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57041</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:45:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-planning-authorities-on-implementing-planning-requirements-of-the-eu-waste-framework-directive-2008-98-ec"/>
    <title>Guidance for local planning authorities on implementing planning requirements of the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC)</title>
    <summary>A guidance note to ensure compliance with the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC) (‘the Directive’) provides an overarching legislative framework for the management of waste across Europe. This guidance note provides advice on the measures required by local planning authorities to ensure compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is aimed primarily at waste planning authorities, but it highlights the main legal and policy provisions of relevance to all planning authorities, and the action we expect them to take to assist them in ensuring compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be read alongside the government’s planning policy for waste management, currently set out in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;Planning Policy Statement 10&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-a-companion-guide-to-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;companion guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56834</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the north west plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919154703/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationnwrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the north west regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56725</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:32:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"/>
    <title>Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation guidance for suppliers</title>
    <summary>Seeking views on revised guidance about complying with the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation which take latest legislation into account.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of it comes from sustainable renewable sources. Guidance has been in place to assist suppliers with compliance since the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; was first introduced. Obligated suppliers are consulted each year on revisions to the guidance. These have taken into account the latest European and domestic legislative developments and experience in operating the obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"&gt;Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57003</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:29:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"/>
    <title>Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market</title>
    <summary>An assessment of the tallow market and impacts caused by changes to the way renewable energy targets are counted by EU member states.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport asked Ecofys to produce a report on the current animal fat (tallow) market to assess whether there has been any impact from allowing double counting of biodiesel produced from category 1 tallow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to explain the issue, the risks, and the available data relating to the tallow market to enable the department to set out its approach to monitoring impacts and also seek stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"&gt;Consultation about the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation suppliers’ guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56662</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:38:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change"/>
    <title>Taking international action to mitigate climate change</title>
    <summary>How we’re working with other countries to reduce global greenhouse gas emissions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the global average temperature rises more than 2°C above pre-industrial levels, significant negative impacts of climate change will be more likely and the cost of managing them will rise sharply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution led to an increase in greenhouse gas emissions caused by human activity. The Earth’s surface has consequently warmed by about 0.8°C since around 1900, with much of this warming occurring in the past 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have a 50% chance of keeping climate change to within 2°C of pre-industrial levels, global greenhouse gas emissions need to peak before 2020 and then decline steeply. The UK can’t make this happen on its own – the government has to work at an international level to make sure all countries do what is needed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/encouraging-the-eu-to-demonstrate-leadership-on-climate-change"&gt;encouraging the EU to demonstrate leadership on climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/international/negotiations/negotiations.aspx"&gt;negotiating for a comprehensive global climate change agreement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/What-we-do/Key-Issues/Climate-and-environment"&gt;reducing the impact of climate change in developing countries and the overseas territories&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing £2.9 billion through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/international-climate-fund-icf"&gt;International Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; to help developing countries mitigate and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financially supporting developing countries through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/reducing-emissions-from-deforestation-and-forest-degradation-redd"&gt;REDD+&lt;/a&gt; to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/leading-the-diplomatic-effort-to-mitigate-climate-change"&gt;leading the diplomatic effort to mitigate climate change&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;evidence base to understand and predict climate change&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/supporting-pages/scientific-evidence-to-help-us-understand-climate-change"&gt;scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; that climate change is happening and mainly due to increasing greenhouse gases emitted as a result of human activity, the UN negotiated a treaty at its Conference on Environment and Development in 1992. This treaty is known as the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/2860.php"&gt;United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (&lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; and the UK is one of the 195 parties to it. Parties to the convention meet annually at the Conference of the Parties (&lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-18-doha-2012"&gt;Conference of the Parties 18, Doha 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18 agreed to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;close 2 of the 3 parallel negotiating tracks so that future negotiations will all focus on the new agreement in 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a work plan for negotiation of a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/items/6240.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-17-durban-2011"&gt;Conference of the Parties 17, Durban 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17 agreed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/bodies/body/6645.php"&gt;Durban Platform for Enhanced Action&lt;/a&gt;, which aims to negotiate a new legally binding global climate change agreement by 2015 and increase action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions before the new agreement comes into force in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide in 2012 a second period of commitments under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/2830.php"&gt;Kyoto Protocol&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establish a board for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/durban_nov_2011/session/6294.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conference-of-the-parties-16-cancun-2010"&gt;Conference of the Parties 16, Cancun 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties at &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16 agreed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an overall 2°C target to limit temperature rise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to use the UN system to assess different countries’ actions against climate change &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on a system of measurement, reporting and verification to gauge how countries are meeting their promises to reduce greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to establish the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://gcfund.net/home.html"&gt;Green Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt; and help developing countries access low carbon technology and adapt to climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to halt, slow, and reverse the destruction of trees through the development of international rules and a monitoring system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/meetings/cancun_nov_2010/session/6254.php"&gt;Further information on the outcomes of &lt;abbr title="Conference of the Parties"&gt;COP&lt;/abbr&gt; 16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://unfccc.int/essential_background/items/6031.php"&gt;Further information on earlier Conferences of Parties to the &lt;abbr title="United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change"&gt;UNFCCC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16449</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/climate-public-private-partnership-cp3"/>
    <title>Climate Public Private Partnership (CP3)</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is helping to boost investment in climate projects in developing countries.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; will invest £130 million in 2 commercial private equity funds, which will aim to leverage private co-investment. These funds will be run on a strictly commercial basis by professional fund managers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an equity investment of £110 million, the project will include technical assistance to support the development of the project pipeline and facilitate pioneering projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Private-investment-to-help-tackle-climate-change/"&gt;Private investment to help tackle climate change press release.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/5720-business-case-for-icf-support-for-the-climate-publ.pdf"&gt;Business case for ICF support of the Climate Public Private Partnership.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16444</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/asian-development-bank-solar-loan-guarantee-facility"/>
    <title>Asian Development Bank Solar Loan Guarantee Facility</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is helping unlock India’s huge solar energy potential.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; contributed £6 million to this scheme, which works by offsetting part of the financing cost of using &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.adb.org/"&gt;Asian Development Bank (ADB)&lt;/a&gt; guarantees on commercial loans for small-scale solar plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected to stimulate an estimated £265 million of private sector investment in clean energy generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/4781-business-case-for-india-solar-power-generation-gua.pdf"&gt;Business case for India Solar Power Generation Guarantee Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16453</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/partnership-for-market-readiness-pmr"/>
    <title>Partnership for Market Readiness (PMR)</title>
    <summary>How the International Climate Fund (ICF) is supporting the development of marketing mechanisms to help middle-income countries reduce greenhouse gas emissions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; has given £7 million to the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;, which is a grant-based trust fund that helps middle-income countries develop and pilot market-based policies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt; brings together policy makers from governments with experts and stakeholders to provide a platform for piloting these market-based policies. It builds on developing countries’ own mitigation priorities and recipient countries include Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Mexico, China, Indonesia, Thailand, Turkey and the Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thepmr.org/"&gt;More about the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/pn_036/pn_036.aspx"&gt;Press notice: UK government to support developing countries in reducing their carbon emissions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/internationalclimatechange/5528-icf-support-for-world-bank-partnership-for-market-.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Climate Fund"&gt;ICF&lt;/abbr&gt; support for World Bank’s Partnership for Market Readiness.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
