<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/community-and-society</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Community and society"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13413</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-it-easier-to-set-up-new-town-and-parish-councils-discussion-paper"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils: discussion paper</title>
    <summary>Consultation about a range of measures to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils. This discussion paper presents a range of proposals that would help achieve this. We would like your views on these, as well as any other comments or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12777</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-future-of-the-citizenship-survey"/>
    <title>The future of the citizenship survey</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The citizenship survey is a face-to-face household survey carried out by the Department for Communities and Local Government covering a representative core sample of almost 10,000 adults in England and Wales each year, plus a minority ethnic boost sample of 5,000 and a Muslim boost sample of 1,200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statistical consultation sets out the intention to cancel the future citizenship survey, and in doing so, seeks to identify the uses of the survey data, the implications of stopping and options for alternative information sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12768</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-right-to-challenge--2"/>
    <title>Community Right to Challenge</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the provisions being made by government in the Localism Bill to introduce a Community Right to Challenge. It seeks views on the detail of how the right will work in practice, which will be set out in regulations. It also invites views on what type of support and guidance should be provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12769</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-right-to-bid"/>
    <title>Community Right to Bid</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the provisions being made by government in the Localism Bill to assist community organisations who wish to purchase assets of community value. It seeks views on the detail of how the scheme should be delivered, which will be set out in regulations. It also invites views on what type of support and guidance should be provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12765</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/sustainable-communities-act-2007-regulations"/>
    <title>Sustainable Communities Act 2007 regulations</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 December 2010 the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government issued a second invitation to local authorities under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007 (‘The Act’). He invited councils to consult people, ask them how they would like to see their local area improved and to take whatever action they see fit to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If councils, having consulted and reached agreement with their local communities, find that a bureaucratic barrier prevents them from taking action, they can submit a formal ‘proposal’ asking government to remove the barrier through the online portal at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). This portal is also open to anyone who wishes to ask the government to remove a barrier which is stopping local action. We would, for example, welcome requests to remove barriers from organisations such as town and parish councils, and County Associations of Parish Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act was amended in April 2010 to allow the procedures for receiving, considering and deciding proposals under the Act to be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act now allows the arrangements for the consideration of proposals submitted in response to the invitation to be set out in regulations, following a period of consultation. There will be no deadlines for the submission of proposals, which can now be submitted straight to the government at any time. Information on the action the government is taking on the proposals will be available online so that councils and communities can track progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act, and the proposed draft regulations set out in this consultation, is a means to hold government to account and ensure each proposal is given the fullest consideration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12755</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-use-of-restrictive-covenants-for-pubs"/>
    <title>The use of restrictive covenants for pubs</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation aims to establish an evidence base regarding the use of restrictive covenants which prevent pubs from being used as such once they are sold, and the impact that this has on local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responses to the consultation will be used by the government to help assess whether action needs to be undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12746</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/neighbourhood-planning-regulations--2"/>
    <title>Neighbourhood planning regulations</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill leaves various procedural and technical requirements of the neighbourhood planning system to regulations. This consultation seeks views on whether the proposed neighbourhood planning regulations are fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12724</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-policy-statement-for-part-2-of-the-localism-act-2011"/>
    <title>Proposed policy statement for part 2 of the Localism Act 2011</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is on a proposed policy statement for Part 2 of the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act provides a substantial and lasting shift in power away from central government and towards local people. The government has given public authorities more powers and freedoms to conduct their business and deliver services to the public. This includes a major reduction in the ‘oversight’ role of central government. Public authorities must, therefore, accept responsibility for the consequences of their actions or omissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2 of the Localism Act is about incentivising public authorities to comply with European law, in order to avoid any financial sanctions in the first place. The proposed policy statement sets out a fair, proportionate and reasonable approach for the use of Part 2. The statement has been developed with the Local Government Association and the Greater London Authority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12710</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposals-from-town-and-parish-councils-under-the-sustainable-communities-act-2007"/>
    <title>Proposals from town and parish councils under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 December 2010 the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government issued a second invitation to local authorities under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007. He invited local authorities to consult people, ask them how they would like to see their local area improved and to take appropriate action to make it happen. The Localism Act has given them far more freedom and flexibility to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If local authorities, having consulted and reached agreement with their local communities, find that a bureaucratic barrier prevents them from taking action, they can submit a formal ‘proposal’ under the Sustainable Communities Act 2007 asking Government to remove the barrier through the online portal at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;http://barrierbusting.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). This portal is also open to anyone who wishes to ask the government to remove a barrier which is stopping local action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation is seeking views on whether the existing arrangements for submitting barrier busting proposals are appropriate or whether town and parish councils should be able to submit proposals using the Sustainable Communities Act as well as local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14760</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-sends-her-best-wishes-on-diwali"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes on Diwali</title>
    <summary>On 13 November, Hindu, Jain and Sikh communities will gather to celebrate the Festival of Lights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister, Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes to all of those celebrating Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As people celebrate this special time in communities across the country, I send my warmest wishes to you all for a peaceful and happy Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Diwali provides an important opportunity for prayer and reflection as the festival which celebrates the victory of good over evil and light over darkness. It is a time for family and friends, the reaffirmation of hope and renewed commitment to friendship and goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In celebrating Diwali we can appreciate the diversity that characterises this country and also recognise the common values of compassion, honesty and goodwill in which we can all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As communities across the country begin their celebrations, I am delighted to wish everyone a very happy Diwali and a prosperous new year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
