<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/community-and-society</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Community and society"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16403</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T13:59:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nick-boles-attends-launch-of-national-business-competition"/>
    <title>Nick Boles attends launch of national business competition</title>
    <summary>Communities Minister sees young people being inspired through business at the launch of this year’s Mosaic Enterprise Challenge competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting Westminster City School, Nick Boles spoke to the winners of last year’s competition and saw the how they invented a winning product by taking part in an online business game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Nick Boles with last year’s winners" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1108/mosaicwinners2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Nick Boles speaking to students from Southfields Community College, winners of last year’s competition&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;School teams are supported by specialist business mentors to compete through the game, which places them into a realistic business situation in which they must develop and market a new product and respond to simulated business competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The competition aims to promote entrepreneurship and inspire knowledge and enthusiasm about business among young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mosaicnetwork.co.uk/en_gb/portal/enterprise-challenge"&gt;Enterprise Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the department, will this year involve over 3,000 students in 80 schools who will be supported by more than 300 mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Apax-Mosaic Enterprise Challenge is an excellent way of enabling pupils to learn practical business skills such as sales, marketing and finance from within the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fantastic to speak to last year’s competition winners and hear how they have benefited from taking part and how much they enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the Department is supporting this for another year and wish everyone taking part the best of luck.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632046112497/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16140</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/faith-minister-visits-temple-to-start-diwali-celebrations"/>
    <title>Faith Minister visits temple to start Diwali celebrations</title>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi joined spectators at a fireworks display to mark the start of Diwali celebrations at London’s famous Neasden Temple.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neasden Temple is the first traditional Hindu Mandir in Europe and the largest temple outside India. During her visit, the Faith and Communities Minister received a traditional welcome by the trustees of the temple and heard about their work before embarking on a tour of the building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She met volunteers and heard about the central role the temple plays within the local community and beyond - having attracted devotees and visitors from across the world since it opened in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was then invited to set off the spectacular fireworks display enjoyed by the thousands of people who had travelled to the temple to mark the beginning of Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every year I look forward to celebrating Diwali, the festival of lights, so it was a particular honour to mark it this year at the magnificent Neasden Temple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fascinating to hear about the central role the temple plays within the local community, from hosting school visits and organising charitable events - and how the Mandir has attracted devotees from all corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to the trustees and volunteers many hours of devotion and commitment and thank them for the warm hospitality I received during my visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632012718099/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14760</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-sends-her-best-wishes-on-diwali"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes on Diwali</title>
    <summary>On 13 November, Hindu, Jain and Sikh communities will gather to celebrate the Festival of Lights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister, Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes to all of those celebrating Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As people celebrate this special time in communities across the country, I send my warmest wishes to you all for a peaceful and happy Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Diwali provides an important opportunity for prayer and reflection as the festival which celebrates the victory of good over evil and light over darkness. It is a time for family and friends, the reaffirmation of hope and renewed commitment to friendship and goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In celebrating Diwali we can appreciate the diversity that characterises this country and also recognise the common values of compassion, honesty and goodwill in which we can all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As communities across the country begin their celebrations, I am delighted to wish everyone a very happy Diwali and a prosperous new year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16083</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T20:07:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/an-integration-nation-breaking-down-the-barriers"/>
    <title>An integration nation: breaking down the barriers</title>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi’s speech to Operation Black Vote at the Young Foundation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain wouldn’t be the place it is today without the contribution of people from ethnic minority backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the Commonwealth soldiers who served with the allies in the wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the immigrants, people like my dad, who came here to build up our industries in the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of our diverse communities contributing to every section of society today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of Mo Farah. Our national hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Mo crossed the finish line - twice - this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation got behind this London lad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one batted an eyelid over the fact that he was a Somali-born Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, this guy is British - very British.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he told one interviewer: “Look mate, this is where I grew up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is my country and when I put on my Great Britain vest I’m proud.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It said a lot about the diverse, integrated state of our country today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where everyone - black, white and brown - was proud to drape themselves in red, white and blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite great individual examples, there are still barriers to integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today this is more of a problem for us as a country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because today Britain is in a global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can’t just rely on Mo Farah to win this one for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a race that pits us against counties around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a huge challenge of global, economic competition that will determine our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have got a secret weapon to succeed in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The races from around the globe that make up Britain today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our diverse communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with links to places across the world, with business acumen and ideas, with cultural insight and experience and with endless untapped talent and networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s our duty - it’s crucial to our future - to unlock this potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it flies in the face of the survey in which 52% of people said that migrants in Britain were bad for our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I want to focus on what the barriers are to integration and how we can overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="barriers"&gt;Barriers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s look at the barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the things that stop people getting on with each other are the same as the things that stop them getting on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, integration and social mobility are inextricably linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ethnic minority groups have much lower levels of English than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15% of Bangladeshi and 12% of Pakistani women report having little or no English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research shows that English language is the second biggest predictor in occupational success, after qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And 60% of people believe that the biggest barrier to being integrated is not speaking the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to get on top of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution isn’t to throw money at translation and interpretation services or at teaching assistants for non-English speaking pupils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s helping more people to learn English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’m delighted at my department’s commitment to fund English language learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I want to see us go further, finding new and innovative ways to help people learn English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s a DVD at home, a CD in the car, a volunteer at the community centre, or an after-school club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because a common language is the fundamental basis of common understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just language that holds the key to integration. It’s also got to start in our schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were huge gaps in attainment on the basis of ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With British Caribbean, British Pakistani and British Roma children falling way behind the national average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means freeing up communities to start free schools in areas of deprivation, like the King’s Academy in Bradford, so that everyone, whatever their background, has access to the best schooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means supporting failing comprehensives to become Academies, so that hard done by catchment areas suddenly get the best facilities and the best chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also means changing the way we support and engage with different communities to bring them into the fold - not leave them out in the cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government has moved away from intervention on the basis of race towards increasing the impact of mainstream policies on minority communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backing mainstream organisations, like Youth United, which bring together people of all backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And championing National Citizens’ Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just funding national bodies, but also supporting local projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My good friend, the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government, Eric Pickles, has led the way in this endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spearheading the Big Lunch and the Bandstand Marathon, which have brought people together over food and music - shared experience in shared spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Championing A Year of Service and the Near Neighbours programme, which have united people of different faiths so they can make a difference, together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And driving forward the Localism Act, so people can bid to run local services and shape the areas in which they live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sends out a clear message to our BME communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No longer are you getting the crumbs off the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You now have a stake in the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="values"&gt;Values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, let’s look at our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people to integrate in our society, I think Britain needs to be better at asserting its values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2006, Tony Blair urged minority communities to adopt British values and to integrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he forgot to point out that Britain needs to be equally sure of its values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nation, we need to be stronger about asserting shared British principles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like freedom, fairness and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunity, aspiration and tolerance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing as you would be done by, being proud of the country in which you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we ask people to sign up to our values if we are not sure of them ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’ve been so outspoken on Britain remembering its Christian heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I went to the Vatican and called on Europe to assert its Christian identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Christian Britain was more sure of its own identity it would be less rejecting of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I believe this government’s pro-faith agenda has reflected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Britain, once again, growing confident of its Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I’ve been so outspoken on the need for schools to teach history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted that Michael Gove has put history at the heart of our curriculum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, as I’ve said for years, how can we know where we’re going if we don’t know where we come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not only must we assert our values - we must ensure those values are afforded to everyone, whatever their faith, colour or creed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long authorities have dismissed many of the more difficult issues facing minority communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some said “don’t meddle in these matters”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others steered well clear for fear of offending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been treating our communities like foreign embassies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where rules from abroad apply and wider society keeps well out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for too long, cultural sensitivities have often led our leaders to become morally blind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we’ve dealt with matters differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came to forced marriage, we said enough was enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the same with the issue of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a drug is harming a specific communities it’s not enough to say it’s part of their cultural practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s right to say they deserve the same protection from harmful drugs like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why for many years I have campaigned for the banning of khat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise we should come down equally hard on attitudes that can lead to tragic consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I spoke out on the issue of child sexual grooming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said that a small minority of predominantly Pakistani men thought women were second class citizens and white women were third class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if we shy away from the difficult issues in this country, however uncomfortable, we will never confront them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how can people integrate in a society when, in the name of cultural sensitivity, we continue to entrench barriers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="discrimination"&gt;Discrimination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, let’s look at discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discrimination, intolerance, prejudice and bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stamp these out if we want our society to be better integrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These un-British traits mean that at best some people feel they don’t belong and at worst their lives and livelihoods are under threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in 2010, we made it a requirement for all police forces to record anti-Semitic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are funding tighter security measures in Jewish faith schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We appointed the first UK Envoy for Post-Holocaust issues, Sir Andrew Burns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are funding the Holocaust Education Trust’s Lessons from Auschwitz project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And are committing further funds to the Holocaust Memorial Day Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more than that - we are now finally starting to tackle the more recent scourge of anti-Muslim hatred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we announced last week, we are funding the Measuring Anti-Muslim Attacks (MAMA) programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we established the Cross Government Anti-Muslim Hatred Group, allowing us to respond to the growing problem of Islamophobia, department by department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighting bigotry and intolerance is key to enable people to integrate, to participate and to reach their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-of-britain"&gt;Future of Britain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t afford to let people be held back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it by language, by education, by discrimination, by disengagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, Britain’s migrant communities are key to our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to sell Britain to the world than our diverse communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whose links extend from Ankara to Islamabad, from Shanghai to Saint-Lucia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to offer the world the products it wants?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Than the country that sells naan bread to India; canoes to the Eskimos; tacos to Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who better to rebalance our economy and accelerate our recovery?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Than some of our most can-do businessmen and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our diaspora communities and entrepreneurs hold the key to linking businesses across continents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Thatcher once said: “Britain is now, more than ever, a multicultural society: and I think that we are beginning to appreciate the challenges and opportunities for learning that this diversity offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new resilience derived from diversity can only strengthen Britain.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates show that our economy is missing out on £8.6 billion a year - probably more - from failing to fully empower people from ethnic minorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine what Britain could do if we unlocked all that untapped talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to break down these barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expose those opportunities and those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring people in from the sidelines, into the mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the young black British boy doesn’t think he’s more likely to fail at school and less likely to get on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But realises that he is not part of the problem, he’s part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron has called on us to become an aspiration nation if we want to win the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we also need to be an integration nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking away those barriers that stop people playing their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asserting shared British values – and affording everyone those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing discrimination, tackling bigotry and hatred, wherever they arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, crucially, unlocking the full talent of Britain’s diversity - a diversity which is so essential to our country’s future prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14067</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/troubled-families-case-studies"/>
    <title>Troubled families case studies</title>
    <summary>This document describes how families were helped in Sheffield, Bradford, Lancashire, Leeds and Norfolk. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work with family intervention projects can make a significant difference to families’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14281</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:39:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-congratulate-the-new-archbishop-of-canterbury"/>
    <title>Ministers congratulate the new Archbishop of Canterbury</title>
    <summary>Eric Pickles and Baroness Warsi congratulate Justin Welby on his appointment as Archbishop of Canterbury.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Congratulations to the Right Reverend Justin Welby on his appointment as Archbishop of Canterbury following Dr Rowan Williams’ decade of guidance and leadership for the Church of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Archbishop can offer a unique perspective as an ex-businessman, following many years experience in a commercial environment, and that of previously serving as a parish priest, Dean of Liverpool and Bishop of Durham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish him every success and know that, with the challenges that will come, he will draw upon his diverse experience and demonstrate dedication to the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Church of England plays a valued and important role in the culture and constitution of our nation and I very much look forward to meeting the Archbishop soon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to welcome the Right Reverend Justin Welby as the newly appointed Archbishop of Canterbury and would like to wish him well following Dr Rowan Williams’ successful decade as leader of the Anglican church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With experience of both the business and religious world, he can bring a wide range of skills to his new role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to meeting him and discussing the ways in which the government and the church can continue to work together to improve local communities and increase interactions across all religions.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13584</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:55:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-calls-on-mosques-to-encourage-hate-crime-reporting"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi calls on mosques to encourage hate crime reporting</title>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi is to call on mosques to encourage victims of anti-Muslim hate crime to come forward.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Senior Minister for Faith at the Department for Communities and Local Government is to write to all imams to urge them to do more to tackle the problem in their areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures show there have been nearly 500 recorded incidents of anti-Muslim attacks in England since a new government-funded helpline was established in February this year to monitor them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Baroness Warsi, who argued last year that Islamophobia had “passed the dinner table test”, believes that the real figure may be much higher, with victims feeling unsupported to come forward or believing that reporting will not be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the minister will say that mosques can play a crucial part in helping victims have confidence that attacks will be treated seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mosques can encourage members, through notices and talks, to report any incidents of hate crime,” she will say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just as important, the mosque’s management team can put in place a register to monitor incidents and arrange to communicate this information to the police in the first instance. I know that more mosques are already doing these things, but some mosques could do more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She will add that, as well as enabling more prosecutions, clear and accurate data can help build a case for stronger action to be taken by all authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For me, statistics are a vital first step to tackling this issue and engaging the relevant agencies to do more to persuade others of the seriousness of the problem and do more about it,” she will say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The data still needs to be validated, but early indications are that nearly 60% of reported religious hate crime in 2011 was directed at Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That shows the scale of the problem, but we need better reporting and recording and more community awareness to allow us to build up a complete picture.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16048</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/bringing-people-together-in-strong-united-communities"/>
    <title>Bringing people together in strong, united communities</title>
    <summary>We're promoting widespread social integration in communities and encouraging them to identify shared aspirations and values.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to achieve more integrated communities and to create the conditions for everyone to live and work successfully alongside each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integration is a vital local issue and requires a local response. Although government has an important role to play, we want local communities to identify the issues which affect their area and to shape their own response.	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that people can come together in strong, united communities if we encourage and support them to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have shared aspirations and values&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have a strong sense of mutual commitments and obligations, promoting personal and social responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take part in local and national life and decision-making &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fulfil their potential to get on in life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;challenge extremism and hate crime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We believe that action to achieve strong communities is usually most effective when it is led by the people it most concerns. But in a few cases government also provides funding and support for activities to demonstrate ways to promote community integration. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/bringing-people-together-in-strong-united-communities/supporting-pages/projects-to-support-strong-communities" title="Projects to support strong communities"&gt;These projects&lt;/a&gt; are in partnership with businesses, voluntary organisations and communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tackling-extremism-and-hate-crime"&gt;Tackling extremism and hate crime&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to ensuring that everyone has the freedom to live free from hostility or harassment. 
Projects aimed at tackling extremism and intolerance include: working with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.annefrank.org.uk/" title="Anne Frank Trust website"&gt;Anne Frank Trust&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.srtrc.org/" title="Show Racism the Red Card website"&gt;Show Racism the Red Card&lt;/a&gt; to help educate young people on the dangers of racism; work by the Searchlight Educational Trust to build local communities’ resilience to extremist far right narratives; and support to Measuring Anti-Muslim Attacks (&lt;abbr title="Measuring Anti-Muslim Attacks (MAMA)"&gt;MAMA&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="promoting-faith-and-the-freedom-to-pray"&gt;Promoting faith and the freedom to pray&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith groups are involved in a huge range of activities and projects to improve communities, and we are providing them support to promote and celebrate their faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have given all major local councils in England a ‘general power of competence’. This should give them the freedom to include prayers as part of their formal meetings, if they wish. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-adults-with-english-language-skills"&gt;Helping adults with English language skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re providing funding to support English language provision for those adults who are not in employment or are actively seeking employment and are unable to afford the cost of language classes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reducing-inequalities-faced-by-the-gypsy-and-traveller-community"&gt;Reducing inequalities faced by the Gypsy and Traveller community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up a dedicated ministerial group in November 2011 to coordinate action across government to help improve the life chances of Gypsies and Traveller communities. In April 2012, the group published a progress report that includes 28 commitments from across government that will help service providers to work more effectively with these communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="future-actions"&gt;Future actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promoting-understanding-of-british-life-and-values"&gt;Promoting understanding of British life and values&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking at how the settlement and citizenship process and ‘Life in the UK Test’ can better promote an understanding not just of English language, but also of British life and of the values and principles which underlie British society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="supporting-ethnic-minority-entrepreneurs"&gt;Supporting ethnic minority entrepreneurs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at what more could be done to support ethnic minority entrepreneurs, including examining any barriers to black and ethnic minority groups accessing business finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/creating-the-conditions-for-a-more-integrated-society" title="Creating the conditions for integration"&gt;Creating the conditions for integration&lt;/a&gt; in February 2012. This set out our approach to creating integrated communities, which is achieved in part through promoting social mobility and equality of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="social-mobility"&gt;Social mobility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2011, the government published its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files_dpm/resources/opening-doors-breaking-barriers.pdf" title="Social mobility strategy"&gt;social mobility strategy&lt;/a&gt;
In May 2012, we published an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files_dpm/resources/HMG_SocialMobility_acc.pdf" title="Update to the social mobility strategy"&gt;update on the social mobility strategy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="equality"&gt;Equality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2010, the government published its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/equalities/equality-strategy-publications/equality-strategy/" title="Equality strategy"&gt;equality strategy.&lt;/a&gt;
On 22 May 2012, we published a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/equalities/equality-strategy-publications/progress-report" title="progress report on the equality strategy"&gt;progress report on the equality strategy.&lt;/a&gt; This describes how the new approach to equality is beginning to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/creating-the-conditions-for-a-more-integrated-society" title="Creating the conditions for integration"&gt;Creating the conditions for integration&lt;/a&gt; sets out our views on what is important to promote integrated communities, but does not represent the end of the process. We will continue to discuss our approach with partners and help them to take action in response to the issues raised in the document. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011 on www.legislation.gov.uk"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;  introduces new rights for communities to take greater control in their local areas.
The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents" title="Equality Act 2010 on www.legislation.gov.uk"&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt; bans unfair treatment and helps achieve equal opportunities in the workplace and in wider society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16432</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:09:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:09:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood"/>
    <title>Giving people more power over what happens in their neighbourhood</title>
    <summary>We're giving local communities new rights so that local people can come together to influence public services and planning decisions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long communities have not had a big enough say in what happens in their local area – whether it be about what happens to local amenities, how local services are delivered, or how new development is planned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) is taking action to give local communities new rights. These rights will give community, voluntary and charity groups the opportunity to take the initiative when it comes to how local public services are run and planning decisions are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are offering support to groups who want to use these new rights – providing information, guidance and funding to help them navigate and exercise the rights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-right-to-bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid" title="Community Right to Bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt; will give community groups the right to prepare and bid to buy community buildings and facilities that are important to them. It came into effect on 21 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-right-to-challenge"&gt;Community Right to Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-challenge" title="Community Right to Challenge"&gt;Community Right to Challenge&lt;/a&gt; allows voluntary and community groups, charities, parish councils and local authority staff to bid to run a local authority service where they believe they can do so differently and better. This may be the whole service or part of a service. It came into force on 27 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning" title="Neighbourhood planning"&gt;neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; measures allow communities to shape new development by coming together to prepare neighbourhood plans. They came into force on 6 April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-right-to-build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; allows local communities to propose small-scale, site-specific, community-led developments. It came into force on 6 April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-right-to-reclaim-land"&gt;Community Right to Reclaim Land&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-reclaim-land" title="Community Right to Reclaim Land"&gt;Community Right to Reclaim Land&lt;/a&gt; helps communities to improve their local area by giving them the right to ask that under-used or unused land owned by public bodies is brought back into beneficial use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="design-support-for-communities"&gt;Design support for communities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re supporting an industry-led review to help in putting together a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/design-support-for-communities" title="Design support for communities"&gt;cross-sector package of design support for communities.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/13875</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:00:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:00:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around"/>
    <title>Helping troubled families turn their lives around</title>
    <summary>We're working with local authorities and their partners to help solve and prevent troubled families' problems in the long term</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troubled families are those that have problems and cause problems to the community around them, putting high costs on the public sector. The government is committed to working with local authorities and their partners to help 120,000 troubled families in England turn their lives around by 2015. We want to ensure the children in these families have the chance of a better life, and at the same time bring down the cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Troubled Families programme government will work alongside local authorities to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get children back into school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce youth crime and anti-social behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;put adults on a path back to work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce the high costs these families place on the public sector each year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will encourage local authorities to work with families in ways the evidence shows is more effective, such as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joining up local services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dealing with each family’s problems as a whole rather than responding to each problem, or person, separately &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointing a single key worker to get to grips with the family’s problems and work intensively with them to change their lives for the better for the long term &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using a mix of methods that support families and challenge poor behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is increasing local authority budgets by £448 million over 3 years on a payment-by-results basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Troubled Families programme was launched by the Prime Minister in 2011 and is led by Louise Casey &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Order of Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Troubled Families team, based in &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;, has been established to join up efforts across the whole of government and to provide expert help to local authorities to drive forward the programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team has been drawn from across government departments and includes a Director of Children’s Services with wide experience of family intervention on secondment from local government, as well as staff with a background in other areas of local government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government data collected in October and November 2011 estimated that £9 billion is spent annually on troubled families – an average of £75,000 per family each year. Of this, an estimated £8 billion is spent reacting to the problems these families have and cause with just £1 billion being spent on helping families to solve and prevent problems in the longer term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 18 July 2012 Louise Casey &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Order of Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families" title="Listening to troubled families"&gt;report highlighting the chaotic personal histories&lt;/a&gt; of the kinds of families who are eligible as part of the government’s commitment to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.education.gov.uk/publications/RSG/AllRsgPublications/Page11/DFE-RR174" title="Monitoring and evaluation of family intervention projects and services (February 2007 to March 2011)"&gt;An evaluation report&lt;/a&gt; by the National Centre for Social Research shows that intensive intervention to support and challenge troubled families is effective in turning round their lives – a family getting intensive support and challenge is twice as likely to stop anti-social behaviour as one not getting the intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/troubled-families-case-studies" title="Troubled families: case studies"&gt;family intervention work with troubled families&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/sets/72157628427403485" title="Why we need to turn troubled families around"&gt;There are compelling reasons for turning troubled families around&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities have been involved with the work of the Troubled Families team from the start – giving their views on the design of the programme, the payment-by-results financial framework and the ways of working with families which will bring about most success. The team has held workshops and meetings to enable all local authorities to have their say and work through ideas and queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixteen families were interviewed by Louise Casey in person for her report and were sourced by 6 local authorities and family intervention services across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the interviews was to listen to families talk about their lives and the problems they have experienced (and caused) to begin to understand how best they can be helped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey has also consulted many local authority, charity and family workers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
