<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/community-and-society</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Community and society"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T12:52:08+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64224</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T12:52:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/why-we-must-continue-to-tackle-far-right-extremism-head-on"/>
    <title>Why we must continue to tackle far right extremism head on</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Don Foster to council leaders at the first meeting of the national special interest group on the far right.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all - thank you for inviting me here today and thank you for the work you are doing for each of your councils. I would have loved to have stayed for the whole day but I am told that you have a lot of work to do and so I am looking forward to hearing how the day went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremism is an affront to our society in every form, including the far right and the English Defence League (&lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt;) - they are divisive and create fear in our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right does not belong in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially following a year when the Olympics changed the way we see ourselves - gave us real confidence as a society with shared values. The Olympics showed how brilliantly our communities can come together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We basked in the glory of our country’s sporting success stories, whatever their background, skin colour or religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the Secretary of State is passionate about tackling extremism - his commitment is shared by the Prime Minster, the Deputy Prime Minister and across government - everyone is sickened by the messages and activities of the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; and their ilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us share a personal commitment to tackling them. In fact one of the reasons I came into politics was because many years ago the National Front were allowed to hire my children’s school to use as a meeting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their ugly messages and actions could not go ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I campaigned against them to get them out of my children’s school and back into the wilderness where they belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we have the English Defence League marching up and down our streets on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causing local shops and businesses to lose money just when they are struggling with the downturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And causing fear across our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/creating-the-conditions-for-a-more-integrated-society"&gt;Creating the conditions for integration&lt;/a&gt;’ published last February, the government set out its approach to creating and sustaining strong communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major part of the approach is to tackle extremism and intolerance head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right must be isolated, undermined, outflanked and subject to the ridicule they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we are working in schools with 10,000 students across the country to give them the tools to reject the far-right’s messages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we are working with communities in Dudley, Croydon, Barking and Luton, training volunteers to produce community newspapers for 14,000 families that provide an alternative voice to the far right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the government is supporting over 30 projects as part of our integration strategy - you have copies today. We need to invest now to reduce the costs and impacts generated by the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that it is only at local level that we can really address the conditions the far right feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we were so pleased when Blackburn with Darwen and Luton came to us and asked for our help to set up and run this national special interest group on the far right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is through the leadership of councils like Luton, Blackburn and many others that we will ultimately succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already know that there is a lot of good work going on in places up and down the country:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in Luton they have the ‘Luton in Harmony’ campaign involving nearly 70,000 Luton residents saying loud and clear that they do not want the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in their towns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Blackburn they have the ‘hundred voice’ campaign, which puts people at extreme ends of the spectrum of opinions in the same room as each other to thrash it out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are fantastic innovative responses to the challenges we face by the far right but even more is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is critical if we are to succeed in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you that the far right has taken a battering but is still on the move - they haven’t managed to attract the numbers of supporters on marches that they did in their heyday in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to this year, we expect that the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue to decline in numbers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will still manage to get enough supporters out for marches in towns and cities across 2013 - enough to cause disruption and fear.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know that there are splinter groups appearing across the country threatening flash demonstrations and direct action - the Infidels and the English Volunteer Force are just two examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the good work that local authorities and the police have done in minimising the impacts of these people has had an effect but clearly as I said there is more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is absolutely critical in succeeding in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this leadership look like? What does it do? How does it keep its head above the parapet at all times, not just in the run up to &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; demonstrations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is what we are here for today. I would encourage you all to look at the 30 or so projects the government is supporting. These projects include everything from music projects bringing different communities together for a common purpose, to looking at getting scouts and cadets groups in more areas, particularly areas where they may not have existed before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As leaders in your communities you will know this better than us. We look forward to hearing the ideas you come up with and to you sharing them with those leaders who couldn’t make it here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am interested in hearing proposals for innovative projects for undermining extremists of all stripes, so please share your ideas with me and we will see what we can do to support you. There may even be some money for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60117</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-everyone-a-happy-christmas"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish everyone a happy Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for Christmas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the year draws to a close and families up and down the country get ready to celebrate Christmas, we should all be immensely proud of the vital role that churches play in our neighbourhoods and the special place the Christian faith holds in our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our Christian communities have a strong tradition of giving back and improving the lives of those around them, as I saw for myself at a harvest festival service at London’s Borough Market where food and clothing was donated to the homeless, regardless of faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to those who will be selflessly helping others this year, whether through volunteering in a soup-kitchen or collecting and donating gifts - these generous acts make a real difference within our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The upcoming holiday is a strong reminder of the Christian ethos within our country and I wish a very merry Christmas to one and all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith and Communities Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Minister for Faith and Communities I would like to send my warmest wishes to everyone this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Christmas is an extremely special time for Britain, a country where the majority of people identify themselves as Christian. None of us should forget that, amid the turkeys, the tinsel and all the traditions that accompany this festival, lies the true meaning of Christmas: the birth of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a time for goodwill and generosity, reflection and redemption. These are themes we can all celebrate - people of all faiths and of none, who break their busy routines to come together with families and friends in the spirit of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Christmas let’s also remember the positive impact of faith on society and think about those who face persecution for holding a belief. Let’s also be confident in Britain’s Christianity, as I said when I led the largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See earlier this year. We cannot erase this faith from our history any more than we can erase the spires from our landscapes - or, indeed, the stars from the tops of our trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wishing everyone a very merry Christmas and a happy, peaceful New Year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56690</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/louise-casey-calls-for-family-intervention-approach"/>
    <title>Louise Casey calls for family intervention approach</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The head of the Troubled Families programme has endorsed family intervention as the most effective way to turn problem families around and help them get on in life.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a look at the academic evidence, alongside consultation with practitioners and families themselves, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/louise-casey"&gt;Louise Casey&lt;/a&gt; today published a new report that shows the life-changing results that good family intervention can have on even the most challenging households, along with a guide to best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;‘Working with Troubled Families’ report&lt;/a&gt; outlines that family intervention reduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involvement in anti-social behaviour by 59%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;involvement in crime by 45%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truancy, exclusion, bad behaviour at school by 52%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also points to the 5 key features of effective family intervention being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated worker, dedicated to a family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ‘hands on’ support &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a persistent, assertive and challenging approach &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;considering the family as a whole - gathering the intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common purpose and agreed action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey is now calling on councils to review their own ways of working with troubled families and adopt these principles in order to ensure that the significant momentum that has built up behind the programme - with all eligible local authorities in England on board and committed to working with over 40,000 families in this financial year - continues in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to push on with this work and make further progress towards the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015, the Department for Communities and Local Government will also be holding a series of training academies for local authorities in the new year to help share best practice on family intervention and provide masterclasses from some of its leading exponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the government’s Troubled Families programme Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My last report was about listening to troubled families themselves and some of the stories from families were truly appalling. However these were families successfully going through family intervention and the results were impressive - so I wanted to ensure that this practice is adopted as widely as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This report makes a strong case about what works - family intervention that involves one dedicated worker for each family, providing tough but persistent challenge and support, has a dramatic impact, not just on the life chances of those within the families, but on the communities around them who suffer from the effects of truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This important piece of work is a crucial step towards building a wide campaign of support behind the work we are doing to break an inter-generational cycle of misery and failure with these families. It will put rocket boosters under the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around 120,000 troubled families by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Effective family intervention also demonstrates that savings can be made for taxpayers by putting families back on the right track for the long run, rather than wasting money on simply reacting to their problems. We must have aspiration for every family and this work will reach all corners of the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Clare Tickell, Chief Executive of Action for Children, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since developing the initial model, we’ve seen how family intervention can really help vulnerable families facing multiple difficulties in their lives. It works by forming effective relationships with families and building on their strengths. This timely guide is a welcome resource, which will help people understand the key features of the model, learn what really works and ensure that projects are delivered to a high quality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;Working with Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"&gt;Listening to Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, July 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All eligible local authorities are running troubled families programmes in their area and between them have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is today also publishing management information on the work of family intervention projects and services in England up to 31 March 2012. This reports the latest data at a national level for all participating family intervention services. It includes information on the families worked with and the percentage of families considered to have a successful outcome in relation to family functioning and risk, crime/ anti-social behaviour, health and education/ employment. This data was collected by the National Centre for Social Research (NatCen) which ran a secure web-based information system into which family intervention project staff recorded details of the families they worked with between 2007-2012. It can be found at Annex B of the ‘Working With Troubled Families’ report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56541</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"/>
    <title>Working with Troubled Families: a guide to evidence and good practice</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities and their partners on how to work with troubled families.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a tool to help local authorities and their partners, who have asked for guidance on how best to work with troubled families, and for the evidence about family intervention to be brought together in one place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report looks at academic evidence, local evaluations of practice, what practitioners have told us works in their services and what families tell us makes this work different and successful for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/39665</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services"/>
    <title>Ensuring the future of the universal postal service and Post Office network services</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is making sure there will always be a universal postal service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universal postal service - the six-day-a-week, one-price-goes-anywhere service to every address in the UK - is important for communities and the economy. The government needs to make sure the future of the service is secure and that everyone continues to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Post Office network is a unique national asset that provides convenient access to vital social and economic services to local communities across the UK. It needs to be maintained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wholly owns both Royal Mail Group Ltd (which provides the universal postal service in the UK) and Post Office Ltd (which runs the network of post offices). This shareholding is managed by the Shareholder Executive in the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;Attracting private capital into Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect the future of the universal postal service, we aim to end Royal Mail’s dependence on unpredictable funding from the taxpayer by attracting private capital into the company.  We intend to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;sell shares in Royal Mail&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;Funding and modernising the Post Office network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have committed £1.34 billion of funding for the network from financial year 2011 to 2012 to financial year 2014 to 2015. This will enable the Post Office to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;maintain and modernise its network&lt;/a&gt; to help safeguard its future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="separating-the-post-office-and-royal-mail"&gt;Separating the Post Office and Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Mail and the Post Office are different businesses, facing different challenges. In order to maintain the Post Office in public ownership and enable private sector investment in the Royal Mail letters and parcels business, we separated Post Office Ltd from Royal Mail Group Ltd in April 2012 to become a sister company of Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that the two companies will no longer work together. The Chief Executive of Royal Mail has called it “unthinkable” that there would not always be a strong relationship between Royal Mail and the Post Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure the continuation of their existing business relationship, at the time of separation, the management of Royal Mail and the Post Office put in place a commercial contract between the two parties (with the longest possible contract length permitted by law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-royal-mail-pensions"&gt;Funding Royal Mail pensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 1 April 2012 we transferred Royal Mail’s historic liabilities of around £40 billion from Royal Mail’s pension scheme to a new public sector scheme (the Royal Mail Statutory Pension Scheme, RMSPS) to be administered by the government.  At the same time around £28 billion of Royal Mail’s pension assets were transferred to government. The pension scheme left with Royal Mail was left with matching assets and liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-the-regulator"&gt;Changing the regulator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From October 2011 we transferred regulatory responsibility for the postal market from Postcomm to Ofcom, the regulator responsible for the wider communications sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012 Ofcom put in place new regulations for postal services for the next 7 years. Ofcom’s primary duty is to make sure there continues to be a universal postal service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/coalition-documents"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt; we said we would aim to inject private capital into Royal Mail, and explore opportunities for employee ownership. We also pledged to retain Post Office Ltd in public ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the request of the Business Secretary Vince Cable, Richard Hooper CBE, the former deputy chairman of Ofcom, updated his December 2008 report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file49389.pdf"&gt;Modernise or decline&lt;/a&gt; on the maintenance of the universal postal service in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hooper made three main recommendations in his September 2010 report, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/saving-the-royal-mails-universal-postal-service-in-the-digital-age-an-update-of-the-2008-independent-review"&gt;Saving the Royal Mail’s universal postal service in the digital age&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Royal Mail should have access to private sector capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its historic pension deficit should be resolved; its deficit of £8 billion sapped cash from the business, making it difficult to compete with other operators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way postal services are regulated needed to be better balanced so as to allow competition whilst ensuring the universal service remains available  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We agreed and introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; to implement the recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 we &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/post-office-mutualisation"&gt;consulted on the move towards an agreed model for a mutual Post Office&lt;/a&gt;. Our response to the consultation was published in July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two Acts specifically cover postal services in the UK:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;, which lifted restrictions on the ownership of Royal Mail, allowed for a future mutual ownership model for Post Office Limited (ie ownership across a mix of invested stakeholders, such as employees, subpostmasters and consumers, with no one party having an overall majority), enabled the transfer of the Royal Mail’s historic pension liabilities to government and put the framework in place to deliver a new regulatory regime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/26/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; - some of which was replaced or amended by the 2011 Act - has a number of important provisions still in force. These include provisions relating to offences in relation to the mail, the schemes (ie setting out details of services’ terms and conditions) of universal service providers, application of customs and excise legislation to postal packets, and financing and restructuring of the Royal Mail group of companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU Postal Services Directives require member states to ensure the provision of a universal postal service.  The requirements of the directives are implemented in UK law by the above Postal Services Acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/"&gt;Ofcom&lt;/a&gt; - the independent regulator and competition authority for the UK’s communications industries, and its responsibilities now include the postal sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consumerfocus.org.uk/"&gt;Consumer Focus&lt;/a&gt; - champions the needs of consumers, across markets, including the postal services sector, with a particular regard to the vulnerable, including those who have been or are about to be disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60886</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-shareholder-executive-publications"/>
    <title>The Shareholder Executive: publications</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Working with shareholder departments in government to improve fundamentally the government’s capabilities and performance as a shareholder.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="senior-team"&gt;Senior team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_61576"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/thumbnail_shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf"&gt;Shareholder Executive: Senior team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;173 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="portfolio-unit"&gt;Portfolio unit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_61575"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-61575-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/thumbnail_shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-61575-accessibility-help"&gt;Shareholder Executive: Portfolio Unit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;247 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;36 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-61575-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:Shareholder.Executive@bis.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Shareholder%20Executive%3A%20Portfolio%20Unit%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Shareholder%20Executive%3A%20Portfolio%20Unit%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;Shareholder.Executive@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Shareholder Executive: Portfolio Unit").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50196</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for the Jewish holiday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish community has made, and continues to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>A report setting out the progress the government is making to 'decentralise' power from Whitehall across the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18642</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-announces-150-000-to-boost-great-british-pubs"/>
    <title>Minister announces £150,000 to boost Great British pubs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Community Pubs Minister Brandon Lewis has announced £150,000 funding for the Pub in The Hub community services project.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement followed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pubisthehub.org.uk/"&gt;Pub is The Hub&lt;/a&gt; ‘10 Years On’ event on 5 December 2012 where the minister was a keynote speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke about the key role pubs play in the social and economic life of many communities, often as community hubs, local service providers and a place where community relationships are formed and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to say that pubs contribute, on average, £100,000 per pub to the local economy as well as being strong sources of local employment for younger people to get involved in an entrepreneurial and innovative industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community pubs minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to announce we are giving Pub is The Hub £150,000 for their project. The government is taking decisive action to support community pubs including doubling business rate relief, which gives up to 100% discounts for small firms including pubs and postponing revaluation will also avoid local pubs facing an 11% rise in their business rates bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is on top of abolishing the last government’s cider tax, cutting red tape on live music in pubs and stopping unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price by supermarkets. We have given councils powers to offer local business rate discounts and the Community Right to Bid lets communities protect their pubs and guard against their unnecessary loss.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to see community pubs thriving everywhere and has introduced a series of measures to support them including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to introduce local business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, the department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17574</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:27:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As part of inter-faith week, the winners have been announced for the Faith Through a Lens photography competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;'There but for the Grace of God'. Picture: Rob Boler&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and the other winners and finalists in the competition can be found on the awards and highlights section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ftal.staged.ws/awards-highlights-from-2012/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Together in Service event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632131148440/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
