<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/community-and-society</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Community and society"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T12:20:49+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/64315</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:20:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:20:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around"/>
    <title>Helping troubled families turn their lives around</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>We're working with local authorities and their partners to help solve and prevent troubled families' problems in the long term</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troubled families are those that have problems and cause problems to the community around them, putting high costs on the public sector. The government is committed to working with local authorities and their partners to help 120,000 troubled families in England turn their lives around by 2015. We want to ensure the children in these families have the chance of a better life, and at the same time bring down the cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Troubled Families programme, the government will work alongside local authorities to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get children back into school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce youth crime and anti-social behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;put adults on a path back to work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce the high costs these families place on the public sector each year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will encourage local authorities to work with families in ways the evidence shows is more effective, such as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joining up local services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dealing with each family’s problems as a whole rather than responding to each problem, or person, separately &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointing a single key worker to get to grips with the family’s problems and work intensively with them to change their lives for the better for the long term &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using a mix of methods that support families and challenge poor behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is increasing local authority budgets by £448 million over 3 years on a payment-by-results basis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Troubled Families programme was launched by the Prime Minister in 2011 and is led by Louise Casey &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Order of Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Troubled Families team, based in &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;, has been established to join up efforts across the whole of government and to provide expert help to local authorities to drive forward the programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team has been drawn from across government departments and includes a Director of Children’s Services with wide experience of family intervention on secondment from local government, as well as staff with a background in other areas of local government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government data collected in October and November 2011 estimated that £9 billion is spent annually on troubled families – an average of £75,000 per family each year. Of this, an estimated £8 billion is spent reacting to the problems these families have and cause with just £1 billion being spent on helping families to solve and prevent problems in the longer term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 18 July 2012 Louise Casey &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Order of Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families" title="Listening to troubled families"&gt;report highlighting the chaotic personal histories&lt;/a&gt; of the kinds of families who are eligible as part of the government’s commitment to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.education.gov.uk/publications/RSG/AllRsgPublications/Page11/DFE-RR174" title="Monitoring and evaluation of family intervention projects and services (February 2007 to March 2011)"&gt;An evaluation report&lt;/a&gt; by the National Centre for Social Research shows that intensive intervention to support and challenge troubled families is effective in turning round their lives – a family getting intensive support and challenge is twice as likely to stop anti-social behaviour as one not getting the intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 15 December 2012 the Troubled Families team published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;report which looked at the academic evidence&lt;/a&gt; underpinning family intervention techniques and how effective they can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/troubled-families-case-studies" title="Troubled families: case studies"&gt;family intervention work with troubled families&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/number10gov/sets/72157628427403485" title="Why we need to turn troubled families around"&gt;There are compelling reasons for turning troubled families around&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities have been involved with the work of the Troubled Families team from the start – giving their views on the design of the programme, the payment-by-results financial framework and the ways of working with families which will bring about most success. The team has held workshops and meetings to enable all local authorities to have their say and work through ideas and queries. The team is also &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-troubled-families-turn-their-lives-around/supporting-pages/training-the-troubled-families-workforce"&gt;consulting training organisations to make sure that local authorities can get appropriate training materials.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixteen families were interviewed by Louise Casey in person for her report and were sourced by 6 local authorities and family intervention services across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the interviews was to listen to families talk about their lives and the problems they have experienced (and caused) to begin to understand how best they can be helped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey has also consulted many local authority, charity and family workers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65293</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-to-receive-cash-boost-for-choosing-development"/>
    <title>Communities to receive cash boost for choosing development</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles announces new cash incentives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities that tackle the legacy of inadequate house-building and choose to accept new housing will benefit directly from new generous cash incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods that take a proactive approach by drawing up a neighbourhood development plan, and securing the consent of local people in a referendum, will receive 25% of the revenues from the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; arising from the development that they choose to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cash boost will be paid directly to parish and town councils and can be used to back the community’s priorities for example to re-roof a village hall, refurbish a municipal pool or take over a community pub. Neighbourhoods without a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood development plan&lt;/a&gt; but where the levy is still charged will still receive a capped 15% share of the levy revenue arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities without a parish or town council will still benefit from this incentive, with the local planning authority retaining it and spending it in accordance with the wishes of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of hectoring people and forcing development on communities, the government believes that we need to persuade communities that development is in everyone’s interest. Incentives are key to getting the homes built that we both need for today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital this country increases the number of homes it builds to meet the needs of its increasing population. The failure of previous administrations to build enough homes, latterly despite the credit boom, led to a severe housing shortage that has been made worse by the rapid increase in the number of households. The number of people living alone has rocketed, and immigration has led to an influx of 1.7 million people into England in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to tackle this housing shortage and make best use of what we already have the government has invested £160 million to deal with the 250,000 homes empty for more than 6 months - 50,000 fewer then in 2009. This money combined with a share of £300 million announced in September’s housing growth package, will help put more than 15,000 empty homes back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also made clear that planning should encourage the effective use of land, including brownfield land that is not of high environmental value. The majority of all new homes - 76% of those completed in 2010 - were built on brownfield land. But this will not be enough and some undeveloped land will need to be made available for house-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a simple choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. We can shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or we can accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land and resolve that we will make these decisions locally and build beautiful places like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is determined to persuade communities to accept more house-building by giving them a tangible share of the benefits it brings. By undertaking a neighbourhood plan that makes space for new development, communities can secure revenues to make the community more attractive for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is an important way to make sure that development has the backing of the community. It is right that the areas that have organised themselves to bring forward a neighbourhood plan and have taken the plan through all the stages of the neighbourhood planning (including a successful examination and referendum) should be rewarded for their positive, pro-active approach to delivering growth. This is why they are entitled to an extra 10% of the levy arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy amount passed to neighbourhoods reflects the rates the local planning authority set for the levy. These charge a rate or different rates for development in the local area in pounds per square metre. The neighbourhood funding element will be calculated based on the levy receipts from the relevant development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The levy’s charges will become due from the date that a chargeable development is commenced. The neighbourhood funding element will be passed to parish or community councils in accordance with a timetable agreed between the local planning authority and the local council.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the money is transferred to a parish council (in England) or a community council (in Wales) they will decide how the money will be spent - although they will be expected to work with the local planning authority. Where the money stays with the local planning authority (in areas without a parish or community council) the local planning authority will engage with the communities where the development has happened to agree how best to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In areas that have not been subject to neighbourhood planning there will be a cap of £100 per council tax dwelling on the neighbourhood funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We aim to have these incentives in place from Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We previously &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;consulted&lt;/a&gt; on allowing councils the choice whether to spend their levy receipts on affordable housing but given other ongoing policies to support housing, we are not proposing to make this change at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also going to enable a mayoral development corporation to impose a Community Infrastructure Levy charge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64224</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T12:52:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/why-we-must-continue-to-tackle-far-right-extremism-head-on"/>
    <title>Why we must continue to tackle far right extremism head on</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Don Foster to council leaders at the first meeting of the national special interest group on the far right.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all - thank you for inviting me here today and thank you for the work you are doing for each of your councils. I would have loved to have stayed for the whole day but I am told that you have a lot of work to do and so I am looking forward to hearing how the day went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremism is an affront to our society in every form, including the far right and the English Defence League (&lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt;) - they are divisive and create fear in our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right does not belong in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially following a year when the Olympics changed the way we see ourselves - gave us real confidence as a society with shared values. The Olympics showed how brilliantly our communities can come together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We basked in the glory of our country’s sporting success stories, whatever their background, skin colour or religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the Secretary of State is passionate about tackling extremism - his commitment is shared by the Prime Minster, the Deputy Prime Minister and across government - everyone is sickened by the messages and activities of the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; and their ilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us share a personal commitment to tackling them. In fact one of the reasons I came into politics was because many years ago the National Front were allowed to hire my children’s school to use as a meeting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their ugly messages and actions could not go ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I campaigned against them to get them out of my children’s school and back into the wilderness where they belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we have the English Defence League marching up and down our streets on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causing local shops and businesses to lose money just when they are struggling with the downturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And causing fear across our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/creating-the-conditions-for-a-more-integrated-society"&gt;Creating the conditions for integration&lt;/a&gt;’ published last February, the government set out its approach to creating and sustaining strong communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major part of the approach is to tackle extremism and intolerance head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right must be isolated, undermined, outflanked and subject to the ridicule they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we are working in schools with 10,000 students across the country to give them the tools to reject the far-right’s messages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we are working with communities in Dudley, Croydon, Barking and Luton, training volunteers to produce community newspapers for 14,000 families that provide an alternative voice to the far right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the government is supporting over 30 projects as part of our integration strategy - you have copies today. We need to invest now to reduce the costs and impacts generated by the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that it is only at local level that we can really address the conditions the far right feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we were so pleased when Blackburn with Darwen and Luton came to us and asked for our help to set up and run this national special interest group on the far right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is through the leadership of councils like Luton, Blackburn and many others that we will ultimately succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already know that there is a lot of good work going on in places up and down the country:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in Luton they have the ‘Luton in Harmony’ campaign involving nearly 70,000 Luton residents saying loud and clear that they do not want the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in their towns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Blackburn they have the ‘hundred voice’ campaign, which puts people at extreme ends of the spectrum of opinions in the same room as each other to thrash it out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are fantastic innovative responses to the challenges we face by the far right but even more is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is critical if we are to succeed in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you that the far right has taken a battering but is still on the move - they haven’t managed to attract the numbers of supporters on marches that they did in their heyday in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to this year, we expect that the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue to decline in numbers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will still manage to get enough supporters out for marches in towns and cities across 2013 - enough to cause disruption and fear.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know that there are splinter groups appearing across the country threatening flash demonstrations and direct action - the Infidels and the English Volunteer Force are just two examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the good work that local authorities and the police have done in minimising the impacts of these people has had an effect but clearly as I said there is more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is absolutely critical in succeeding in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this leadership look like? What does it do? How does it keep its head above the parapet at all times, not just in the run up to &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; demonstrations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is what we are here for today. I would encourage you all to look at the 30 or so projects the government is supporting. These projects include everything from music projects bringing different communities together for a common purpose, to looking at getting scouts and cadets groups in more areas, particularly areas where they may not have existed before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As leaders in your communities you will know this better than us. We look forward to hearing the ideas you come up with and to you sharing them with those leaders who couldn’t make it here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am interested in hearing proposals for innovative projects for undermining extremists of all stripes, so please share your ideas with me and we will see what we can do to support you. There may even be some money for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60117</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-everyone-a-happy-christmas"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish everyone a happy Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for Christmas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the year draws to a close and families up and down the country get ready to celebrate Christmas, we should all be immensely proud of the vital role that churches play in our neighbourhoods and the special place the Christian faith holds in our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our Christian communities have a strong tradition of giving back and improving the lives of those around them, as I saw for myself at a harvest festival service at London’s Borough Market where food and clothing was donated to the homeless, regardless of faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to those who will be selflessly helping others this year, whether through volunteering in a soup-kitchen or collecting and donating gifts - these generous acts make a real difference within our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The upcoming holiday is a strong reminder of the Christian ethos within our country and I wish a very merry Christmas to one and all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith and Communities Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Minister for Faith and Communities I would like to send my warmest wishes to everyone this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Christmas is an extremely special time for Britain, a country where the majority of people identify themselves as Christian. None of us should forget that, amid the turkeys, the tinsel and all the traditions that accompany this festival, lies the true meaning of Christmas: the birth of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a time for goodwill and generosity, reflection and redemption. These are themes we can all celebrate - people of all faiths and of none, who break their busy routines to come together with families and friends in the spirit of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Christmas let’s also remember the positive impact of faith on society and think about those who face persecution for holding a belief. Let’s also be confident in Britain’s Christianity, as I said when I led the largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See earlier this year. We cannot erase this faith from our history any more than we can erase the spires from our landscapes - or, indeed, the stars from the tops of our trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wishing everyone a very merry Christmas and a happy, peaceful New Year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56690</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/louise-casey-calls-for-family-intervention-approach"/>
    <title>Louise Casey calls for family intervention approach</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The head of the Troubled Families programme has endorsed family intervention as the most effective way to turn problem families around and help them get on in life.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a look at the academic evidence, alongside consultation with practitioners and families themselves, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/louise-casey"&gt;Louise Casey&lt;/a&gt; today published a new report that shows the life-changing results that good family intervention can have on even the most challenging households, along with a guide to best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;‘Working with Troubled Families’ report&lt;/a&gt; outlines that family intervention reduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involvement in anti-social behaviour by 59%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;involvement in crime by 45%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truancy, exclusion, bad behaviour at school by 52%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also points to the 5 key features of effective family intervention being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated worker, dedicated to a family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ‘hands on’ support &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a persistent, assertive and challenging approach &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;considering the family as a whole - gathering the intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common purpose and agreed action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey is now calling on councils to review their own ways of working with troubled families and adopt these principles in order to ensure that the significant momentum that has built up behind the programme - with all eligible local authorities in England on board and committed to working with over 40,000 families in this financial year - continues in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to push on with this work and make further progress towards the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015, the Department for Communities and Local Government will also be holding a series of training academies for local authorities in the new year to help share best practice on family intervention and provide masterclasses from some of its leading exponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the government’s Troubled Families programme Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My last report was about listening to troubled families themselves and some of the stories from families were truly appalling. However these were families successfully going through family intervention and the results were impressive - so I wanted to ensure that this practice is adopted as widely as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This report makes a strong case about what works - family intervention that involves one dedicated worker for each family, providing tough but persistent challenge and support, has a dramatic impact, not just on the life chances of those within the families, but on the communities around them who suffer from the effects of truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This important piece of work is a crucial step towards building a wide campaign of support behind the work we are doing to break an inter-generational cycle of misery and failure with these families. It will put rocket boosters under the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around 120,000 troubled families by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Effective family intervention also demonstrates that savings can be made for taxpayers by putting families back on the right track for the long run, rather than wasting money on simply reacting to their problems. We must have aspiration for every family and this work will reach all corners of the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Clare Tickell, Chief Executive of Action for Children, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since developing the initial model, we’ve seen how family intervention can really help vulnerable families facing multiple difficulties in their lives. It works by forming effective relationships with families and building on their strengths. This timely guide is a welcome resource, which will help people understand the key features of the model, learn what really works and ensure that projects are delivered to a high quality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;Working with Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"&gt;Listening to Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, July 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All eligible local authorities are running troubled families programmes in their area and between them have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is today also publishing management information on the work of family intervention projects and services in England up to 31 March 2012. This reports the latest data at a national level for all participating family intervention services. It includes information on the families worked with and the percentage of families considered to have a successful outcome in relation to family functioning and risk, crime/ anti-social behaviour, health and education/ employment. This data was collected by the National Centre for Social Research (NatCen) which ran a secure web-based information system into which family intervention project staff recorded details of the families they worked with between 2007-2012. It can be found at Annex B of the ‘Working With Troubled Families’ report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56541</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"/>
    <title>Working with Troubled Families: a guide to evidence and good practice</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities and their partners on how to work with troubled families.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a tool to help local authorities and their partners, who have asked for guidance on how best to work with troubled families, and for the evidence about family intervention to be brought together in one place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report looks at academic evidence, local evaluations of practice, what practitioners have told us works in their services and what families tell us makes this work different and successful for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/39665</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services"/>
    <title>Ensuring the future of the universal postal service and Post Office network services</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is making sure there will always be a universal postal service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universal postal service - the six-day-a-week, one-price-goes-anywhere service to every address in the UK - is important for communities and the economy. The government needs to make sure the future of the service is secure and that everyone continues to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Post Office network is a unique national asset that provides convenient access to vital social and economic services to local communities across the UK. It needs to be maintained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wholly owns both Royal Mail Group Ltd (which provides the universal postal service in the UK) and Post Office Ltd (which runs the network of post offices). This shareholding is managed by the Shareholder Executive in the Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;Attracting private capital into Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect the future of the universal postal service, we aim to end Royal Mail’s dependence on unpredictable funding from the taxpayer by attracting private capital into the company.  We intend to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/attracting-private-capital-into-royal-mail"&gt;sell shares in Royal Mail&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;Funding and modernising the Post Office network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have committed £1.34 billion of funding for the network from financial year 2011 to 2012 to financial year 2014 to 2015. This will enable the Post Office to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/ensuring-the-future-of-the-universal-postal-service-and-post-office-network-services/supporting-pages/funding-and-modernising-the-post-office-network"&gt;maintain and modernise its network&lt;/a&gt; to help safeguard its future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="separating-the-post-office-and-royal-mail"&gt;Separating the Post Office and Royal Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Mail and the Post Office are different businesses, facing different challenges. In order to maintain the Post Office in public ownership and enable private sector investment in the Royal Mail letters and parcels business, we separated Post Office Ltd from Royal Mail Group Ltd in April 2012 to become a sister company of Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that the two companies will no longer work together. The Chief Executive of Royal Mail has called it “unthinkable” that there would not always be a strong relationship between Royal Mail and the Post Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure the continuation of their existing business relationship, at the time of separation, the management of Royal Mail and the Post Office put in place a commercial contract between the two parties (with the longest possible contract length permitted by law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-royal-mail-pensions"&gt;Funding Royal Mail pensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 1 April 2012 we transferred Royal Mail’s historic liabilities of around £40 billion from Royal Mail’s pension scheme to a new public sector scheme (the Royal Mail Statutory Pension Scheme, RMSPS) to be administered by the government.  At the same time around £28 billion of Royal Mail’s pension assets were transferred to government. The pension scheme left with Royal Mail was left with matching assets and liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-the-regulator"&gt;Changing the regulator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From October 2011 we transferred regulatory responsibility for the postal market from Postcomm to Ofcom, the regulator responsible for the wider communications sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012 Ofcom put in place new regulations for postal services for the next 7 years. Ofcom’s primary duty is to make sure there continues to be a universal postal service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/coalition-documents"&gt;Coalition Agreement&lt;/a&gt; we said we would aim to inject private capital into Royal Mail, and explore opportunities for employee ownership. We also pledged to retain Post Office Ltd in public ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the request of the Business Secretary Vince Cable, Richard Hooper CBE, the former deputy chairman of Ofcom, updated his December 2008 report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file49389.pdf"&gt;Modernise or decline&lt;/a&gt; on the maintenance of the universal postal service in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hooper made three main recommendations in his September 2010 report, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/saving-the-royal-mails-universal-postal-service-in-the-digital-age-an-update-of-the-2008-independent-review"&gt;Saving the Royal Mail’s universal postal service in the digital age&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Royal Mail should have access to private sector capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its historic pension deficit should be resolved; its deficit of £8 billion sapped cash from the business, making it difficult to compete with other operators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way postal services are regulated needed to be better balanced so as to allow competition whilst ensuring the universal service remains available  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We agreed and introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; to implement the recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 we &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/post-office-mutualisation"&gt;consulted on the move towards an agreed model for a mutual Post Office&lt;/a&gt;. Our response to the consultation was published in July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two Acts specifically cover postal services in the UK:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/5/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;, which lifted restrictions on the ownership of Royal Mail, allowed for a future mutual ownership model for Post Office Limited (ie ownership across a mix of invested stakeholders, such as employees, subpostmasters and consumers, with no one party having an overall majority), enabled the transfer of the Royal Mail’s historic pension liabilities to government and put the framework in place to deliver a new regulatory regime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/26/contents"&gt;Postal Services Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; - some of which was replaced or amended by the 2011 Act - has a number of important provisions still in force. These include provisions relating to offences in relation to the mail, the schemes (ie setting out details of services’ terms and conditions) of universal service providers, application of customs and excise legislation to postal packets, and financing and restructuring of the Royal Mail group of companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU Postal Services Directives require member states to ensure the provision of a universal postal service.  The requirements of the directives are implemented in UK law by the above Postal Services Acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/"&gt;Ofcom&lt;/a&gt; - the independent regulator and competition authority for the UK’s communications industries, and its responsibilities now include the postal sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consumerfocus.org.uk/"&gt;Consumer Focus&lt;/a&gt; - champions the needs of consumers, across markets, including the postal services sector, with a particular regard to the vulnerable, including those who have been or are about to be disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60886</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-shareholder-executive-publications"/>
    <title>The Shareholder Executive: publications</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Working with shareholder departments in government to improve fundamentally the government’s capabilities and performance as a shareholder.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="senior-team"&gt;Senior team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_61576"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/thumbnail_shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/43450/shareholder-executive-senior-team.pdf"&gt;Shareholder Executive: Senior team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;173 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;13 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;h2 id="portfolio-unit"&gt;Portfolio unit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;section class="attachment embedded" id="attachment_61575"&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-thumb"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-61575-accessibility-help" class="thumbnail"&gt;
      &lt;img alt="" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/thumbnail_shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="attachment-details"&gt;
    &lt;h3 class="title"&gt;&lt;a href="/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/35746/shareholder-executive-portfolio-unit.pdf" aria-describedby="attachment-61575-accessibility-help"&gt;Shareholder Executive: Portfolio Unit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p class="metadata"&gt;
      &lt;span class="type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Portable Document Format"&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,
      &lt;span class="file-size"&gt;247 KB&lt;/span&gt;,
        &lt;span class="page-length"&gt;36 pages&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="accessibility-warning js-toggle-accessibility-warning" id="attachment-61575-accessibility-help"&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;This file may not be accessible.
          &lt;span class="toggler"&gt;Request a different format.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p class="help-block"&gt;
          To request this document in an alternative format such as braille, audio
          or a different file type please email
          &lt;a href="mailto:Shareholder.Executive@bis.gsi.gov.uk?body=%0A%0ADetails%20of%20document%20required%3A%0A%0ATitle%3A%20Shareholder%20Executive%3A%20Portfolio%20Unit%0AISBN%3A%20%0AUnique%20reference%3A%20%0ACommand%20paper%20number%3A%20%0A%20%20%20%20%20%20&amp;amp;subject=Request%20for%20%27Shareholder%20Executive%3A%20Portfolio%20Unit%27%20in%20an%20alternative%20format"&gt;Shareholder.Executive@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
          quoting your address, telephone number along with the title of the
          publication ("Shareholder Executive: Portfolio Unit").
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50196</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for the Jewish holiday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish community has made, and continues to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>A report setting out the progress the government is making to 'decentralise' power from Whitehall across the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
