<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/community-and-society</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/community-and-society.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Community and society"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39676</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities Ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for the Jewish holiday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish Community have made, and continue to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <summary>A report setting out the progress the government is making to 'decentralise' power from Whitehall across the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18642</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-announces-150-000-to-boost-great-british-pubs"/>
    <title>Minister announces £150,000 to boost Great British pubs</title>
    <summary>Community Pubs Minister Brandon Lewis has announced £150,000 funding for the Pub in The Hub community services project.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement followed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pubisthehub.org.uk/"&gt;Pub is The Hub&lt;/a&gt; ‘10 Years On’ event on 5 December 2012 where the minister was a keynote speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke about the key role pubs play in the social and economic life of many communities, often as community hubs, local service providers and a place where community relationships are formed and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to say that pubs contribute, on average, £100,000 per pub to the local economy as well as being strong sources of local employment for younger people to get involved in an entrepreneurial and innovative industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community pubs minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to announce we are giving Pub is The Hub £150,000 for their project. The government is taking decisive action to support community pubs including doubling business rate relief, which gives up to 100% discounts for small firms including pubs and postponing revaluation will also avoid local pubs facing an 11% rise in their business rates bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is on top of abolishing the last government’s cider tax, cutting red tape on live music in pubs and stopping unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price by supermarkets. We have given councils powers to offer local business rate discounts and the Community Right to Bid lets communities protect their pubs and guard against their unnecessary loss.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to see community pubs thriving everywhere and has introduced a series of measures to support them including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to introduce local business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, the department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17574</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:27:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <summary>As part of inter-faith week, the winners have been announced for the Faith Through a Lens photography competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;'There but for the Grace of God'. Picture: Rob Boler&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and the other winners and finalists in the competition can be found on the awards and highlights section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ftal.staged.ws/awards-highlights-from-2012/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Together in Service event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632131148440/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <summary>The flag representing the historic county of Lancashire has been hoisted above Whitehall to coincide with the county day on 27 November.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48919</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T10:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"/>
    <title>Flying flags: a plain English guide</title>
    <summary>A guide to the flags that can be flown without permission from your local planning authority.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has recently made changes to regulations which widen the types of flags you may fly in England. This guide provides a brief summary of the new rules over flag flying that were introduced on 12 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17189</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T18:39:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/inter-faith-week-and-a-year-of-service-speech"/>
    <title>Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service speech</title>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Faith Minister Baroness Warsi on interfaith action and identity.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to thank you all for coming to this a wonderful event, marking both Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks also to the Faith-based Regeneration Network, Mitzvah Day, the Co-exist Foundation and others for their help in making the event a reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for the people here, it’s Inter Faith Week every week and it’s A Year of Service every year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because day in, day out, you are giving your time, your energy, your hearts and your souls to making your communities better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United by faith and driven by faith - whichever faith that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Sikh-run Nishkam Centre in Birmingham, which provides a whole range of training and educational opportunities for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Sewa Day, which inspires Hindus across the country to acts of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like the St Vincent de Paul Society, which provides gifts and hospitality to the needy in the run-up to Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These projects and many more prove that faith motivates good works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today you have a government that doesn’t deny that fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a government that supports, celebrates and - in my case - shares that motivation. A government that does God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know that people who ‘do God’ do good things up and down the country every single day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys show people of religious observance are more likely to become volunteers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see that fact in the 30,000 faith-based charities making a difference throughout Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="interfaith-action"&gt;Interfaith action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the interfaith movement officially started in 1893 with the ‘World’s Parliament of Religions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s major religions came together in Chicago for serious discussions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I don’t think they would have a parliament; they’d have a day of social action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because today interfaith dialogue has become much more about interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always argued that interfaith shouldn’t just be tea in a draughty church hall or a samosa in the local mosque between the imam and the vicar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t just be clergy to clergy: it should be congregation to congregation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I helped get a programme called Active Faith off the ground - which, of course, became Near Neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the wonderful projects we see here today are just a small selection of the 300 local projects that have been supported so far.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producing projects like the Departure Café, a drop-in centre and community hub for Tower Hamlets, which I hope to visit soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of local congregations coming together to ‘do their bit’ underpin our support for the A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’ll agree - there can be no better way of marking Her Majesty the Queen’s many years of service to our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Year of Service has produced some fantastic projects, like the wonderful Mitzvah Mummies, who I went to see yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers and their toddlers, meeting, talking to and sharing moments with residents of a retirement home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integenerational interaction - such a simple idea and so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Faith and Communities, every day I see the power and the potential of interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last Thursday as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a catch-up with the Chief Rabbi… A meeting with Christian groups… An introduction with the Buddhist Network… A speech at my department’s Eid event… And a House of Lords debate on the importance of religion in society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the common thread running through these events wasn’t the fact these people observed a faith. It was that they were inspired to do good things as a result of their belief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I’m so proud that we have so many local and national 300 inter faith organisations in the UK - more than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I’m so proud that 3 Faiths Forum, the Joseph Interfaith Foundation, the Christian-Muslim Forum are leading the way in the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I am so heartened to see the launch this week of advice to couples and families on interfaith marriages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-identities"&gt;Stronger identities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had my own theory on inter faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that if you are stronger in your identity then you are more tolerant of others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who don’t associate with people of other beliefs because they think it somehow weakens theirs - they have got it the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if you’re a person who unites with people of other faiths for a common goal - it doesn’t make you less of a Muslim, less of a Hindu, less of a Jew - it makes you more of one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is no more powerful demonstration of one’s security in one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I went to the Vatican earlier this year and argued that Europe should be stronger in its Christian identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Christian heritage of Britain is what has made me feel comfortable here in practising my faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending my daughter to an Anglican convent school made her feel stronger in her identity. When she would swap ‘Amen’ for ‘Ameen’ during the Lord’s Prayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain leads the world in its interfaith ethos. But I think we can build on the progress we’ve made since that conference in American back in 1893. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that if we - people of all faiths and none - pull together, we can defeat the intolerance and bigotry faced by people of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, an attack on a mosque is an attack on a church; an attack on a gudwara is an attack on a synagogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, an attack on one faith is an attack on all faiths. So let’s be inspired by the story of Siavosh Derakhi, who has recently been recognised for founding Young Muslims Against Anti-Semitism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by the words of President Obama, following the release of the abhorrent, gratuitously offensive ‘Innocence of Muslims’ film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he said: “to be credible, those who condemn that slander must also condemn the hate we see when the image of Jesus Christ is desecrated, churches are destroyed, or the Holocaust is denied. Let us condemn incitement against Sufi Muslims, and Shia pilgrims.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by all the good things that are done and can be done in the name of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the subject of inspiration I want to present this beautiful piece of artwork.
Doctor Fox, I know you’re accepting this on behalf of the Evelina Hospital, so thank you, and also to the extremely talented artist Sam Cowan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m off to see some more fantastic artwork now as I go and award the winner of the Faith Through a Lens competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me once again thank you for coming today and thank you for all you do. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16487</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T13:59:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nick-boles-attends-launch-of-national-business-competition"/>
    <title>Nick Boles attends launch of national business competition</title>
    <summary>Communities Minister sees young people being inspired through business at the launch of this year’s Mosaic Enterprise Challenge competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting Westminster City School, Nick Boles spoke to the winners of last year’s competition and saw the how they invented a winning product by taking part in an online business game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt=" Nick Boles with students" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1125/mosaicwinners2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Nick Boles speaking to students from Southfields Community College, winners of last year’s competition&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;School teams are supported by specialist business mentors to compete through the game, which places them into a realistic business situation in which they must develop and market a new product and respond to simulated business competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The competition aims to promote entrepreneurship and inspire knowledge and enthusiasm about business among young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mosaicnetwork.co.uk/en_gb/portal/enterprise-challenge"&gt;Enterprise Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the department, will this year involve over 3,000 students in 80 schools who will be supported by more than 300 mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Apax-Mosaic Enterprise Challenge is an excellent way of enabling pupils to learn practical business skills such as sales, marketing and finance from within the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fantastic to speak to last year’s competition winners and hear how they have benefited from taking part and how much they enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the Department is supporting this for another year and wish everyone taking part the best of luck.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632046112497/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16140</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/faith-minister-visits-temple-to-start-diwali-celebrations"/>
    <title>Faith Minister visits temple to start Diwali celebrations</title>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi joined spectators at a fireworks display to mark the start of Diwali celebrations at London’s famous Neasden Temple.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neasden Temple is the first traditional Hindu Mandir in Europe and the largest temple outside India. During her visit, the Faith and Communities Minister received a traditional welcome by the trustees of the temple and heard about their work before embarking on a tour of the building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She met volunteers and heard about the central role the temple plays within the local community and beyond - having attracted devotees and visitors from across the world since it opened in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was then invited to set off the spectacular fireworks display enjoyed by the thousands of people who had travelled to the temple to mark the beginning of Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every year I look forward to celebrating Diwali, the festival of lights, so it was a particular honour to mark it this year at the magnificent Neasden Temple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fascinating to hear about the central role the temple plays within the local community, from hosting school visits and organising charitable events - and how the Mandir has attracted devotees from all corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to the trustees and volunteers many hours of devotion and commitment and thank them for the warm hospitality I received during my visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632012718099/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14760</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-sends-her-best-wishes-on-diwali"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes on Diwali</title>
    <summary>On 13 November, Hindu, Jain and Sikh communities will gather to celebrate the Festival of Lights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister, Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes to all of those celebrating Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As people celebrate this special time in communities across the country, I send my warmest wishes to you all for a peaceful and happy Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Diwali provides an important opportunity for prayer and reflection as the festival which celebrates the victory of good over evil and light over darkness. It is a time for family and friends, the reaffirmation of hope and renewed commitment to friendship and goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In celebrating Diwali we can appreciate the diversity that characterises this country and also recognise the common values of compassion, honesty and goodwill in which we can all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As communities across the country begin their celebrations, I am delighted to wish everyone a very happy Diwali and a prosperous new year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
