<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Consumer rights and issues"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T18:30:29+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/8477</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:30:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:30:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"/>
    <title>Providing better information and protection for consumers</title>
    <summary>How the government is changing some laws to help consumers</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government believes that consumers who are well-informed about their rights and what they’re buying are more confident and more likely to spend money. We also think that consumers who feel properly protected by the law are more likely to spend money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to give consumers more confidence - and legal back-up - to deal with bad service or shoddy goods. We also want to encourage consumers to spend money, as this will help the economy grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-bill-of-rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to simplify and clarify consumer law with a new bill (Act of Parliament). This will contain a clear list of rights for consumers, along with new measures to protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-bill-of-rights" title="Consumer bill of rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/a&gt; will also contain remedies for when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform"&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘consumer landscape’ is the network of organisations that help consumers - Citizens Advice, for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘competition landscape’ is the network of organisations that deal with competition issues and anti-competitive activities in business – the Office of Fair Trading, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning to reorganise both the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="consumer and competition landscapes"&gt;consumer and competition landscapes&lt;/a&gt; between now and 2014, to make them both simpler to understand and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-201183eu"&gt;Implementing the Consumer Rights Directive 2011/83/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-2011-83-eu" title="Consumer Rights Directive."&gt;Consumer Rights Directive (CRD)&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; measure. All &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CRD gives consumers additional rights when buying in the UK and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. We’re aiming to make the CRD part of UK law by June 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="misleading-and-aggressive-selling"&gt;Misleading and aggressive selling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/misleading-and-aggressive-selling" title="Misleading and aggressive selling."&gt;improving the rights of people who have been misled into buying something&lt;/a&gt;, or who have been pressured into buying something. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="personal-data"&gt;Personal data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re helping consumers make better buying decisions by giving them improved access to the personal data companies hold about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/midata" title="Midata"&gt;midata project.&lt;/a&gt;. We’re working with business, consumer and privacy groups. The project is led by an independent data expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midata project runs on a voluntary basis, but we’ll pass a law to make industry cooperation compulsory if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-buying"&gt;Community buying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers can combine their buying power to buy goods and services together. This can get them better deals. The government is supporting community buying in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by providing clear advice to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/community-buying" title="Community groups"&gt;community groups&lt;/a&gt; who want to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by running the ‘Buy better together challenge’, which has a £60,000 fund to be shared amongst innovative collective purchasing projects - the challenge was won by Smarterbuys, an organisation that helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so they can buy essential goods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="who-can-i-contact-for-help-and-advice"&gt;Who can I contact for help and advice?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t help with individual problems – but here are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/consumer-protection-rights" title="Help and advice"&gt;some people who can.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/" title="Trading Standards."&gt;Trading Standards&lt;/a&gt; have worked on mainly local cases and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://oft.gov.uk/" title="Office of Fair Trading."&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/a&gt; (OFT) worked on some national ones. A National Audit Office (NAO) report was critical of this split and the ‘enforcement gap’ it caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews."&gt;Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews&lt;/a&gt; were published in spring 2012. They recommended a number of changes including transferring the main responsibility for consumer advice to the Citizens Advice service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consulted in June 2011 with proposals for reforming consumer institutions – the ‘consumer landscape’. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/empowering-and-protecting-consumers?cat=closedwithresponse" title="Empowering and Protecting Consumers: Consultation"&gt;Empowering and protecting consumers&lt;/a&gt; had 184 responses and closed in September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted in summer 2012 about whether we should have an ‘order-making power’ for midata. This power would give us the legal authority to make businesses release personal data to their customers. Following the consultation, we announced that we would legislate if companies didn’t release customers’ data voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital.pdf" title="proposals to update and simplify consumer law"&gt;proposals to update and simplify consumer law.&lt;/a&gt;  How would they affect consumers and businesses? That consultation closed on 5 October 2012. We’ll publish the results in spring 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital" title="Goods, services, digital content"&gt;Consultation on the supply of goods, services and digital content (July 2012)&lt;/a&gt; here and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-961-supply-of-digital-content-impact.pdf" title="Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content."&gt;Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1008-consultation-ban-above-cost-payment-surcharges" title="Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges."&gt;Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 15 October with the government response due in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-999-consultation-implementation-of-consumer-rights-directive.pdf" title="Consumer rights consultation"&gt;implementation of the Consumer Rights Directive&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 1 November. The government response is due in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-543-enhancing-consumer-confidence-effective-enforcement-consultation.pdf" title="Consumer law enforcement powers"&gt;Simplifying consumer law enforcement powers.&lt;/a&gt; The government response is expected in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re consulting on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending" title="Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law."&gt;Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;. This opened on 2 November and closes on 31 December with government response due early in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to know your views on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending"&gt;Give your views about extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked with a number of partners to produce our ‘Guide for community buying groups’. All of the organisations below contributed or checked material for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action with Communities in Rural England (ACRE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allen Valleys Oil Buying Co-operative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brighter Living Partnership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citizens Advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oxfordshire Rural Community Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The R Shop Bulk Buying Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solar 100 Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sustain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up2Us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also worked with the Law Commission and the Scottish Law Commission, who both did studies on misleading and aggressive selling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/17542</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6"/>
    <title>Making consumer credit markets fairer</title>
    <summary>The government wants to make sure that lenders treat borrowers fairly.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorly regulated lenders and debt collectors can cause people problems or add to their problems when they borrow money or they’re in debt. People with debt problems can become vulnerable to unfair practices by credit or debt firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make sure that lenders treat borrowers fairly. We also want to make the credit market itself fairer for all borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working to make borrowing money fairer and more transparent. For example, we’re working with finance trade associations to make it clearer how payday loans work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6/supporting-pages/consumer-credit-markets" title="Consumer credit markets"&gt;Consumer credit markets&lt;/a&gt; will make it easier for people to get debt advice if they fall into money problems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re proposing to move responsibility for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6/supporting-pages/consumer-credit-regulation" title="Consumer credit regulation"&gt;consumer credit regulation&lt;/a&gt; from the Office of Fair Trading (OFT) to the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) in April 2014. We believe this will provide a more responsive organisation along with stronger consumer protection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government published its response to the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; select committee’s report on debt management in May 2012. We set out a number of actions relevant to the committee’s report. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transferring consumer credit powers from the OFT to the Financial Conduct Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with payday loan trade associations to agree better protection for consumers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;holding an industry-wide meeting on debt management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/11-1341-consumer-credit-and-insolvency-response-on-credit.pdf" title="Consumer credit and personal insolvency review"&gt;Consumer credit and personal insolvency review&lt;/a&gt; finished in November 2011. The review suggested actions on unfair bank charges, store cards and the high cost credit market, many of which have since been taken forward in 2012.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56423</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-trade"/>
    <title>Making it easier to trade</title>
    <summary>How the government is updating some of the older laws covering estate agents and street traders.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the laws designed to protect consumers are now so out of date that they’re hampering economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to simplify or repeal these laws without losing any that give consumers the protection they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="estate-agents"&gt;Estate agents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Estate Agents Act was written before the internet existed. As a result, it can be difficult to run certain kinds of online property sites. These sites only put buyers and sellers in touch with each other and don’t offer personal advice. We’re changing the law to make it easier for this kind of online business to operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be making these changes in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="street-traders"&gt;Street traders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the laws covering street traders date from the 19th century. This makes some of them unfit for the 21st century and they need to be updated. Additionally, new European regulations say the UK’s street trading laws are too complex. We need to make some changes to the law for street traders as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be making these changes in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2010 survey by the Office of Fair Trading found that, although many buyers use the internet as a way of looking for property, there wasn’t much choice for consumers who wanted to buy or sell a home without using an estate agent. The government felt that there was space in the market for new players to provide online property marketplaces for private sellers, as long as we made some changes to the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laws on street trading and pedlary are part of retail law. This means they come under the EU’s European Services Directive. As a result, we have to change any street trading or pedlary laws to meet the directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="estate-agents-1"&gt;Estate agents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/p/12-931-proposal-amend-estate-agents-act-1979.pdf" title="Encouraging new business models - proposal to amend the Estate Agents Act 1979"&gt;Encouraging new business models - proposal to amend the Estate Agents Act 1979&lt;/a&gt;     closed in August 2012. We published our response on 13 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had over 400 responses from 271 different organisations and individuals. These included traditional estate agents, owners of online property sites, the National Association of Estate Agents, the National Federation of Property Professionals, Trading Standards offices and the Office of Fair Trading (OFT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="street-trading"&gt;Street trading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England, Wales and Northern Ireland jointly opened a consultation on street trading laws on 23 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-605-street-trading-compliance-with-services-directive-consultation.pdf" title="Street Trading and Pedlary Laws"&gt;Street Trading and Pedlary Laws: consultation on draft regulations to ensure compliance with the requirements of the European Service Directive&lt;/a&gt; asks about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new definition of what a pedlar is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing people under 17 to trade as pedlars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;letting councils grant street trading licences for longer than 12 months&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking away some local authority powers for refusing or revoking a street trading licence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation also contains a proposal to repeal the UK-wide Pedlars Acts to comply with the European Services Directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="wed-like-to-know-what-you-think---the-consultation-is-open-till-15-february-2013-you-can-respond-herehttpwwwbisgovukconsultationsstreet-trading-pedlary-lawscatopen-response"&gt;We’d like to know what you think - the consultation is open till 15 February 2013. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/street-trading-pedlary-laws?cat=open" title="Response"&gt;You can respond here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/17716</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing anti-competitive activities</title>
    <summary>What the government is doing to reduce anti-competitive activities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competitive markets are the best way of making sure a country’s resources are put to their best use. They encourage enterprise and widen choice for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can develop in any economy. They can harm consumers and stifle innovation and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an anti-competitive activity would be when two companies agree to charge the same price for a similar product. This protects the companies’ profits but means consumers get less choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-competitive activities can be very bad for consumers. That’s why they have to be identified and stopped as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the government’s three growth objectives is that the UK should become the best place to start, finance and grow a business. Reforming and improving the laws on anti-competitive activities is a major part of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changing-competition-law"&gt;Changing competition law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is reforming the laws that cover competition and anti-competitive activities in business, including those relating to mergers, markets and illegal activities such as price-fixing and cartels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also reforming the institutions that police competition and anti-competitive activities, and strengthening their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These laws, institutions and powers are collectively known as the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="competition-landscape"&gt;Competition landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re making changes to the organisations that deal with competition and anti-competitive activities in business. We’re doing this between now and the end of 2014. This work is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and competition landscape reforms."&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reforms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="setting-up-a-new-watchdog-for-the-grocery-industry"&gt;Setting up a new watchdog for the grocery industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re creating a new watchdog for the grocery industry. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/groceries-code-adjudicator" title="Groceries Code."&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt; will give suppliers, including farmers supplying the bigger supermarket chains, more protection against anti-competitive activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-legal-challenges-easier"&gt;Making legal challenges easier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to make it easier for consumers and small businesses to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-anti-competitive-activities/supporting-pages/private-actions-pro-tem" title="Private Action."&gt;challenge anti-competitive behaviour&lt;/a&gt; by bringing a legal challenge (also known as a private action) against anti-competitive activities.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-aid"&gt;State aid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re modernising the rules on state aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State aid is when a public body (such as a local authority) or publicly funded body (such as the Big Lottery) provides a business, charity or other organisation with financial help that could give them an advantage over another business. This kind of financial help is generally outlawed by the European treaty, as it’s an anti-competitive practice. State aid regulations set legal ways to give this kind of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/state-aid"&gt;detailed guide on state aid&lt;/a&gt; for public authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different rules - also covered in the detailed guide - apply to agriculture, aquaculture, fisheries, transport and maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK competition law has to comply with EU law. Article 101 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/competition/antitrust/overview_en.html"&gt;Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU)&lt;/a&gt; bans any agreements between businesses ‘which have as their object… the prevention [or] restriction… of competition within the common market.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55440</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:48:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement"/>
    <title>Minister for Europe renews UK commitment to EU enlargement </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has set out the UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister gave a press briefing for European journalists today following his participation in the General Affairs Council meeting in Brussels on 11 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK remains a strong supporter of EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey. I’ve just returned from the General Affairs Council in Brussels where I was pleased to have a long discussion on EU enlargement. Its conclusions make clear the EU’s continued support for enlargement. This is important, and a message that I hope will be heard clearly in the accession and pre-accession countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is good for the EU and one of the EU’s greatest achievements. The European Union, alongside NATO, has been an instrument of peace and reconciliation that has helped spread democracy and the rule of law across our continent, and helped make armed conflict between EU members unthinkable. At the same time an enlarged Single Market, another of the key success stories of the EU, has opened up prosperity and opportunity to hundreds of millions of people. An outward-looking approach and a continuing commitment to enlargement should be seen by all EU Member States as signs of strength and vigour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is also good for wider security and prosperity across the continent. The accession of new Member States helps promote security, stability and prosperity across Europe, based on a firm foundation of democracy, human and civil rights, and respect for the law. The focus on good neighbourly relations is particularly important for a region such as the Western Balkans which saw conflict only two decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a respect for this firm foundation and its benefits which drives the UK’s scrutiny of progress and focus on conditionality. So the UK is clear that there will be no pause after Croatia’s accession. But equally there will be no movement without progress on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Foreign Secretary visited Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia and Kosovo in October. He set out clearly the UK’s support for each country’s EU future. But he stressed to the political leaders that they needed to take the necessary steps to deliver. I hope political leaders in all of the aspiring countries will do so and that we will see further progress being made towards the EU early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the UK remains committed to Turkey’s EU membership. We strongly believe that this would contribute to Europe’s prosperity and security, and the EU remains the strongest lever for reform in Turkey. We are focused on making real progress on the accession process in 2013 and we fully support the Irish Presidency in their desire to open a new acquis Chapter during their Presidency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=842001782" title="Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council in a Written Ministerial Statement.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56727</id>
    <published>2012-12-01T18:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T18:04:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-single-market-centre"/>
    <title>UK Single Market Centre</title>
    <summary>New UK Single Market Centre launched by Department for Business on 1st December 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Single Market Centre brings together all the Single Market operational tools within a single team, including the Internal Market Scoreboard, SOLVIT (the problem solving mechanism that seeks to resolve the misapplication of rules by public authorities) and the Point of Single Contact (the online licensing service hosted on www.gov.uk for Services Directive Implementation). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key benefits of the Single Market Centre are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased awareness and confidence amongst UK businesses and consumers of the support available to trade and shop in the internal Market. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stronger links between Single Market policy and operations &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater visibility and focus within Government on improving the UK’s performance in implementing Internal Market measures &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-is-solvit"&gt;What is SOLVIT?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SOLVIT is an informal problem-solving network that aims to provide a practical solution to a problem that arises with public authorities, where citizens and businesses exercise their free movement rights. The problem must concern the misapplication or misinterpretation of EC legislation, causing a denial of Internal Market rights for the applicant. There is a SOLVIT Centre in all EU Member States plus Norway, Lichtenstein and Iceland that aim to solve problems within a short deadline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As SOLVIT uses an informal approach to resolving disputes, it cannot be used in situations where: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legal proceedings, such as an appeal, are already underway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem relates to a barrier established by legislation, as this cannot be resolved informally or within 
the deadline &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where deadlines under national law need to be respected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-point-of-single-contact-psc-"&gt;What is the Point of Single Contact (PSC) ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PSC is an online E-Government portal that enables service businesses to research information on how to do business in a particular region or service sector within a specific European country and identify what authorisations they need in order to do business. The PSC also allows them to apply remotely for any authorisations or permissions needed, including making any payment electronically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-is-the-internal-market-scoreboard"&gt;What is the Internal Market Scoreboard?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internal Market Scoreboard is published twice a year. It was created to ensure effective implementation of Internal Market law within Member States. It does this by benchmarking Member States’ efforts and providing an overview of each Member State’ s enforcement performance. BIS is responsible for monitoring the Scoreboard in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Scoreboard each year, covers Directives that are not fully transposed in a Member State, and have a transposition deadline up to and including 30 April. The second Scoreboard covers those Directives that are outstanding in a Member State, with a transposition deadline up to and including 31 October. The Commission publishes the results of each Scoreboard in a report around 3 months afterwards and it is here that the Commission analyses the performance of each Member State and highlights those where performance has improved, or declined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:SOLVIT@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Contact Solvit UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/uk-welcomes-business/licences"&gt;The UK’s Point of Single Contact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/eu-go/index_en.htm"&gt;Links to other EU Member States’ PSCs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/score/index_en.htm"&gt;Internal Market Scoreboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56251</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-pencils-and-graphic-instruments-safety-regulations-1998-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>The Pencils and Graphic Instruments (Safety) Regulations 1998: impact assessment</title>
    <summary>Assesses the impact of the government's proposals to revoke pencils and graphic instruments regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of the government’s proposals to revoke pencils and graphic instruments regulations, as they are outdated and no longer reflect current products and processes. See the related &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"&gt;red tape challenge: retail and manufacturing consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56408</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T15:48:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-pyrotechnic-articles-safety-regulations-2010-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>The Pyrotechnic Articles (Safety) Regulations 2010: impact assessment</title>
    <summary>Assesses the impact of proposals to amend the pyrotechnic articles regulations reducing the age at which Christmas crackers can be purchased</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of government proposals to amend the pyrotechnic articles regulations to reduce the age at which Christmas crackers can be purchased from 16 to 12, as the regulations are unnecessarily restrictive. See the related &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"&gt;red tape challenge:retail and manufacturing consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47149</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/buying-smarter-together"/>
    <title>Buying Smarter Together</title>
    <summary>Better shopping deals for the consumer gets a boost as the winner of the UK Buy Better Together Challenge is announced.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;28 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Smarterbuys’ scheme, which helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so that they can buy essential goods, has scooped the £15,000 Buy Better Together Challenge prize, presented by Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Challenge was launched by BIS and Co-operatives UK in December 2011 to encourage groups of consumers to get together and negotiate discounted rates for buying goods and services in bulk. The Challenge received 110 entries, which were whittled down by a panel of independent judges to seven finalists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Fair Food Carlisle’ was awarded the runner-up prize for their scheme which uses buying groups to provide workplaces with a weekly supply of food from local businesses, winning £5,000 which will be invested in improving business processes and hiring staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event Jo Swinson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;” The Buy Better Together Challenge has highlighted hundreds of fantastic ideas and examples from local communities, who banded together to make their money work harder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Collective purchasing is of immense value to groups, not just to make cost savings, but to increase social links in the community and reach out to vulnerable consumers who may not have access to online research or internet shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The schemes we have heard about today aren’t just benefitting consumers though; businesses have seen first-hand how they can gain more customers by working with these groups and communities, often beating competitors in the process. Many congratulations are due to the organisers of ‘Smarterbuys’, which is a positive example of how collective purchasing can challenge existing markets and provide better results. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I also congratulate ‘Fair Food Carlisle’ in supporting local produce growers and taking an innovative approach to boosting their local food economy. These schemes are a clear example of what can be done when consumers are empowered and work together to get better deals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/-Buy-Better-Together-prize-awarded-to-creative-bargain-hunters-683f0.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Buy Better Together prize awarded to creative bargain hunters &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/buy-better-together-challenge"&gt;Buy Better Together Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Nov/hwww.smarterbuys.org.uk"&gt;Smarter Buys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
