<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/consumer-rights-and-issues.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Consumer rights and issues"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-27T15:03:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60881</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T15:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T15:03:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-know-your-shoppers-rights-before-you-hit-the-winter-sales"/>
    <title>Press Release: Know your shopper's rights before you hit the winter sales</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Boxing Day sales begin and January sales loom, Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson is urging consumers to shop responsibly and be aware of their rights to a refund or exchange. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent figures show that more shoppers are choosing to buy their festive treats online, but with internet shopping and many other methods of buying, it can be difficult for consumers to know exactly what the rules are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The festive period is the one time we happily push away scrooge-like thoughts and shop for gifts for our loved ones or to take advantage of the wide range of sales. We are increasingly being spoilt for choice with a wide range of goods, services and shops to choose from, but the variety of choice can mean that consumers forget to take note of the different shoppers’ rights that apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would urge consumers to take note of when they are entitled to a refund or exchange, and to bear in mind any restrictions on certain purchases. When shoppers do buy something, and later change their mind or have a problem with the purchase, I want them to be aware of their rights and obligations to make sure they can get their money back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The current laws that apply to buying goods and services need to be clearer, as do the rules on shopping online or buying digital content. The proposed Consumer Bill of Rights aims to clarify and modernise the law, ensuring consumers are confident about their rights across all areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="general-rules"&gt;General rules&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a consumer buys goods, they must be of satisfactory quality, fit for purpose, last a reasonable time and match any description given. If they don’t the consumer can usually get either a repair, replacement, refund or partial refund. The consumer has the right to any claim for 6 years from purchase, or 5 years in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to be aware that sometimes these rights won’t apply. For example if a consumer just changes their mind they will not have the same rights unless the shop they bought from offers them under its own store policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="return-deadlines"&gt;Return deadlines&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers have a “reasonable time”, often around 4 weeks (although it may be less, depending on the goods in question), to return faulty goods and get a full refund. After this, they may only be entitled to an exchange or partial refund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="faulty-goods"&gt;Faulty goods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If goods are faulty, consumers don’t need to have a receipt to return the item, just proof of purchase. However they may not be entitled to a refund if the fault is due to normal wear and tear, or if the consumer damages the item themselves. This will also be the case where the consumer was aware of the fault before they bought the item. If a consumer keeps the goods for too long before telling the shop or trying to fix the problem themselves, they might not be entitled to get all of their money back. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sale-items"&gt;Sale items&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers have the same rights for sale items as they do for full price items. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="gifts"&gt;Gifts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most shops offer gift receipts, legally only the person who paid has a right to return faulty goods.  To avoid any hassle it’s best to use gift receipts where available, or get the trader to write ‘‘this is a gift for —’’ on any receipt or invoice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="dangerous-or-unsafe-goods"&gt;Dangerous or unsafe goods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an item is suspected to be dangerous or unsafe, the individual should stop using it immediately. Dangerous or unsafe goods should be reported to Trading Standards on 08454 04 05 06.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="private-purchases"&gt;Private purchases&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a shopper buys directly from a private seller, they cannot get their money back if the goods are not satisfactory or fit for purpose. They do however have the right to get their money back if the item doesn’t match the description, e.g. if the seller says the item works and it doesn’t. Consumers should always ask for a receipt and contact details from sellers where they can, and keep copies of any relevant adverts or website pages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="online-auction-sites"&gt;Online auction sites&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general shopper’s rights apply when buying from a seller who makes some or all of their income from selling through online auction sites. If the seller is just an occasional private seller, the more limited rules of private purchases apply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="online-mail-order-and-telephone-shopping"&gt;Online, mail order and telephone shopping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers who opt for these buying methods have extra rights in addition to the general rights. If they buy a service they can cancel their order up to 7 working days after making it, and if they buy goods they can cancel 7 working days after receiving the item. Consumers can claim a refund if they don’t receive their item within 30 days. However, consumers can’t return certain goods that they have changed their mind about, including opened CDs or DVDs, food, personalised goods, newspapers and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When buying online consumers should be able to see certain information about the seller, the goods, and the seller’s terms and conditions on the seller’s website. To see exactly what information required visit Citizen’s Advice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="future-proposals"&gt;Future proposals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, BIS consulted on proposals for a new Consumer Bill of Rights, which will set out a clear code of shopping rights with workable remedies when things go wrong.  It will empower consumers, making it easier for them to understand their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clarify the nature of consumers’ rights and remedies in relation to the supply of goods, which is currently an area where the law is unnecessarily complex.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bring the services regime more in line with the regime for goods, by strengthening consumer rights and remedies in relation to faulty services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modernise the law on digital content to protect consumers, by establishing a clear digital content regime with its own tailored set of rights and associated remedies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There will also be one clear set of rules governing public investigations of breaches of consumer law.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Bill of Rights consultation closed in October, and the government will respond in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-advice"&gt;Further advice:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information on shoppers’ rights visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.adviceguide.org.uk/england/consumer_e.htm"&gt;Citizens Advice Bureau webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For advice on money or debt contact the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.moneyadviceservice.org.uk/"&gt;Money Advice Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information on the Consumer Bill of Rights can be found at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-proposals-for-consumer-rights"&gt;Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further information on the Consumer Bill of Rights can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/consumer-bill-of-rights/"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/consumer-bill-of-rights/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60855</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T08:30:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T08:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-repeal-of-the-property-misdescriptions-act-1991"/>
    <title>Consultation on the repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills is seeking views on the possible repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991 (PMA). The PMA makes it an offence to make false or misleading statements in the course of an estate agency or property development business about property offered for sale. The Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (CPRs) provide similar protections for consumers. This duplication may be unnecessary; putting additional burdens on business, without providing additional protection for consumers. The consultation considers whether the Government should repeal the PMA, now that the CPRs are in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/11-505-consultation-repeal-property-misdescriptions-act.pdf"&gt;Consultation on the repeal of the Property Misdescriptions Act 1991 (PDF, 304 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/60105</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T16:57:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:57:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"/>
    <title>Providing better information and protection for consumers</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is changing some laws to help consumers</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government believes that consumers who are well-informed about their rights and what they’re buying are more confident and more likely to spend money. We also think that consumers who feel properly protected by the law are more likely to spend money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to give consumers more confidence - and legal back-up - to deal with bad service or shoddy goods. We also want to encourage consumers to spend money, as this will help the economy grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-bill-of-rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to simplify and clarify consumer law with a new bill (Act of Parliament). This will contain a clear list of rights for consumers, along with new measures to protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-bill-of-rights" title="Consumer bill of rights"&gt;Consumer bill of rights&lt;/a&gt; will also contain remedies for when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform"&gt;Consumer and competition landscape reform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘consumer landscape’ is the network of organisations that help consumers - Citizens Advice, for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘competition landscape’ is the network of organisations that deal with competition issues and anti-competitive activities in business – the Office of Fair Trading, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re planning to reorganise both the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="consumer and competition landscapes"&gt;consumer and competition landscapes&lt;/a&gt; between now and 2014, to make them both simpler to understand and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-201183eu"&gt;Implementing the Consumer Rights Directive 2011/83/&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/implementing-the-consumer-rights-directive-2011-83-eu" title="Consumer Rights Directive."&gt;Consumer Rights Directive (CRD)&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; measure. All &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CRD gives consumers additional rights when buying in the UK and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. We’re aiming to make the CRD part of UK law by June 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="misleading-and-aggressive-selling"&gt;Misleading and aggressive selling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/misleading-and-aggressive-selling" title="Misleading and aggressive selling."&gt;improving the rights of people who have been misled into buying something&lt;/a&gt;, or who have been pressured into buying something. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="personal-data"&gt;Personal data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re helping consumers make better buying decisions by giving them improved access to the personal data companies hold about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/personal-data"&gt;midata project.&lt;/a&gt;. We’re working with business, consumer and privacy groups. The project is led by an independent data expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midata project runs on a voluntary basis, but we’ll pass a law to make industry cooperation compulsory if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-buying"&gt;Community buying&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers can combine their buying power to buy goods and services together. This can get them better deals. The government is supporting community buying in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by providing clear advice to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/community-buying" title="Community groups"&gt;community groups&lt;/a&gt; who want to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by running the ‘Buy better together challenge’, which has a £60,000 fund to be shared amongst innovative collective purchasing projects - the challenge was won by Smarterbuys, an organisation that helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so they can buy essential goods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="who-can-i-contact-for-help-and-advice"&gt;Who can I contact for help and advice?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t help with individual problems – but here are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/consumer-protection-rights" title="Help and advice"&gt;some people who can.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/" title="Trading Standards."&gt;Trading Standards&lt;/a&gt; have worked on mainly local cases and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://oft.gov.uk/" title="Office of Fair Trading."&gt;Office of Fair Trading&lt;/a&gt; (OFT) worked on some national ones. A National Audit Office (NAO) report was critical of this split and the ‘enforcement gap’ it caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers/supporting-pages/consumer-and-competition-landscape-reform" title="Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews."&gt;Consumer and Competition Landscape Reviews&lt;/a&gt; were published in spring 2012. They recommended a number of changes including transferring the main responsibility for consumer advice to the Citizens Advice service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consulted in June 2011 with proposals for reforming consumer institutions – the ‘consumer landscape’. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/empowering-and-protecting-consumers?cat=closedwithresponse" title="Empowering and Protecting Consumers: Consultation"&gt;Empowering and protecting consumers&lt;/a&gt; had 184 responses and closed in September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted in summer 2012 about whether we should have an ‘order-making power’ for midata. This power would give us the legal authority to make businesses release personal data to their customers. Following the consultation, we announced that we would legislate if companies didn’t release customers’ data voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital.pdf" title="proposals to update and simplify consumer law"&gt;proposals to update and simplify consumer law.&lt;/a&gt;  How would they affect consumers and businesses? That consultation closed on 5 October 2012. We’ll publish the results in spring 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-937-enhancing-consumer-consultation-supply-of-goods-services-digital" title="Goods, services, digital content"&gt;Consultation on the supply of goods, services and digital content (July 2012)&lt;/a&gt; here and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-961-supply-of-digital-content-impact.pdf" title="Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content."&gt;Impact assessments on the supply of goods, services and digital content here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1008-consultation-ban-above-cost-payment-surcharges" title="Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges."&gt;Early implementation of a ban on above cost payment surcharges&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 15 October with the government response due in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-999-consultation-implementation-of-consumer-rights-directive.pdf" title="Consumer rights consultation"&gt;implementation of the Consumer Rights Directive&lt;/a&gt; This closed on 1 November. The government response is due in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/e/12-543-enhancing-consumer-confidence-effective-enforcement-consultation.pdf" title="Consumer law enforcement powers"&gt;Simplifying consumer law enforcement powers.&lt;/a&gt; The government response is expected in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re consulting on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending" title="Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law."&gt;Extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;. This opened on 2 November and closes on 31 December with government response due early in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to know your views on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/12-1193-civil-enforcement-remedies-consultation-on-extending"&gt;Give your views about extending the range of remedies available to public enforcers of consumer law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked with a number of partners to produce our ‘Guide for community buying groups’. All of the organisations below contributed or checked material for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acre.org.uk/"&gt;Action with Communities in Rural England (ACRE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.allenvalleys.co.uk/oil/"&gt;Allen Valleys Oil Buying Co-operative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.brighterliving.org.uk/"&gt;Brighter Living Partnership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/"&gt;Citizens Advice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oxonrcc.org.uk/"&gt;Oxfordshire Rural Community Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://socialinnovation.typepad.com/silk/2009/10/bulk-buying-project.html"&gt;The R Shop Bulk Buying Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solar 100 Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sustainweb.org/"&gt;Sustain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up2Us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also worked with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://lawcommission.justice.gov.uk/"&gt;Law Commission&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scotlawcom.gov.uk/"&gt;Scottish Law Commission,&lt;/a&gt; who both did studies on misleading and aggressive selling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60051</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/better-choices-better-deals-report-on-progress-on-the-consumer-empowerment-strategy"/>
    <title>Better choices: better deals. Report on progress on the consumer empowerment strategy</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This report covers the progress that has been made in the 18 months since the consumer enpowerment strategy was launched. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consumer empowerment strategy Better Choices: Better Deals was published in April 2011. This progress report describes how the wide range of commitments made then have been taken forward. Many of these have involved two or more of government, businesses, economic regulators, consumer groups and individual consumers coming together to develop practical ways to help empower people to make better choices and get better deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empowerment strategy established midata, a programme of work involving government, consumer groups and leading businesses to give consumers more control and access to the data that companies hold about them. The aim of the midata programme is to give consumers access to their transaction data in a way that is electronic, portable and safe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55937</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6"/>
    <title>Making consumer credit markets fairer</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>The government wants to make sure that lenders treat borrowers fairly.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorly regulated lenders and debt collectors can cause people problems or add to their problems when they borrow money or they’re in debt. People with debt problems can become vulnerable to unfair practices by credit or debt firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make sure that lenders treat borrowers fairly. We also want to make the credit market itself fairer for all borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working to make borrowing money fairer and more transparent. For example, we’re working with finance trade associations to make it clearer how payday loans work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6/supporting-pages/consumer-credit-markets" title="Consumer credit markets"&gt;Consumer credit markets&lt;/a&gt; will make it easier for people to get debt advice if they fall into money problems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re proposing to move responsibility for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-consumer-credit-markets-fairer--6/supporting-pages/consumer-credit-regulation" title="Consumer credit regulation"&gt;consumer credit regulation&lt;/a&gt; from the Office of Fair Trading (OFT) to the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) in April 2014. We believe this will provide a more responsive organisation along with stronger consumer protection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government published its response to the &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; select committee’s report on debt management in May 2012. We set out a number of actions relevant to the committee’s report. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transferring consumer credit powers from the OFT to the Financial Conduct Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with payday loan trade associations to agree better protection for consumers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;holding an industry-wide meeting on debt management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/c/11-1341-consumer-credit-and-insolvency-response-on-credit.pdf" title="Consumer credit and personal insolvency review"&gt;Consumer credit and personal insolvency review&lt;/a&gt; finished in November 2011. The review suggested actions on unfair bank charges, store cards and the high cost credit market, many of which have since been taken forward in 2012.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56471</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-trade"/>
    <title>Making it easier to trade</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the government is updating some of the older laws covering estate agents and street traders.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the laws designed to protect consumers are now so out of date that they’re hampering economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to simplify or repeal these laws without losing any that give consumers the protection they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="estate-agents"&gt;Estate agents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Estate Agents Act was written before the internet existed. Parts of the Act make it difficult to run some online property sites - the kind that puts buyers and sellers in touch with each other, but don’t offer personal advice. We’re changing the law to make trading easier for this kind of online business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be making these changes in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="street-traders"&gt;Street traders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the laws covering street traders date from the 19th century. This makes some of them unfit for the 21st century and they need to be updated. Additionally, new European regulations say the UK’s street trading laws are too complex. We need to make some changes to the law for street traders as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be making these changes in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2010 survey by the Office of Fair Trading found that, although many buyers use the internet as a way of looking for property, there wasn’t much choice for consumers who wanted to buy or sell a home without using an estate agent. The government felt that there was space in the market for new players to provide online property marketplaces for private sellers, as long as we made some changes to the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laws on street trading and pedlary are part of retail law. This means they come under the EU’s European Services Directive. As a result, we have to change any street trading or pedlary laws to meet the directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="estate-agents-1"&gt;Estate agents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/p/12-931-proposal-amend-estate-agents-act-1979.pdf" title="Encouraging new business models - proposal to amend the Estate Agents Act 1979"&gt;Encouraging new business models - proposal to amend the Estate Agents Act 1979&lt;/a&gt;     closed in August 2012. We published our response on 13 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had over 400 responses from 271 different organisations and individuals. These included traditional estate agents, owners of online property sites, the National Association of Estate Agents, the National Federation of Property Professionals, Trading Standards offices and the Office of Fair Trading (OFT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="street-trading"&gt;Street trading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England, Wales and Northern Ireland jointly opened a consultation on street trading laws on 23 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/consumer-issues/docs/s/12-605-street-trading-compliance-with-services-directive-consultation.pdf" title="Street Trading and Pedlary Laws"&gt;Street Trading and Pedlary Laws: consultation on draft regulations to ensure compliance with the requirements of the European Service Directive&lt;/a&gt; asks about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new definition of what a pedlar is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing people under 17 to trade as pedlars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;letting councils grant street trading licences for longer than 12 months&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking away some local authority powers for refusing or revoking a street trading licence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation also contains a proposal to repeal the UK-wide Pedlars Acts to comply with the European Services Directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="wed-like-to-know-what-you-think---the-consultation-is-open-till-15-february-2013-you-can-respond-herehttpwwwbisgovukconsultationsstreet-trading-pedlary-lawscatopen-response"&gt;We’d like to know what you think - the consultation is open till 15 February 2013. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/street-trading-pedlary-laws?cat=open" title="Response"&gt;You can respond here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56408</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T15:48:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-pyrotechnic-articles-safety-regulations-2010-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>The Pyrotechnic Articles (Safety) Regulations 2010: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Assesses the impact of proposals to amend the pyrotechnic articles regulations reducing the age at which Christmas crackers can be purchased</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of government proposals to amend the pyrotechnic articles regulations to reduce the age at which Christmas crackers can be purchased from 16 to 12, as the regulations are unnecessarily restrictive. See the related &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"&gt;red tape challenge:retail and manufacturing consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56251</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-pencils-and-graphic-instruments-safety-regulations-1998-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>The Pencils and Graphic Instruments (Safety) Regulations 1998: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Assesses the impact of the government's proposals to revoke pencils and graphic instruments regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of the government’s proposals to revoke pencils and graphic instruments regulations, as they are outdated and no longer reflect current products and processes. See the related &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"&gt;red tape challenge: retail and manufacturing consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47149</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/buying-smarter-together"/>
    <title>Buying Smarter Together</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Better shopping deals for the consumer gets a boost as the winner of the UK Buy Better Together Challenge is announced.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;28 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Smarterbuys’ scheme, which helps provide affordable loans to disadvantaged people so that they can buy essential goods, has scooped the £15,000 Buy Better Together Challenge prize, presented by Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Challenge was launched by BIS and Co-operatives UK in December 2011 to encourage groups of consumers to get together and negotiate discounted rates for buying goods and services in bulk. The Challenge received 110 entries, which were whittled down by a panel of independent judges to seven finalists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Fair Food Carlisle’ was awarded the runner-up prize for their scheme which uses buying groups to provide workplaces with a weekly supply of food from local businesses, winning £5,000 which will be invested in improving business processes and hiring staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event Jo Swinson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;” The Buy Better Together Challenge has highlighted hundreds of fantastic ideas and examples from local communities, who banded together to make their money work harder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Collective purchasing is of immense value to groups, not just to make cost savings, but to increase social links in the community and reach out to vulnerable consumers who may not have access to online research or internet shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The schemes we have heard about today aren’t just benefitting consumers though; businesses have seen first-hand how they can gain more customers by working with these groups and communities, often beating competitors in the process. Many congratulations are due to the organisers of ‘Smarterbuys’, which is a positive example of how collective purchasing can challenge existing markets and provide better results. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I also congratulate ‘Fair Food Carlisle’ in supporting local produce growers and taking an innovative approach to boosting their local food economy. These schemes are a clear example of what can be done when consumers are empowered and work together to get better deals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/-Buy-Better-Together-prize-awarded-to-creative-bargain-hunters-683f0.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Buy Better Together prize awarded to creative bargain hunters &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;Co-operatives UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/buy-better-together-challenge"&gt;Buy Better Together Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Nov/hwww.smarterbuys.org.uk"&gt;Smarter Buys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48230</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-trading-and-pedlar-laws-compliance-with-the-european-services-directive-a-joint-consultation-on-the-draft-regulations-repeal-of-the-pedlars-acts-uk-wide-and-changes-to-street-trading-legislation-in-england-and-wales-and-northern-ireland"/>
    <title>Street trading and pedlar laws: compliance with the European Services Directive. A joint consultation on the draft regulations - repeal of the Pedlars Acts (UK-wide), and changes to street trading legislation in England and Wales and Northern Ireland</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses by 15 February 2013. Consultation seeking views on draft regulations to amend national street trading legislation for England and Wales and for Northern Ireland. Also covers proposals to repeal the Pedlars Act 1871 and 1881 for the whole of the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
