<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/crime-and-policing</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/crime-and-policing"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/crime-and-policing.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Crime and policing"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe Ministerial Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56873</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:23:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/private-security-companies"/>
    <title>Private Security Companies</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the development of a regulatory system for private security companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aims to raise the global standards of private security companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) working in complex and high risk environments overseas. To this end, we have been working closely with interested partners, including industry and civil society, to establish a voluntary, independently audited and internationally recognised regulatory system that is practicable, effective and affordable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification to professional standards is the next step towards effective voluntary regulation. First the Government endorsed the Montreux Document in 2008, in which States commit to observe existing international legal obligations relevant to the operations of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in areas of armed conflict. Secondly, in 2010, an International Code of Conduct for Private Security Providers (&lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt;) was created. This provides a set of principles to guide companies. The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been signed by over 500 &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;, around a third of them British. We have reviewed options on setting new professional standards to make the Code effective. We now intend to issue an HMG publication specifying that ASIS PSC 1-2012 is the applicable standard for UK-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments on land overseas. I will place a copy of the publication in the libraries of both Houses. Companies, independent auditors and the UK Accreditation Service (&lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) will then take the further steps to enable auditing against these standards to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; mandated the development of auditable standards to ensure that signatory companies are implementing their commitments under the code. In response to this requirement, the international security trade association, ASIS, was funded by the Department of Defense to develop the standard – ‘PSC1’ – for the regulation of private security companies operating on land in complex environments overseas. This standard was drafted in a multinational and multi-stakeholder forum in which UK Government, UK industry and UK civil society fully participated.  It was published in March 2012 as an approved American National Standard and is the only standard currently available for companies operating in this field. &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; seeking certification in the UK to this new standard will have to be audited by independent third party auditors accredited by &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our trade association partners, the Security in Complex Environments Group, will, in consultation with Government, develop guidance to help British &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; meet the requirements of the new standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ambition is to have a single, internationally agreed standard and we therefore welcome the fact that PSC1 was recently submitted to the International Standards Organisation (ISO) to be considered for adoption as an international standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments. This process may take some time. We will review the need for a separate HMG publication of this standard once the ISO process has been completed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working with other States, industry and civil society internationally to ensure that there should be globally recognised standards and that UK companies are not unfairly disadvantaged by raising their standards. We expect that the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; governing board, when established, will advise that certification to the PSC 1 standard by suitably accredited independent auditors will meet the Code’s requirements for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to have auditable professional standards. We are still consulting with industry and civil society partners on what additional steps &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; might need to take to obtain full certification by the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; that they are meeting the Code’s principles but I can confirm that there will be no need for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to go through duplicate auditing procedures to become certified.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; was drafted with land-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in mind. However, since 2010 there has been a rapid rise in the number of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on anti-piracy operations at sea. Although many of the principles relating to &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on land and at sea are similar, there are important legal and practical differences. The Government is therefore also contributing to an international drafting process under the ISO for an equivalent professional standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in the maritime sector. A draft maritime standard was introduced at the International Maritime Organisation in late November. If and when this standard is adopted, &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will start the process of accrediting suitably qualified independent third party auditors to certify UK-based maritime &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity on the standards against which &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; should be audited is an important step forward in the drive to raise standards in this industry through voluntary action, but independently audited. It is also a practical illustration of the Government’s commitment to human rights and to working with business and civil society to find effective ways to implement our commitments even in the most challenging environments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56611</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-welcomes-new-counter-terrorism-centre-in-uae"/>
    <title>UK welcomes new counter terrorism centre in UAE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has welcomed the opening of a Centre of Excellence on Countering Violent Extremism in Abu Dhabi.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the broad experience and expertise of the 30 Global Counter-Terrorism Forum (GCTF) founding member nations, the Centre will lead global research on the drivers of terrorism, deliver training to address these, and identify practical, operational initiatives to reduce the threat from terrorism. It was launched at the third ministerial meeting of the GCTF in the United Arab Emirates (UAE), which was attended by representatives from all member nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tunisia, where he is on an official visit, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s launch in Abu Dhabi of the Centre of Excellence for Countering Violent Extremism (CVE) is an important milestone in the global fight against terrorism. In particular I welcome the leadership that His Excellency Foreign Minister Abdullah bin Zayed has shown and the Emirati commitment to host the Centre and make it a reality. The UK will continue to give it our full support. We have nominated an expert to serve as a Member of the International Steering Board and are seconding a Director of Training &amp;amp; Capacity-Building into the Centre’s senior management team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to do our utmost to tackle the root causes of terrorism by ensuring a collaborative international approach to the common threat of terrorism. The Global Counter Terrorism Forum offers us an excellent platform from which to address this constantly changing challenge, drawing on the expertise and experience of its members”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thegctf.org/web/guest/about" title="Global Counter-Terrorism Forum"&gt;Global Counter-Terrorism Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55664</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism"/>
    <title>Protecting the UK against terrorism</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Preventing terrorist attacks on the UK, and on British people and businesses abroad.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a threat to the UK, British nationals and our interests abroad from terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of these threats come from outside the UK and cannot be resolved by concentrating efforts in the UK alone. The government is addressing these threats at their source overseas before they reach the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s Counter Terrorism Strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/counter-terrorism-strategy/"&gt;CONTEST&lt;/a&gt;, reduces the risk from international terrorism so that people can go about their daily lives freely and with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on 4 main actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent: to stop people from becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pursue: to stop terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protect: to strengthen our protection against terrorist attack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prepare: where an attack cannot be stopped, to mitigate its impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prevent"&gt;Prevent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to stop people becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism in the UK and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;responding to the ideological challenge of terrorism and the threat we face from those who promote it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing people from being drawn into terrorism and ensuring that they are given appropriate advice and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with sectors and institutions where there are risks of radicalisation which we need to address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/prevent/prevent-strategy/"&gt;latest information on the Prevent strategy&lt;/a&gt; on the Home Office website. This includes the full text of the strategy and the outcomes of the Prevent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pursue"&gt;Pursue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/pursue/"&gt;Pursue&lt;/a&gt; strand of the strategy means working to detect and investigate terrorist networks and disrupt their activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving our ability to identify and understand the terrorist threat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disrupting terrorist activity and taking action to frustrate terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing terrorists to justice through prosecution – this  includes strengthening the legal framework against terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing international co-operation with partners and allies to strengthen our ability to work together to disrupt terrorist networks, for instance by using &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism/supporting-pages/deportation-with-assurances"&gt;Deportation with Assurances&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="protect"&gt;Protect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/protect/"&gt;Protect&lt;/a&gt; strand means seeking to reduce the vulnerability of the UK and its interests overseas from terrorist attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing accurate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/"&gt;FCO travel advice&lt;/a&gt; on the threat from domestic and international terrorism, with advice for British companies abroad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting key foreign governments to develop their ability to protect areas such as aviation and maritime security, energy infrastructure, crowded places and ‘soft’ targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prepare"&gt;Prepare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/prepare/"&gt;Prepare&lt;/a&gt; strand means working to mitigate the impact of a terrorist attack where it cannot be stopped. This includes work to manage an ongoing attack and recover from its aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preparing the FCO network to respond to terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting foreign governments to develop their own ability to respond to terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advances in technology by both terrorists and organised crime groups create challenges to our national security. The UK’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/science-and-technology/science-and-technology-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;Science and Technology Strategy for Countering International Terrorism&lt;/a&gt; uses innovation, science and technology to reduce the risk to the UK and its interests overseas from international terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al Qaeda is weaker than at any time since 9/11. It has played no role in recent political change in North Africa and the Middle East. Its ideology has been widely discredited and it has failed in all its objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continued international pressure has further reduced its capability and the UK is working with other countries to weaken terrorist threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, al Qaeda continues to be a significant threat and other terrorist groups, some affiliated to al Qaeda, have become stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/"&gt;Home Office&lt;/a&gt; is responsible for keeping the UK safe from the threat posed by terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The determination of the government and everyone involved in the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games was to create a safe and secure event that the UK and the world could enjoy. We thoroughly tested our plans to see how government departments, police and emergency services could respond to a range of incidents.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The games’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/olympics/olympic-safety-security-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;safety and security strategy&lt;/a&gt; has helped communities become more resilient to crime and the threat from violent extremism, and relationships between police and other security agencies have improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the event of a terrorist incident, the Office for Security and Counter-Terrorism is responsible for activating and co-ordinating the Home Office response. We provide a crisis response 24 hours a day, 365 days of the year. The government’s response to all kinds of emergencies, including terrorism, is set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaem.com/regions/iaemeuropa/documents/UKConOps.pdf"&gt;Central government arrangements for responding to an emergency: concept of operations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/34532</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/preventing-and-reducing-piracy-off-the-coast-of-somalia"/>
    <title>Preventing and reducing piracy off the coast of Somalia  </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>UK counter-piracy activity off the coast of Somalia, and HMG advice to the shipping industry and travellers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2008 there has been a sharp rise in attacks by pirates off the coast of Somalia on ships transiting the Gulf of Aden and  Indian Ocean. Armed gangs have been hijacking vessels and demanding ransoms for the  release of both vessels and crew. These attacks affect the peace and security of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, the UK is playing a lead role in international operations aimed at stopping the pirates, and providing humanitarian and development assistance to Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to ensure pirates (and the proceeds from piracy) are stopped, and that the shipping and travel industry can conduct its business as safely as possible, the UK is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;supporting counter-piracy missions - &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/topics_48815.htm"&gt;Operation Ocean Shield&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.eunavfor.eu/"&gt;NAVFOR Operation ATALANTA&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/Combined-Task-Force-151"&gt;Combined Task Force 151&lt;/a&gt; in the Horn of Africa region, and supports the UK Maritime Trade Operation (run by the Royal Navy and based in the British Embassy in Dubai) - and provide humanitarian and development assistance to Somalia to counteract the root causes of piracy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting countries in the region to let seized pirates be prosecuted regionally - the UK has agreements in place with the Seychelles, Mauritius and Tanzania&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting Somalia in reducing poverty and to enhance stabilisation, peace building and reconciliation at national, regional and local levels. This supports our counter-piracy and counter-terrorism objectives by helping, over the longer term, to bring down the causes of piracy and terrorism and to prevent their continuation. The Department for International Development’s (&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) 4-year £250 million Somalia programme will play a crucial role in achieving this outcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting the shipping industry advice on self-protection measures on how to avoid, deter and delay pirate attacks, and through government  guidelines on the use of armed guards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing advice to travellers in the region so you ‘know before you go’ and can be aware of any risks in the area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting the recognition of Somalia’s Exclusive Economic Zone, which will help protect its natural maritime resources up to 200 nautical miles from its coastal baselines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading efforts to undermine the piracy business model, including through establishing a Regional Anti-Piracy Prosecution and Intelligence Co-ordination Centre (&lt;abbr title="Regional Anti-Piracy Prosecution and Intelligence Coordination Centre"&gt;RAPPICC&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Seychelles.  The &lt;abbr title="Regional Anti-Piracy Prosecution and Intelligence Coordination Centre"&gt;RAPPICC&lt;/abbr&gt; will target the leaders, financiers and enablers of piracy by building evidence packages for use in their prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Piracy Ransoms Task Force was established by David Cameron in February 2012 for threatened countries to work together to reduce the threat of piracy and ransom payments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK continues to work with the international community to provide humanitarian and development assistance. This helps to tackle the underlying causes of piracy: long term instability and lack of development in the Somali region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is working with the UN Office on Drugs and Crime, the UN Development Programme (&lt;abbr title="UN Development Programme"&gt;UNDP&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the International Maritime Organization to develop sustainable livelihoods in coastal communities, which complements &lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;’s programme of building long-term and sustainable jobs and economic opportunities in Somalia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example of such work is the Sustainable Employment and Economic Development Programme, a joint project with &lt;abbr title="UN Development Programme"&gt;UNDP&lt;/abbr&gt; Somalia.  The programme is aimed at working to improve the livelihoods of various stakeholders in the fisheries sector in Puntland.  It will result in improved regulation and development through public-private partnerships, with the aim to create 20,000 long-term jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has lead responsibility in the Contact Group on Piracy off the Coast of Somalia for working group one, whose focus is on regional capacity development and military engagement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naval operations to counter piracy and armed robbery off the coast of Somalia operate under the authority of the UN Security Council. Since 2008, the Security Council has passed a number of resolutions authorising military operations, the most recent of which is the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/N11/604/21/PDF/N1160421.pdf?OpenElement"&gt;UN Security Council Resolution 2077&lt;/a&gt; (2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/Depts/los/convention_agreements/convention_overview_convention.htm"&gt;UN Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS)&lt;/a&gt; defines the act of piracy and provides the basis for the prosecution of piracy and maritime crime offences.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50198</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:45:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/piracy-ransoms-task-force-publishes-recommendations"/>
    <title>Piracy Ransoms Task Force publishes recommendations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Today the Piracy Ransoms Task Force presented its conclusions on how to work together to reduce the threat of piracy and ultimately ransom payments to pirates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Task Force was established by the Prime Minister, David Cameron, after the London Conference on Somalia in February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14-nation Task Force, brought together policy makers from some of the world’s largest Flag States (countries where vessels are registered), nations whose seafarers are most commonly at risk, and those countries at the forefront of the military response to piracy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Task Force made four recommendations in its final report to the Contact Group on Piracy off the Coast of Somalia in New York:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a new strategic partnership between Flag States, the private sector and law enforcement agencies that brings together those tackling piracy and those subjected to it in a united effort to break the piracy business model;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a more co-ordinated approach to information-sharing to provide evidence to pursue and prosecute all involved in piracy;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen co-ordination between Flag States, the private sector and military responders to prepare for potential hostage situations; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage implementation of anti-piracy measures, including greater compliance with Best Management Practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s conclusions from the Piracy Ransoms Task Force are a welcome step in the right direction. International action, led by the UK, is starting to beat back in the global fight against piracy. The dramatic reduction in pirate activity in the past year shows how important collective action is, and the recommendations of the Task Force should make it harder for pirates to receive, and to profit from, ransom payments. But seafarers of all nations remain at risk, and we must continue to work to break the piracy business model, with the ultimate ambition of bringing an end to ransom payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Government firmly supports and endorses the conclusions of the Piracy Ransoms Task Force. Only through the international community working together to break the pirates’ business model will we reach a position whereby pirates are no longer able to receive or profit from ransom payments. The Government will continue to work as a leading member of the Contact Group and with industry in taking forward the implementation of the task force’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council in a Written Ministerial Statement.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35286</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-09T20:31:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-sharpens-skills-for-the-gulf"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth sharpens skills for the Gulf</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The ship's company of Royal Navy warship HMS Monmouth have been keeping themselves in shape and ready for operations in the Gulf while transiting the Mediterranean.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate and crew of 215 left Plymouth last month and will be policing busy shipping lanes in the Gulf crucial to maritime trade in order to disrupt and deter piracy and other illegal activities at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep the ship at a high level of readiness takes a lot of training and hard work, so, during the ship’s transit to the region, the crew have been taking part in a wide variety of physical and military exercises to keep themselves ready for operational duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A period in the eastern Mediterranean allowed the weapon engineering department to take advantage of a NATO training exercise in Crete and prove the accuracy of all sensors and weapon systems on board. This also allowed the ship’s Royal Navy and Royal Marines boarding teams to participate in multiple boarding exercises with Greek forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One dramatic element of the training was ‘fast roping’ down to the ship from a Lynx helicopter operated and maintained by members of the ship’s flight from 815 Naval Air Squadron, who are embarked for the deployment. The warfare department also provided gun shoots and small-arms firings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Marine White takes part in a continuation shoot on board HMS Monmouth whilst transiting the Mediterranean en route to the Gulf " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1587/HMS_Monmouth_sharpens_skills_for_the_Gulf2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Marine White takes part in a continuation shoot on board HMS Monmouth whilst transiting the Mediterranean en route to the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Ben Shread, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While shooting, fast roping and simulated boarding of small boats took place above deck, the chefs were busy cooking meals for the ship’s company but still found the time to make a replica chocolate version of Nelson’s flagship Victory for the wardroom’s Trafalgar Night dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sailors themselves are also being put through their paces by Leading Physical Trainer Danny Card who has been running boxing circuits and early morning workouts each day to keep them fighting fit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Almost 100 per cent of the ship’s company are in date for their standard fitness test and the majority are highly motivated to get fitter during the deployment,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a high demand for lots of different types of fitness training, with every range of fitness represented taking part in physical exercise on board each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This busy period for the ship’s company supplements the months of operational training they had before leaving the UK - the crew of HMS Monmouth is ready in all respects if called into action in the patrol area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35569</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-highlights-risk-of-kidnap-to-british-nationals-in-sahel-region"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa highlights risk of kidnap to British nationals in Sahel region</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, met members of the travel industry today to explain and emphasise the FCO’s travel advice on the Sahel region to British nationals, including the high risk of kidnap in certain areas of the Sahel and North Africa.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Simmonds detailed how the kidnap threat to western travellers in Mali and some neighbouring areas had grown as a result of instability in the region.  He reinforced how seriously the British Government takes the threat to British nationals overseas. Foreign Office officials asked the industry to highlight the risks and consider alternative options where travellers can still find adventure, but be safe too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Simmonds said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The British government takes the threat to British nationals overseas extremely seriously.  We urge tour operators, including rally organisers, to work with us to make sure that British nationals are fully aware of the serious risks involved in travelling to these areas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The terrorist groups Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb (AQ-M) and the splinter group, the Movement for Unity and Jihad in West Africa, pose the greatest kidnap threat. Since the recent coup in Mali, both groups have increased their operational reach and have proven capability to travel long distances to kidnap victims.  They have also been known to use criminal gangs to conduct attacks and pass hostages to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Attacks have taken place in Mali, Niger, Mauritania and Algeria. We also assess that they have operational reach into the north of Burkina Faso and southern Libya and I am sorry to say that the situation is likely to still get worse.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
