<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/crime-and-policing</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/crime-and-policing"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/crime-and-policing.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Crime and policing"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65670</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--107"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"&gt;updated parliament on the crisis in Syria&lt;/a&gt; and outlined further UK action for the coming weeks. He said: “Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;meeting organised by the UK this week,&lt;/a&gt; the Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt will &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"&gt;answer questions about the UK’s policy on Syria&lt;/a&gt; via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"&gt;Foreign Secretary met the Secretary General of the League of Arab States&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the Middle East Peace Process and Syria. Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Secretary said: “We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bahrain"&gt;Bahrain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt expressed dismay at the decision&lt;/a&gt;, saying: “I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pakistan"&gt;Pakistan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"&gt;condemned the brutal terrorist attacks in Quetta and Swat this week.&lt;/a&gt; He said: “The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="saudi-arabia"&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemned the beheading&lt;/a&gt; of a Sri Lankan national Rizana Nafeek and reiterated the UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"&gt;urged the Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of respected community leader Sombath Somphone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Baugh the British Ambassador to Somalia &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/mattbaugh/2013/01/09/somalia-a-new-years-resolution-together-into-2013/"&gt;blogged about how the changes of 2012 offer better prospects for improved stability in Somalia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We advised British nationals travelling in Australia to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"&gt;check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65623</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns terrorist attacks in Pakistan </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has condemned yesterday’s terrorist attacks in Pakistan and sent his condolences to those affected. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was extremely saddened to hear of the brutal terrorist and sectarian attacks in Quetta and Swat yesterday. My thoughts are with the families of those who have been killed. I wish all those injured in the attacks a swift recovery. The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60315</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-warship-spends-christmas-on-operations"/>
    <title>Royal Navy warship spends Christmas on operations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sailors of HMS Monmouth keeping the oceans safe from criminals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While their families celebrate Christmas at home, the crew of  the Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate, will be spending Christmas engaged in countering piracy, smuggling and similar illegal activity. The ship, also known as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="the Black Duke"&gt;the Black Duke&lt;/a&gt; after its traitor namesake, is part of a coalition naval force policing the Gulf and keeping crucial trade routes safe for the UK’s imports and exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of the busy programme, members of the crew have found some time to prepare for the festivities with both the chaplain and the chefs limbering-up for the seasonal cheer and religious service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Chef Paul Gough said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve stocked the freezers in anticipation that we’ll be getting through more than two hundred pounds of turkey, beef and gammon for Christmas lunch; and yes, we’ve also made sure we’ve got plenty of sprouts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5807/Xmas_operations_room__HMS_Monmouth_2012.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It's beginning to look at lot like Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reverend Andrew Allcock, the ship’s chaplain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas is often a time for both celebration and reflection – the latter probably more so this year as we are away from home. It’s my hope that most people on board will have an opportunity to do both with our Christmas services including a traditional midnight communion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship will be patrolling the Gulf region until her return to the UK in the spring. While principal tasks on this deployment involve intercepting and boarding suspect vessels, HMS Monmouth is also ready and equipped to provide humanitarian aid or mount an evacuation in the case of war or natural disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe Ministerial Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56873</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:23:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/private-security-companies"/>
    <title>Private Security Companies</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the development of a regulatory system for private security companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aims to raise the global standards of private security companies (&lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;) working in complex and high risk environments overseas. To this end, we have been working closely with interested partners, including industry and civil society, to establish a voluntary, independently audited and internationally recognised regulatory system that is practicable, effective and affordable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certification to professional standards is the next step towards effective voluntary regulation. First the Government endorsed the Montreux Document in 2008, in which States commit to observe existing international legal obligations relevant to the operations of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in areas of armed conflict. Secondly, in 2010, an International Code of Conduct for Private Security Providers (&lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt;) was created. This provides a set of principles to guide companies. The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; has now been signed by over 500 &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt;, around a third of them British. We have reviewed options on setting new professional standards to make the Code effective. We now intend to issue an HMG publication specifying that ASIS PSC 1-2012 is the applicable standard for UK-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments on land overseas. I will place a copy of the publication in the libraries of both Houses. Companies, independent auditors and the UK Accreditation Service (&lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;) will then take the further steps to enable auditing against these standards to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; mandated the development of auditable standards to ensure that signatory companies are implementing their commitments under the code. In response to this requirement, the international security trade association, ASIS, was funded by the Department of Defense to develop the standard – ‘PSC1’ – for the regulation of private security companies operating on land in complex environments overseas. This standard was drafted in a multinational and multi-stakeholder forum in which UK Government, UK industry and UK civil society fully participated.  It was published in March 2012 as an approved American National Standard and is the only standard currently available for companies operating in this field. &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; seeking certification in the UK to this new standard will have to be audited by independent third party auditors accredited by &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our trade association partners, the Security in Complex Environments Group, will, in consultation with Government, develop guidance to help British &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; meet the requirements of the new standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ambition is to have a single, internationally agreed standard and we therefore welcome the fact that PSC1 was recently submitted to the International Standards Organisation (ISO) to be considered for adoption as an international standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in complex environments. This process may take some time. We will review the need for a separate HMG publication of this standard once the ISO process has been completed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working with other States, industry and civil society internationally to ensure that there should be globally recognised standards and that UK companies are not unfairly disadvantaged by raising their standards. We expect that the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; governing board, when established, will advise that certification to the PSC 1 standard by suitably accredited independent auditors will meet the Code’s requirements for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to have auditable professional standards. We are still consulting with industry and civil society partners on what additional steps &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; might need to take to obtain full certification by the &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; that they are meeting the Code’s principles but I can confirm that there will be no need for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; to go through duplicate auditing procedures to become certified.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="International Code of Conduct for Private Security Service Providers"&gt;ICOC&lt;/abbr&gt; was drafted with land-based &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; in mind. However, since 2010 there has been a rapid rise in the number of &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on anti-piracy operations at sea. Although many of the principles relating to &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working on land and at sea are similar, there are important legal and practical differences. The Government is therefore also contributing to an international drafting process under the ISO for an equivalent professional standard for &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; working in the maritime sector. A draft maritime standard was introduced at the International Maritime Organisation in late November. If and when this standard is adopted, &lt;abbr title="UK Accreditation Service"&gt;UKAS&lt;/abbr&gt; will start the process of accrediting suitably qualified independent third party auditors to certify UK-based maritime &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; under it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity on the standards against which &lt;abbr title="private security companies"&gt;PSCs&lt;/abbr&gt; should be audited is an important step forward in the drive to raise standards in this industry through voluntary action, but independently audited. It is also a practical illustration of the Government’s commitment to human rights and to working with business and civil society to find effective ways to implement our commitments even in the most challenging environments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56611</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-welcomes-new-counter-terrorism-centre-in-uae"/>
    <title>UK welcomes new counter terrorism centre in UAE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has welcomed the opening of a Centre of Excellence on Countering Violent Extremism in Abu Dhabi.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the broad experience and expertise of the 30 Global Counter-Terrorism Forum (GCTF) founding member nations, the Centre will lead global research on the drivers of terrorism, deliver training to address these, and identify practical, operational initiatives to reduce the threat from terrorism. It was launched at the third ministerial meeting of the GCTF in the United Arab Emirates (UAE), which was attended by representatives from all member nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tunisia, where he is on an official visit, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s launch in Abu Dhabi of the Centre of Excellence for Countering Violent Extremism (CVE) is an important milestone in the global fight against terrorism. In particular I welcome the leadership that His Excellency Foreign Minister Abdullah bin Zayed has shown and the Emirati commitment to host the Centre and make it a reality. The UK will continue to give it our full support. We have nominated an expert to serve as a Member of the International Steering Board and are seconding a Director of Training &amp;amp; Capacity-Building into the Centre’s senior management team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to do our utmost to tackle the root causes of terrorism by ensuring a collaborative international approach to the common threat of terrorism. The Global Counter Terrorism Forum offers us an excellent platform from which to address this constantly changing challenge, drawing on the expertise and experience of its members”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thegctf.org/web/guest/about" title="Global Counter-Terrorism Forum"&gt;Global Counter-Terrorism Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55664</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism"/>
    <title>Protecting the UK against terrorism</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Preventing terrorist attacks on the UK, and on British people and businesses abroad.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a threat to the UK, British nationals and our interests abroad from terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of these threats come from outside the UK and cannot be resolved by concentrating efforts in the UK alone. The government is addressing these threats at their source overseas before they reach the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s Counter Terrorism Strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/counter-terrorism-strategy/"&gt;CONTEST&lt;/a&gt;, reduces the risk from international terrorism so that people can go about their daily lives freely and with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on 4 main actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent: to stop people from becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pursue: to stop terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protect: to strengthen our protection against terrorist attack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prepare: where an attack cannot be stopped, to mitigate its impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prevent"&gt;Prevent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to stop people becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism in the UK and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;responding to the ideological challenge of terrorism and the threat we face from those who promote it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing people from being drawn into terrorism and ensuring that they are given appropriate advice and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with sectors and institutions where there are risks of radicalisation which we need to address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/prevent/prevent-strategy/"&gt;latest information on the Prevent strategy&lt;/a&gt; on the Home Office website. This includes the full text of the strategy and the outcomes of the Prevent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pursue"&gt;Pursue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/pursue/"&gt;Pursue&lt;/a&gt; strand of the strategy means working to detect and investigate terrorist networks and disrupt their activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving our ability to identify and understand the terrorist threat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disrupting terrorist activity and taking action to frustrate terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing terrorists to justice through prosecution – this  includes strengthening the legal framework against terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing international co-operation with partners and allies to strengthen our ability to work together to disrupt terrorist networks, for instance by using &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism/supporting-pages/deportation-with-assurances"&gt;Deportation with Assurances&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="protect"&gt;Protect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/protect/"&gt;Protect&lt;/a&gt; strand means seeking to reduce the vulnerability of the UK and its interests overseas from terrorist attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing accurate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/"&gt;FCO travel advice&lt;/a&gt; on the threat from domestic and international terrorism, with advice for British companies abroad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting key foreign governments to develop their ability to protect areas such as aviation and maritime security, energy infrastructure, crowded places and ‘soft’ targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prepare"&gt;Prepare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/prepare/"&gt;Prepare&lt;/a&gt; strand means working to mitigate the impact of a terrorist attack where it cannot be stopped. This includes work to manage an ongoing attack and recover from its aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preparing the FCO network to respond to terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting foreign governments to develop their own ability to respond to terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advances in technology by both terrorists and organised crime groups create challenges to our national security. The UK’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/science-and-technology/science-and-technology-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;Science and Technology Strategy for Countering International Terrorism&lt;/a&gt; uses innovation, science and technology to reduce the risk to the UK and its interests overseas from international terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al Qaeda is weaker than at any time since 9/11. It has played no role in recent political change in North Africa and the Middle East. Its ideology has been widely discredited and it has failed in all its objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continued international pressure has further reduced its capability and the UK is working with other countries to weaken terrorist threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, al Qaeda continues to be a significant threat and other terrorist groups, some affiliated to al Qaeda, have become stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/"&gt;Home Office&lt;/a&gt; is responsible for keeping the UK safe from the threat posed by terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The determination of the government and everyone involved in the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games was to create a safe and secure event that the UK and the world could enjoy. We thoroughly tested our plans to see how government departments, police and emergency services could respond to a range of incidents.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The games’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/olympics/olympic-safety-security-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;safety and security strategy&lt;/a&gt; has helped communities become more resilient to crime and the threat from violent extremism, and relationships between police and other security agencies have improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the event of a terrorist incident, the Office for Security and Counter-Terrorism is responsible for activating and co-ordinating the Home Office response. We provide a crisis response 24 hours a day, 365 days of the year. The government’s response to all kinds of emergencies, including terrorism, is set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaem.com/regions/iaemeuropa/documents/UKConOps.pdf"&gt;Central government arrangements for responding to an emergency: concept of operations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
