<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Defence and armed forces"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-13T16:30:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65763</id>
    <published>2013-01-13T16:30:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-13T16:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/united-kingdom-assistance-for-french-mali-operation"/>
    <title>United Kingdom assistance for French Mali operation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds spoke about the situation in Mali in a series of media interviews on Sunday 13 January.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the BBC News channel, Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds discussed the UK Government’s offer of logistical support to the French Government:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK has offered, at French request, two transport aircraft. As the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary have confirmed, there’ll be no British forces involved in a combat role at all. We’ve been concerned alongside the international community about the situation in northern Mali for some time. The northern part of Mali is controlled by al Qaeda and other terrorist organisations and that poses a potential direct threat to the UK and regional stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re working with the United Nations where there have been two resolutions and the African Union and ECOWAS, which is the African regional organisation, to provide both an immediate and a long term sustainable solution to the challenge that is faced in Mali.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier on Sky’s Murnaghan programme, Mark Simmonds underlined the importance of regional action on Mali. He said it was right that ECOWAS, the western African organisation, would ultimately be at the forefront of action. ECOWAS will form part of the future deployment of a longer-term African led intervention force authorised by UN Security Council Resolutions last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds also noted that there were ongoing discussions on providing training for the Malian Army through a European Union training mission.  This was most recently discussed at the European Council in December. He said that the UK would continue to work with international partners to encourage progress on an inclusive political process in Mali which would be important for long-term stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/statement-on-pm-call-with-president-hollande/"&gt;Statement on UK assistance to the French Mali operation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs//2013/sc10878.doc.htm"&gt;United Nations Security Council Press Statement on Mali, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2085%282012%29"&gt;United Nations Security Council Resolution 2085 on Mali, 20 December 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2071%282012%29"&gt;United Nations Security Council Resolution 2071 on Mali and the Sahel, 10 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65670</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--107"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"&gt;updated parliament on the crisis in Syria&lt;/a&gt; and outlined further UK action for the coming weeks. He said: “Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;meeting organised by the UK this week,&lt;/a&gt; the Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt will &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"&gt;answer questions about the UK’s policy on Syria&lt;/a&gt; via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"&gt;Foreign Secretary met the Secretary General of the League of Arab States&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the Middle East Peace Process and Syria. Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Secretary said: “We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bahrain"&gt;Bahrain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt expressed dismay at the decision&lt;/a&gt;, saying: “I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pakistan"&gt;Pakistan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"&gt;condemned the brutal terrorist attacks in Quetta and Swat this week.&lt;/a&gt; He said: “The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="saudi-arabia"&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemned the beheading&lt;/a&gt; of a Sri Lankan national Rizana Nafeek and reiterated the UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"&gt;urged the Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of respected community leader Sombath Somphone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Baugh the British Ambassador to Somalia &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/mattbaugh/2013/01/09/somalia-a-new-years-resolution-together-into-2013/"&gt;blogged about how the changes of 2012 offer better prospects for improved stability in Somalia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We advised British nationals travelling in Australia to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"&gt;check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65619</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T14:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T15:05:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-typhoon-aircraft-exercise-in-uae"/>
    <title>RAF Typhoon aircraft exercise in UAE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Typhoon aircraft of 6 Squadron have been exercising with a multinational contingent at Al Dhafra Air Base in the United Arab Emirates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has been the first time that aircraft, engineers and pilots from the squadron, normally based at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars, have deployed together on the Advanced Tactical Leadership Course (&lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;), which runs each year at Al Dhafra Air Base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Mike Baulkwill, Officer Commanding  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/6squadron.cfm" title="6 Squadron RAF web page"&gt;6 Squadron&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been sent out here to conduct this multinational exercise that looks at large scale air operations involving many aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been run over a number of weeks, giving the pilots, ground crew and support staff an opportunity to work alongside other nations. The squadron have been running air interdiction missions, self-escort missions and offensive and defensive counter air missions as part of the exercise. This has required the pilots and aircraft to be quick and reactive in a multi-role platform in all types of operational scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been conducted in 2 parts - one wave of flying per day in support of the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt; missions and one following wave each day where the pilots can fly alongside multinational aircraft to conduct further training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Baulkwill added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen the ground crew and pilots from 6 Squadron lead and operate in a very different environment. Everybody at every rank is learning something from this exercise. We are learning to operate fully combat capable aircraft in a hot and dry environment which is very different to conditions at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senior Aircraftman Sam Norry, an Aircraft Maintenance Mechanic on 6 Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my first detachment and it has been much harder work out here. There are a lot more elements to contend with - temperatures alone are incredible, you have to drink a lot more water. Not only that, on the engineering side of things, you don’t have that instant support that you have in the UK - there are fewer people to work on the aircraft so you really have to work together and work hard to get the jobs done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An RAF Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6026/AUAB_UNC_20121210_239_026.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;To summarise the squadron’s support to the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Wing Commander Baulkwill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been operating huge missions with other nations, sometimes operating an air picture involving 60 aircraft with simulated high threat missions. It has been incredibly hard work for all of the pilots and the ground crew to support this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have found ourselves pushed hard, and the  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon FGR4 web page"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; aircraft has performed exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The systems that it has on board are second-to-none and we have seen the benefit of that - it has been impressive to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65623</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns terrorist attacks in Pakistan </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has condemned yesterday’s terrorist attacks in Pakistan and sent his condolences to those affected. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was extremely saddened to hear of the brutal terrorist and sectarian attacks in Quetta and Swat yesterday. My thoughts are with the families of those who have been killed. I wish all those injured in the attacks a swift recovery. The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65592</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"/>
    <title>FCO Minister to answer questions on Syria via Twitter</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions on Syria live via Twitter on 14 January 11:15am-12:00pm GMT.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his statement to Parliament on 10 January, the Foreign Secretary set out further UK action on Syria in the coming weeks. On 9-10 January, the UK organised a successful meeting at Wilton Park as part of our efforts in stepping up support for Syrian-led political transition and planning for the day after Assad. The meeting was an important step in taking forward this support. The Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives from 14 countries and international organisations agreed, alongside the Syrian National Coalition, that transition should build towards a Syria which offers equal opportunities for all, through which all Syrians can help determine the shape of a future Syria. This was an important milestone in Syria’s journey towards a lasting and peaceful democracy and we hope that our contributions play an important role in shaping it. The UK stands ready to support transition in Syria. But it will be a collective international effort to assist the Syrian National Coalition to bring about the changes the Syrian people so truly deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions about the UK’s policy towards Syria live via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm GMT. Questions can be submitted to Mr Burt &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt; using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt;. He will answer questions in English and as many as time allows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can follow the Q&amp;amp;A using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65593</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T10:38:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-pistols-for-uk-armed-forces"/>
    <title>New pistols for UK Armed Forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Armed Forces are to be supplied with more than 25,000 new Glock sidearms to replace the ageing Browning pistols currently in service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://us.glock.com/products/model/g17gen4" title="Glock 17 Gen4 pistol web page"&gt;Glock 17 Gen4 pistol&lt;/a&gt; is not only much lighter than the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/forceprotection/browning9mmpistol.cfm" title="Browning 9mm pistol web page"&gt;Browning L9A1&lt;/a&gt;, it is also more accurate and its magazines can carry more bullets. It has an increased magazine capacity of 17 rounds, compared to 13 rounds for the Browning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel across all 3 Services will begin to receive the new 9-millimetre (mm) calibre Glock 17s in the coming weeks and troops deployed to Afghanistan will be among the first to use the new weapon. The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.vikingarms.com/" title="Viking Arms Ltd website"&gt;Viking Arms &lt;abbr title="Limited"&gt;Ltd&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Harrogate, Yorkshire, also includes more than 25,000 holsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Glock 17 pistol (left) and a Browning 9mm pistol" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6012/ArmyHQ-2013-003-052_aGlock_17_pistol_EMBARG_00.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Glock 17 pistol (left) and the Browning the new pistols will replace [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Mark Anderson, Royal Marines, who trialled the new weapon before the contract was awarded, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pistols are vital in close combat and are a key part of a soldier’s armoury. Reliable, light and easy to carry, the Glock inspires confidence and performs exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide our troops with the best possible personal kit available and these new Glock 17s will give them greater firepower and accuracy on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Glock pistol is fired on a range" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6013/Emb_DES-2013-003-0250.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines firearms instructor Sergeant Steve Lord demonstrates the new Glock pistol on the range at Woolwich Barracks in London [Picture: Andrew Linnett, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sidearms are a valuable weapon for servicemen and women on the battlefield, and the new Glock, manufactured in Austria, will complement the wide range of weapons already available to our forces, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA80A2 assault rifles, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light machine guns, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharpshooter rifles, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;general purpose machine guns, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;combat shotguns, which fire 12-gauge cartridges; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sniper systems, which fire 8.59mm rounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Glock pistols will replace the Browning which after being used by the Armed Forces for more than 40 years has become increasingly expensive to maintain. The contract for a replacement pistol was put out to tender 2 years ago and is not in response to any specific or increased threat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65367</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-lynx-aids-capture-of-suspected-pirates"/>
    <title>Royal Navy Lynx aids capture of suspected pirates</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A Lynx helicopter and a crew from the Royal Navy have helped arrest 12 armed suspected pirates off the coast of Somalia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flight 217 of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; is currently deployed on board the French frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/News-and-Events/Latest-News/2013/January/03/121220-Blog-Surcouf" title="Read the blog from 815 Lynx Squadron on board the French frigate Surcouf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf&lt;/a&gt; as part of Operation Atalanta, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s counter-piracy mission off the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lynx was sent ahead by the French warship to find the suspected pirates after the &lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Halyburton, operating as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.manw.nato.int/page_operation_ocean_shield.aspx" title="Operation Ocean Shield web page"&gt;Operation Ocean Shield&lt;/a&gt;, received a distress call from a merchant vessel reporting she was under attack from 6 men armed with rocket-propelled grenades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6008/20130110surcouf3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel as Flight 217's Lynx helicopter hovers above [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;abbr title="Merchant Ship Characteristic"&gt;MSC&lt;/abbr&gt; Jasmine, sailing 260 miles off the Somali coast, managed to repel the attack themselves, a German &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; maritime patrol aircraft was scrambled to track the suspect vessel, which was by then towing another boat with several more men on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy Lynx sped to the scene and ordered the vessels to stop while French commandos from Surcouf arrived alongside in a fast boat and quickly boarded, resulting in the suspected pirates swiftly surrendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon searching the pirates’ boats, the commandos also discovered containers of diesel and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 12 suspects are now being held on board &lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf for evidence collection in order to fully assess the possibility of prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="French frigate Sucouf seen from Lynx helicopter cockpit" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6009/20130110surcouf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of the French frigate Sucouf from the Lynx helicopter cockpit of Flight 217 from 815 Naval Air Squadron [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commander of Flight 217, Lieutenant Mike Curd, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The whole operation was an excellent exercise in teamwork, with the US ship and Surcouf co-ordinating their efforts, including both units’ helicopters, to successfully track the 2 suspect vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our Lynx actually performed the ‘stop’ and support to boarding of both the suspect vessels and provided airborne support to the subsequent boarding operations. It was a long and tiring day that began before dawn, but by the end of it we were proud of a job well done; the procedures and routines we’d practised so many times worked extremely efficiently and by nightfall we knew we had played a large part in the successful apprehension of a dozen suspected pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of the Royal Navy’s Lynx on board the Surcouf is the first of its kind as part of the terms of the Lancaster House Treaty. Under this the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; and France agreed military co-operation to assure their international commitments and strengthen their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65345</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-health-partnership-awards-launched"/>
    <title>2013 Health Partnership Awards launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nominations are now open for this year's Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards which were launched today in Cardiff and Edinburgh.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ceremony honours the people, projects and initiatives that provide serving military personnel, including reservists, and their families and veterans with the very best in healthcare and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awards are open to civilian health staff and military medics working within the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-medical-services" title="Defence Medical Services website"&gt;Defence Medical Services&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/" title="NHS website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and private or voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 awards ceremony, to be held on 21 May, is being hosted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/" title="Welsh Government website"&gt;Welsh Government&lt;/a&gt; and, from today, people can nominate individuals or teams who provide care and support to Service personnel. Nominations close on 21 February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two launch ceremonies took place today - one at the Army’s Dreghorn Barracks in Edinburgh and one at the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/11018.aspx" title="203 Field Hospital web page"&gt;203 (Welsh) Field Hospital&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards provide a great opportunity to pay tribute to the dedication and fantastic results that our military and civilian colleagues achieve by working together to improve military health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to encourage people to visit the website to nominate all those who have provided the very best health and social care to our Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the awards in Cardiff, Welsh Health Minister Lesley Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud Wales is hosting the 2013 awards. The awards celebrate the hard work, commitment and dedication shown by health professionals from across the public, private and voluntary sectors in caring for the men and women of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important we recognise the immense contribution the Armed Forces and veterans have made to our country. We owe them a huge debt of gratitude and a duty of care, particularly those who have developed health problems as a result of their military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Tri-Service healthcare specialists" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6006/hqscot-2013-001-4476.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The awards honour the people who provide military personnel with the best health and social care [Picture: Mark Owens, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also vital we acknowledge the role of those who care for and support Service personnel and veterans, especially in recent years when the Armed Forces have been heavily engaged overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would encourage people to consider nominating either themselves or others for these awards as it is important we recognise their contribution to improving the lives of Service personnel and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Health Minister Dr Dan Poulter said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These awards will shine a light on the efforts of the military, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Service charities to make sure members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans have the best care possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such important work should not go unnoticed. I urge people to put themselves or their colleagues forward to have their efforts and achievements in caring for our Armed Forces, their families and veterans recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;203 Field Hospital was founded in 1914 and consists of reservist volunteers made up of civilian, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and military medics. The unit has already begun preparations for its upcoming deployment to Afghanistan in support of the Regular Army on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event included a demonstration of the treatment of a casualty from ambulance to resuscitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Lesley Griffiths was accompanied by Surgeon Rear Admiral Calum McArthur, Brigadier Philip Napier, Commander of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/28224.aspx" title="160 (Wales) Brigade web page"&gt;160 (Wales) Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, and Colonel Tina Donnelly, Commanding Officer of 203 Field Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the awards, including how to apply or nominate, are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org/" title="Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards website"&gt;www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65616</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:17:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sails-into-london-boat-show"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sails into London Boat Show</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Royal Navy looks set to be a major draw at the London Boat Show, which opens at the ExCel Exhibition Centre this weekend.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an island nation, the UK’s prosperity and security are dependant on its ability to access the sea. That is why the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk" title="Royal Navy website"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; is globally deployed and has a range of versatile ships, submarines and aircraft operated by professional sailors, aviators and Royal Marines Commandos. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy will be at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonboatshow.com/2013/home.aspx" title="London Boat Show website"&gt;London Boat Show&lt;/a&gt; from 12 to 20 January, where visitors can learn more about naval life and how, every minute of every day, somewhere in the world they are protecting the nation’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cougar beach landing rehearsal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5921/offshoreraidingcraft.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from 45 Commando and HMS Bulwark carry out a beach assault in Plymouth [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as celebrating the Navy’s rich heritage, show visitors can learn how they operate across a variety of missions from anti-terrorism and counter-narcotics to disaster relief and peacekeeping operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy stand will include an opportunity to get up close to an advanced offshore raiding craft (&lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt;). Measuring 9 metres long and able to travel in excess of 35 knots, the craft were part of the Navy’s commitment to keeping the public safe during the Olympic Games. The &lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt; can also be equipped with general purpose machine guns, making them a highly-flexible and potent deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Boat Show, a Navy Search and Rescue Sea King Mark 5 will take to the skies beside ExCeL at 1400hrs on Saturday, 12 January, to illustrate what a rescue operation entails. The renowned Mark 5 is now the Navy’s workhorse of choice, operating in extreme conditions and ready to respond at a moment’s notice in an emergency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A four-man crew from 771 Naval Air Squadron in Cornwall will manoeuvre the helicopter with precision to make a simulated rescue from the dock. The helicopter will return on Sunday, 13 January, for a further demonstration at 1130hrs before heading back to its Cornish base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the show, the Search and Rescue crew will be at the C180 stand to meet the public and answer questions about the service, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/About-the-Royal-Navy/The-Navy-and-the-Environment/In-the-Air" title="Fleet Air Arm web page"&gt;Fleet Air Arm&lt;/a&gt; and the wider Royal Navy. There will also be the opportunity to attend a free daily presentation exploring the role of Search and Rescue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
