<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/defence-and-armed-forces.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Defence and armed forces"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60315</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-warship-spends-christmas-on-operations"/>
    <title>Royal Navy warship spends Christmas on operations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sailors of HMS Monmouth keeping the oceans safe from criminals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While their families celebrate Christmas at home, the crew of  the Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate, will be spending Christmas engaged in countering piracy, smuggling and similar illegal activity. The ship, also known as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="the Black Duke"&gt;the Black Duke&lt;/a&gt; after its traitor namesake, is part of a coalition naval force policing the Gulf and keeping crucial trade routes safe for the UK’s imports and exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of the busy programme, members of the crew have found some time to prepare for the festivities with both the chaplain and the chefs limbering-up for the seasonal cheer and religious service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Chef Paul Gough said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve stocked the freezers in anticipation that we’ll be getting through more than two hundred pounds of turkey, beef and gammon for Christmas lunch; and yes, we’ve also made sure we’ve got plenty of sprouts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5807/Xmas_operations_room__HMS_Monmouth_2012.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It's beginning to look at lot like Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reverend Andrew Allcock, the ship’s chaplain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas is often a time for both celebration and reflection – the latter probably more so this year as we are away from home. It’s my hope that most people on board will have an opportunity to do both with our Christmas services including a traditional midnight communion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship will be patrolling the Gulf region until her return to the UK in the spring. While principal tasks on this deployment involve intercepting and boarding suspect vessels, HMS Monmouth is also ready and equipped to provide humanitarian aid or mount an evacuation in the case of war or natural disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60566</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-diamond-arrives-home-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Diamond arrives home in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Diamond has returned home to Portsmouth today following her maiden deployment to the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyer&lt;/a&gt; sailed more than 31,000 miles (50,000 kilometres) on security and counter-piracy patrols in the Indian Ocean, Gulf of Oman and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; left Portsmouth in June shortly after launching the nation’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations with a ceremonial entry into the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth" title="Portsmouth Naval Base"&gt;naval base&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After travelling through the Mediterranean she transited the Suez Canal before taking over from sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Daring" title="HMS Daring"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Daring&lt;/a&gt;. Diamond then spent the following 5 months as part of the Combined Task Force, a 27-nation partnership promoting security in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship worked with the French Carrier Group in the Mediterranean and three United States Carrier Strike Groups (&lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Middle East, including the escort of the US carriers through the Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s fighter controllers exercised with the US Navy’s F18 Hornets and controlled F22 Raptor and F15 Strike Eagle aircraft from the United States Air Force. The ship’s Lynx aircraft also demonstrated its ability to conduct air intercepts for the task groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also exercised with the navies of Australia, Canada, France, Kuwait, and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While conducting counter-piracy operations the ship’s specialist embarked military force carried out assurance visits to local fishermen and traders and held boarding training with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Commander Ian Clarke is greeted by his family" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5814/FX120552013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond's Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, is greeted by his wife, Joanne, and daughter Rebecca, aged 3 [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have achieved a tremendous amount this deployment and I pay tribute to my fantastic ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have provided reassurance in the Middle East, under the Combined Maritime Forces, worked closely with regional allies and three US &lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt; and really pushed the air defence capability of these fantastic new destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also worked alongside other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; assets, such as minehunters based out of Bahrain and their support ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Bay-Class-Landing-Ships/RFA-Cardigan-Bay" title="RFA Cardigan Bay"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Cardigan Bay&lt;/a&gt;. Helicopters of the Fleet Air Arm were also involved - with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-ASaC" title="Sea King Mk7 Airborne Surveillance and Control"&gt;Sea King Mark 7&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/854" title="854 Squadron"&gt;854 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; making its first ever landing on a Type 45 - while Merlin aircraft also interacted with Diamond at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as time at sea in the region, she has visited Bahrain, Jordan, Kuwait, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, as well as Gibraltar and Crete and the cities of Athens and Barcelona while on transit to and from the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer David Turner said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a busy few months but working with the other navies has been enjoyable, as have all the fascinating places we have visited. Although what we have achieved has been immensely rewarding, after six months away it is good to know that we are back in time to be reunited with our loved ones for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore The Hon Michael Cochrane, Commander Portsmouth Flotilla, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome Diamond back after what has been an exciting and high-profile deployment for the ship’s company, whose work has seen them entering new fields of interest for the air defence community. I am sure they will enjoy their well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond is the third of the UK’s fleet of six Type 45 destroyers. She was launched in 2007, arrived in Portsmouth in the autumn of 2010 and was commissioned in the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60139</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-choir-a-year-with-the-military-wives"/>
    <title>The Choir: a year with the Military Wives</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Choirmaster Gareth Malone and key members of the Military Wives Choir reflect on their extraordinary journey in a Christmas Day television special.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, Gareth Malone went to the military base at Chivenor to set up a choir for the wives left at home alone while their men are on duty for months at a time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html" title="The Choir: a year with the Military Wives"&gt;the Christmas Day show&lt;/a&gt;, we hear from Gareth and key members of the choir as they reflect on their extraordinary journey including their performance of a song, specially written by royal composer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paulmealor.com/" title="Paul Mealor website"&gt;Paul Mealor&lt;/a&gt;, at The Royal Albert Hall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rehearsals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5783/choirpractise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gareth Malone and Military Wives rehearse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film shows the women as they launch their first single, which topped the Christmas charts, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="10 Downing Street website"&gt;10 Downing Street&lt;/a&gt;, perform at the Golden Jubilee and win a Classical Brit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also hear of the legacy of the original choir - the setting up of a charitable foundation that provides the support for a growing network of over 60 military wives choirs in bases across the UK, Europe and the Falkland Islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soloist Sam Stevenson says: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was Gareth’s dream and it came true and not many people can say their dreams have come true in life. I don’t even think I could express to Gareth how grateful we all are for it, it’s just, he’s really changed our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html"&gt;The Choir: A year with the Military Wives&lt;/a&gt; will be on Christmas Day, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo" title="BBC Two website"&gt;BBC2&lt;/a&gt; at 8.45pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60323</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-gives-blueprint-to-potential-infrastructure-partners"/>
    <title>MOD gives blueprint to potential infrastructure partners</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Defence Infrastructure Organisation (DIO), the Ministry of Defence's (MOD) property and services provider, has issued the document which allows the three short-listed teams to prepare detailed bids to potentially become its Strategic Business Partner (SBP).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Invitation to Negotiate (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt;) asks each team to further prove it can provide the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; with a proposal to bring the right skills and expertise, before the organisation makes a final decision regarding its preferred option next summer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organisation, which manages the delivery of infrastructure projects and services for the UK Armed Forces and its civilian support staff, will introduce new ways of working from Spring 2013. However, procuring a &lt;abbr title="Strategic Business Partner"&gt;SBP&lt;/abbr&gt; could realise further savings to benefit Defence as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Manley, Chief Executive, &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s principle objective is to support our military personnel in its Standing Commitments and in preparing for operations. We do this by providing and maintaining the places where they live, work and train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In addition &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; is central to supporting the Government’s wider objectives in construction, property management and the delivery of supporting the services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changing the way we deliver infrastructure services offers a real opportunity to build a leading-edge infrastructure delivery organisation that will serve the needs of our Armed Forces long into the future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are striving to create a high-performing and innovative enterprise. Our search for a Strategic Business Partner is expected to extend our capability by allowing &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; further access to private sector skills and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; has been working to ensure that the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a robust platform to effectively explore the use of private sector expertise. However, a contract will only be awarded if it can be found to provide value for money to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a robust procurement exercise, launched in May 2012, three teams were selected to participate in the next stage of the competition. They consist of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.telerealtrillium.com/" title="Telereal Trillium website"&gt;Telereal Trillium&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kpmg.com/uk/en/pages/default.aspx" title="KPMG website"&gt;KPMG&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.macegroup.com/" title="Mace website"&gt;Mace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.serco.com/" title="Serco website"&gt;Serco&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dtz.com/UK" title="DTZ website"&gt;DTZ&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bechtel.com/" title="Bechtel website"&gt;Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.capita.co.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Capita website"&gt;Capita&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.urscorp.com/" title="URS website"&gt;URS&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paconsulting.co.uk/" title="PA Consulting website"&gt;PA Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60310</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/david-cameron-visits-troops-in-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>David Cameron visits troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Prime Minister praised armed forces success during visit to Camp Bastion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister flew into Afghanistan yesterday morning, 20 December. He visited Camp Bastion, where he met with military commanders before joining troops for an early Christmas dinner and a carol service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s visit came a day after he told &lt;abbr title="Members of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Parliament that troop numbers will almost halve to around 5,200 by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron meets troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5805/PMmeetstroops.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;David Cameron visits Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told journalists on the trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is still a difficult and dangerous place but we’ve made real progress. It is tough, it is difficult, and we’ve paid a high price but their efforts have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander Task Force Helmand, reiterated confidence in the growing capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is now absolutely appropriate we hand more and more control over to the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Cameron met troops who he praised for their service in Afghanistan and thanked them for making the country “prouder than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a message to the armed forces, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well it is a good time to come to Afghanistan and say a really big thank you to our troops for everything they do, and particularly at Christmas time when they’re away from loved ones.  But I think it’s an opportunity to say to all our forces all over the world…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You make us incredibly proud; we’re always proud of you, and this year perhaps prouder than ever for your extraordinary work in Afghanistan, for the amazing things you do over the whole of Africa to keep us safe from terrorism and piracy, for the extraordinary things you did at the Olympics where the military stepped up, put a smiling face on the greatest show on earth, won a lot of medals too and made the country very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military really are the best of the best and we can’t thank them enough for what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
