<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17252</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T16:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-air-rail-conference"/>
    <title>UK Air-Rail Conference</title>
    <summary>The economic importance of air-rail connections, and the government’s record of investment and modernisation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along, it’s a genuine pleasure to be here this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-nation-was-ever-ruined-by-trade"&gt;No nation was ever ruined by trade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Benjamin Franklin, one of America’s founding fathers, who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No nation was ever ruined by trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That statement was spot on when Ben Franklin made it back in the 18th century and it is spot on today, in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade is Britain’s economic lifeblood. We’re an island nation that’s at our best when we’re a trading nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the very reason this government is re-balancing our economy - moving Britain from a ‘spend and borrow’ past to a ‘make and sell’ future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if they’re going to trade, then our entrepreneurs have to connect - connect with customers and markets, connect with other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the modern world that usually means a business trip and a seat on a plane - which also means a journey to an airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why air-rail links matter so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the theme of your conference rightly reminds us, these links are all about ‘connecting for growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now ‘growth’ is the word on everyone’s lips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s hardly surprising in these testing times of a Eurozone crisis, a fragile global economy and a record-breaking inherited debt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, while there is sill a long way to go, recent economic figures show we are moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do think there is a tendency in some quarters to talk about growth as though it’s an abstract concept - something that’s separate and stand-alone; something with a life-force all of its very own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s almost as though some commentators believe growth will magically appear of its own volition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that it’ll come about if you say the word often enough, or you want it badly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well actually, out there in the real world, you can’t talk or wish an economy into growing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t wave a wand and conjure up growth from thin air. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can’t sit back and wait for it to fall in your lap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth comes through hard slog: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the competitive company and the skilled workforce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the inventors and innovators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the risk takers and wealth creators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and yes… a supportive and empowering government &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is who and what drives growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s where transport can play such a massive part - by providing the vital connections that help to support and sustain growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the bottom line is - the government understands the overriding economic imperative of modernising our railways, our airports and the links between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="railways"&gt;Railways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take each of those areas in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First the railways, where we’re engaged in a massive effort to renew and rebuild Britain’s rail networks - and just this summer we announced a new rail investment programme worth more than £9 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re driving through landmark projects like Crossrail, Thameslink and the Northern Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to electrify more than 850 miles of track, compared to the 10 miles electrified by the last administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, right across the country, we’re making rail travel a whole lot better with new services and extra carriages, more seats and faster journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our focus doesn’t begin and end with the conventional railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also recognise the huge potential benefits of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that our country and our economy need more than a high speed line - they need a high speed network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s exactly what we’re going to build with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only links London and Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also speeds further north to Manchester and Leeds, and possibly to Edinburgh and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only opens up business opportunities at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also opens up business opportunities abroad by ensuring passengers have an opportunity to connect up with the Channel Tunnel rail link (HS1) and Heathrow airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will, of course, give people much quicker journey times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is so much more than simply a faster way to get from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; also means more capacity and better connected cities and regions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which, in turn, means that British businesses will be able to use it to exploit new markets, win new customers and attract new investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will create and support tens of thousands of jobs and so help to power up the recovery and put people back to work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also help to deliver better life chances for millions of people by opening up access to employment opportunities and essential services like education and health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s even a persuasive environmental case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because it will offer people and businesses a high speed, low carbon alternative to short-haul flying and long-distance motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no exaggeration to say that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will transform the way we live and work every bit as much as it transforms the way we travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So make no mistake - the government’s commitment to this game-changing project is full on and flat out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="airports"&gt;Airports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now turn to the subject of airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the Wright Brothers defied gravity in a box-shaped biplane made of spruce and covered in cotton, air travel has shrunk our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in doing so, it has also broadened our horizons, personal and business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So airports have a front and centre role in keeping our country prosperous, as well as keeping it connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we’re working hard to make sure the aviation sector continues to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the Civil Aviation Bill, legislation that will improve the passenger experience by reforming the 25 year old set of regulations that currently govern our main airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve consulted on our draft Aviation Policy Framework - a framework that forms the basis for future sustainable aviation growth in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, to increase reliability and reduce delays, we’ve been trialling operational freedoms at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re thinking ahead too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that the future of aviation in Britain is one where our airports are globally competitive and where you can connect to places all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m not talking about the future as just the next 4 or 5 years, but in terms of the next 4 and 5 decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation faces long-term challenges that require long-term solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lots of people and lots of organisations have ideas about what those solutions should look like including, I’m sure, many of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve asked Sir Howard Davies to chair an independent Airports’ Commission to explore the evidence, consider the options and make recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Howard has now named the members of his commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its terms of reference have been published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job of work is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so let me be clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is determined to build the consensus needed to deliver a lasting solution to this country’s aviation needs, and we believe that the Airports’ Commission is the way to do precisely that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="air-rail-links"&gt;Air-rail links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you take a look at this country’s major airports you will probably notice any number of things that mark them out and make them unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look again though and you’ll also see there are 2 things they have in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they act as global gateways to new markets and new customers - which means they are not just national transport assets, they are national economic assets too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But second, they’re set to become much easier places to get to and fly from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because we’re making real and lasting improvements to those crucial connections between the train and the plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me highlight some of the key investments and modernisations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;electrification of the Midland Mainline improves access to Luton, while Valleys electrification improves access to Cardiff Airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electrification and capacity enhancements between Leamington and Coventry enables more Crosscountry trains to run via Birmingham Airport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extra platform capacity at Redhill means more opportunity for Gatwick services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Greater Manchester the Metrolink tram extension is due to open in 2016 and will take passengers from the city centre into Manchester Airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as part of the Northern Hub improvements, there will be an extra platform at Manchester Airport, which will allow more and longer trains to serve the airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investment in the Ordsall Chord and additional platforms at Piccadilly station means that trains from Bradford, Halifax and Rochdale will be able to get to Manchester Airport for the first time &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new £500 million rail link will give direct western access to Heathrow Airport and is expected to cut passenger journey times from the Thames Valley, the south-west, Wales and the west Midlands by around half an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once it’s completed, Crossrail will provide new services linking Heathrow with the West End, the City of London and Canary Wharf.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thanks to Thameslink, Gatwick will get new direct services to destinations north of London, such as Cambridge, Stevenage and Welwyn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, not only will &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; make it much easier for passengers from London and the south-east to get to Birmingham Airport… &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will also mean that people and businesses in the Midlands and the north of England get improved access to Heathrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an impressive list of projects and programmes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if you add it all up, what you get are train services that work for rail passengers and air passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay - whenever I make a speech I’m always conscious of the words of President Bill Clinton who gave the following advice about public speaking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;if you can’t say what you want to say in 20 minutes or less, you should go away and write a book about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’m sure that lovers of literature everywhere will be greatly relieved to know that I have no plans whatsoever to be an author - which means it’s time for me to conclude my speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I finish up though there’s something I want you to know, and it’s this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting for growth isn’t just at the top of your priority list – it’s right at the heart of our transport policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seamless air-rail journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better, faster, closer links between the station platform and the check-in desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s our vision, that’s our ambition and, step by step, that’s what we’re delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17108</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:08:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"/>
    <title>Cash boost to get England cycling</title>
    <summary>An extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cities, towns and villages across England are set to benefit from an extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure.  The new funding was announced today by Transport Minister Norman Baker, at a conference in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new funding will help people take to two wheels.  Projects could include better cycle facilities at railway stations, improved cycle links, or projects to improve the layout of road junctions to make them more cycle-friendly. Previous investment has seen some great projects making a real difference in communities, including better cycle routes from residential areas to schools to encourage the next generation of cyclists to cycle more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference in Leicester, attended by Public Health Minister Anna Soubry and Norman Baker, explores how councils’ health and transport officials can work better together to deliver better options for cycling and walking in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is great for your health, the economy, and for the environment so we are determined to make it easier for people to cycle whether for leisure, getting to the shops or as part of their commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the success of the Olympics, there is a huge appetite for more cycling provision from the travelling public and we need to capitalise on this enthusiasm at local and national level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are investing £20 million in cycling infrastructure and getting councils to bring an end to silo working in their offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public Health Minister Anna Soubry said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being active helps us stay healthy and protects against life threatening conditions such as heart disease, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a great way for adults to get their recommended 150 minutes of physical activity each week and this funding will help encourage more people to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million announced today is in addition to £30 million already announced for similar projects this year which drew in an additional £15 million in matched funding from local sources.  The projects to be funded will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"&gt;written statement&lt;/a&gt; was laid in Parliament this morning &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence today also published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nice.org.uk/"&gt;guidance on public health for local authorities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17109</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T09:50:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Additional funding for cycling infrastructure</title>
    <summary>An additional £20m for existing infrastructure projects to support cycling.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has today made available an additional £20m for our existing infrastructure projects to support cycling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will increase the total available for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Community Linking Places Fund (in addition to the £15m announced on 7 February 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving cycle safety at junctions (in addition to the £15m announced on 26 June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Community Linking Places Fund is primarily for improvements to cycling and walking infrastructure, facilities and links. This includes improving access to the rail network by bicycle. In addition the fund aims to support jobs, enhance access to employment and encourage greater use of more environmentally friendly transport.   Projects currently being supported were announced on 6 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment in junctions - for use by English local authorities outside London - will help to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured, or are deemed to be at greater risk.  Local authorities are currently submitting bids for funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand from local authorities, Sustrans and train operating companies, who are delivering the infrastructure, has been high.  An increase of £20m to the total funding available will allow the Government to support more high quality proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the projects to be supported under the additional funding will be published early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"&gt;Cash boost to get England cycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17476</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T16:29:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-regulated-agents-and-in-flight-suppliers"/>
    <title>Department for Transport regulated agents and in-flight suppliers</title>
    <summary>A list of aviation related agencies that are regulated by the Department for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-number-for-all-enquiries"&gt;Contact number for all enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;phone: 020 7944 6430&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;email: &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="communication-with-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Communication with in-flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please send all non-urgent communication to inspectors on their mobile email addresses listed below. Please provide as much detail as possible in your message and inspectors will endeavour to provide a prompt response. If regulated suppliers do not have a named email contact, a message to the office email address &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; will allow for the message to be passed on to the appropriate inspector. Inspectors would be grateful for the assistance of the industry in this matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christian Whitley, senior compliance inspector cargo and in-flight supplies &lt;a href="mailto:christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gillian Stephens, IFS compliance inspector &lt;a href="mailto:gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carole Cousins &lt;a href="mailto:carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin Gurney &lt;a href="mailto:martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jonathan Hogben &lt;a href="mailto:jonathan.hogben@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jonathan.hogben@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daz Salmon &lt;a href="mailto:daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nicholas Short &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.short@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;nicholas.short@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Sidney &lt;a href="mailto:james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maurice Stearn &lt;a href="mailto:maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="validation-and-known-consignors-scheme"&gt;Validation and known consignors scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;contact number for all initial enquiries: 020 7944 2875&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;email all enquires to &lt;a href="mailto:current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="aviation-security-compliance-office-address"&gt;Aviation Security Compliance office address&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Transport Security Compliance  
&lt;br&gt;3rd Floor, Fry Building  
&lt;br&gt;2 Marsham Street  
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1P 4DF
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17099</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T13:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-sets-out-government-support-for-lifeline-shops"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk sets out government support for "lifeline shops"</title>
    <summary>Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk has pledged full government backing to the nation’s ”lifeline shops”.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the Association of Convenience Stores, Mr Prisk described them as a vital service for the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He warned against overlooking the crucial role the army of small shopkeepers across the country plays not only economically but also socially - offering a friendly face and social hub to local communities, and especially older people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister pointed to research suggesting that around a quarter of elderly people use their local shop, often a convenience store, every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convenience stores represent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;almost 40% of all rural shops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over a third of shops in urban areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a quarter of all shops in the suburbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the age of supermarkets and online retail it’s easy to forget that convenience stores make up more than quarter of all shops. Yet they are not just an important part of the economy. For many people their local shop is also a lifeline. Whether they’re used for daily supplies or the occasional pint of milk, they are an essential part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s why this government is introducing measures specifically designed to support convenience stores. That means reforming the planning system, easing the financial pressures with business rate support, and offering practical ways to attract new custom, all in order to keep this vital local resource intact.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-support-to-convenience-stores"&gt;Government support to convenience stores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk acknowledged the new economic challenges traditional shops now face, especially the changing way that people shop - whether online or in out-of-town retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he also highlighted some of the key actions the government is taking to help them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s work to cut the deficit by a quarter in 2 years, which has kept interest rates lower for longer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new changes to the planning system to ensure that existing town centres should be the first preference for new retail facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expert support and a multi-million pound fund for Portas Pilots and Town Team Partners will encourage strong and bold local leadership to create competitive high streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doubled small business rates relief and a 20% reduction of corporation tax are helping smaller firms manage their bills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a delayed business rate revaluation, providing a more stable business environment and preventing an increase in rates for around 800,000 premises &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to help town centres adapt to changing demands, making it easier to convert empty offices into homes and bringing people back into the town centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"&gt;speech to the Association of Convenience Stores&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17387</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:56:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/speed-limit-exemption-for-life-saving-services"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemption for life-saving services</title>
    <summary>Proposals to allow drivers from a wider range of emergency services to break the speed limit have been published today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proposals to allow drivers from a wider range of emergency services to break the speed limit in order to save lives, have been published today for consultation by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance services are already allowed to exceed speed limits in the course of their emergency response duties and this is not changing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3 month consultation exercise will examine the possibility of extending the exemption to other services including those carrying organs for transplant, bomb disposal units and coastguard vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at amending road safety legislation so that emergency drivers would be required by law to complete high-speed training before exceeding the limit. But this will not place any additional burden on police, fire and ambulance services which already run an effective voluntary training scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance service drivers are highly trained individuals who are at times required to exceed the speed limit in order to save lives. It is only right that we look at allowing other services whose duties can mean the difference between life and death to exceed the speed limit when responding to emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also time to look at the legal requirements of emergency vehicle training so we can build on the rigorous standards the police, fire and ambulance services have already applied through their code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While emergency service drivers are not exempt from the offences of dangerous and careless driving, the current legislation allows drivers in some circumstances to break speed limits legally as well as exempting them from certain traffic regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be viewed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"&gt;DfT website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services currently exempt from speed limits include Police, the Fire Service, the Ambulance Service and the Serious Organised Crime Agency (shortly to be replaced by the National Crime Agency)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The full list of services who have expressed an interest in being exempt are listed within section 5 of the consultation document, they include Ministry of Defence bomb disposal units, fire (other than for fire and rescue authorities which are covered), conveyance of human tissue for transplant, blood transfusion, mountain rescue, mine rescue, radiation emergencies, coastguard and lifeboat launching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The emergency services set up a joint emergency services’ speed limit exemption driver training group to develop their procedures. It also includes representatives from the Driving Standards Agency, the Institute of Advanced Motoring and the Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents. It has developed a Code of Practice which is based around current best practice for each of the exempt organisations and reflects what is being taught there, recognising that there are organisation specific competencies. The consultation proposes using this Code of Practice as the basis for the regulated standards for the mandatory training courses to be used following the proposed legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation includes a set of criteria designed to establish the rationale of each request, balancing the operational need for the exemption against any potential road safety risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation proposes amending the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984 and make any legal exemption dependent on drivers attaining the core competencies identified in the Emergency Services’ Code of Practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"&gt;Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles&lt;/a&gt; written statement by Stephen Hammond MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16998</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:52:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:52:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemptions</title>
    <summary>This consultation proposes that section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) be brought into effect.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes that section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) be brought into effect. This would replace section 87 of the Road Traffic Regulation Act (1984) in relation to exemptions from speed limits for certain vehicle purposes. Regulations are needed to bring it into effect and set out the detail of how it would work. This document contains the department’s proposed approach to implementing the regulations in Section 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes would have two major effects. Firstly it will allow certain other vehicle purposes to be included in speed limit exemption regulations. Secondly it will prescribe a high speed training course that drivers must undertake (or be in the process of taking) before they are permitted to exceed speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation document also considers regulations related to 5 other exemptions from road traffic laws (related to signals, signalled crossings, certain signs and motorway hard shoulders) It includes proposals to amend some of these other provisions at the same time that section 19 is commenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document will also seek views about the planned introduction of a further exemption from seat belt requirements related to the treatment of patients in the back of ambulances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16979</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/widespread-support-for-greater-rail-devolution"/>
    <title>Widespread support for greater rail devolution</title>
    <summary>Consultation responses published today reveal widespread support for rail devolution.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers and local communities could achieve better rail services and value for money for taxpayers if they have more say on how their railways are run, according to responses to a government consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback published today also reveals widespread support for rail devolution. The consultation asked individuals, regional groups and interested organisations to give their views on how devolution might work and what the benefits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide the best possible rail services for passengers and ensure that we reduce the cost of running our railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring decisions are taken by those best placed to make them – those who live and work in those areas – could make certain not only that services are planned to maximise value for money for taxpayers but that passengers get services they need and want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also revealed enthusiastic expressions of interest in helping to manage the railways from regional groups in London, the West Midlands and the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responses highlighted the success of regions where the operation of rail services has already been devolved, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merseyside, where Merseytravel has been responsible for the management of rail services since 2003&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London, where Transport for London has been responsible for the operation of London Overground services since 2007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland and Wales, where the operation of regional services is managed by the Scottish government and the Welsh Assembly government&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses also showed support for transport models specifically designed for particular regions on the basis of local geography and the structure of local networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A consultation document, ‘Rail decentralisation’, was published on 8 March 2012. Comments were invited by the end of June 2012. This is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport’s response to the rail decentralisation consultation is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government remains committed to seeking to implement an appropriate form of decentralisation in those parts of England where it is sensible to do so. Following the responses to the consultation, &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue informal discussions with those bodies who have submitted proposals or firm expressions of interest. It will consider further a number of issues that need to be resolved in order to proceed with any decentralisation agreement, subject to any changes to franchising policy which may emerge from the Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most train services are specified, procured and funded centrally by the Department for Transport in London. A public consultation has shown broad support for devolving greater responsibility for local rail services to local authorities, Passenger Transport Executives (PTEs) and Transport for London, where conditions are right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposals for decentralisation have been received from the Rail in the North consortium comprising Transport for Greater Manchester, West Yorkshire PTE with York City Council and South Yorkshire PTE; Centro and Transport for London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressions of interest have been received from West of England Partnership (the Greater Bristol area), Devon and Cornwall Councils, Merseytravel, the Association of North East Councils and Cumbria County Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is envisaged that interested bodies will be ready to submit formal proposals in the first half of next year. In the meantime, the Department for Transport will continue informal discussions with these bodies as they prepare and consult on their formal proposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 70% of respondents to the consultation said they supported devolution of powers to manage the railways to regional bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16975</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:45:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:45:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"/>
    <title>Rail decentralisation: devolving decision-making on passenger rail services in England</title>
    <summary>Most train services in England are specified, funded and managed centrally by the Department for Transport based in London. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most train services in England are specified, funded and managed centrally by the Department for Transport based in London. Passenger Transport Executives’ (&lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) and local authorities’ influence over the rail services provided in their local area is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with its aspirations for localism, the government is seeking to devolve, where appropriate, more accountability and decision-making related to local rail services to sub-national bodies, such as local authorities and &lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. This consultation explores how this might be done in parts of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="why-we-are-consulting"&gt;Why we are consulting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wishes to seek views on whether improved outcomes for transport users might be achieved in some cases if more decisions relating to local rail services were made closer to the communities they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also inviting sub-national bodies - &lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and local authorities - to indicate their interest and come forward with outline proposals for taking on decision-making responsibility for passenger rail services in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation complements the command paper, ‘Reforming our railways’, published today. That sets out the government’s vision for rail and responds to Sir Roy McNulty’s independent report on value for money on the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/reforming-our-railways/"&gt;Command paper: Reforming our railways&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-09/"&gt;Consultation: Rail fares and ticketing review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/greening-20120308a/"&gt;Rail reform command paper oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 8 March 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120308a/"&gt;Ending inflation-busting rail fare rises press release, 8 March 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17271</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T16:00:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/transport-scotland-high-speed-rail-summit"/>
    <title>Transport Scotland high speed rail summit</title>
    <summary>Video speech by Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport Norman Baker.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2gEnT-LreI&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA"&gt;Transport Scotland high speed rail summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello and thank you for the opportunity to put on record coalition government’s commitment to high speed rail, and its determination that all parts of our country, including of course Scotland, should benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing demand for inter-city rail travel is putting increasing pressure on existing infrastructure. Without planning for additional capacity, passengers face the prospect of increasingly crowded and more unreliable services. To be clear, the primary, though not the only, justification for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a clear need for extra capacity north to south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plans for a high speed rail network from London to the West Midlands and on to Leeds and Manchester will be the backbone of a new transport system for the 21st century.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2026, Phase 1 of High Speed 2 will link London and Birmingham. Comfortable trains travelling at 225 miles per hour will cut the journey time to just 45 minutes, compared to the 84 minutes it currently takes. Importantly for Scotland, the first phase of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide connections to the existing network at Birmingham, and also link &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt;, opening up the opportunities for through trains to run from Scotland to Paris and Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completion of the Y network to Leeds and Manchester will further spread the benefits of high speed rail across the country, increasing capacity and enhancing connectivity all the way to Scotland by relieving pressure on the most congested southern end of the line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition agreement makes it clear that our ultimate goal is a genuinely national network, with high speed services from London to the Midlands and the north, including Scotland. We see phases one and two of the High Speed 2 project as the best way to make progress towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport ministerial team is very much engaged in the question of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; as it affects and, indeed, benefits Scotland. I visited Glasgow last year, the former Secretary of State went in March this year, and the current Secretary of State intends to visit later this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last month we announced the launch of a study on ways to get fast journeys further north and to Scotland, making sure that the north-east benefits too. The aim is to fully understand and articulate transport needs in Scotland and the north of England, setting out the remit for any future work, using completion of the ‘Y’ network as a starting point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study won’t start with any preconceptions but will be open to all options that offer good value for money to the taxpayer. This may include a full high speed solution, upgrades to existing infrastructure, or a combination of the two.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands today the network is expected to deliver up to £50 billion of business benefits alone and that will be felt very much in Scotland and the north of England as well as the South. The claim by some opponents of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; that better and faster transport links between north and south will see economic activity pulled into London and away from the UK’s other great cities is defeatist and misguided, and out of line with public opinion. The further north you go, the louder are the voices in support of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing Edinburgh and Glasgow closer to London as well as the cities of the midlands and the north of England will undoubtedly boost growth across all of our major conurbations. That confidence is based on the evidence from our European neighbours, who began their high speed rail journey a generation before we had even started arguing about our first 67 mile stretch of high speed track from the channel tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With passengers enjoying faster journeys, there has been more extensive modal shift between rail and air as the train becomes the mode of choice for more travellers. High speed rail is already greener than flying and the gap between the two modes will widen as we make progress in decarbonising the sources of our electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will benefit every type of traveller, not just on the new network, but on existing lines too, freeing up more space and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, not only will high speed rail help boost the Scottish economy and support thousands of jobs in Scotland and throughout the UK, it gives us a once-in-a-generation opportunity to reshape the economic geography of the whole country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever way you look at it, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a national scheme in the national interest driven by a national government. Realising the full benefits of high speed rail for Scotland is crucial to the economic wellbeing of the whole country, and I can assure you we will continue to work very closely with our partners in Scotland to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
