<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T19:01:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/3161</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:01:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:01:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england"/>
    <title>Boosting private sector employment in England</title>
    <summary>Supporting private sector projects and partnerships that have the potential for long-term economic growth in the UK</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain parts of the country have been dependent on the public sector for employment. To help these areas grow their private sectors - and create more jobs - the government has established a regional growth fund (RGF) of £2.4 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have up to £1 billion of funding to allocate under the RGF to stimulate economic growth and encourage private sector investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund/how-to-apply" title="apply for funding"&gt;apply for funding&lt;/a&gt; from now until 13 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund will support private sector projects and public/private partnerships that have the potential for long-term economic growth and the creation of sustainable jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="who-can-apply-for-funding"&gt;Who can apply for funding?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private or public-private organisations in England can apply for funding. It can be used for capital investment, research and development or training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations must apply for a minimum of £1 million funding. Funding can be a grant, loan or loan guarantee. We will assess projects on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value for money for taxpayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ability to create jobs in the private sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;project management expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Projects must fit the European Union’s rules on state aid - we need to ensure any funding does not give a company unfair competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011, we allocated £1.4 billion of the RGF in 2 rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round 1, April 2011: £450 million was allocated to 50 bids, attracting £2.5 billion in private sector investment. The projects will create or safeguard over 27,000 direct jobs, with around 100,000 more in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round 2, October 2011: £950 million was invested in 126 bids, attracting nearly £6 billion of private investment. Around 200,000 jobs will be created or protected: around 37,000 direct jobs, with more than 164,000 in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the &lt;a href="government/admin/detailed-guides/16467"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/6982</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/strengthening-uk-relationships-in-asia-latin-america-and-africa-to-support-uk-prosperity-and-security"/>
    <title>Strengthening UK relationships in Asia, Latin America and Africa to support UK prosperity and security</title>
    <summary>Opening up new markets for secure trade and investment with British businesses.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political weight is shifting east and south. This means that fast-growing economies in Asia, Latin America and Africa are essential to our interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to increase Britain’s prosperity and security by improving links with the economic and political powers of tomorrow. We are helping these markets grow so UK business can enjoy the mutual benefits of trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has already reallocated resources to boost the UK’s presence in the fastest-growing parts of the world. Ministers across government are planning their overseas travel strategically to meet influential politicians, business and community leaders in the fastest-growing parts of the world, and host them when they visit the UK. These meetings concentrate on building links, including trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emerging Powers Fund launched in autumn 2012, supporting projects to the value of £1.8 million over 3 years to build links with the fastest-growing parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prosperity Fund was launched in April 2011 so that the UK can create the conditions for sustainable global growth and development. In its first year the fund gave £19.4 million to 248 projects in 14 countries and regions to build links with the fastest-growing parts of the world. In 2012-2013, the fund is allocating £19 million in 15 countries and regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment’s (&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;) new strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/item/148300.html"&gt;Britain open for business&lt;/a&gt;, launched in May 2011, explains our plans to provide practical support to exporters and inward investors over 5 years, including winning high-value overseas opportunities for UK businesses. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-charter-for-business"&gt;Business Charter&lt;/a&gt; launched alongside the &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strategy, shows how the government supports UK business abroad, including in the fastest-growing parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In every overseas post, Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office (&lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt;) staff undertake press and communications work, which includes building relations with local media, and communicating the advantages of investing in and trading with the UK. A small London-based team works with the 1,700 London-based international media to ensure they understand the UK’s economic strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; operates websites in 53 local languages around the world, which attract 10 million visitors every year. These platforms are used to champion the UK’s reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since publishing the white paper on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/international-trade-investment-and-development/docs/t/11-717-trade-investment-for-growth.pdf"&gt;Trade and investment for growth&lt;/a&gt;  in February 2011, the government has: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;supported businesses to secure more than £800 million of high-value opportunities overseas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helped more than 20,000 small and medium-sized enterprises to export and break into new high-growth markets like India, China, Brazil and Turkey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;launched new export finance products to support smaller businesses to sell their products abroad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced Strategic Relationship Management for large UK exporting firms and important inward investors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;worked with the World Trade Organisation to agree Russia’s accession, after 18 years of negotiations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trade and investment for growth white paper: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/trade-white-paper-progress-and-achievements-in-year-1"&gt;Progress and achievements in year one&lt;/a&gt; explains the progress made against the commitments in that white paper as part of the government’s effort to rebalance the UK economy through trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-charter-for-business"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Business Charter&lt;/a&gt;, launched in May 2011, describes the support the &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; provides to British businesses, helping them to identify and pursue new opportunities overseas, manage risks and build relationships abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charter was launched alongside the &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s 5-year strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/item/148300.html"&gt;Britain open for business&lt;/a&gt;, which explains how the government is generating growth through trade and supporting exporters and inward investors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/6980</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-uk-s-exports-and-attracting-inward-investment"/>
    <title>Increasing the UK’s exports and attracting inward investment</title>
    <summary>Helping businesses increase their exports and making the UK more competitive.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inward investment into the UK economy created or secured more than &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/aboutukti/item/344820.html"&gt;112,000 jobs in 2011 to 12&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to help double the UK’s exports to £1 trillion by 2020 and attract more inward investment in UK infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are determined to remain one of the top countries for ease of doing business, by providing more support for British businesses to export their goods and services, and reducing corporation tax to competitive levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment’s (&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/item/301280.html"&gt;Passport to Export&lt;/a&gt; is an assessment and skills-based programme that gives new and inexperienced exporters the training, planning and ongoing support needed to succeed overseas. Passport to Export also helps companies to research, visit and select markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British businesses can carry out export marketing research on all the major aspects of any export venture using &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/export/howwehelp/exportmarketingresearchscheme.html"&gt;Export Marketing Research Scheme&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/item/109254.html"&gt;Export Communications Review&lt;/a&gt; gives companies impartial advice on language and cultural issues to improve their competitiveness in export markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/d/corporate_tax_reform_part1a_roadmap.pdf"&gt;simplifying and reducing corporation tax&lt;/a&gt; to encourage inward investment. The reduction to the rate of 24% means that the UK now has the lowest main rate in the G7 and the fifth lowest in the G20. We plan to reduce the rate to 21% from April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt; established the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/investintheuk/ukadvisorynetwork.html"&gt;UK Advisory Network&lt;/a&gt; in 2007 to provide high-quality and trusted support to investors setting up in the UK and UK companies doing business overseas through closer working between the government and the private sector. The network makes access to private sector expertise easier and more effective and allows those experts to share knowledge and market information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-charter-for-business"&gt;FCO’s Business Charter&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2011, shows how FCO resources can meet the needs of British business. It is part of the FCO’s work to create lasting prosperity for the UK, explaining the specific contribution that the FCO makes to support business across the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="www.ukti.gov.uk"&gt;&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has an ongoing programme of research that looks into the effect of exporting on UK companies across the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/download/160040/4/68420_EET_Acc_Access.pdf.html"&gt;Bringing home the benefits: how to grow through exporting&lt;/a&gt; found that for many UK companies the decision to grow through exporting has been profitable. Those companies who venture into new export markets tend to be rewarded both directly through boosted turnover, and indirectly through improved levels of efficiency, innovation and credibility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/download/160040_117340/New%20markets,%20new%20ideas.pdf.html"&gt;New markets, new ideas: How exporting fosters innovation and growth&lt;/a&gt; suggests that many British companies are embracing a new era of internationalisation. This can be seen in both an increasing number of companies doing business overseas and the rising number of firms that export from an early stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also investigates the benefits business experience as a result of exporting including increased levels of growth, productivity and innovation. More young companies are grabbing international opportunities from an early stage; almost one in five (17%) new companies currently active abroad are classified as ‘Born Global’ - so have been doing business overseas since the outset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many internationalised firms experience a ‘virtuous circle’ where exporting led to innovation, and where those innovations then led to further exporting. Over half of all firms (53%) said that a new product or service evolved because of their business overseas. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/50204</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-stability-throughout-the-western-balkans--2"/>
    <title>Promoting stability throughout the Western Balkans</title>
    <summary>Securing peace and creating the conditions for EU membership in the Western Balkans.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1990s saw the violent break-up of the former Yugoslavia and the beginning of the transition from communism in the region. The region has since started the long route to greater stability and prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stability in the Western Balkans matters; the region is on Europe’s doorstep and instability or conflict would affect the UK, including through migration and organised crime. The UK is therefore working to reduce the risk of conflict in the region, promote stability and reconciliation, and support reforms, as the region moves towards future EU and NATO membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a strong supporter of future EU and NATO membership for all countries of the Western Balkans (along with Iceland and Turkey). To reach this future in the EU and NATO, countries need to meet conditions for membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU accession process, leading to membership, requires serious reform efforts from the region, including on rule of law, organised crime and corruption, public administration, and economic reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is supporting these reforms with £3 million of Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office (FCO) programme funds for Albania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Kosovo, Macedonia, Montenegro, Serbia (and Turkey), for example funding judicial reform or media freedom projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also providing expertise supporting accession-related reforms from across the civil service as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twinning.org/en/page/the-european-union.html"&gt;EU twinning programme&lt;/a&gt;, means to help people understand the aims of the EU, to develop a stronger sense of European identity, and to bring the EU closer to its citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms reduce security threats to the UK and promote a strong environment for British business interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reconciliation is crucial for the region, following the conflict and atrocities of the past. Cooperation with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.icty.org/"&gt;International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia&lt;/a&gt;, the UN court of law dealing with war crimes that took place during the conflicts in the Balkans in the 1990s, remains important, as does the leadership in the region openly and honestly acknowledging the events of the past, such as the genocide in Srebrenica. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also supporting conflict prevention efforts in the region, with around £10 million provided jointly from the FCO, Ministry of Defence and Department for International Development. The work is focused on Bosnia and Herzegovina and on Kosovo and includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UK troops joining, in December 2012, the regional reserve for the peacekeeping mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support for the Srebrenica prosecutions team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK judges hearing war crime cases in Kosovo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;projects to support ethnic minorities returning to rebuilt homes following the Kosovo war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK continues to support safeguards against instability in Bosnia and Herzegovina, particularly the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohr.int/"&gt;Office of the High Representative&lt;/a&gt;, the international institution responsible for overseeing implementation of civilian aspects of the Peace Agreement ending the war in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.euforbih.org/"&gt;EUFOR Althea peacekeeping operation&lt;/a&gt;, the EU’s military operation that launched on 2 December 2004 and has contributed to the maintenance of the safe and secure environment in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="albania"&gt;Albania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albania is already a member of NATO and has made an application for EU membership. The UK encourages further progress on reforms, particularly rule of law and democracy, for Albania to move forward on towards their EU future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bosnia-and-herzegovina"&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK remains wholly and actively committed to Bosnia and Herzegovina as a sovereign, stable country with functioning state-level institutions. Significant political progress is needed if progress towards NATO and EU membership is to be made, but such progress will bring benefits to citizens throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="croatia"&gt;Croatia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Croatia will accede to the EU in July 2013. The European Commission’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/hr_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;Comprehensive Monitoring Report on Croatia’s state ofpreparedness for EU membership&lt;/a&gt;, published in October 2012, noted the progress made by Croatia in its preparations for accession. The commission also identified a number of areas where further improvements are necessary in order to fully meet all membership requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN06327"&gt;Croatia Accession Bill&lt;/a&gt; would allow the UK to ratify Croatia’s accession treaty. All existing EU member states must ratify the accession treaty before Croatia can join the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="kosovo"&gt;Kosovo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK recognised Kosovo’s declaration of independence in February 2008 and is a longstanding supporter of Kosovo’s independence, sovereignty and territorial integrity. The UK is a firm supporter of a stable, prosperous and multi-ethnic Kosovo making progress towards eventual EU and NATO membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="macedonia"&gt;Macedonia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports Macedonia’s progress towards EU and NATO membership. Since March 2002, the European Commission has reported regularly to the EU Council and Parliament on progress made by the countries of the Western Balkans region. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/mk_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;2012 report&lt;/a&gt; describes the progress made by the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia in preparing for EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="montenegro"&gt;Montenegro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/fule/headlines/news/2012/06/20120629_en.htm"&gt;Montenegro opened accession negotiations&lt;/a&gt; with the EU in June 2012. The UK supports an early focus on rule of law issues in the negotiations, notably strengthening the judiciary and tackling organised crime and corruption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="serbia"&gt;Serbia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a long-standing supporter of Serbia’s EU future and welcomed Serbia becoming an official EU candidate in March 2012. We urge Serbia to make further progress normalising its relations with Kosovo in order to meet the criteria for opening accession negotiations with the EU. Domestic reforms and regional cooperation remain important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55440</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:48:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement"/>
    <title>Minister for Europe renews UK commitment to EU enlargement </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has set out the UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister gave a press briefing for European journalists today following his participation in the General Affairs Council meeting in Brussels on 11 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK remains a strong supporter of EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey. I’ve just returned from the General Affairs Council in Brussels where I was pleased to have a long discussion on EU enlargement. Its conclusions make clear the EU’s continued support for enlargement. This is important, and a message that I hope will be heard clearly in the accession and pre-accession countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is good for the EU and one of the EU’s greatest achievements. The European Union, alongside NATO, has been an instrument of peace and reconciliation that has helped spread democracy and the rule of law across our continent, and helped make armed conflict between EU members unthinkable. At the same time an enlarged Single Market, another of the key success stories of the EU, has opened up prosperity and opportunity to hundreds of millions of people. An outward-looking approach and a continuing commitment to enlargement should be seen by all EU Member States as signs of strength and vigour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is also good for wider security and prosperity across the continent. The accession of new Member States helps promote security, stability and prosperity across Europe, based on a firm foundation of democracy, human and civil rights, and respect for the law. The focus on good neighbourly relations is particularly important for a region such as the Western Balkans which saw conflict only two decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a respect for this firm foundation and its benefits which drives the UK’s scrutiny of progress and focus on conditionality. So the UK is clear that there will be no pause after Croatia’s accession. But equally there will be no movement without progress on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Foreign Secretary visited Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia and Kosovo in October. He set out clearly the UK’s support for each country’s EU future. But he stressed to the political leaders that they needed to take the necessary steps to deliver. I hope political leaders in all of the aspiring countries will do so and that we will see further progress being made towards the EU early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the UK remains committed to Turkey’s EU membership. We strongly believe that this would contribute to Europe’s prosperity and security, and the EU remains the strongest lever for reform in Turkey. We are focused on making real progress on the accession process in 2013 and we fully support the Irish Presidency in their desire to open a new acquis Chapter during their Presidency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=842001782" title="Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/54839</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T13:22:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:22:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"/>
    <title>Improving high streets and town centres</title>
    <summary>Town centres across the country are being given the support and the opportunity to revitalise their high streets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High streets are recognised as important hubs of social interaction and cohesion, as well as providers of local jobs. They’re a visible indicator of how well, or how badly, a local economy is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our high streets and town centres are facing serious challenges from out-of-town shopping centres and the growth of online and mobile retailing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recognises that our high streets have to offer something new and different that neither shopping centres nor the internet can match. They need to offer an experience that goes beyond retail - the high street should be a destination for socialising, culture, health, wellbeing, creativity and learning, with schools, doctors’ surgeries and offices along with shops. Our high streets should be social places that make creative use of public spaces and with a vibrant evening economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review (see ‘Background’ below), we are running a number of high street Town Team ‘Portas Pilots’ in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams on 26 May:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bedford, Bedfordshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Croydon, Greater London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dartford, Kent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bedminster, Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liskeard, Cornwall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margate, Kent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Market Rasen, Lincolnshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nelson, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newbiggin by the Sea, Northumberland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockport, Greater Manchester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton on Tees, North Yorkshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wolverhampton, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 25 July, 15 more Town Teams were selected as the second wave of Portas Pilots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ashford, Kent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Berwick, Northumberland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Braintree, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brighton (London Road),West Sussex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hatfield, Hertfordshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leamington (Old Town), Warwickshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liverpool (Lodge Lane), Merseyside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Waterloo – Lower Marsh and The Cut, Greater London &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forest Hill, Kirkdale and Sydenham, Greater London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chrisp Street, Watney Market, Roman Road (Tower Hamlets), Greater London &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loughborough, East Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowestoft, Suffolk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Morecombe, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rotherham, South Yorkshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tiverton, Somerset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each winning bid will receive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;funding of up to £100,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a dedicated contact point in government to provide advice and support in identifying and overcoming challenges to local business growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;free support from retail industry leaders including Mary Portas’s own team and access to a range of sector experts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opportunities to meet and discuss with fellow pilots to share their experiences and lessons learned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department is awarding grant funding for a support package for Town Teams to help them transform their local high streets. The support focuses on improving local leadership and delivery in ‘Portas Pilots’ and sharing learning with ‘Town Team Partners’. See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/town-teams-support-package-prospectus-and-application-form"&gt;Town Teams support package prospectus&lt;/a&gt; for more detail. Applications must be received by 16 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A map of the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?msa=0&amp;amp;msid=214017557671758190387.0004c5a32875c37f5db12&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;ll=53.396432,-2.570801&amp;amp;spn=6.553757,14.260254&amp;amp;z=6&amp;amp;source=embed" title="link to Portas Pilots locations on Google Maps"&gt;Portas Pilots locations can be found here&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-team-partners"&gt;Town Team Partners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has offered all those Town Teams that were not selected to be become a Portas Pilot the opportunity to become a Town Team Partner to help improve their high streets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 400 towns applied to be a Portas Pilot and 27 teams were selected. The establishment of 326 Town Team Partners will help to maintain the momentum and energy that the competition generated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those registered to become Town Team Partners will receive a share of a multi-million pound fund to take forward elements of their plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Town Team Partners will also be able to get to support from the Association of Town Centre Management which will work with Town Team Partners to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify their needs and requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hold information events to help deal with the most pressing challenges facing struggling town centres &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up an advice line &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offer a network of advisers to help improve local towns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All those towns that have registered to become Town Team Partners have the backing of their local MP, who has pledged to support their high street. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-local-markets"&gt;Supporting local markets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government promoted the retail markets industry by organising and supporting a National Markets Day. This was part of a ‘Love Your Local Market’ fortnight of events aimed at helping new market traders starting up businesses, and to celebrate and promote our local markets as part of the retail mix that a place can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the fortnight, 4,000 pitches were made available to business entrepreneurs, young start-ups and would-be retailers to set up a stall and test out their business ideas. Over 1,400 of these subsidised pitches were taken up in 400 markets.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-support-for-high-streets"&gt;More support for high streets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting a range of measures in response to the Portas High Street review, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a £1 million ‘Future High Street X-Fund’ for creative and effective schemes that have been completed to rejuvenate town centres (the competition closes on 6 December 2012 and the awards will be made before the end of March 2013) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a £500,000 Business Improvement Districts loan fund will be announced in the autumn to help finance the development of new business improvement districts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a share in a new £10 million High Street Innovation Fund was awarded in March 2012 to 100 places whose high streets had been most affected by the 2011 summer riots and those with the highest number of empty shops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, we’ve introduced a number of measures to support high streets, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief for 2 and a half years to help small shops and make it easier for small firms to claim small business rate relief through the Localism Act&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scrapping Whitehall planning guidance which forced up parking charges, allowing councils to attract shoppers by setting competitive parking charges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing planning rules to allow councils to provide more parking spaces in town centres so they can compete with out-of-town supermarkets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;updating licensing laws to give councils more powers to tackle late night, anti-social behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focusing retail development in town centres through a ‘town centre first’ planning policy, making it easier to convert empty offices into residential use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the growth agenda, the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister commissioned retail expert Mary Portas to conduct an independent review of the high street’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.maryportas.com/news/2011/12/12/the-portas-review/" title="Mary Portas website - The Portas Review"&gt;‘The Portas Review: an independent review into the future of our high streets’&lt;/a&gt; was published on 13 December 2011. It set out what Mary Portas thought had led to the decline of the high street and made 28 recommendations about what could be done – by government, local authorities and business – to breathe life back into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister asked Grant Shapps to take forward the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/high-streets-at-the-heart-of-our-communities-government-response-to-the-mary-portas-review" title="Government response to the Portas Review"&gt;government’s response&lt;/a&gt; to the recommendations and this was published on 30 March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other organisations are supporting the Portas Pilots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.artscouncil.org.uk/" title="Arts Council England website"&gt;Arts Council England&lt;/a&gt;, who will offer advice, expertise and potentially grant support to help develop the cultural and artistic elements of planning the pilots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.localdatacompany.com/" title="Local Data Company website"&gt;Local Data Company&lt;/a&gt;, who has agreed to support the pilots by providing free access to its current and historical data and insight along with peering to national trends. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.spring-board.info/" title="Springboard Research Ltd website"&gt;Springboard Research Ltd&lt;/a&gt;, who have also agreed to provide access data and run workshops for pilots. Evidence-based research is important to enable the pilots to get a thorough understanding of the issues that they face and the potential solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bcsc.org.uk/index.asp" title="British Council of Shopping Centres website"&gt;British Council of Shopping Centres&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bpf.org.uk/" title="British Property Federation website"&gt;British Property Federation&lt;/a&gt;, who are coordinating a mentor scheme online so that pilot towns can access free specialist advice on issues like property and planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <summary>Opening up access to the Tipner site for businesses and visitors.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54869</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:23:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/town-teams-support-package-prospectus-and-application-form"/>
    <title>Town Teams support package: prospectus and application form</title>
    <summary>Prospectus inviting applications for funding to provide a support package to Portas Pilots and other town teams.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department is awarding grant funding for a support package for Town Teams to help them transform their local high streets into social places, bustling with people, services and jobs. The support focuses on improving local leadership and delivery in ‘Portas Pilots’ and sharing learning with ‘Town Team Partners’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us-by-16-january-2013"&gt;Contact us by 16 January 2013&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications should be sent to &lt;a href="mailto:HighStreets@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;HighStreets@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;. Please use the application form above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54835</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-monitoring-and-evaluation-framework"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport fund monitoring and evaluation framework</title>
    <summary>Expectations for the monitoring and evaluation of projects funded through the Local Sustainable Transport fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework sets out the department’s requirements from the monitoring and evaluation activity of Local Sustainable Transport fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) projects and the roles of the department and project teams in delivering these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework articulates which &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects are expected to fulfil which elements of monitoring and evaluation and provides project teams with the flexibility to collect evidence in a way that reflects the local variation of projects and data availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/50140</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T10:57:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/integrated-transport-block-funding"/>
    <title>Integrated Transport Block funding</title>
    <summary>The Integrated Transport Block fund gives assistance to local authorities outside of London. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We seeks views on the future calculation and distribution of the Integrated Transport Block. This is capital funding given to local authorities in England, outside of London, for small transport improvement schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
