<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16957</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-weston-transport-improvements"/>
    <title>Green light for Weston transport improvements</title>
    <summary>Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare has been given final approval today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will support economic growth in Weston-super-Mare and reduce congestion in the town centre. The work will also improve links between local roads and the M5 motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to increase capacity of the M5 Junction 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new link road for buses to access Worle railway station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bus priority measures at junctions and bus only sections to improve bus access to the south of Worle Station, linking it with regeneration areas at Weston Airfield and Locking Parklands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new 320 space car park with a bus interchange, drop-off and cycle facilities together with improvements to the north-side car park at Worle Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased capacity between the town centre and the regeneration areas through road widening and new routes for pedestrians and cyclists as well as bus priority measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great scheme that will support employment, reduce congestion and make it easier for people using public transport in and around Weston-super-Mare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £10.4 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country and the region needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Weston package scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work is currently planned to start in March 2013 with the package scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Weston package scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The package of measures, promoted by North Somerset Council, is scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16877</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:47:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/greater-anglia-franchise-specific-agreement"/>
    <title>Greater Anglia franchise specific agreement</title>
    <summary>Franchise agreements for Greater Anglia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that the Public Register of Franchise Agreements is updated on a quarterly basis and that the data held on the website may not be necessarily be the most current information held by the department. If you cannot find the information that you need, please contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications?tag=public-register-of-franchise-agreements"&gt;Public Register of Franchise Agreements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16857</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T09:27:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link inspector's report</title>
    <summary>Report by the inspector who held inquiries following the publication of Cornwall Council's side roads order and compulsory purchase order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This inspector’s report was written by the inspector who held inquiries following the publication of Cornwall Council’s side roads order and compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-decision-letter/" title="decision letter"&gt;Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link decision letter, 22 November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16855</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T09:27:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link decision letter</title>
    <summary>Features the Secretary of State's decision on Cornwall Council's side roads order and compulsory purchase order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This decision letter features the Secretary of State’s decision on Cornwall Council’s side roads order and compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-inspectors-report" title="inspectors report"&gt;Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link inspector’s report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16873</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T14:50:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:50:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/crucial-road-improvements-to-be-delivered-twice-as-fast"/>
    <title>Crucial road improvements to be delivered twice as fast</title>
    <summary>Accelerated improvements to various motorways will see more benefits for drivers and hauliers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and hauliers will benefit from increased capacity on England’s motorways by spring 2015 thanks to the acceleration of three upgrades, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be delivered in this spending review period rather than the next, as the government introduces major improvements to the way road schemes are planned and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new way of working should in future see lanes added to motorways in up to half the time it normally takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three schemes being accelerated are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vital improvements to A160/A180 route to the Port of Immingham will also start construction sooner than originally planned in the summer of 2015 and completed autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half by dismantling procedures that have slowed us down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Together these schemes will increase capacity for millions of road users by 72 miles. My ambition is that in future all major road schemes will be accelerated, tackling congestion more quickly and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a keynote speech to the &lt;abbr title="Confederation of British Industry"&gt;CBI&lt;/abbr&gt; yesterday, the PM announced that “it’s our ambition to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Highways Agency has looked hard at how to speed up the decision making process and the time it takes to have roads ready for use by motorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1km of managed motorway (using the hard shoulder as extra lanes and variable speed limits) can be built every two weeks, instead of every four. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected more complex, traditional capacity improvements on non motorway routes, such as the A160/A180 Immingham improvements, will be delivered up to 25% quicker/a quarter more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to faster delivery means this government will bring forward £75 million of investment forward into this spending review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There are four schemes in the programme where this new approach to road upgrades will be piloted, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A160/A180 Immingham dualling scheme - improving access to the Port of Immingham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 rather than during 2016. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £159 million (minimum) to £223 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is located on 13.4 miles of the M3 Motorway between Junction 12 of the M25 (M3 J2) to the A327 (M3 J4a) in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide more reliable journeys from London and Heathrow to Solent Ports – important for both leisure and business commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn is expected to start 2013/14 instead of 2014/15 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £140 million (minimum) to £201 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is located on a 9.6-mile stretch of the M6 between junctions 10a and 13, to the north west of Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support the economic development in and around the M6 by increasing business efficiency and improving reliability for business travellers, freight and logistics operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will add extra capacity on the M1 near Sheffield, between junctions 28 and J31 (18.9 miles), which is the primary strategic link between Nottingham and Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity improvement will support the economic development in the 7th and 8th largest urban areas in the United Kingdom by increasing business efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Immingham A160 and A180 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme is expected to start in summer 2015 instead of during 2016 and complete by autumn 2016 instead of during 2018 - this is subject to the successful completion of statutory processes, and the construction budget being agreed (for the next spending review period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an original five-and-a-half year programme, our ambition is to cut 18 months off the completion date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £89 million (minimum) to £132 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to improve the A160/A180 by upgrading it to a dual carriageway and improve access to the Port of Immingham. The A160 is approximately three miles long and has sections of both single carriageway and dual carriageway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the A160 carries around 13,000 vehicles per day, including approximately 5,700 heavy goods vehicles (44%) with road users experiencing severe congestion at times, particularly along the single carriageway sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Road schemes can be delivered more quickly by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undertaking concurrent planning, design and construction preparation activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking more work off-site and bringing to site as pre-fabricated/pre-assembled units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving toward a 24 hour operation with more people on site working on multiple phases at once &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16871</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:44:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-transport-bodies"/>
    <title>Guidance for Local Transport Bodies</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has announced its firm intention to devolve funding for local major transport schemes to Local Transport Bodies from 2015. The guidance sets out the necessary arrangement Local Transport Bodies will need to have in place to ensure value for money and sound decision making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16840</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T10:48:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/list-of-certifications-granted-for-approved-devices"/>
    <title>List of certifications granted for 'approved devices'</title>
    <summary>CCTV and evidence-recording equipment must be certified under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List of certifications granted by the Secretary of State for Transport for ‘approved devices’, CCTV and associated evidence-recording equipment, under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tma-part-6-certification-of-approved-devices"&gt;Civil traffic enforcement: certification of approved devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16634</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T10:41:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T10:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/targeted-consultation-on-a-proposed-amendment-to-the-renewable-transport-fuel-obligations-order-2007-as-amended-civil-penalties"/>
    <title>Targeted consultation on a proposed amendment to the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligations Order 2007 (as amended) - civil penalties</title>
    <summary>The Government is proposing to amend the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligations Order (RTFO) 2007.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of the fuel they supply comes from sustainable renewable sources. To ensure effective enforcement of the scheme the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; administrator has powers to issue civil penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is proposing to amend the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligations Order 2007 to put it beyond doubt that civil penalties issued under the scheme are enforceable as civil debts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16621</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/passengers-to-benefit-from-olympic-boost-to-services--2"/>
    <title>Passengers to benefit from Olympic boost to services</title>
    <summary>Plans to make it easier for train operators to adjust timetables and better serve passengers when dealing with music and sporting events.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Music lovers and sports fans travelling to gigs and games will benefit from more convenient train services under plans to make it easier for operators to offer more flexible timetables, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes, which are being introduced after a successful trial during the London 2012 Games, will mean that on special occasions train operators will be able to adjust a small portion of the timetable to better serve passengers without seeking permission from the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games were a massive success and proved our transport system was able to successfully carry record numbers of passengers. We helped train operators cope with the changing demand by giving them more flexibility to give passengers the services they needed.
&amp;gt;This has proved such an unqualified success that we have decided to permanently cut the red tape involved in adjusting small portions of the timetable. The changes give train companies the opportunity to ensure passengers are able to plan ahead to ensure they make it to their football matches and concerts and back home again on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Roberts, Chief Executive of the Association of Train Operating Companies (&lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is good news for passengers. Train companies have been seeking greater freedom to adapt their timetables to suit the needs of their customers and this move will be a big boost for people wanting to enjoy many special events across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes enable operators in England to adapt their timetables to cater for events in the calendar year when changes in passenger demand are expected to be significantly different – such as during sporting and cultural events or during school holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train operators will be allowed to adjust up to 30% of their timetabled services for special occasions, ensuring that more frequent passengers are still able to enjoy regular services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary will retain discretion over all timetable changes and the new measures and passenger benefits gained will be reviewed within the next 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The General Consent protocol, which enables train operators to adjust a small portion of their timetables for special events, was trialled with Southern Trains from the 17 April – 23 June 2012. This was then extended to all English train operators during the London 2012 Games.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The decision follows the success of the pilots and following consultation with Passenger Focus, London TravelWatch and &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Secretary of State is not responsible for the management of services within Scotland and Wales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16627</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:30:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/contact-telephone-numbers-for-crosscountry-rail"/>
    <title>Contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry rail</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information request regarding geographical contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
