<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16871</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:44:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-transport-bodies"/>
    <title>Guidance for Local Transport Bodies</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has announced its firm intention to devolve funding for local major transport schemes to Local Transport Bodies from 2015. The guidance sets out the necessary arrangement Local Transport Bodies will need to have in place to ensure value for money and sound decision making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16840</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T10:48:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/list-of-certifications-granted-for-approved-devices"/>
    <title>List of certifications granted for 'approved devices'</title>
    <summary>CCTV and evidence-recording equipment must be certified under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List of certifications granted by the Secretary of State for Transport for ‘approved devices’, CCTV and associated evidence-recording equipment, under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tma-part-6-certification-of-approved-devices"&gt;Civil traffic enforcement: certification of approved devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16621</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/passengers-to-benefit-from-olympic-boost-to-services--2"/>
    <title>Passengers to benefit from Olympic boost to services</title>
    <summary>Plans to make it easier for train operators to adjust timetables and better serve passengers when dealing with music and sporting events.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Music lovers and sports fans travelling to gigs and games will benefit from more convenient train services under plans to make it easier for operators to offer more flexible timetables, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes, which are being introduced after a successful trial during the London 2012 Games, will mean that on special occasions train operators will be able to adjust a small portion of the timetable to better serve passengers without seeking permission from the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games were a massive success and proved our transport system was able to successfully carry record numbers of passengers. We helped train operators cope with the changing demand by giving them more flexibility to give passengers the services they needed.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This has proved such an unqualified success that we have decided to permanently cut the red tape involved in adjusting small portions of the timetable. The changes give train companies the opportunity to ensure passengers are able to plan ahead to ensure they make it to their football matches and concerts and back home again on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Roberts, Chief Executive of the Association of Train Operating Companies (&lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is good news for passengers. Train companies have been seeking greater freedom to adapt their timetables to suit the needs of their customers and this move will be a big boost for people wanting to enjoy many special events across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes enable operators in England to adapt their timetables to cater for events in the calendar year when changes in passenger demand are expected to be significantly different – such as during sporting and cultural events or during school holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train operators will be allowed to adjust up to 30% of their timetabled services for special occasions, ensuring that more frequent passengers are still able to enjoy regular services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary will retain discretion over all timetable changes and the new measures and passenger benefits gained will be reviewed within the next 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The General Consent protocol, which enables train operators to adjust a small portion of their timetables for special events, was trialled with Southern Trains from the 17 April – 23 June 2012. This was then extended to all English train operators during the London 2012 Games.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The decision follows the success of the pilots and following consultation with Passenger Focus, London TravelWatch and &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Secretary of State is not responsible for the management of services within Scotland and Wales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16627</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:30:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/contact-telephone-numbers-for-crosscountry-rail"/>
    <title>Contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry rail</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information request regarding geographical contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16872</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:48:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-major-ports-group-annual-parliamentary-reception"/>
    <title>UK Major Ports Group annual parliamentary reception</title>
    <summary>Ports are an essential part of the economic growth of the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Charles (Charles Hammond – Chairman UK Major Ports Group/UKMPG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along - I’m delighted to have this chance to meet with you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="facts-are-stubborn-things"&gt;Facts are stubborn things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Adams, second President of the United States, said, “Facts are stubborn things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me, the stubborn facts prove that Britain’s ports are a national asset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every year more than 500 million tonnes of freight and well over 20 million international passengers pass through our ports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they account for over 95% of our imports and exports by volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and they employ around 130,000 people and contribute close to £7 billion to &lt;abbr title="Gross Domestic Product"&gt;GDP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Oxford Economics Report 2011)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="our-ports-matter-more-than-ever"&gt;Our ports matter more than ever&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, our ports matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with Britain facing the most serious economic challenge in a generation, they matter more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you create wealth, jobs and growth right here at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that contribution is absolutely vital to the health of our national economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But your economic importance doesn’t start and finish at our borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because you connect our country and our companies to new markets and new customers overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody has more experience, or more expertise, in accessing the global economy - seizing its opportunities, maximising its potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working day and night so that Britain is always open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure we’re a top trading nation, as well as a leading maritime nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who you are. It’s what you do - better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why you are key players. The people and the firms who can help Britain out-compete and out-produce the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-evangelist-for-the-ports-industry"&gt;An evangelist for the ports industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I have a tough act to follow in my predecessor Mike Penning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this audience will agree that Mike was a vocal and effective champion for this country’s ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I’m determined to pick up where Mike left off by being an evangelist for your industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So be in no doubt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trust port or private company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small, medium or large enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;north, south, east or west&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will be on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name on the ministerial door may be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our strategy and our policy for the maritime sector remains exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-right-environment-to-grow-and-succeed"&gt;The right environment to grow and succeed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m looking forward to visiting many of the ports you represent, to see for myself how they are coping in what remains a difficult trading climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know these are tough and testing times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as always, your members have been equal to them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the fact that UK ports increased their total traffic by 1.5 per cent last year is a huge achievement when set against the backdrop of continuing worldwide economic difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that suggests your members are well placed to benefit as the economy picks up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, with interest rates at their lowest for generations, now is a good time for stable, profitable businesses to invest for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this government knows that we must play our part too.  And there are 2 main strands to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creating an environment in which ports and maritime-related business of all kinds can succeed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making sure that the infrastructure for which government has direct responsibility complements and supports the work you do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re supporting major container port developments like those already under construction at Felixstowe, London Gateway and Southampton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial if these ports are to welcome the largest container vessels which are coming into service.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ships have the choice not to call in Britain at all if the infrastructure isn’t there.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these investments will help make sure that as many deep-sea boxes as possible are delivered directly to this country.  And that the country is ready for recovery and growth in trade in manufactured goods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which UK port will they come? That’s up to you. I’ll be as interested as anyone to see how the competition in this sector plays out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And others will follow. Liverpool, Bristol, Dover and Teesport also have the necessary consents to expand their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond the container sector, it’s imperative that every port is able to pursue a vision for the future - whether that’s responding to the opportunities brought by offshore energy, or it’s tapping into the potential of the tourism and leisure market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of the business model or maritime market your members choose, I want to make sure the government creates the right environment for them to grow and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="better-infrastructure-less-regulation"&gt;Better infrastructure, less regulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create that environment we’re absolutely committed to investing in the strategic roads and rail infrastructure that serves UK ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes far-reaching improvements to the rail freight network…as part of a £9.4 billion rail investment package announced this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the new initiatives is a high capacity ‘electric rail spine’ running from the south coast ports to the west Midlands and Yorkshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at ways to relieve the congestion on road routes to and from ports&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, we’ve set out a major scheme to boost the capacity of the A14 linking Felixstowe with the Midlands and the North,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most crucial arteries for goods coming into the country and -  together with measures to boost rail freight - this modernisation will help ease the flow of traffic around one of our biggest ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also removing the barriers you face so you can do your job efficiently and profitably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being responsible for ports and shipping, I also have the title ‘Minister for Better Regulation’ within the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I also regard myself as ‘Minister for Less Regulation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So believe me, if I find suffocating red tape that’s getting in your way and slowing you down, I will cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where there are regulations which add no value, I will scrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while we’ve already run through the Red Tape Challenge formalities, here’s a challenge that remains open to you: let me know where there is still any redundant regulation and I will try to get rid of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the case I’ve put this evening is that our ports have a front and centre role in the life of our nation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boosting jobs and growth in Britain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acting as international gateways for trade and travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping us transform our economic prospects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But then you have always been fundamental to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours is the industry that helped turn a small island nation into a major global player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industry with a proud story to tell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also an industry with a great future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it’s a pleasure to be here this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16723</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T08:31:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decision-letter-greater-manchester-light-rapid-transit-system"/>
    <title>Greater Manchester (Light Rapid Transit System) decision letter</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decision letter to authorise a modification to the route of an extension of the Metrolink system near Oldham Town Centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16873</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T14:38:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:50:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/crucial-road-improvements-to-be-delivered-twice-as-fast"/>
    <title>Crucial road improvements to be delivered twice as fast</title>
    <summary>Accelerated improvements to various motorways will see more benefits for drivers and hauliers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and hauliers will benefit from increased capacity on England’s motorways by spring 2015 thanks to the acceleration of three upgrades, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be delivered in this spending review period rather than the next, as the government introduces major improvements to the way road schemes are planned and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new way of working should in future see lanes added to motorways in up to half the time it normally takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three schemes being accelerated are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vital improvements to A160/A180 route to the Port of Immingham will also start construction sooner than originally planned in the summer of 2015 and completed autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half by dismantling procedures that have slowed us down. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Together these schemes will increase capacity for millions of road users by 72 miles. My ambition is that in future all major road schemes will be accelerated, tackling congestion more quickly and boosting the economy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a keynote speech to the &lt;abbr title="Confederation of British Industry"&gt;CBI&lt;/abbr&gt; yesterday, the PM announced that “it’s our ambition to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Highways Agency has looked hard at how to speed up the decision making process and the time it takes to have roads ready for use by motorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1km of managed motorway (using the hard shoulder as extra lanes and variable speed limits) can be built every two weeks, instead of every four. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected more complex, traditional capacity improvements on non motorway routes, such as the A160/A180 Immingham improvements, will be delivered up to 25% quicker/a quarter more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to faster delivery means this government will bring forward £75 million of investment forward into this spending review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There are four schemes in the programme where this new approach to road upgrades will be piloted, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A160/A180 Immingham dualling scheme - improving access to the Port of Immingham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 rather than during 2016. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £159 million (minimum) to £223 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is located on 13.4 miles of the M3 Motorway between Junction 12 of the M25 (M3 J2) to the A327 (M3 J4a) in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide more reliable journeys from London and Heathrow to Solent Ports – important for both leisure and business commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn is expected to start 2013/14 instead of 2014/15 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £140 million (minimum) to £201 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is located on a 9.6-mile stretch of the M6 between junctions 10a and 13, to the north west of Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support the economic development in and around the M6 by increasing business efficiency and improving reliability for business travellers, freight and logistics operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will add extra capacity on the M1 near Sheffield, between junctions 28 and J31 (18.9 miles), which is the primary strategic link between Nottingham and Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity improvement will support the economic development in the 7th and 8th largest urban areas in the United Kingdom by increasing business efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Immingham A160 and A180 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme is expected to start in summer 2015 instead of during 2016 and complete by autumn 2016 instead of during 2018 - this is subject to the successful completion of statutory processes, and the construction budget being agreed (for the next spending review period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an original five-and-a-half year programme, our ambition is to cut 18 months off the completion date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £89 million (minimum) to £132 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to improve the A160/A180 by upgrading it to a dual carriageway and improve access to the Port of Immingham. The A160 is approximately three miles long and has sections of both single carriageway and dual carriageway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the A160 carries around 13,000 vehicles per day, including approximately 5,700 heavy goods vehicles (44%) with road users experiencing severe congestion at times, particularly along the single carriageway sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Road schemes can be delivered more quickly by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undertaking concurrent planning, design and construction preparation activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking more work off-site and bringing to site as pre-fabricated/pre-assembled units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving toward a 24 hour operation with more people on site working on multiple phases at once &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16458</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-port-security-regulations-2009-at-certain-ports"/>
    <title>Implementation of Port Security Regulations 2009 at certain ports</title>
    <summary>This is a consultation on draft designation orders implementing Port Security Regulations 2009.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Directive 2005/65/EC is to enhance security coordination in the wider area at certain ports. The directive requires the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designation of a port security authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointment of a port security officer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a port security risk assessment to be conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a port security plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft designation orders which we are are consulting on here append plan(s) outlining the area which the port security authority will have responsibility over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16298</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T09:29:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-lighting"/>
    <title>Street lighting</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information response regarding the switching off of street lighting on sections of some roads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16471</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:30:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/westbourne-hs2-alliance-dinner"/>
    <title>Westbourne HS2 Alliance dinner</title>
    <summary>Speech by the Rt Hon Simon Burns MP, Minister of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction James (James Bethall, Westbourne Comms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough the importance of the work the Alliance does to build up a coalition of support for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value your support for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; and we need other organisations to continue make the case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; in a positive manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your efforts are highly regarded and greatly appreciated, so it’s a genuine pleasure to be with you all this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-only-game-in-town"&gt;The only game in town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaac Singer, the Polish-American author and Noble Prize winner, once told a journalist: “We have to believe in free will. We’ve got no choice”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s pretty much how I feel about high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I’m convinced that a high speed rail network won’t simply transform the way we travel in Britain, it will also transform the way we live, work and do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And transform it for generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also one hundred per cent certain that opting out of a high speed future would be a disaster for Britain, a missed opportunity we’d regret for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for me, there’s only one choice that makes sense for our country’s success and our children’s future, and that’s &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really is the only game in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bigger-picture"&gt;Bigger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; debate, we can talk about the line of route, design and technology or even mitigation measures and compensation packages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of these things matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also vital that we never ever lose sight of the bigger picture - the long-term potential of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the brief time I have tonight, that’s what Id like to focus on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-potential"&gt;Economic potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s economic potential:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will mean faster journey times, more capacity and better connected cities and regions - which, in turn, means that British businesses will be able to use it to exploit new markets and win new customers both at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also create and support tens of thousands of jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; can help to power up the recovery and put people back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="social-potential"&gt;Social potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to close the decades’ long north-south divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will help to open up access to employment opportunities and essential services like education and health for millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in a very real sense, a high speed rail network is as much about delivering better life chances as it is about getting from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="environmental-potential"&gt;Environmental potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me then, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; makes economic and social sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can also see a persuasive environmental case for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because I really do believe that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will offer people and businesses a high speed, low carbon alternative to short-haul flying and long-distance motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="willing-to-accept-unwilling-to-postpone-determined-to-meet"&gt;Willing to accept, unwilling to postpone, determined to meet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I look at the bigger &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; picture I don’t just see an investment in a high &lt;abbr title="technology"&gt;tech&lt;/abbr&gt;, high capacity, high speed rail network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see an investment in a stronger economy, a fairer society and a cleaner and greener environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why it has my full on and flat commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know that building high speed rail will be a test of Britain’s energy and skills. And yes, I know this challenge is as big as they come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know this country - .its people and its companies, its spirit and resolve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I am absolutely convinced it’s a challenge that we in Britain are willing to accept, unwilling to postpone and determined to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, when I first started out in politics I was told that the Golden Rule of public speaking was exhaust neither the subject nor the audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, down the years I’ve discovered another rule - never keep an audience from their dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ahead of our dinner and discussion, it only remains for me to say thank you for listening and here’s to a night of good food and great conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
