<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/64205</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"/>
    <title>Stopping up and diversion orders: reform of the application process for local highways</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the ‘Penfold review’, this consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway where this is required for the purpose of property development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose to permit applications for a stopping-up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission for the proposed development (whereas under the existing legislation the developer can only apply after securing planning permission), and options for devolving decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 9 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--2"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 16 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64307</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:03:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"/>
    <title>Implementation of the Penfold Review</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Proposals to simplify the process of stopping up or diverting a highway will be announced in a consultation response today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a government response to the consultation that closed on 24 August detailing proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up or diversion of a highway, where this is required for the purposes of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main options presented in the consultation were to permit applications for a stopping up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission and to devolve decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided not to devolve the stopping up and diversion order process to a local level. Consultation responses suggested that any devolution should be accompanied by a charging regime; additional costs and charges would be borne by both local authorities and those making applications, with no guarantee of a simpler or faster process. The government does not feel that placing additional burdens on local authorities and costs on developers is right at this time. And the government is aware that the speed of processing applications for stopping up or diversion orders has increased considerably in the last year. Additionally, we do not propose to reform or encourage a greater use of section 116 of the Highways Act 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government continues to support the first option, to allow stopping up and diversion applications to be made alongside planning applications. The government considers this will remove a significant barrier to growth, by speeding up the process and allowing a reduction of burdens on both applicants and local authorities, as both applications can be considered concurrently. Legislation currently in Parliament, as part of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, will give effect to this measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government response will be available in the libraries of both Houses and on the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"&gt;department’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64032</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Explaining the Secretary of State's decision about the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This letter gives details about the Secretary of State’s decision on the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It explains that the Secretary of State has decided to confirm the order subject to a specified modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector’s report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64036</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector's report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report was written by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It contains recommendations to amend words in the order and then confirm it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk//government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61518</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-guide-to-good-practice-on-port-marine-operations"/>
    <title>A guide to good practice on port marine operations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This supplement to the 'Port marine safety code' contains detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is a supplement to the ‘Port marine safety code’. It contains more detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. It is designed to provide general guidance and examples of how a harbour authority can meet its commitments in terms of compliance with the code. The guidance applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide should not be viewed as the only means of complying with the code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"&gt;Port marine safety code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64055</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-lighthouse-fund-report-and-accounts-2012"/>
    <title>General Lighthouse Fund: report and accounts 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report and accounts for the General Lighthouse Fund (year ended 31 March 2012)</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report and accounts of the General Lighthouse Fund (GLF) are prepared pursuant to Section 211(5) of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995. These accounts have been prepared in accordance with the 2011/12 Government Financial Reporting Manual (&lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt;) issued by HM Treasury. The accounting policies contained in the &lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt; follow International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) to the extent that it is meaningful and appropriate to the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/61368</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T11:22:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:22:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones"/>
    <title>Supporting economic growth through local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones have been created to drive public sector growth and reduce administrative burdens. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our economy is currently too dependent on a narrow range of industry sectors. We need an economy driven by private sector growth, with business opportunities evenly balanced across the country and between industries. We also need to reduce burdens for businesses, particularly in terms of lower tax levels, planning and other administrative burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve worked with local authorities to create &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/supporting-pages/local-enterprise-partnerships" title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;local enterprise partnerships&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;) across the whole country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve created 24 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/supporting-pages/enterprise-zones" title="Enterprise Zones"&gt;enterprise zones&lt;/a&gt; across England. For information on each of the zones go to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/" title="Enterprise Zones website"&gt;Enterprise Zones&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government and the Department for Transport have created the £730 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growing-places-fund-prospectus" title="Growing places fund prospectus"&gt;Growing Places Fund.&lt;/a&gt; The fund is used by local enterprise partnerships to support infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-enterprise-partnerships"&gt;Local enterprise partnerships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coalition agreement, the government committed to establishing local enterprise partnerships to replace the Regional Development Agencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2010 we invited businesses and councils to come together to form local enterprise partnerships whose geography properly reflects the natural economic areas of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/cm7961-local-growth-white-paper.pdf" title="Local growth white paper"&gt;Local Growth White Paper,&lt;/a&gt; published in October 2010, set out the roles that local enterprise partnerships can play depending on their local priorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/12-p113b-local-authority-areas-covered-by-leps.xls"&gt;Spreadsheet showing local authority (district/unitary) areas covered by &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Shows the situation for &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; when spreadsheet was last updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enterprise-zones"&gt;Enterprise zones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer announced the first 11 zones in the 2011 Budget. The government has now created 24 enterprise zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) published the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-zone-prospectus" title="Enterprise zone prospectus"&gt;‘Enterprise zone prospectus’&lt;/a&gt; the day after the Budget announcement. The prospectus explains what issues &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; needed to consider when making their application for an enterprise zone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enterprise zones have been awarded to, and are being led by, &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lepnetwork.org.uk/" title="LEP Network"&gt;LEP Network&lt;/a&gt; has been set up to help &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; share knowledge and ideas. Membership of the network is open to representatives of all &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in England. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56666</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england"/>
    <title>Boosting private sector employment in England</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Supporting businesses to create and protect jobs in the private sector, particularly where public sector employment is reducing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain parts of the country are too dependent on the public sector for employment. The government wants to increase the number of lasting, private sector jobs - by supporting the private sector to expand and ensuring that government cash delivers jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re funding large projects that have the potential to create or protect long-term jobs in the private sector, and programmes where partner organisations choose smaller projects to support, which will deliver sustainable jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re doing this through the Regional Growth Fund (&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt;). We have a total of £2.46 billion to give to businesses by 2016 to spend on projects such as capital investment, research and development, or training. (Please note: businesses cannot currently apply to the fund.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects we’ve chosen must attract private funding to match the public funding we provide, and the projects that programmes choose to support must also include investment of private money. We provide grants, loans and loan guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt; is a competitive fund – this means that in order to get our support, businesses must apply during a bidding round explaining how much money they need and what they will use it for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bids are then considered by an expert panel who recommend to ministers which bids to support. Ministers then choose the bids that they believe will give the best value for money to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cross-government fund and is jointly administered by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detail, see &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/understanding-the-regional-growth-fund"&gt;Understanding the Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money was allocated in 3 rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-1-april-2011"&gt;Round 1, April 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£450 million was allocated to 50 bids, attracting £2.5 billion in private sector investment. The projects will create or safeguard over 27,000 direct jobs, with around 100,000 more in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-2-october-2011"&gt;Round 2, October 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£950 million was invested in 126 bids, attracting nearly £6 billion of private investment. Around 200,000 jobs will be created or protected: around 37,000 direct jobs, with more than 164,000 in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-3-october-2012"&gt;Round 3: October 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£1.055 billion was allocated to 130 bids, attracting £6 billion of private investment. The projects will create or safeguard 240,000 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="process"&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations had to apply for a minimum of £1 million funding. Projects were assessed on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value for money for taxpayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ability to create jobs in the private sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;project management expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;state aid rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Projects had to comply with the &lt;a href="/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/supporting-pages/state-aid-rules"&gt;EU’s rules on state aid&lt;/a&gt; to make sure any funding did not give a company an unfair competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/r/12-1291-regional-growth-fund-confirmatory-due-diligence.pdf"&gt;Regional growth fund - confirmatory due diligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/d/declaration-for-due-diligence-providers.doc"&gt;Regional growth fund - declaration for due diligence providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
