<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:46+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61518</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-guide-to-good-practice-on-port-marine-operations"/>
    <title>A guide to good practice on port marine operations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This supplement to the 'Port marine safety code' contains detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is a supplement to the ‘Port marine safety code’. It contains more detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. It is designed to provide general guidance and examples of how a harbour authority can meet its commitments in terms of compliance with the code. The guidance applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide should not be viewed as the only means of complying with the code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"&gt;Port marine safety code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64055</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-lighthouse-fund-report-and-accounts-2012"/>
    <title>General Lighthouse Fund: report and accounts 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report and accounts for the General Lighthouse Fund (year ended 31 March 2012)</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report and accounts of the General Lighthouse Fund (GLF) are prepared pursuant to Section 211(5) of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995. These accounts have been prepared in accordance with the 2011/12 Government Financial Reporting Manual (&lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt;) issued by HM Treasury. The accounting policies contained in the &lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt; follow International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) to the extent that it is meaningful and appropriate to the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/61368</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T11:22:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:22:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones"/>
    <title>Supporting economic growth through local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Local enterprise partnerships and enterprise zones have been created to drive public sector growth and reduce administrative burdens. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our economy is currently too dependent on a narrow range of industry sectors. We need an economy driven by private sector growth, with business opportunities evenly balanced across the country and between industries. We also need to reduce burdens for businesses, particularly in terms of lower tax levels, planning and other administrative burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve worked with local authorities to create &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/supporting-pages/local-enterprise-partnerships" title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;local enterprise partnerships&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;) across the whole country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve created 24 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-growth-through-local-enterprise-partnerships-and-enterprise-zones/supporting-pages/enterprise-zones" title="Enterprise Zones"&gt;enterprise zones&lt;/a&gt; across England. For information on each of the zones go to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/" title="Enterprise Zones website"&gt;Enterprise Zones&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government and the Department for Transport have created the £730 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growing-places-fund-prospectus" title="Growing places fund prospectus"&gt;Growing Places Fund.&lt;/a&gt; The fund is used by local enterprise partnerships to support infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-enterprise-partnerships"&gt;Local enterprise partnerships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coalition agreement, the government committed to establishing local enterprise partnerships to replace the Regional Development Agencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2010 we invited businesses and councils to come together to form local enterprise partnerships whose geography properly reflects the natural economic areas of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/cm7961-local-growth-white-paper.pdf" title="Local growth white paper"&gt;Local Growth White Paper,&lt;/a&gt; published in October 2010, set out the roles that local enterprise partnerships can play depending on their local priorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/l/12-p113b-local-authority-areas-covered-by-leps.xls"&gt;Spreadsheet showing local authority (district/unitary) areas covered by &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Shows the situation for &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; when spreadsheet was last updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enterprise-zones"&gt;Enterprise zones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer announced the first 11 zones in the 2011 Budget. The government has now created 24 enterprise zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) published the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-zone-prospectus" title="Enterprise zone prospectus"&gt;‘Enterprise zone prospectus’&lt;/a&gt; the day after the Budget announcement. The prospectus explains what issues &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; needed to consider when making their application for an enterprise zone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enterprise zones have been awarded to, and are being led by, &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lepnetwork.org.uk/" title="LEP Network"&gt;LEP Network&lt;/a&gt; has been set up to help &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; share knowledge and ideas. Membership of the network is open to representatives of all &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in England. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56666</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T10:58:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england"/>
    <title>Boosting private sector employment in England</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Supporting businesses to create and protect jobs in the private sector, particularly where public sector employment is reducing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain parts of the country are too dependent on the public sector for employment. The government wants to increase the number of lasting, private sector jobs - by supporting the private sector to expand and ensuring that government cash delivers jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re funding large projects that have the potential to create or protect long-term jobs in the private sector, and programmes where partner organisations choose smaller projects to support, which will deliver sustainable jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re doing this through the Regional Growth Fund (&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt;). We have a total of £2.46 billion to give to businesses by 2016 to spend on projects such as capital investment, research and development, or training. (Please note: businesses cannot currently apply to the fund.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects we’ve chosen must attract private funding to match the public funding we provide, and the projects that programmes choose to support must also include investment of private money. We provide grants, loans and loan guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Regional Growth Fund"&gt;RGF&lt;/abbr&gt; is a competitive fund – this means that in order to get our support, businesses must apply during a bidding round explaining how much money they need and what they will use it for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bids are then considered by an expert panel who recommend to ministers which bids to support. Ministers then choose the bids that they believe will give the best value for money to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cross-government fund and is jointly administered by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detail, see &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/understanding-the-regional-growth-fund"&gt;Understanding the Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money was allocated in 3 rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-1-april-2011"&gt;Round 1, April 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£450 million was allocated to 50 bids, attracting £2.5 billion in private sector investment. The projects will create or safeguard over 27,000 direct jobs, with around 100,000 more in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-2-october-2011"&gt;Round 2, October 2011&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£950 million was invested in 126 bids, attracting nearly £6 billion of private investment. Around 200,000 jobs will be created or protected: around 37,000 direct jobs, with more than 164,000 in companies that are suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="round-3-october-2012"&gt;Round 3: October 2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£1.055 billion was allocated to 130 bids, attracting £6 billion of private investment. The projects will create or safeguard 240,000 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="process"&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations had to apply for a minimum of £1 million funding. Projects were assessed on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;value for money for taxpayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ability to create jobs in the private sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;project management expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;state aid rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Projects had to comply with the &lt;a href="/government/policies/boosting-private-sector-employment-in-england/supporting-pages/state-aid-rules"&gt;EU’s rules on state aid&lt;/a&gt; to make sure any funding did not give a company an unfair competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/r/12-1291-regional-growth-fund-confirmatory-due-diligence.pdf"&gt;Regional growth fund - confirmatory due diligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economic-development/docs/d/declaration-for-due-diligence-providers.doc"&gt;Regional growth fund - declaration for due diligence providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60990</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-pinch-point-fund-application-pack"/>
    <title>Local Pinch Point Fund application pack</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These documents make up the application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund. As part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2011_index.htm"&gt;2012 Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt; the government announced the creation of a Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network which are impeding growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application pack consists of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;guidance about how to apply for this funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application form &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme impact pro forma for small project bids &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
