<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/economic-growth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/economic-growth.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Economic growth"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16063</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boxing-day-boost-for-bargain-hungry-passengers"/>
    <title>Boxing day boost for bargain-hungry passengers</title>
    <summary>Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra rail services – which will make it easier for shoppers to access retail hubs in central London, Stratford and Kent – are being provided thanks to an agreement between the Department for Transport, Southeastern, and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have devised a unique agreement to enable Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; to make it easier for their passengers to get to the sales following Christmas, which will provide more services at no cost to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Southeastern ran some very successful services on High Speed 1 during the Olympics and the train operator has shown there is sufficient demand for these services so we were happy to consider allowing them to adjust their timetables. This is an excellent example of the government, infrastructure owners and train operators working innovatively together to improve services for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern’s managing director, Charles Horton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to offer this trial Boxing Day service for our passengers thanks to the collaboration with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our high speed Javelin service will transport people from Ashford to St Pancras International in just 37 minutes, and 19 minutes from Ebbsfleet. We’re also pleased to offer free parking at these 2 stations for Boxing Day so everyone has a little bit extra to spend in the sales!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Ruse, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, the company that owns High Speed 1 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Demand for high speed rail travel is rising all the time and this welcome example of teamwork on the railways means we can offer high speed rail customers a service that will prove hugely popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The half hourly service will run between Ashford International, Ebbsfleet International, Stratford International and St Pancras International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd ran a special timetable through the Olympics and Paralympics with extra high speed services to carry spectators to and from Stratford International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timetables and ticket information can be viewed online at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/"&gt;nationalrail.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/15629</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/caa-board-members-reappointed"/>
    <title>CAA board members reappointed</title>
    <summary>Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin has reappointed 2 members of the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) board for second terms in office.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin has reappointed 2 members of the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) board for second terms in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Gray and Michael Medlicott joined the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; as non-executive Members in November 2009 and February 2010 respectively. David Gray has particular expertise in economic regulation including a period at Ofgem, where he was responsible for gas and electricity price control reviews. Michael Medlicott has many years’ experience in the transport and tourism sectors, including senior roles in the airline and airport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will serve for second terms of 3 years each at their existing salaries of £22,000 per annum for a time commitment of 1 day per week, with additional remuneration for chairing committees and participation in appeals hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A successful, safe and efficient aviation sector is vital to the UK’s success on the global stage. These reappointments recognise the contributions that both individuals have made to ensuring the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; remains an effective, reforming regulator in what has been a challenging period for the aviation sector. I wish them well as they continue in these important roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Authority is responsible for the regulation of civil aviation in the United Kingdom and is the government’s principal advisor on aviation matters. It has specific responsibility for aviation safety, consumer protection, airspace policy and the economic regulation of the industry. It is based mainly in London and Gatwick and has approximately 950 employees. The great majority of the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s funding comes from the charges it imposes on the industry, rather than the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both members were originally appointed following an open competition regulated by the Office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments. The appointments were made on merit and political activity plays no part in the selection process. They have both declared that they have undertaken no relevant political activity during the past 5 years and that they hold no other current public appointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16037</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:35:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-to-scrap-motor-insurance-certificates-launched"/>
    <title>Consultation to scrap motor insurance certificates launched</title>
    <summary>The government has announced a consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates and reduce motor insurance red tape.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drivers could benefit from less motor insurance red tape after a government consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates was launched today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8 week exercise will seek the views of the industry, motorists and other stakeholders on the benefits of moving towards a purely online system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under current law, insurance companies must issue a paper or electronic certificate when agreeing a policy. However, many organisations, including the police and vehicle rental companies, already rely on information stored on the Motor Insurer’s Database (MID) as evidence of valid insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More and more people are using technology to organise their everyday lives so it is only right we look at how we can make life easier for motorists and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are launching a consultation to scrap the legal requirement for insurance certificates to be issued and consolidate a system whereby all information is online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has the potential to make significant savings down the line which I hope will be passed on to policyholders. It will also make the lives of motorists and police easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to moving to an online system include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motorists will no longer be forced to retain certificates as details will be accessible online. This will remove the legal requirement whereby vehicle owners are required to return their certificates to insurance companies in order to cancel the policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;police and the commercial motor industry would be better able to check details at source, instead of relying on policyholder documents which can be forged. The Police already use a download of the MID to identify uninsured drivers on the road.
If the consultation is successful then the Department would look to repeal the current law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposal is part of the government’s Red Tape Challenge, which invited the public and stakeholders to give their views on which regulations should stay, be improved, or be scrapped altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"&gt;consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available on the DfT website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department proposes to amend s147 (1) of the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue motor insurance certificates (whether issued as a paper document or electronically)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Association of British Insurers (ABI) estimate the cost of producing each certificate is about £1 and around 34.2 million insurance documents are issued per annum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15074</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:29:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:29:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"/>
    <title>Removal of motor insurance certificates</title>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on the principle of removing the need for insurers to issue a motor insurance certificate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on amending the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue a motor insurance certificate when an insurance policy is taken out. At present the certificate is used as evidence of valid insurance cover and there are circumstances when it must be produced by the insured to demonstrate they have valid cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurers are required by law to enter details of all motor insurance policies onto the motor insurance database (&lt;abbr title="motor insurance database"&gt;MID&lt;/abbr&gt;). This consultation document considers using the &lt;abbr title="motor insurance database"&gt;MID&lt;/abbr&gt; as the single source for checking if insurance cover is in place and considers what further changes and developments are needed to make this work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15105</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T12:52:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"/>
    <title>Low carbon bus calculator</title>
    <summary>This toolkit can be used to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (LCEB).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the benefits of purchasing a low carbon bus will be different for each operator and will depend on the way in which the bus in service is used. So, Department for Transport economists have produced a transparent, user-friendly toolkit to be used by bus operators and local authorities to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (&lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;). Your assessment should always compare the &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; to an equivalent diesel bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit allows you flexibility in changing the input assumptions to those most relevant to you. You will be able to assess the financial implications of purchasing a &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;, based on the fuel savings on offer (as advised by &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturers or experienced in trials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet tool is intended to provide indicative estimates only and &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; does not vouch for the accuracy of such estimates. Please note that the Department for Transport does not accept any liability for any decisions that may be taken on the basis of such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit will be routinely updated and refined. Details of any updates or changes that are made will be outlined in the ‘Intro’ worksheet of the toolkit. We therefore encourage you to visit this website regularly and download the toolkit to ensure you are using the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15068</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:21:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/driver-and-vehicle-licensing-agency-13-november-2012"/>
    <title>Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency 13 November 2012</title>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Patrick McLoughlin MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has recently run a competition to procure a front office counter service provider for its face to face motoring services from next April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will award Post Office Ltd® a contract to build on the existing counter operation to provide a wider range of services and better accessibility for motorists. The contract will run for 7 years with an option to extend for up to another 3 years. This contract will allow the Post Office to fully develop better services with the requirements of customers at the heart. Under the contract Post Office Ltd® will offer &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; services at over 4,700 outlets for road tax and vehicle transactions, 750 of which will also cater for driver licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new contract provides value for money for the taxpayer resulting in savings of between £13 million and £15 million a year. The contract also gives scope for the Post Office to provide front office counter services for other government departments, to increase efficiencies across government and provide better value for the tax payer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14285</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T12:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T12:35:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/evesham-to-benefit-from-new-8-2-million-bridge"/>
    <title>Evesham to benefit from new £8.2 million bridge</title>
    <summary>Abbey Bridge over the River Avon in Evesham has received final approval to be replaced by Norman Baker.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to replace the Abbey Bridge over the River Avon in Evesham can now start after the proposals received final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridge and viaduct need to be replaced as they are in poor condition and the current structures are already subject to a 7.5 tonne weight restriction. If the structures are not replaced then even lower restrictions would be needed in the near future along with the possibility of full closure to all traffic soon after. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When completed, the new bridge will allow the current weight limit to be removed bringing the bridge up to current national standards and allowing it to be used by HGVs, coaches and buses. The replacement bridge will improve access to Evesham town centre from the south for local residents and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This excellent scheme will restore the full capacity of this important route and provide a boost to the local economy by ensuring that access to the town centre for bus passengers and lorries is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The £5.6 million we are putting into this project shows that the Coalition Government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth both locally and nationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Abbey Bridge replacement scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work can now start on construction with the new bridge scheduled to open in December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants Full (final) Approval to the Abbey Bridge replacement scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The scheme, promoted Worcestershire County Council, is scheduled to open in December 2013. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department will provide a maximum of £5.59 million towards the full scheme cost of £8.2 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15995</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T16:34:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-regulated-agents-and-in-flight-suppliers"/>
    <title>Department for Transport regulated agents and in-flight suppliers</title>
    <summary>A list of aviation related agencies that are regulated by the Department for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-number-for-all-enquiries"&gt;Contact number for all enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone: 0207 944 6430&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="communication-with-cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Communication with Cargo and In-Flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could all non-urgent communication with inspectors, wherever possible, please be sent to their email addresses (listed below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Cargo and in-flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christian Whitley, Team Leader Cargo and In-flight Supplies &lt;a href="mailto:Christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daz Salmon &lt;a href="mailto:daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gillian Stephens &lt;a href="mailto:gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Sidney &lt;a href="mailto:james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jerry Koster &lt;a href="mailto:jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin Gurney &lt;a href="mailto:martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maurice Stearn &lt;a href="mailto:maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carole Cousins &lt;a href="mailto:carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="validation-and-known-consignors-scheme"&gt;Validation and Known Consignors Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email all enquires to &lt;a href="mailto:current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="correspondence"&gt;Correspondence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport  
&lt;br&gt;Transport Security Compliance  
&lt;br&gt;3rd Floor, Fry Building  
&lt;br&gt;2 Marsham Street  
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1P 4DF
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14274</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T12:06:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/aviation-permits"/>
    <title>Aviation permits</title>
    <summary>Outlining procedures for issuing airline operating permits.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-permit-regime-explained"&gt;The permit regime explained&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before operating to, from or within the United Kingdom, all foreign registered aircraft must be in possession of an operating permit issued by the Department for Transport’s International Aviation, Safety &amp;amp; Environment Division (&lt;abbr title="International Aviation, Safety &amp;amp; Environment Division"&gt;IASE&lt;/abbr&gt;) under the 2009 Air Navigation Order. This requirement extends to all scheduled and non-scheduled passenger and cargo charters that are not covered by the provisions of the European market access regulations, and to flights carrying out aerial work (e.g. photography, parachuting, flight training). Foreign aircraft require also permits under the appropriate air navigation orders before operating to the Isle of Man, Channel Islands and the UK overseas territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before granting any operating permits for scheduled flights, &lt;abbr title="International Aviation, Safety &amp;amp; Environment Division"&gt;IASE&lt;/abbr&gt; ensures that the services are operating in conformity with the traffic rights and conditions provided under the UK’s bilateral air services arrangements negotiated with the airlines’ states. In the case of non-scheduled flights we seek reciprocity to ensure that UK airlines are allowed similar opportunities from the respective foreign authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Aviation, Safety &amp;amp; Environment Division"&gt;IASE&lt;/abbr&gt; also ensures that a number of administrative arrangements are completed before an operating permit is granted. These require airlines to provide valid certificates that are recognised by the International Civil Aviation Organisation (ICAO) on competency (ie air operators certificate), insurance, registration, aircraft airworthiness and noise and that aircraft are fitted with a recognised enhanced ground proximity warning system, airborne collision avoidance system and crews are aware of the UK Approach Ban requirements and comply with aerodrome operating minima requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, any airline operating aircraft with a maximum take-off weight of 10,000kgs or more in the United Kingdom must also have a security Direction (known as the Single Consolidated Direction (Aviation) 2010) served on them and so applicants applying for a permit that involves such an operation should also contact &lt;a href="mailto:surefaxupdate@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;surefaxupdate@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; for further information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="departmental-contacts"&gt;Departmental contacts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications to the Secretary of State for airline operating permits should be sent using the appropriate form to the Department for Transport at the address below at least 48 hours in advance of the first flight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="office-hours"&gt;Office Hours&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

1/22 Great Minster House,    
&lt;br&gt;33 Horseferry Road,    
&lt;br&gt;London,    
&lt;br&gt;SW1P 4DR   
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email (office hours): &lt;a href="mailto:%20airlineoperatingpermits@dft.gov.uk"&gt;airlineoperatingpermits@dft.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fax: +44 (0)20 7944 2194&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-for-airlines-registered-in-russia-and-other-former-soviet-union-states-except-baltic-states-countries-in-asia-including-the-indian-sub-continent-and-the-far-east-australasia"&gt;Contact for airlines registered in Russia and other former Soviet Union States (except Baltic States), countries in Asia, including the Indian sub-continent, and the Far East, Australasia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5804 or telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5847&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-for-airlines-registered-in-north-america-central-america-south-america-and-the-caribbean"&gt;Contact for airlines registered in North America, Central America, South America and the Caribbean&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5849 or telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5847&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-for-airlines-registered-in-europe-including-the-baltic-states-and-turkey-africa-and-the-middle-east"&gt;Contact for airlines registered in Europe (including the Baltic States and Turkey), Africa and the Middle East&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5804 or telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5847&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="out-of-office-hours-emergency-only"&gt;Out of office hours (emergency only)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications for urgent emergency ad-hoc flights or last minute substitution flights that need to be made out of office hours, weekends and public holidays should be submitted to the Department for Transport Duty Office:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telephone: +44 (0)20 7944 5999&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fax: +44 (0)20 7944 5369&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;NB: The out of hour’s service is to be used for emergency situations only. Any request for permits to operate series or seasonal programmes of flights will be considered only during office hours. It would be helpful if applicants provide more than one means of contact, in case difficulties arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/aviation-permits-using-leased-foreign-registered-aircraft-in-the-uk/"&gt;Aviation Permits - using leased foreign registered aircraft in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/flying-training-using-foreign-registered-aircraft-in-uk"&gt;Flying training - using foreign registered aircraft in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/aviation-permits-application-forms/"&gt;Aviation permits - application forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/aviation-permits-doc-requirements-foreign-airlines-aircraft"&gt;Aviation Permits - documentary requirements for foreign airlines/aircraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/extra-bilateral-flight-application-procedures/"&gt;Extra-bilateral flight application procedures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14296</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:50:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-urges-shoppers-love-your-local-market"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk urges shoppers: "love your local market"</title>
    <summary>The Love Your Local Market 2013 campaign will entice budding entrepreneurs to trade.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk called on communities and budding entrepreneurs to back their local markets well into the New Year, as part of a wider effort to breathe new life into the nation’s high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister confirmed that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/" title="Love Your Local Market"&gt;Love Your Local Market&lt;/a&gt; campaign in 2013 will take place from 15 May, and will give aspiring retailers the chance to test out their ideas at their local markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Love Your Local Market campaign, new stallholders will be able to take advantage of a ‘Table for a Tenner’ deal - with some offering free pitches - at markets across the country, with many offering mentoring to those setting up shop for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make sure as many high streets as possible can take part, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/" title="National Association of British Market Authorities"&gt;National Association of British Market Authorities&lt;/a&gt; will hold a series of roadshows sharing ideas that councils and other market operators can take to make their events a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 400 local markets across the country were involved this summer, with a locally-defined programme of events designed to attract visitors into town centres and help new start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Markets can play an integral role in reviving our high streets, offering something new and exciting for shoppers in a way the Internet and out-of-town retail centres can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge traders and councils across the country to back this effective and important campaign, offer support to budding entrepreneurs looking to trade and Love Your Local Market.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Wilson, OBE, Chief Executive of the National Association of British Market Authorities, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Love Your Local Market and National Market Day provided a great impetus to the campaign to revitalise the high street and created an opportunity for almost 2000 people to sample market trading for the first time. We now want to build on this success and make LYLM 2013 bigger and better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Harrison, Chief Executive of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmtf.co.uk/" title="National Market Traders Association"&gt;National Market Traders’ Federation&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We, at the National Market Traders’ Federation, are happy to see this campaign running again for a second year, and are delighted to support it. We do hope it has an even bigger impact than the first event with regard to the encouragement of new start-up businesses within the industry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="following-up-on-a-successful-fortnight"&gt;Following up on a successful fortnight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows the success of the Love Your Local Markets event in June this year, which saw over 400 markets run over the dedicated 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this scheme:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;around 400 markets took part under the Love Your Local Markets banner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just under 2,000 new traders joined local markets during last year’s campaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over 3,000 ‘Tables for a Tenner’ and free pitches were offered - over half of which were taken up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Rogers, whose chocolate stall is now a regular fixture at Ludlow Market, with visitors now looking to buy her products online and making bookings for her to cater weddings and other events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obi Nwosu, who started selling during Love Your Local Market at Portobello in London, and now has stalls in six locations across the Capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Smith, who started his Natural Ingredients stall at Fleetwood Market earlier this year, but is now trading on every market day of the week, and sell into retail outlets including food halls and other local specialist markets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
