<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/energy</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/energy"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/energy.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Energy"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/13604</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"/>
    <title>Working towards nuclear disarmament</title>
    <summary>The UK is committed to the long-term goal of a world without nuclear weapons and zero tolerance of proliferation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, because of the continued existence of large nuclear arsenals around the world, the possibility of further &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"&gt;proliferation of nuclear weapons&lt;/a&gt; and the risk of increased international instability and tension, we believe that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-an-effective-independent-nuclear-deterrent"&gt;the UK’s nuclear deterrent&lt;/a&gt; remains an important element of our national security. However, we will continue to take steps towards a safer and more stable world where countries with nuclear weapons feel able to relinquish them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that sustainable nuclear disarmament can only be achieved through a multilateral process. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/disarmament/WMD/Nuclear/NPT.shtml"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; provides the basis for global efforts to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons, to promote the safe and secure use of civil nuclear energy and to pursue the goal of a world without nuclear weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reducing-the-uks-nuclear-weapons-stockpile"&gt;Reducing the UK’s nuclear weapons stockpile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are reducing the UK’s stockpile of nuclear weapons to no more than 180 warheads, and a maximum of 40 per boat. This will be complete by the mid-2020s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty-action-plan"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty action plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty is reviewed every 5 years. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;64-point action plan&lt;/a&gt; was agreed at the 2010 Review Conference by nuclear and non-nuclear-weapons states. This demonstrates the broad international commitment to the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan included actions on nuclear disarmament, non-proliferation and the peaceful uses of nuclear energy. The government is working closely with all states to progress these actions across all 3 ‘pillars’ of the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; (see Legislation section). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action plan contains a number of specific recommendations on disarmament for the 5 nuclear-weapon states including the UK.   We are discussing ways we can work together to make progress on these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next Review Conference will take place in New York in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/prod_consum_dg/groups/dg_digitalassets/@dg/@en/documents/digitalasset/dg_191634.pdf"&gt;Strategic Defence &amp;amp; Security Review (&lt;abbr title="Strategic Defence &amp;amp; Security Review"&gt;SDSR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; reaffirmed our commitment to maintaining a minimum effective nuclear deterrent, but also contained a number of new disarmament measures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2010 the government announced that it would reduce the overall size of the UK’s nuclear weapons stockpile to 225. Publishing information about the total number of weapons goes beyond our previous policy, which declared only ‘operationally available’ weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a further review, in October 2011 the Prime Minister announced that by the mid-2020s the overall size of the UK nuclear weapons stockpile will reduce to no more than 180 warheads. No more than 120 will be operationally available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2011, the government &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm110629/wmstext/110629m0001.htm"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; the early implementation of these reductions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/prod_consum_dg/groups/dg_digitalassets/@dg/@en/documents/digitalasset/dg_191634.pdf"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a new, stronger assurance that the UK will not use or threaten to use nuclear weapons against non-nuclear weapons states party to the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. These announcements mean that the UK has been more transparent than ever about our arsenal and declaratory policy, which we believe will help to build trust between nuclear and non-nuclear weapon states, and contribute to efforts to reduce the number of nuclear weapons worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; entered into force in 1970 and is the basis of the global nuclear non-proliferation regime. It consists of 3 ‘pillars’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pillar 1 relates to non-proliferation. The recognised nuclear-weapon states (China, France, Russia, UK, US) undertake not to transfer knowledge or equipment to other states, and non-nuclear-weapon states commit to not trying to acquire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pillar 2 relates to multilateral nuclear disarmament. It commits all states party to pursue negotiations in good faith towards the cessation of the nuclear arms race and to multilateral nuclear disarmament as part of general and complete disarmament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pillar 3 relates to the peaceful use of nuclear energy. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; recognises that all states party have an ‘inalienable right’ to use civil nuclear power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; Review Conference concluded in New York on 28 May 2010 with an action plan covering all 3 ‘pillars’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50193</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T09:23:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T09:23:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch</title>
    <summary>Commenting on the launch of DPRK’s satellite, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague said:</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I strongly condemn the DPRK’s satellite launch today. This launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 as it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. This provocative act will increase tensions in the region. I deplore the fact that the DPRK has chosen to prioritise this launch over improving the livelihood of its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be summoning the DPRK Ambassador to the UK to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office and the UK will urgently consult partners in the United Nations Security Council on our response to this development. It is essential that the DPRK refrain from further provocative action and take constructive steps towards denuclearisation and lasting peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/34784</id>
    <published>2012-07-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:01:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/105-2012-mod-experts-to-help-iraqis-destroy-legacy-chemical-weapons"/>
    <title>105/2012 - MOD Experts to help Iraqis destroy legacy chemical weapons</title>
    <summary>Scientists from the Ministry of Defence are to provide training which will support the Iraqi Government’s efforts to dispose of remnants of the chemical weapons amassed during Saddam Hussein’s regime.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under an agreement signed in Baghdad, experts from the MoD’s Defence Science and Technology Laboratory (Dstl) will provide training to Iraqi personnel, which will help them to safely dispose of partially destroyed chemical munitions and agents, along with other contaminated materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The materials are contained in two sealed bunkers at the old Al Muthanna Chemicals Weapons Complex, a large site in the western desert some 80km north-west of Baghdad, which was the principal manufacturing plant for both chemical agents and munitions during Saddam Hussein’s rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of tonnes of chemical weapons were produced, stored and deployed by the Saddam Hussein regime. Iraq used these weapons during the Iran – Iraq war (1980 to 1988) and against the Kurds in Halabja in 1988. Following the First Gulf War, most of Iraq’s chemical munitions were destroyed under supervision of UN inspectors (UNSCOM) and the partially destroyed contents of these two sealed bunkers are all that remain of those legacy weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chemical Weapons Convention, which Iraq joined in 2009, requires that although the material is unusable and does not pose a significant security risk, it must be disposed of. The nature of the material contained in the two bunkers will make the destruction process difficult and technically challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has therefore agreed to provide training to Iraqi personnel at Dstl’s site in Porton Down – a world-leading centre of excellence for chemical defence. The training will take place later this year and will teach technical personnel how to safely handle toxic chemicals. The team at Dstl will also offer training to Iraqi medical personnel on how to deal with the health risks associated with the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Minister Nick Harvey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were glad to support Iraq when it joined the Chemical Weapons Convention in 2009. One of the key obligations of member states is to destroy any chemical weapons it possesses, so the UK is delighted to be able to help Iraq by providing world-leading expertise and high quality training to Iraqi personnel involved in this difficult and dangerous task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chemical Weapons Convention (CWC) obliges Iraq to destroy its chemical weapons as soon as possible. Due to the complex nature of the task faced by Iraq, the US, United Kingdom and Germany offered assistance to Iraq to help them achieve their obligations under the CWC.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information, please contact MoD Press Office on 0207 218 7907.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
