<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/environment</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/environment"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/environment.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Environment"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:00:19+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/57081</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:00:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:00:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment"/>
    <title>Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the environment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009 buildings accounted for about 43% of all the UK’s carbon emissions. Buildings and other developments can also damage the environment, through poor waste management or inefficient use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the natural and built environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have included policies in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to explain how developments should be planned to reduce carbon emissions and protect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce carbon emissions from buildings, we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are requiring local planning authorities to make sure that new developments are energy efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will require all new homes to be zero carbon from 2016 and are considering extending this to include all other buildings from 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/green_deal/green_deal.aspx" title="Green deal"&gt;green deal&lt;/a&gt; to enable people to pay for home improvements over time using savings on their regular energy bills &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have improved &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/energy-performance-of-buildings" title="Energy Performance Certificates"&gt;Energy Performance Certificates&lt;/a&gt; to make them more informative and user-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/code-for-sustainable-homes" title="Code for sustainable homes"&gt;Code for Sustainable Homes&lt;/a&gt; which provides a single national standard for the design and construction of sustainable new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect trees we have simplified the system for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/tree-preservation-orders" title="Tree preservation certificates"&gt;tree preservation orders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work with the 9 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/aggregate-working-parties" title="Aggregate working parties"&gt;aggregate working parties&lt;/a&gt; who provide technical advice about the supply and demand for aggregates such as sand, gravel and crushed rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is responsible for developing town and country planning policy and rules that affect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policies on planning and the environment are set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework-and-the-environment" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012 following extensive public consultation. The framework is an important part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more easy to understand, and to promote sustainable growth. It replaced and simplified a series of earlier planning policy statements and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the government’s policy to revoke existing regional strategies outside London. However, any final decision on this must take account of assessments of, and consultation on, the possible environmental effects. We are updating the earlier environmental reports and undertaking further consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/abolition-of-regional-strategies"&gt;written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt; made by Baroness Hanham on 25 July 2012 sets out the background and explains why the reports are being updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All EU member states must follow the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive. This requires that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all properties (homes, commercial and public buildings) must have an Energy Performance Certificate when sold, built or rented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger public buildings must display a Display Energy Certificate &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all air-conditioning systems over 12kW must be regularly inspected by an Energy Assessor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60040</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:34:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-our-buildings"/>
    <title>Recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings. The requirements of the Directive were implemented on a phased basis by the Energy Performance of Buildings (Certificates and Inspections) (England and Wales) Regulations 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key requirements were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be produced on the sale, rent or construction of a building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;display energy certificate to be produced and displayed in large public buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;air conditioning equipment above a certain size to be inspected regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes have been made to the regulations, to transpose the requirements of a recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive in England and Wales. The main requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013 and are summarised below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;property advertisements to include details of energy performance certificate rating where available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no longer a requirement to attach front page of the energy performance certificate to written material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extension of current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m².  Unlike buildings larger than 1,000m²,  display energy certificates for smaller public buildings will be valid for 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² where one has been previously issued&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidance documents have been revised to reflect the changes and can be viewed via the links above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new regulations consolidate all existing regulations which have been revoked. They are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/" title="legislation.gov.uk"&gt;legislation.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61102</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T11:59:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-communities-and-local-government-approved-software-for-the-production-of-non-domestic-energy-performance-certificates-epc"/>
    <title>Department for Communities and Local Government approved software for the production of Non Domestic Energy Performance Certificates (EPC) </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive (&lt;abbr title="Energy Performance of Buildings Directive"&gt;EPBD&lt;/abbr&gt;) became part of EU law in December 2002. The &lt;abbr title="Energy Performance of Buildings Directive"&gt;EPBD&lt;/abbr&gt; has been implemented into law via the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2007/991/contents/made"&gt;Energy Performance of Buildings (Certificates and Inspections) (England and Wales) Regulations 2007&lt;/a&gt; (S.I. 2007/991 as amended) (“the 2007 regulations”) in respect of sales and lettings, and in regulation 29 to 33 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; (S.I. 2010/2214 as amended or superseded) (the Building Regulations) in respect of the duty on construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulation 24 of the Building Regulations 2010 (the Building Regulations) requires the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government (the Secretary of State) to approve a National Calculation Methodology (&lt;abbr title="National Calculation Methodology"&gt;NCM&lt;/abbr&gt;) for calculating the energy performance of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All software that is used to assess the energy performance of buildings must be validated to ensure that it operates in a manner, and to a standard, consistent with the &lt;abbr title="National Calculation Methodology"&gt;NCM&lt;/abbr&gt; before it can be approved by the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see the attached latest list of approved software for the production of non domestic Energy Performance Certificates (EPCs), Domestic Energy Performance Certificates (DECs) and Air Conditioning Inspection Reports (ACIRs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57041</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:45:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-planning-authorities-on-implementing-planning-requirements-of-the-eu-waste-framework-directive-2008-98-ec"/>
    <title>Guidance for local planning authorities on implementing planning requirements of the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>A guidance note to ensure compliance with the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC) (‘the Directive’) provides an overarching legislative framework for the management of waste across Europe. This guidance note provides advice on the measures required by local planning authorities to ensure compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is aimed primarily at waste planning authorities, but it highlights the main legal and policy provisions of relevance to all planning authorities, and the action we expect them to take to assist them in ensuring compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be read alongside the government’s planning policy for waste management, currently set out in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;Planning Policy Statement 10&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-a-companion-guide-to-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;companion guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by The Right Honourable Don Foster MP on changes to the building regulations regime in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56834</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the north west plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919154703/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationnwrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the north west regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/48343</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy in force for the East of England).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/39671</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T17:19:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/energy-performance-of-buildings-directive-article-8-equivalence-uk-biennial-reports"/>
    <title>Energy Performance of Buildings Directive article 8 equivalence - UK biennial reports</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Equivalence reports produced by the Building Research Establishment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive, published in January 2003, is designed to improve the energy efficiency of buildings across Europe. Article 8 of the Directive is specifically aimed at improving the performance of heating systems. The directive offers two alternatives for implementing article 8: option (a) which involves the implementation of an inspection regime; or option (b) which involves the provision of advice, but this option can also include ‘alternative solutions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has chosen to adopt option (b) and has prepared biennial Article 8 equivalence reports to demonstrate that this approach has an impact that is ‘broadly equivalent’ to that produced through the provisions of option (a).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reports were produced in January 2008 and November 2010 and we are publishing them in the interests of transparency and as part of our Freedom of Information commitment to publish the results of all commissioned research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17572</id>
    <published>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/zero-carbon-for-new-non-domestic-buildings"/>
    <title>Zero carbon for new non-domestic buildings</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation about working towards the government's ambition for all new non-domestic buildings to be zero carbon from 2019.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out proposals for working towards the government’s ambition that all new non-domestic buildings should be zero carbon from 2019, with the public sector leading the way from 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17341</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T13:09:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the South West Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194318/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationswrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the South West regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S6 from the ‘Somerset and Exmoor National Park joint structure plan’ relating to the green belt in North East Somerset. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the coalition agreement to safeguard the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
