<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Equality, rights and citizenship"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64188</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"/>
    <title>Minister “dismayed” at verdict in Bahraini activists’ appeal </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt, has called on Bahrain to guarantee its citizens’ fundamental liberties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court today upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. Commenting earlier, Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am deeply dismayed at the decision of the Bahraini Cassation Court to uphold the sentences of 13 political activists in today’s appeal hearing. At the time these individuals were sentenced, reports which were acknowledged by the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry suggested that some had been abused in detention, denied access to legal counsel and were coerced into confessing. I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bahrain-independent-commission-of-inquiry-bici"&gt;Minister comments on Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60215</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens"/>
    <title>Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has reaffirmed UK support for imprisoned Human Rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the United Nations vote on the human right situation in Iran, the Foreign Secretary has released a video. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic freedoms of ordinary Iranians are being denied. Many citizens live in constant fear of arbitrary arrest, false imprisonment and, in some cases, death. There is undeniable evidence of abuse: the recent death in custody of blogger Sattar Beheshti is one tragic example. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also spoke about Nasrin Sotoudeh, who recently ended a 49-day hunger strike in protest against the harassment of her family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have sacrificed your own freedom, family life and health in order to help others. I want you to know that we are following your case closely. And that I echo the many calls upon Iran for your immediate release. Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regime hopes to silence those who call for basic human rights in Iran. I want to make clear that the promotion and protection of human rights is at the heart of UK foreign policy. And we are committed to supporting and protecting those who defend human rights and work tirelessly to advance personal freedoms, often at great personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OHQkieCYSZg"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/ukiniran/punishing-a-human-rights-defender-nasrin-sotoudehs" title="Nasrin Sotoudehs story"&gt;Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family" title="UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60204</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria"/>
    <title>UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria  </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt: The UK will continue to support work of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria to ensure accountability. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the publication of a new UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today the UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria published its latest report on the human rights situation in Syria. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. The Commission concludes that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commission has received credible accounts of Government soldiers executing captives. Incidents of direct targeting of civilians by aerial bombardment, including “barrel bombs,” rocket attacks and machine gun fire have risen significantly over recent months. There is testimony of systematic patterns of torture in detention centres, including of children. This report is a stark reminder of the horrific situation in Syria. I call upon all sides to put an end to the violence and pursue a process of genuine political transition which reflects the will of the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work undertaken by the UN Commission of inquiry, in difficult circumstances, is vital to ensure that human rights violations and abuses committed by all parties are documented. We will continue to do all we can to support their work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Countries/SY/ColSyriaDecember2012.pdf" title="UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Countries/MENARegion/Pages/SYIndex.aspx" title="UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe Ministerial Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60060</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:14:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-national-strategy-on-the-protection-of-civilians-in-armed-conflict"/>
    <title>UK National Strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This 2012 Annual report summarises the UK's work on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2010 the United Kingdom launched a national strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict (PoC). The strategy, a collaboration between the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Department for International Development and the Ministry of Defence, sets out what the Government is doing to keep the Protection of Civilians at the forefront of our work on political, security and humanitarian fronts. The strategy covers the period 2010-2013, and provides for annual progress reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 2012 report summarises the UK’s work in four policy areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political engagement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protection by peace support operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanitarian action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State capacity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57035</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:56:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-foreign-offices-human-rights-work-in-2011"/>
    <title>The Foreign Office's Human Rights work in 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Office response to the Foreign Affairs Committee's recommendations regarding the Foreign Office's Human Rights work.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government welcomes the attentive scrutiny of its human rights work during 2011 carried out by the Foreign Affairs Committee. The Government agrees with the FAC’s assessment that the UK has a strong record in upholding human rights across the world. We welcome the FAC’s comment that our Annual Report on Human Rights and Democracy for 2011 provides ample evidence of our work in promoting higher standards of human rights abroad, sometimes in difficult circumstances. We were pleased that the FAC recognise the considerable effort that went into the production of the FCO’s Annual Human Rights Report for 2011. We have taken steps to strengthen our human rights reporting over the last two years in response to direction from Ministers and feedback from the FAC and others. We will continue to ensure that our reporting is targeted to meet the needs of Parliament and our national and international readership.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Command Paper sets out the Government’s response to the Foreign Affairs Committee’s report of 17 October 2012 into the Foreign and Commonwealth Office’s Human Rights Work in 2011. The Committee’s recommendations are set out in bold. Unless otherwise indicated, references are to paragraphs in the Foreign Affairs Committee Report (HC116).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
