<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/equality-rights-and-citizenship.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Equality, rights and citizenship"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60215</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens"/>
    <title>Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has reaffirmed UK support for imprisoned Human Rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the United Nations vote on the human right situation in Iran, the Foreign Secretary has released a video. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic freedoms of ordinary Iranians are being denied. Many citizens live in constant fear of arbitrary arrest, false imprisonment and, in some cases, death. There is undeniable evidence of abuse: the recent death in custody of blogger Sattar Beheshti is one tragic example. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also spoke about Nasrin Sotoudeh, who recently ended a 49-day hunger strike in protest against the harassment of her family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have sacrificed your own freedom, family life and health in order to help others. I want you to know that we are following your case closely. And that I echo the many calls upon Iran for your immediate release. Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regime hopes to silence those who call for basic human rights in Iran. I want to make clear that the promotion and protection of human rights is at the heart of UK foreign policy. And we are committed to supporting and protecting those who defend human rights and work tirelessly to advance personal freedoms, often at great personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OHQkieCYSZg"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/ukiniran/punishing-a-human-rights-defender-nasrin-sotoudehs" title="Nasrin Sotoudehs story"&gt;Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family" title="UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60204</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria"/>
    <title>UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria  </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt: The UK will continue to support work of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria to ensure accountability. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the publication of a new UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today the UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria published its latest report on the human rights situation in Syria. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. The Commission concludes that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commission has received credible accounts of Government soldiers executing captives. Incidents of direct targeting of civilians by aerial bombardment, including “barrel bombs,” rocket attacks and machine gun fire have risen significantly over recent months. There is testimony of systematic patterns of torture in detention centres, including of children. This report is a stark reminder of the horrific situation in Syria. I call upon all sides to put an end to the violence and pursue a process of genuine political transition which reflects the will of the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work undertaken by the UN Commission of inquiry, in difficult circumstances, is vital to ensure that human rights violations and abuses committed by all parties are documented. We will continue to do all we can to support their work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Countries/SY/ColSyriaDecember2012.pdf" title="UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Countries/MENARegion/Pages/SYIndex.aspx" title="UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60124</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:34:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/organisation-for-security-and-cooperation-in-europe"/>
    <title>Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe Ministerial Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Rt Hon William Hague): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 6 December I travelled to Dublin to attend the 19th Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) Ministerial Council - the Organisation’s key decision making body, which marked the culmination of Ireland’s 2012 OSCE Chairmanship-in-Office (CiO). My right honourable friend, the Minister for Europe also attended.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key outcome was agreement on a new initiative designed to inject a fresh dynamic into the OSCE as we approach the 40th anniversary of the Helsinki Final Act in 2015. The ‘Helsinki +40’ process tasks upcoming CiOs (Ukraine 2013, Switzerland 2014, Serbia 2015) to strengthen cooperation, enhance implementation of existing commitments and develop new approaches to realising a comprehensive ‘security community’ well equipped to respond to the evolving threats to our collective security and prosperity. I spoke in support of the initiative urging all OSCE participating States to use this opportunity to develop a clear, reinvigorated vision of how the OSCE can best support security and stability across the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my plenary intervention I called on all States to implement sincerely and consistently their OSCE commitments, not least on human rights. I urged the OSCE to concentrate its efforts where it had most relevance and impact, in particular on election observation, media freedom, conflict resolution, violence against women, cyber-security, and conventional arms control and confidence and security-building measures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Irish CiO’s overriding objective was to agree a balanced package of decisions across the OSCE’s 3 dimensions: politico-military, economic and environmental and human. This was a pragmatic aim which this Government fully supported. Significant agreements were reached on a statement on the Transnistrian conflict, the first of its kind since 2002; development of a framework on counter-terrorism, as part of the OSCE’s work to address transnational threats; and a declaration on good governance, anti-corruption and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the human dimension the UK supported adoption of decisions on media freedom, and racism and xenophobia; both key strands of the OSCE’s human rights work. It was disappointing that, in a repeat of the 2011 Vilnius Ministerial Council, no agreements were possible in this dimension; a clear indication of the divisions that persist within the OSCE on approaches to human rights issues. We are deeply concerned that a number of participating states appear to be falling short of their human rights commitments in the OSCE. The UK will work with the incoming Ukraine CiO to ensure that human rights, democracy and fundamental freedoms are at the forefront of the OSCE’s agenda through 2013.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60060</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:14:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-national-strategy-on-the-protection-of-civilians-in-armed-conflict"/>
    <title>UK National Strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict</title>
    <summary>This 2012 Annual report summarises the UK's work on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2010 the United Kingdom launched a national strategy on the Protection of Civilians in Armed Conflict (PoC). The strategy, a collaboration between the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Department for International Development and the Ministry of Defence, sets out what the Government is doing to keep the Protection of Civilians at the forefront of our work on political, security and humanitarian fronts. The strategy covers the period 2010-2013, and provides for annual progress reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 2012 report summarises the UK’s work in four policy areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political engagement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protection by peace support operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanitarian action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State capacity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57035</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:56:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-foreign-offices-human-rights-work-in-2011"/>
    <title>The Foreign Office's Human Rights work in 2011</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Office response to the Foreign Affairs Committee's recommendations regarding the Foreign Office's Human Rights work.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government welcomes the attentive scrutiny of its human rights work during 2011 carried out by the Foreign Affairs Committee. The Government agrees with the FAC’s assessment that the UK has a strong record in upholding human rights across the world. We welcome the FAC’s comment that our Annual Report on Human Rights and Democracy for 2011 provides ample evidence of our work in promoting higher standards of human rights abroad, sometimes in difficult circumstances. We were pleased that the FAC recognise the considerable effort that went into the production of the FCO’s Annual Human Rights Report for 2011. We have taken steps to strengthen our human rights reporting over the last two years in response to direction from Ministers and feedback from the FAC and others. We will continue to ensure that our reporting is targeted to meet the needs of Parliament and our national and international readership.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Command Paper sets out the Government’s response to the Foreign Affairs Committee’s report of 17 October 2012 into the Foreign and Commonwealth Office’s Human Rights Work in 2011. The Committee’s recommendations are set out in bold. Unless otherwise indicated, references are to paragraphs in the Foreign Affairs Committee Report (HC116).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56983</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust </title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague marks the 70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Seventy years ago the British Government, shocked by mounting evidence from Poland of Nazi extermination of the Jews, joined eleven other war-time allies in a sharp united condemnation of what was happening on the continent of Europe. Sir Anthony Eden’s Statement to Parliament on 17 December 1942 was followed by much public and Parliamentary discussion in the UK and among the United Nations about what could be done to stop the genocide and had a strong impact on subsequent allied planning for the post-war trials of Nazi leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The disastrous events of the Holocaust continue to reverberate through Western society, as the Stockholm Declaration in 2000 so eloquently reaffirmed. The British Government supports the work of the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research (&lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and looks forward to assuming the chairmanship of the &lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2014/15.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.holocausttaskforce.org/about-the-itf.html" title="Holocaust Task Force"&gt;Information on the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56976</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet"/>
    <title>UK has serious concerns about human rights in Tibet</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has said that the UK has serious concerns about the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a European Union statement on self-immolations in Tibet, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We strongly support the recent statement from Baroness Ashton about the situation in Tibet. We continue to have serious concerns about the human rights situation there, including the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We urge the Chinese authorities to exercise restraint. At the same time, I join Baroness Ashton in calling on Tibetans not to resort to extreme forms of protest such as self-immolation, and urge their community and religious leaders to use their influence to stop this tragic loss of life. We strongly support the resumption of meaningful dialogue to resolve the underlying grievances of Tibetan communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I also urge the Chinese government to ensure unrestricted access to the Tibetan Autonomous Region and other Tibetan areas of China for diplomats, international media and other concerned parties. We believe a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/en/cfsp/134378.pdf" title="EU statement on Tibetan self-immolations"&gt;European Union statement on Tibetan self-immolations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56877</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-palestinian-refugee-camp-bombing-in-damascus"/>
    <title>UK condemns Palestinian refugee camp bombing in Damascus</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the attack by the Syrian regime which killed at least 20 people yesterday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of Syrian government air strikes on the Yarmouk refugee camp in Damascus, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I condemn the Syrian regime’s aerial bombardment of the Yarmouk Palestinian refugee camp in Damascus, which killed at least 20 people yesterday. They are among four hundred Syrians killed across the country this weekend in yet another tragic reminder that the Assad regime continues to attack its own people with brutality and without remorse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Syrian government actions have already driven hundreds of thousands of Syrian civilians from their homes into neighboring countries. The senseless targeting of Palestinian refugees, who had hitherto looked to Syria for shelter and protection, will only exacerbate the risk of contagion across the region. Our objective remains an end to the violence and a transition to a more democratic and stable Syria.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP led a trade mission to Burma earlier this week.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
