<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/europe</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/europe"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/europe.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Europe"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/50204</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-stability-throughout-the-western-balkans--2"/>
    <title>Promoting stability throughout the Western Balkans</title>
    <summary>Securing peace and creating the conditions for EU membership in the Western Balkans.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1990s saw the violent break-up of the former Yugoslavia and the beginning of the transition from communism in the region. The region has since started the long route to greater stability and prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stability in the Western Balkans matters; the region is on Europe’s doorstep and instability or conflict would affect the UK, including through migration and organised crime. The UK is therefore working to reduce the risk of conflict in the region, promote stability and reconciliation, and support reforms, as the region moves towards future EU and NATO membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a strong supporter of future EU and NATO membership for all countries of the Western Balkans (along with Iceland and Turkey). To reach this future in the EU and NATO, countries need to meet conditions for membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU accession process, leading to membership, requires serious reform efforts from the region, including on rule of law, organised crime and corruption, public administration, and economic reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is supporting these reforms with £3 million of Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office (FCO) programme funds for Albania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Kosovo, Macedonia, Montenegro, Serbia (and Turkey), for example funding judicial reform or media freedom projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also providing expertise supporting accession-related reforms from across the civil service as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twinning.org/en/page/the-european-union.html"&gt;EU twinning programme&lt;/a&gt;, means to help people understand the aims of the EU, to develop a stronger sense of European identity, and to bring the EU closer to its citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms reduce security threats to the UK and promote a strong environment for British business interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reconciliation is crucial for the region, following the conflict and atrocities of the past. Cooperation with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.icty.org/"&gt;International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia&lt;/a&gt;, the UN court of law dealing with war crimes that took place during the conflicts in the Balkans in the 1990s, remains important, as does the leadership in the region openly and honestly acknowledging the events of the past, such as the genocide in Srebrenica. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also supporting conflict prevention efforts in the region, with around £10 million provided jointly from the FCO, Ministry of Defence and Department for International Development. The work is focused on Bosnia and Herzegovina and on Kosovo and includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UK troops joining, in December 2012, the regional reserve for the peacekeeping mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support for the Srebrenica prosecutions team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK judges hearing war crime cases in Kosovo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;projects to support ethnic minorities returning to rebuilt homes following the Kosovo war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK continues to support safeguards against instability in Bosnia and Herzegovina, particularly the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohr.int/"&gt;Office of the High Representative&lt;/a&gt;, the international institution responsible for overseeing implementation of civilian aspects of the Peace Agreement ending the war in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.euforbih.org/"&gt;EUFOR Althea peacekeeping operation&lt;/a&gt;, the EU’s military operation that launched on 2 December 2004 and has contributed to the maintenance of the safe and secure environment in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="albania"&gt;Albania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albania is already a member of NATO and has made an application for EU membership. The UK encourages further progress on reforms, particularly rule of law and democracy, for Albania to move forward on towards their EU future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bosnia-and-herzegovina"&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK remains wholly and actively committed to Bosnia and Herzegovina as a sovereign, stable country with functioning state-level institutions. Significant political progress is needed if progress towards NATO and EU membership is to be made, but such progress will bring benefits to citizens throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="croatia"&gt;Croatia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Croatia will accede to the EU in July 2013. The European Commission’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/hr_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;Comprehensive Monitoring Report on Croatia’s state ofpreparedness for EU membership&lt;/a&gt;, published in October 2012, noted the progress made by Croatia in its preparations for accession. The commission also identified a number of areas where further improvements are necessary in order to fully meet all membership requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN06327"&gt;Croatia Accession Bill&lt;/a&gt; would allow the UK to ratify Croatia’s accession treaty. All existing EU member states must ratify the accession treaty before Croatia can join the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="kosovo"&gt;Kosovo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK recognised Kosovo’s declaration of independence in February 2008 and is a longstanding supporter of Kosovo’s independence, sovereignty and territorial integrity. The UK is a firm supporter of a stable, prosperous and multi-ethnic Kosovo making progress towards eventual EU and NATO membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="macedonia"&gt;Macedonia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports Macedonia’s progress towards EU and NATO membership. Since March 2002, the European Commission has reported regularly to the EU Council and Parliament on progress made by the countries of the Western Balkans region. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/mk_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;2012 report&lt;/a&gt; describes the progress made by the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia in preparing for EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="montenegro"&gt;Montenegro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/fule/headlines/news/2012/06/20120629_en.htm"&gt;Montenegro opened accession negotiations&lt;/a&gt; with the EU in June 2012. The UK supports an early focus on rule of law issues in the negotiations, notably strengthening the judiciary and tackling organised crime and corruption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="serbia"&gt;Serbia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a long-standing supporter of Serbia’s EU future and welcomed Serbia becoming an official EU candidate in March 2012. We urge Serbia to make further progress normalising its relations with Kosovo in order to meet the criteria for opening accession negotiations with the EU. Domestic reforms and regional cooperation remain important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55440</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:48:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement"/>
    <title>Minister for Europe renews UK commitment to EU enlargement </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has set out the UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister gave a press briefing for European journalists today following his participation in the General Affairs Council meeting in Brussels on 11 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK remains a strong supporter of EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey. I’ve just returned from the General Affairs Council in Brussels where I was pleased to have a long discussion on EU enlargement. Its conclusions make clear the EU’s continued support for enlargement. This is important, and a message that I hope will be heard clearly in the accession and pre-accession countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is good for the EU and one of the EU’s greatest achievements. The European Union, alongside NATO, has been an instrument of peace and reconciliation that has helped spread democracy and the rule of law across our continent, and helped make armed conflict between EU members unthinkable. At the same time an enlarged Single Market, another of the key success stories of the EU, has opened up prosperity and opportunity to hundreds of millions of people. An outward-looking approach and a continuing commitment to enlargement should be seen by all EU Member States as signs of strength and vigour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is also good for wider security and prosperity across the continent. The accession of new Member States helps promote security, stability and prosperity across Europe, based on a firm foundation of democracy, human and civil rights, and respect for the law. The focus on good neighbourly relations is particularly important for a region such as the Western Balkans which saw conflict only two decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a respect for this firm foundation and its benefits which drives the UK’s scrutiny of progress and focus on conditionality. So the UK is clear that there will be no pause after Croatia’s accession. But equally there will be no movement without progress on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Foreign Secretary visited Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia and Kosovo in October. He set out clearly the UK’s support for each country’s EU future. But he stressed to the political leaders that they needed to take the necessary steps to deliver. I hope political leaders in all of the aspiring countries will do so and that we will see further progress being made towards the EU early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the UK remains committed to Turkey’s EU membership. We strongly believe that this would contribute to Europe’s prosperity and security, and the EU remains the strongest lever for reform in Turkey. We are focused on making real progress on the accession process in 2013 and we fully support the Irish Presidency in their desire to open a new acquis Chapter during their Presidency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=842001782" title="Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council in a Written Ministerial Statement.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12153</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the single market more effective</title>
    <summary>Plans to make the single market more competitive, easier to do business in and create new jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the EU expanded to include more states, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate acheived by other EU states. However, the European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at a rate as low as just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the EU and other dynamic markets, such as South Korea, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the EU as a whole. To achieve higher growth and increased employment, all member states and the EU institutions will need to take action. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which encourages all member states to reinforce financial stability, create jobs and improve competitiveness, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong single market creates jobs and benefits all member states. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234 billion, went to the EU. The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other EU prime ministers, urged the EU to improve the single market, concentrating on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update EU single market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting EU consumers in cyberspace. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;.  Member States must implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013. E-invoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-invoicing within the EU could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;EU-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; which came into force on 1 July 2011 is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for EU exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act (2011)&lt;/a&gt; sets out twelve ways to boost growth and improve confidence in European business. In October 2012 the European Commission proposed a second set of actions, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smact/docs/single-market-act2_en.pdf"&gt;Single Market Act II&lt;/a&gt;, to further develop the single market’s economic opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act II (2012)&lt;/a&gt; describes the EU’s goals of improving the digital economy, including e-commerce and electronic invoicing, and creating more efficient transport and energy networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/u/11-760-uk-response-single-market-act"&gt;response to The Single Market Act&lt;/a&gt; in February 2011 looks at how the UK will work with other member states on reforms that will create the most jobs and economic growth at the lowest cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a study, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/e/11-517-economic-consequences-of-completing-single-market"&gt;The economic consequences for the UK and the EU of completing the single market&lt;/a&gt;, in February 2011. This paper considers the benefits of the single market and the negative effects of the UK opting out of future European trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; published a study in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/feeds/~/media/568CC723188C40DFBB02E868353B40B9.ashx"&gt;The UK and the single market: trade and investment analytical papers topic 4 of 18&lt;/a&gt;, that examines the importance of the EU for British exporters and investors. The analysis found that businesses have benefited from the opportunities provided by the single market. Such benefits include: better connected and cheaper networks; mutual recognition of standards; and easier access to cheap and competitive inputs for British manufacturers. In addition greater competition within the single market has fostered innovation. For consumers, the single market has created more choice and lowered prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35654</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-written-ministerial-statement-on-the-balance-of-competences-of-the-european-union"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary Written Ministerial Statement on the Balance of Competences of the European Union</title>
    <summary>Full text of the Foreign Secretary's statement updating Parliament on the Balance of Competences of the European Union.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform the House that, further to my oral statement at the launch of the Balance of Competences Review (Official Report 12 July 2012, Column 468), the Foreign and Commonwealth Office is today publishing the timetable for the review including departmental responsibility for the reports into each individual area of competence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will complete its work during 2014 and will look at the scope of the EU’s competences (the power to act in particular areas conferred on it by the EU Treaties) as they affect the UK, how they are used, and what that means for Britain and our national interests.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will be divided into four semesters, each containing six to ten reports.  This will allow reports on related topics to be grouped together.   The reports from each semester will be published at the end of that semester.  If necessary, changes to this timetable will be made in order to take account of any events which could impact upon the timing of a report.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Semesters are:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semester One:  Autumn 2012 - Summer 2013&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Semester Two:  Spring 2013 - Winter 2013&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Semester Three:  Autumn 2013 - Summer 2014&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Semester Four:  Spring 2014 - Autumn 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first semester reviews will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an overview on the Single Market;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taxation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;animal health and welfare and food safety;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;health;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;development; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;foreign policy.     &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Single Market encompasses such a broad area of competence that it is being split, with further reports on the four freedoms - goods, persons, services and capital - in semesters two and three.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Departments will take a rigorous approach to the collection and analysis of evidence.  The government department leading each review will, at the appropriate time, publish a Call for Evidence which will set out the scope of their report and include a series of broad questions on which they would like contributors to focus.The Calls for Evidence for first semester reports will be published shortly and will be available through the FCO website and through the website of the department leading each review.The reports into the first six competences will be published in the summer of 2013, along with the evidence received (subject to the provisions of the Data Protection Act).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government departments will consult widely, including Parliament and its committees, business, the Devolved Administrations, and civil society in order to obtain evidence to contribute to their analysis of the issues.  Our EU partners and the EU institutions will also be invited to contribute evidence to the review.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result will be a comprehensive, thorough and detailed analysis of where competence lies and what it means for the United Kingdom.  It will aid our understanding of the nature of our EU membership; and it will provide a constructive and serious contribution to the wider European debate about modernizing, reforming and improving the EU.The review will not produce specific policy recommendations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am placing the timetable in the Library of the House.It will also be published on the  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/european-union/balance-of-competences-review/"&gt;Balance of competences review&lt;/a&gt; pages on Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office website.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Report Title&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Departmental lead&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semester 1 (Autumn ‘12 - Summer ‘13)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal Market: Synopsis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Treasury&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animal Health and Welfare and Food safety&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department of Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for International Development&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Policy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semester 2 (Spring ‘13 - Autumn ‘13)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal Market: Freedom of movement of Goods&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal Market: Free movement of persons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asylum and Immigration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research and Development&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tourism, Culture and Sport&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civil Justice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Justice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semester 3 (Autumn ‘13 - Spring ‘14)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal Market: Services&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal Market: Capital&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Treasury&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EU Budget&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Treasury&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cohesion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social and Employment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agriculture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fisheries&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;23&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Business, Innovation and Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;24&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department of Energy and Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental Rights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Justice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semester 4 (Spring ‘14 - Autumn ‘14)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic and Monetary Union&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Treasury&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;27&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health &amp;amp; safety and consumer protection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and Safety Executive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police and Criminal Justice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;29&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department for Education&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlargement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;31&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administrative cooperation, citizenship, information rights and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabinet Office, Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Ministry of Justice, UK Statistics Authority&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;32&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsidiarity, Proportionality and Article 352&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This order and sequencing may be subject to change as the review progresses&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46831</id>
    <published>2012-04-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-turkey-relations"/>
    <title>UK-Turkey relations</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Spokesperson responds to publication of FAC report on UK-Turkey relations and Turkey’s regional role.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Spokesperson siad;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The House of Commons Foreign Affairs Select Committee (FAC) has published its report on UK-Turkey relations and Turkey’s regional role today. The report reflects the views of the Committee in line with its remit to examine the Government’s foreign policy. The Government will present its official response in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Foreign and Commonwealth Office welcomes the recognition given in the report of Turkey’s growing political and economic role on the world stage, and its analysis of ways to strengthen the UK-Turkey relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We also welcome the Committee’s endorsement of the Government’s steadfast support for Turkey’s EU accession, as an important element of the bilateral relationship. We believe that Turkish accession would be to the wider benefit of the UK and EU, contributing to our prosperity, security and stability. Turkey has made clear its firm strategic commitment to accession to the EU, and successive European Councils have made clear that Turkey is a candidate for full membership of the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK is working closely with the Turkish Government, both bilaterally and with the EU to prepare Turkey for accession to the EU. In 2011/12, we have offered technical assistance on a range of issues, including freedom of expression, women’s rights, and judicial and public administration reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the Committee’s recognition of the strength of UK-Turkey ties. We work closely with Turkey on foreign policy issues critical to UK interests including Syria, the Iran nuclear issue, Somalia, Afghanistan and the Western Balkans. The Prime Minister has committed to doubling bilateral trade with Turkey over the next five years. Total trade reached £9.1 billion in 2011 - an increase of 40% since 2009. The government is committed to building on this success by raising awareness of market opportunities in Turkey amongst UK exporters, and tackling outstanding market access issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Committee has highlighted a number of concerns on human rights, particularly freedom of expression. We share the concerns expressed by the European Commission about Turkey’s human rights record, and we encourage the Turkish Government to take further steps to encourage greater freedom of expression particularly in the media. We welcome recent steps taken by the Turkish Government to reform its judicial system and look forward to further progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Committee also raised the Cyprus settlement negotiations, where we are committed to supporting the UN’s efforts to achieve a settlement based on a bizonal, bicommunal federation with political equality. “  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46784</id>
    <published>2012-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-ministers-agree-further-sanctions-on-iran"/>
    <title>EU Ministers agree further sanctions on Iran</title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague said that the decision to impose further sanctions on Iran demonstrates the EU's growing concern about the country's nuclear programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s action demonstrates the EU’s growing concern about Iran’s nuclear programme, and our determination to increase peaceful, legitimate pressure on Iran to return to negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is action made necessary by Iran’s defiance of six UN Security Council Resolutions and its refusal to enter negotiations over its nuclear programme. Iran’s recent decision to commence 20% enrichment at its underground site at Qom shows that it continues to choose a path of provocation. This is an enrichment programme that has no plausible civilian use, in a site that the Iranian authorities hoped to keep secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call again on Iran to answer the serious questions raised by the International Atomic Energy Agency, to adhere to UN Security Council Resolutions and to suspend its enrichment programme in accordance with them. Iran has it in its power to end sanctions by changing course and addressing the concerns of the international community. We are ready to talk at any point if Iran puts aside its preconditions. Today’s sanctions show how serious EU member states are about preventing nuclear proliferation and pressing Iran to return to the negotiating table. We will urge other nations across the world to implement similar measures and to increase the impact of the measures the EU has adopted”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/EN/foraff/127446.pdf"&gt;Read the full Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46805</id>
    <published>2012-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/statement-on-european-court-judgement-on-taxation-in-gibraltar"/>
    <title>Statement on European Court Judgement on taxation in Gibraltar</title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague has made a written statement to Parliament on the European Court Judgement on taxation in Gibraltar.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“On 15 November 2011 the Court of Justice of the European Union (ECJ) published its judgment in appeal cases brought by the European Commission and Spain against the United Kingdom and the Government of Gibraltar on the issue of whether corporation tax changes proposed by the Government of Gibraltar in 2002 breached EU rules on State aid. In this judgment the ECJ has set aside the earlier judgment of the General Court of the European Union (General Court) dated 18 December 2008 and has found that the proposed tax regime, which was abandoned some time ago and was never implemented in Gibraltar, constituted State aid on grounds of material selectivity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to this case is that in August 2002 the UK notified the Commission, pursuant to Article 88(3) of the then EC Treaty (now Article 108(3) TfEU), that Gibraltar proposed to make changes to its tax system that would involve the introduction of a Payroll Tax and a Business Property Occupation Tax (BPOT). The Commission’s Decision of March 2004 found that the Payroll Tax and BPOT were materially selective because they would inherently favour offshore companies that had no physical presence in Gibraltar and which, as a consequence, would not incur corporation tax. The Commission also found that the proposed changes to Gibraltar’s tax system were regionally selective on the grounds that they provided for a system under which companies in Gibraltar would be taxed, in general, at a lower rate than those in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and the Government of Gibraltar both contested the Commission’s Decision in respect of both material and regional selectivity. On 18 December 2008 the Court of First Instance (now the General Court) annulled the Commission’s Decision. The General Court found that Gibraltar’s tax proposals did not breach EU rules on State aid on grounds of material selectivity. Moreover the General Court ruled that the frame of reference for assessing whether Gibraltar’s proposals were regionally selective corresponded exclusively to Gibraltar’s territorial limits. The General Court therefore upheld, under EU law, Gibraltar’s freedom to set tax rates that are different from those in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission and Spain both brought appeal actions asking the ECJ to set aside the General Court’s judgment. The Commission’s single ground of appeal was on the question of material selectivity. Spain appealed on both regional and material selectivity. The ECJ’s judgment of 15 November 2011 is the final ruling in these proceedings. The ECJ found that Gibraltar’s tax proposals were materially selective in that they granted selective advantages to offshore companies. It held that in view of its finding on material selectivity it was not relevant to examine whether Gibraltar’s proposals were regionally selective.          &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECJ’s decision not to examine the issue of regional selectivity means that there has been no change in the principles established by the Court in the Azores case (ECJ case C-88/03 Portugal v Commission). According to those principles autonomous regional bodies within an EU Member State may set lower levels of tax than in the rest of the Member State without giving rise to State aid provided that certain criteria for determining the autonomous status of the regional body are met. In accordance with its constitutional arrangements, Gibraltar is a fiscally autonomous entity with responsibility for the management of its economy, including taxation, vested in the Government of Gibraltar. The UK is committed to upholding the Gibraltar Constitution. The ECJ’s judgment of 15 November 2011 does not change Gibraltar’s constitutional relationship with the UK or Gibraltar’s freedom to set a tax regime that differs from the UK’s.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is for the Government of Gibraltar, as the authority responsible for the tax system in Gibraltar, to consider the implications for Gibraltar of the ECJ’s ruling on material selectivity.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 15 November 2011 the then Government of Gibraltar issued a statement which stated that the judgment would have no adverse impact on Gibraltar since the proposed tax scheme that was examined by the ECJ had never been implemented and the proposal had since been abandoned in favour of an income tax of 10% for all companies. The new Government of Gibraltar takes the same view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government will keep the House informed of any further significant developments.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46809</id>
    <published>2011-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/written-ministerial-statement-on-the-general-affairs-council-and-foreign-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Written Ministerial Statement on the General Affairs Council and Foreign Affairs Council</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council were held on 10-11 October in Luxembourg.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a written statement the Minister for Europe David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council were held on 10-11 October in Luxembourg.  My Rt. Hon. Friend the Foreign Secretary and I represented the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council-fac"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council (FAC)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FAC was chaired by Baroness Ashton.  A provisional report of the meeting, and all Conclusions adopted, can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/foraff/125028.pdf"&gt;http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/foraff/125028.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bosnia-and-herzegovina-bih"&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina (BiH)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although BiH was not a formal agenda item, Ministers agreed Conclusions which reaffirmed the EU’s support for the continuation of the EU’s military force’s (EUFOR Althea) executive mandate.  The Conclusions also included a reference to ‘looking forward to discussions’ on the future of the Office of the High Representative (OHR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="belarus"&gt;belarus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed to renew the EU’s restrictive measures against belarus, and added sixteen new names to the travel ban and assets freeze list.  There was broad agreement that the EU should not consider renewing a dialogue with the belarusian authorities until all political prisoners have been released and rehabilitated.  Ministers also endorsed ongoing work by Commissioner Stefan Fule on engaging civil society in belarus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ukraine"&gt;Ukraine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers expressed concern about the trial and upcoming verdict on Yulia Tymoshenko.  There was a discussion about the impact the verdict might have on finalising the EU’s Association Agreement with Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after the FAC, Yuliya Tymoshenko was sentenced to seven years in prison.  Speaking after the verdict the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The conviction of the Ukrainian opposition politician, Yuliya Tymoshenko, by a court in Kyiv is deeply concerning. Independent legal experts including the Danish Helsinki Committee have concluded that Ms Tymoshenko’s trial was subject to numerous and serious violations of fundamental legal principles, in direct contradiction of common European values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ukraine says it wants to join the EU one day. The UK supports that objective. But that cannot happen until Ukraine can show that it adheres to the highest democratic standards, including respect for human rights, the rule of law and an independent, transparent and fair judicial process.  The conviction of Ms Tymoshenko and the ongoing cases against other former members of the government call into question Ukraine’s commitment to these values. This could pose a major obstacle to the signature and ratification of the Association Agreement and Deep and Comprehensive Free Trade Agreement with the EU.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-china-summit"&gt;EU-China Summit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers reviewed preparations for the fourteenth EU-China Summit, which takes place in China on 25 October.  The Foreign Secretary stressed the need for the EU to focus on increased market access for EU businesses.  He also urged the EU to continue to raise human rights issues at the highest level, and underlined the importance of global cooperation on cyber security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Ashton set out the results of the Tunisian Task Force meeting of 28-29 September.  She had co-chaired the meeting with the Prime Minister of Tunisia, which had also been attended by Member States, European institutions, the European Investment Bank, the EBRD, the World Bank, the Africa Bank and representatives from the private sector.  Around €4 billion was pledged to Tunisia over the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Egypt, concern was expressed by many Ministers about the recent outbreaks of violence.  There was broad agreement on the importance of protecting freedom of religion and belief.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed Conclusions on Libya which:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reaffirmed the EU’s support for the National Transition Council.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Welcomed the continuation of the operation to enforce UNSCR 1973 and ensure the protection of the Libyan population.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Welcomed the adoption of UNSCR 2009 and the return of Libya to the UN as represented by the National Transitional Council.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stressed the need for all in Libya to respect all international obligations and the rule of law.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressed concern about the dissemination of conventional weapons in Libya.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set out the EU’s willingness to work under UN coordination to consider Libyan needs in the fields of democratisation, rule of law, institution-building, security sector reform and police training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed Conclusions on Syria which condemned the ongoing brutal repression by the Syrian regime. Ministers expressed disappointment with the failure of the UN Security Council to adopt a resolution against Syria. They reiterated their determination to continue with targeted sanctions against the Syrian regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Yemen, Ministers agreed Conclusions which stressed concern about the situation in the country.  They called for President Saleh to sign and implement the Gulf Cooperation Council initiative.  And they welcomed the report of the High Commissioner for Human Rights, and urged the authorities in Yemen to act on its recommendations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the European Neighbourhood Policy, the Foreign Secretary and others stressed the need to hold out the possibility of meaningful market access to the neighbourhood, in exchange for real political and democratic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed Conclusions which reiterated their support for Baroness Ashton’s efforts on behalf of the EU to re-launch the Peace Process.  There was an appeal for both parties to resume negotiations under the terms set out in the Quartet Statement of 23 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers expressed their disappointment with the recent settlement expansion in the East Jerusalem settlement of Gilo.  Baroness Ashton briefed Ministers on the Quartet Envoys’ meeting of 9 October in Brussels and plans to invite the parties to meet in the coming days. The Foreign Secretary emphasised the need for continued EU unity in response to any resolutions proposed at the United Nations in New York. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion on Iran focused on two areas:  the EU’s growing concern over human rights, and Iran’s nuclear programme.  On human rights, Ministers agreed to add twenty-nine names to its sanctions list, in addition to the thirty-two officials previously agreed in April.  On the nuclear issue, Baroness Ashton briefed Ministers on E3+3 talks in New York in the margin of the UN General Assembly and her meeting with the Iranian Foreign Minister.  She also outlined plans for taking forward talks with Iran.  The Foreign Secretary made the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the EU’s agreement today to impose restrictive measures on a further twenty-nine Iranians responsible for grave human rights abuses. Those targeted include Government Ministers, members of the security forces, prison staff and judiciary responsible for serious human rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In recent months the human rights situation in Iran has continued to deteriorate. As we mark World Day against the Death Penalty we should recall that Iran has now executed over 500 people this year, including a 17 year old boy. The government has violently suppressed protests over the mismanagement of a lake in north-west Iran, and families of a number of journalists have been arrested and harassed. We will continue to identify and list those who seriously violate the human rights of the Iranian people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s decision sends a clear message to every individual on this list, and others in the Iranian regime, that we will not stand by. They will be held to account for their actions and should not involve themselves in the appalling abuses we continue to witness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-external-representation"&gt;EU External Representation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers had a brief informal exchange on EU external representation in international organisations.  The Foreign Secretary said we supported effective external action by the EU, in accordance with the Treaties.  But we needed to ensure that this did not affect the balance of competences between the EU and Member States; and that Member States remained free to act where they had the right to do so.  He agreed that the EAS should propose effective arrangements in line with these principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council-gac"&gt;General Affairs Council (GAC)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC was chaired by the Polish EU Presidency (Mikolaj Dowgielewicz, State Secretary for European Affairs).  A draft record of the meeting can be found at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/genaff/125036.pdf"&gt;http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/genaff/125036.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cohesion-policy"&gt;Cohesion Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers heard a presentation by Commissioner Hahn (Regional Policy) of proposals for rules on implementing the EU’s policy on economic and social cohesion in 2012-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="growth-enhancing-measures"&gt;Growth-Enhancing Measures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency presented its report “Towards a European consensus on growth” (see link below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://pl2011.eu/sites/default/files/users/shared/spotkania_i_wydarzenia/presidency_report_on_growth.pdf"&gt;http://pl2011.eu/sites/default/files/users/shared/spotkania_i_wydarzenia/presidency_report_on_growth.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report identifies potential growth-enhancing measures which might help the EU overcome the current economic crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="g20-summit-in-cannes"&gt;G20 Summit in Cannes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers discussed with Commissioner Sefcovic (Inter-Institutional Relations and Administration) preparations for the G-20 Summit in Cannes on 3-4 November.  The Commissioner  set out proposed EU priorities: the Eurozone and the global economic recovery; the resilience of the international monetary system; tackling commodity prices; providing a way forward for Doha and the WTO; development; food security; a strong message on Climate Change and Durban; and the proposed Financial Transaction Tax (FTT).  I stressed that the UK was firmly against promoting a FTT at the G20 Summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-of-the-october-european-council"&gt;Preparation of the October European Council&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the GAC, the President of the Council, Van Rompuy, joined Ministers by video link to discuss preparations for the Council.  He explained that the Council had been pushed back to Sunday 23 October to allow Heads of State and Government to consider issues relating to Greece, the European banks and the Eurozone governance more comprehensively as a package.  I argued that any future institutional changes to governance in the Eurozone had to protect fully the interests of all 27 Member States, and there had to be clear language to that effect in the European Council Conclusions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also stressed the need for the Council Conclusions to address some significant foreign policy developments, particularly Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will deposit copies of this note in the libraries of both Houses. And I will also continue to update Parliament on future Foreign and General Affairs Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/26564</id>
    <published>2011-06-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:17:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/what-the-eu-needs-to-do-to-remain-competitive"/>
    <title>What the EU needs to do to remain competitive</title>
    <summary>Minister for Europe David Lidington has welcomed the publication of a report by British business leaders on priorities for ensuring a strong and competitive EU economy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Europe David Lidington today attended the launch of Business for New Europe’s new publication, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bnegroup.org/images/uploads/publications/files/BNE_Competitiveness_Publication_singles.pdf"&gt;Competitiveness: What the EU needs to do&lt;/a&gt; at Aviva plc. The publication includes essays from business leaders and identifies priorities for securing economic growth in the EU: completing the single market, supporting innovation, reducing the burdens of regulation and opening Europe for trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributors to the report include Sir Roger Carr, Chairman of Centrica, Roland Rudd, Chairman of BNE, Andrew Moss, CEO of Aviva, Vittorio Colao, CEO of Vodafone, Dr Chris Gibson-Smith, Chairman of the London Stock Exchange, and other leading business figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his foreword to the report, Minister for Europe David Lidington calls for governments and businesses across Europe to work together to drive greater innovation and enterprise across the EU:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have the ideas, industry and drive to return Europe to strong economic growth. Combining these assets with an open and liberal outlook provides the surest way for Europe to prosper…We know what needs to be done. The challenge now is to make it happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the launch of the report David Lidington said, “I am delighted to welcome this publication from Business for New Europe. It shows that the UK’s business leaders are thinking about what is needed for a strong and competitive European Union economy. I firmly believe that together we can ensure future economic success for all Europe’s citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report by Business for New Europe follows the Prime Minister’s recent pamphlet &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/EU_growth.pdf"&gt;Let’s Choose Growth&lt;/a&gt; which makes the case for completing the Single Market to boost growth, and sets out the risks to Europe if it allows itself to fall behind other leading economies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
