<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/foreign-affairs</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/foreign-affairs"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/foreign-affairs.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Foreign affairs"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60061</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/commonwealth-reform-package-endorsed-by-commonwealth-heads-of-government"/>
    <title>Commonwealth reform package endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government</title>
    <summary>The agreed reforms include a new Commonwealth Charter and measures to strengthen work on election observation and human rights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A landmark Commonwealth Charter and a package of reforms to modernise and sharpen the impact of the Commonwealth have been endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings to a close discussion on Commonwealth reform which began at the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Perth, Australia, in October 2011, and included consideration of the Eminent Persons Group report A Commonwealth of the People: Time for Urgent Action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreed proposals include a new Commonwealth Charter setting out the core values and aspirations of the Commonwealth and its members, and commitments to strengthen the Secretariat’s work on election observation and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Commonwealth, the Rt. Hon. Hugo Swire MP, commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Commonwealth Heads of Government have agreed a new Commonwealth Charter and endorsed a package of reforms to strengthen the Commonwealth. This marks an important milestone in Commonwealth modernisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Commonwealth Ministers devoted a great deal of effort to achieve this result. This reflects our belief that the Commonwealth can make a strong, positive contribution on a range of global issues and nurturing democratic standards worldwide.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms, now adopted, show vision and a genuine desire by all members to increase the Commonwealth’s impact and relevance. All parts of the Commonwealth family must now work together to implement these reforms, to ensure that the organisation is as strong and effective as it can be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ability to protect core democratic values is central to the Commonwealth’s credibility. I hope that the Charter becomes a useful tool to promote these values throughout the Commonwealth. We look forward to events in the coming months to officially launch the Charter, and will play our part in raising its profile in the UK.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/news/34580/252051/191212epgcharter.htm"&gt;Commonwealth Secretariat press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-take-steps-to-strengthen-the-commonwealth?id=816829782&amp;amp;view=News"&gt;Ministerial statement, Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60044</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-announces-reduction-in-uk-troop-numbers-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prime Minister announces reduction in UK troop numbers in Afghanistan</title>
    <summary>UK force levels in Afghanistan are to reduce to around 5,200 by the end of 2013, the Prime Minister announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="Number 10"&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt; told &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/" title="UK Parliament"&gt;Parliament&lt;/a&gt; that UK forces would shift from mentoring Afghan troops at battalion level to brigade level next year. This reflects the progress made in Helmand and the increasing ability and confidence of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;) to lead security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown, agreed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-security-council" title="National Security Council"&gt;National Security Council&lt;/a&gt; this week, is in line and consistent with both UK military advice and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;North Atlantic Treaty Organization&lt;/a&gt; strategy agreed at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/events_66529.htm" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization Summit, Lisbon 2010"&gt;Lisbon Summit in 2010&lt;/a&gt;, under which &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) forces continue to operate across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK forces will end combat operations by the end of 2014. It is part of transition to an enduring commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement comes as the previously announced reduction of UK force levels from 9,500 to 9,000 is being achieved with service personnel due to arrive home in time for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed work on how force levels will reduce in 2013 is ongoing and will be conducted in line with operational requirements and the transition process which remains on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Afghan forces increasingly take the lead, UK combat operations will give way to an increasing focus on training and advising. By the end of 2013, it is expected that UK forces will not routinely need to mentor Afghan forces below brigade level, allowing the reduction in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real progress being made on the ground in Helmand province will allow us, on current planning, to reduce British troops to around 5,200 by the end of 2013. This is a direct result of the success of the Afghan National Security Forces in assuming a lead role in delivering security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The phased process of transition of security responsibility agreed at the Lisbon Summit is well advanced and on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have consistently said that there will not be a cliff-edge reduction in troop numbers at the end of 2014. This gradual drawdown is firmly in line with the planning of our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; partners and the advice of military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces will continue to operate alongside their Afghan counterparts, albeit in lower numbers, until our combat operations cease at the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There remain huge challenges ahead for the Afghan people. Our combat mission is drawing to a close, but our commitment to the Afghan people is long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Afghan National Army" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5775/JMOCCCT-2012-014_Op_Horhari_Afghan_004.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Afghan National Army take part in an operation in Helmand province (stock image) [Picture: Sergeant Steve Blake RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir David Richards, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Army and Police have greatly improved in the past years. Their capability has increased so that today they enjoy the trust of some 84 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As they develop, and in agreement with the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, the efforts of our Armed Forces will continue to shift from a combat role to one that focuses on training, advice and assistance. That will allow us to make appropriate and measured reductions in our force levels in line with the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; plan and our Chicago commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These drawdown plans are based on military advice and following discussion with General Allen [Commander &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces]. I am confident that the progress we have seen in Helmand and across Afghanistan can be maintained and that we can complete the tasks we have been set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be in the position where we are now able to commit to reducing UK force levels to around 5,200 by the end of next year is testament to the professionalism and courage of those personnel who have served, and continue to serve, in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We must remember that the UK’s commitment to the operation in Afghanistan will continue beyond the end of 2014 as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/" title="Department for International Development"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [Department for International Development] and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign Office&lt;/a&gt; continue to build the government and nation while the UK’s pledge to support the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, including training the military’s officers, will be ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significant progress in Afghanistan continues with 75% of the Afghan population now being secured by the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; and at least 80% of all patrols being &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;-led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 80 UK bases at the start of the HERRICK 16 deployment this April, only 32 remain active with the others having been handed over to Afghan forces or closed. Afghan National Army numbers in Helmand province now stand at about 18,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59945</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice"/>
    <title>Christmas Holiday Travel Advice</title>
    <summary>A few simple preparations before and during your holiday can help to make your Christmas trip safe and trouble free.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you do get into problems while abroad then we are here to help, but you can avoid a lot of difficulties in the first place by following these basic tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/staying-safe/travel-insurance/" title="Travel insurance"&gt;take out comprehensive travel insurance&lt;/a&gt; - make sure it covers you for any activities you are likely to undertake such as extreme or water sports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nathnac.org/" title="NaTHNaC"&gt;The National Travel Health Network and Centre’s website&lt;/a&gt;T or contact your GP’s surgery as early as possible before you travel to find out if you need any vaccinations or other medication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for certain countries your passport must be valid for six months after the date you travel - check the entry requirements section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take enough money for your trip and some back-up funds in a mix of cash and cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-pack-explore-a-new-guide-for-travellers" title="Plan. Pack. Explore. – a new guide for travellers"&gt;download our Plan. Pack. Explore. app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="winter-sports"&gt;Winter sports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New research reveals that a third of people taking their first winter sports holiday risk serious injury because they are not sufficiently in shape when they hit the slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research also reveals that two out of five winter sports enthusiasts have injured themselves at least once, highlighting the importance of getting in shape and warming up properly before skiing or snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/get-fit-for-ski" title="Get Fit For Ski"&gt;Find out more about our Get Fit For Ski campaign.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visiting-friends-or-family-abroad"&gt;Visiting friends or family abroad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You still need to take the same preparations as if you were going on holiday. Our research shows that nearly half of young people did not take out insurance the last time they stayed with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56575</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T09:02:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T09:02:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the single market more effective</title>
    <summary>Plans to make the single market more competitive, easier to do business in and create new jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the EU expanded to include more states, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate acheived by other EU states. However, the European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at a rate as low as just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the EU and other dynamic markets, such as South Korea, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the EU as a whole. To achieve higher growth and increased employment, all member states and the EU institutions will need to take action. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which encourages all member states to reinforce financial stability, create jobs and improve competitiveness, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong single market creates jobs and benefits all member states. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234 billion, went to the EU. The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other EU prime ministers, urged the EU to improve the single market, concentrating on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update EU single market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting EU consumers in cyberspace. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;.  Member States must implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013. E-invoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-invoicing within the EU could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;EU-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; which came into force on 1 July 2011 is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for EU exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act (2011)&lt;/a&gt; sets out twelve ways to boost growth and improve confidence in European business. In October 2012 the European Commission proposed a second set of actions, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smact/docs/single-market-act2_en.pdf"&gt;Single Market Act II&lt;/a&gt;, to further develop the single market’s economic opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act II (2012)&lt;/a&gt; describes the EU’s goals of improving the digital economy, including e-commerce and electronic invoicing, and creating more efficient transport and energy networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/u/11-760-uk-response-single-market-act"&gt;response to The Single Market Act&lt;/a&gt; in February 2011 looks at how the UK will work with other member states on reforms that will create the most jobs and economic growth at the lowest cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a study, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/e/11-517-economic-consequences-of-completing-single-market"&gt;The economic consequences for the UK and the EU of completing the single market&lt;/a&gt;, in February 2011. This paper considers the benefits of the single market and the negative effects of the UK opting out of future European trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; published a study in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/feeds/~/media/568CC723188C40DFBB02E868353B40B9.ashx"&gt;The UK and the single market: trade and investment analytical papers topic 4 of 18&lt;/a&gt;, that examines the importance of the EU for British exporters and investors. The analysis found that businesses have benefited from the opportunities provided by the single market. Such benefits include: better connected and cheaper networks; mutual recognition of standards; and easier access to cheap and competitive inputs for British manufacturers. In addition greater competition within the single market has fostered innovation. For consumers, the single market has created more choice and lowered prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/59931</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T14:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories: Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds has updated parliament on the first Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council meeting.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chaired the first meeting of the Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council in London from 4-5 December. This Council brings together the political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers. It provides a forum for the exchange of views on political and constitutional issues and has a mandate to lead work to review and implement the strategy and commitments in the June 2012 White Paper The Overseas Territories: Security Success and Sustainability and to promote the security and good governance of the Territories and their sustainable economic and social development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council agreed a communiqué which identified priority issues and set out a comprehensive action plan for joint work. A copy of this communiqué has been laid in the Library of the House. The communiqué reflects the commitment of the governments of the Overseas Territories and the UK to work together to support economic growth and jobs; to protect the environment and create green growth; to harness effectively the support of the EU, the Commonwealth and other international organisations; and to deliver better government, better education and stronger, healthier and safer communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with our commitment in the White Paper we will report to Parliament on progress in implementing the commitments in the communiqué by territory governments and UK Departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual Joint Ministerial Council succeeds the Overseas Territories Consultative Council set up in 1999. It was attended this year by political leaders and representatives of the following Territories: Anguilla; Bermuda; the British Virgin Islands; the Cayman Islands; the Falkland Islands; Gibraltar; Montserrat; Pitcairn; St Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha; and the Turks and Caicos Islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 December the Prime Minister welcomed Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Overseas Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council" title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council-communique" title=" Joint Ministerial Council communique"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council communiqué&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59902</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements </title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague condemns decision to build new settlements in East Jerusalem.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK condemns the decision by the Jerusalem District Planning Board to give approval for a plan to build 1,500 housing units in the East Jerusalem neighbourhood of Ramat Shlomo, and is extremely concerned by reports that the Board is considering giving the approval to a further 5000 housing units in East Jerusalem this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on yesterday’s announcement the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Israeli settlements are illegal under international law, and I condemn this decision. It is deeply disappointing that despite the international community repeatedly raising our concerns, Israel continues to press ahead with plans to expand them.  Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties.  This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.  If implemented, it would make a negotiated two-state solution, with Jerusalem as a shared capital, very difficult to achieve.  We  urge Israel to reverse this decision and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity”
.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57510</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:04:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth Land </title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary has announced that the southern part of British Antarctic Territory has been named Queen Elizabeth Land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen visited the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office for the second time today, as the last official engagement of her Diamond Jubilee year. Her Majesty’s previous visit was in 1982 to mark the department’s bicentenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of the building, Foreign Secretary William Hague announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory had been named ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’ in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a mark of this country’s gratitude to The Queen for Her service, we are naming a part of the British Antarctic Territory in her honour as ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fitting tribute at the end of Her Majesty’s Diamond Jubilee year, and I am very proud to be able to announce it as she visits the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Territory is a unique and important member of the network of fourteen UK Overseas Territories. To be able to recognise the UK’s commitment to Antarctica with a permanent association with Her Majesty is a great honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area now to be known as Queen Elizabeth Land, which was previously unnamed, is around 169,000 square miles (437,000 sq km), making up just under a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory. This is almost twice the size of the UK, which stands at 94,000 square miles (244,000 sq km).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land is bounded on the North side by the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves, to the North East by Coats Land, on the East by Dronning Maud Land and extending on the West side to a line between the South Pole and Rutford Ice Stream, east of Constellation Inlet.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen has been on the throne for 60 of the 104 years since the UK claimed territory in Antarctica in 1908. This includes the entire time it has been known as the British Antarctic Territory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Queen Elizabeth Land" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5726/QEL-Antarctica-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Antarctic Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt;) extends from 20⁰ to 80⁰ West. It was claimed by the UK in 1908 and was the first official claim in Antarctica. It was designated officially as a separate Overseas Territory in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All claims to territory within Antarctica are held in abeyance under Article IV of the Antarctic Treaty, 1959, which neither confirms nor denies competing claims, but prevents new claims being made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name Queen Elizabeth Land will now be used on all British maps. Because of the unique status of Antarctica, which is covered by an international Treaty that suspends territorial sovereignty, it is for other countries to decide whether or not they will officially recognise this name.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place naming in &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaken on the basis that a currently unnamed area requires a name for scientific or logistical purposes. This approach is fully in line with the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions on names are made by the Commissioner of the British Antarctic Territory, who is based in London. The Commissioner takes advice on new names from the Antarctic Place Names Committee, which meets twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has no permanent population. British presence is maintained via three research stations operated by the British Antarctic Survey. The Territory itself is self-financing, investing modest receipts from stamp sales and the income tax from overwintering British scientists in environmental projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is not the first time that land in Antarctica has been named after The Queen. Princess Elizabeth Land in East Antarctica, which was discovered in 1931 by the Australian Sir Douglas Mawson, was named by him after Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth (now Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II). And in 2006, an unnamed mountain range in the Antarctic Peninsula was named The Princess Royal Range, in recognition of Her Royal Highness’s work to support environmental and heritage protection work in Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Foreign Secretary's speech"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s speech&lt;/a&gt; welcoming Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on supporting the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories" title="Supporting the Overseas Territories"&gt;Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60069</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:47:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners"/>
    <title>Britain and the Commonwealth: Historic Friends, Future Partners</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a speech about the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth at the Royal Commonwealth Society.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Secretary General; High Commissioners; Honourable Members of both Houses; representatives of businesses and NGOs; Welcome to this Commonwealth reception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I must begin by extending my deepest condolences to the people of Samoa who were hit by Cyclone Evan last week. For all those affected – particularly those who lost loved ones – it was a devastating event. Our High Commissioner has conveyed our sympathy to the Samoan Prime Minister. The Cyclone has now also hit Fiji, and our thoughts are with the many Fijians affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an opportune moment for me to commend the work of the Commonwealth, having had the great privilege of meeting its Head, Her Majesty The Queen, this morning, who came to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office on her final Diamond Jubilee year engagement. My short time speaking to her brought to mind the quite extraordinary role she has played for this country and for countries across the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On 21 April 1947, her 21st birthday, Her Majesty was with her parents and younger sister, Princess Margaret, on a tour of South Africa. In a speech broadcast on the radio from Cape Town, she said to the people of the Commonwealth: “I declare before you all that my whole life whether it be long or short shall be devoted to your service and the service of our great imperial family to which we all belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ever since she said those words, her devotion to the Commonwealth has been unwavering. Her Majesty has travelled more than any other monarch in our history. During her reign she has undertaken well over 150 Commonwealth visits, and in 1998 became the first reigning British monarch to undertake State visits to Brunei and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am sure you would all join me this evening, in this historic Diamond Jubilee year, in paying tribute to her work over the past 60 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So it is a real pleasure to be here this evening, in the run-up to Christmas and Parliamentary recess. I would like to thank Danny Sriskandarajah and Peter Kellner for inviting me to speak, and for their tireless work as Director and Chairman of the Royal Commonwealth Society respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Danny has made a disproportionate contribution to the Society and to the Commonwealth more broadly. The vision he demonstrated in designing and delivering the Commonwealth Conversations project, for example – which was the seed that led to our Eminent Persons Group report – was outstanding. We shall miss his energy, vibrancy and innovation, but wish him well in his new life in South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have long been an admirer of the RCS. It is an organisation with deep roots, but one which is constantly evolving. The Society’s role as a promoter of the Commonwealth brand – whether through engaging young people across the world, encouraging public debate on Commonwealth issues, or through spreading awareness of the cultural diversity of its members – is helping to ensure its continued relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And it is on this relevance that I want to focus this evening. Because one can get the sense that for some – British or otherwise – the Commonwealth is an organisation of the past; one which puts on a good sports event every few years, but isn’t in tune with today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to challenge that assertion; to explain why this Government is placing a greater emphasis on the Commonwealth, and what we are trying to do to unlock its true potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-commonwealth-today"&gt;The Commonwealth today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, set out the Government’s vision for Britain’s foreign policy in July 2010, he spoke of our need to respond to an increasingly networked world. Influence today, he said, “increasingly lies with networks of states with fluid and dynamic patterns of allegiance, alliance and connections”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we are to make the most of the opportunities this creates, and respond to the challenges it represents, we need to make full use of our assets and connections. The Commonwealth, one of the world’s greatest – and oldest – networks, remains one of our most valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was therefore delighted when the Prime Minister appointed me as Minister responsible for the Commonwealth – an organisation I have respected for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both the Foreign Secretary and my much-admired predecessor, Lord Howell – who Frank Field described in a debate last week as a “jewel in the crown” of Commonwealth interest – have together put the “C” back into the “FCO”: the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer in the value the Commonwealth adds on the international stage – politically, economically and culturally. So let me first outline what I think are its greatest strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First and foremost is its sheer scale. Its members account for a third of the world’s population, more than a fifth of the Earth’s total land area and have a combined GDP of over £6 trillion. As a whole, it is an organisation with real clout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Secondly, it is a hugely diverse grouping – bringing together different people, united by our shared language, legal systems and values. From the plains of southern Africa to the island nations of the Pacific, the Commonwealth gives all of its members an equal seat at the international table. It can amplify their voices and make sure the views of even the smallest nations are heard by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the Commonwealth provides tangible support very effectively. A few examples spring immediately to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One is election observation. The Commonwealth has observed over 70 elections since 1990, including recent missions to Ghana and Sierra Leone. On each occasion they have provided a trusted, objective judgement on the credibility of the process, the environment in which the elections took place and the final result. But the observation missions don’t just observe: they also submit recommendations, drawing on collective expertise, on how to improve elections in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would also point to the Commonwealth Scholarships and Fellowships Programme, through which Commonwealth governments offer scholarships and fellowships to citizens from other member countries. Since it was established 53 years ago, 27,000 people have benefitted – including, as a topical example, Mark Carney, the next Governor of the Bank of England. In Britain, we have supported the scheme to the tune of £87 million for the four years from 2011 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another practical example is technical assistance to promote development in member states, which I know is a very important element of Commonwealth membership for some countries. The Secretariat’s assistance on good governance and the rule of law is helping to build the solid democratic foundations required for sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And I would add to all of this a fourth – and significant – strength: that the Commonwealth is not just about government contacts. Looking around this hall, I can see representatives from a huge range of backgrounds – parliamentarians, businesses, NGOs, civil society, young people. It is these groups that make the Commonwealth so effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-the-commonwealth-is-changing"&gt;How the Commonwealth is changing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth of today is a dynamic, diverse grouping – one of the world’s leading soft power networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But it is not standing still. Like any organisation, the Commonwealth isn’t perfect. All of its members, the United Kingdom included, recognise that to maintain its relevance, the Commonwealth needs to respond to shifting global trends and the rising expectations of its citizens – particularly its younger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the driving force behind the agenda to modernise the Commonwealth, which has been in train since last year’s Heads of Government meeting in Perth. We have all been working hard on this and have made good progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just this week the Secretary-General confirmed that, following discussions in September by Commonwealth Foreign Ministers, the majority of the reform measures proposed by the Eminent Persons Group have been agreed by Heads of Government. That is good news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that we have agreement on the way ahead, we need to make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Key among the reform measures is the agreement to have a Commonwealth Charter to set out, in a single document, the Commonwealth’s core values. It is important that we now work collectively to raise the Charter’s profile, across the Commonwealth, to embed it within the architecture that ensures members uphold these values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government will, with your help, work to raise the profile of the Charter here in Britain, with a focus on Parliament, civil society and youth organisations. I know the RCS has made its own contribution to this by hosting events on the Charter for civil society organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just as important is the strengthening of the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group, which should enable the organisation to respond more quickly to infringements of Commonwealth values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the swift response of the Action Group to the situation in the Maldives has shown, we are already starting to see the benefits of these changes. Through this and other country engagements the Action Group works on, it must demonstrate that it is living up to its strengthened mandate and can make a real difference on the world stage. This will make a significant contribution to the credibility of the Commonwealth as an international organisation that adds value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-soft-power-network-of-the-future"&gt;The soft power network of the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An increased focus on the Commonwealth has been a key element of this Government’s re-alignment of Britain’s foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In part, this has involved practical steps like the strengthening of our diplomatic network in Commonwealth countries. We opened a new Deputy High Commission in Hyderabad in India in May, with another in Chandigarh to follow soon. We are also strengthening our commercial capacity in Commonwealth countries like Canada, Sierra Leone, Mozambique, Papua New Guinea and Guyana. And here in London we have increased the number of staff working on the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But our renewed focus has also involved a change in approach; a change in the way we work, by seeking to make the most of our Commonwealth contacts. When William Hague visited Australia last year it was the first visit by a British Foreign Secretary for 17 years. In the past twelve months, Foreign and Commonwealth Office Ministers have visited around 20 Commonwealth countries – including my recent visit to Belize and, just last week, to Brunei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of this has left us in a strong position to build on the progress we have already made on our Commonwealth agenda. This is important, because there is much work to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Trade and investment is a prime example: we should be pushing to increase the volume of trade among Commonwealth members, and – connected to this – working to increase prosperity across the network by creating the conditions that allow trade to flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Intra-Commonwealth trade already amounts to around £250 billion each year.  But we should be much more ambitious, as the potential is vast. The Commonwealth’s middle class has expanded by one billion people in the last 20 years. These new consumers represent a significant and rapidly growing market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can add to this the Commonwealth’s in-built advantages. Research conducted by this Society two years ago found that when two trading partners were Commonwealth members, their trade was likely to be a third to a half more than when one or both trade partners was non-Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This ‘Commonwealth effect’ – explained in terms of shared history, values, legal systems and language – should enable us to drive trade to even greater heights. Just look at sub-Saharan Africa, for example: the latest World Bank rankings show that all but four of the top 20 countries in which to do business there are Commonwealth members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But this agenda certainly isn’t just about business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also need to ensure that the Commonwealth stands up for its values and beliefs; that it identifies where its values are not being adhered to; and that it speaks up to turn things around when this happens. The strengthened Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group, for which the Secretary-General has committed to provide additional Secretariat resources, has a critical role here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So too does the Commonwealth Games. The 2014 Games in Glasgow – the Commonwealth’s own Olympics – are as much about promoting Commonwealth values, a key element of its brand, as they are about building prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also need to develop the Commonwealth’s advocacy role to ensure the voices of its members are heard in international negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And we need to increase the Commonwealth’s engagement with Britain’s Overseas Territories, which share many of the challenges facing small Commonwealth states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth Secretariat’s new Strategic Plan for 2013 to 2016 should help us to address these issues. We are working with the Secretariat to ensure its focus is in areas where it has a comparative advantage, to avoid duplicating the work of other international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Next year will offer several opportunities to drive this work forward. This includes the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Colombo. Ahead of the meeting, we will of course look to Sri Lanka – as we would to any Host – to demonstrate its commitment to upholding the Commonwealth values of good governance and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And I look forward to the Commonwealth Week in March which will offer another opportunity to showcase the organisation’s work. Next year’s theme – ‘Opportunity Through Enterprise’ – is particularly relevant at this time of global economic challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth today is as important as it has ever been. Its members represent some of the most fast-growing, dynamic economies in the world. They are political, social and cultural leaders on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With such collective weight, we shouldn’t be surprised that some – including, recently, the British Parliament’s Foreign Affairs Select Committee – think it is an organisation that should do better. They are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Each and every one of us in this room wants a strong Commonwealth; one which makes the most of its considerable assets. I hope I have made clear this afternoon that it already does a lot of things well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we continue to drive forward the reform process, I am confident that we can build an even more successful Commonwealth – one which does less so it can do it better, focusing on those areas in which it adds the most value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These will include strengthening governance and democracy; increasing the resilience of small and vulnerable states; creating more effective frameworks for inclusive economic growth and sustainable development; ensuring members are able to participate in the global trading system; and improving climate financing frameworks for vulnerable states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And for those that still need convincing of the Commonwealth’s relevance in today’s world, I would say this: if it was not important, if it did not play an influential role on the international stage, countries would not be queuing up to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That this is exactly what is happening at the moment is testament to the continued relevance of the Commonwealth today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wish you all a very happy Christmas and a peaceful New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57435</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:28:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office"/>
    <title>Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague welcomed Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II to the Foreign Office. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary announced that an area in the British Antarctic Territory has been named Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are all delighted to welcome you to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office for the final event of your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In a year in which millions of British people have been able to see you and cheer you, we are truly honoured here in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to have you here with us and to take our part in closing this magnificent period of celebration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is an opportunity for everyone here to show how proud they are to serve in your Majesty’s Diplomatic Service and in the Home Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And there are over 10,000 British and locally-engaged staff in our Embassies and High Commissions abroad who will be equally inspired by your visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You embody a life of service to our country, and a lifetime of diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have made over 260 official visits to 116 different countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Promoting reconciliation, as you did on your visit to West Germany in 1965, and to Japan in 1975;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving encouragement to nations after profound change, such as your visit to Russia in 1994 and to South Africa in 1995;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helping to heal the wounds of history and to make peace irreversible, as I saw myself during your truly historic State Visit to Ireland last year;
And all the time steadfastly uniting the Commonwealth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are deeply grateful to you, and to the 11 members of the Royal Family who have travelled to 29 countries and territories for your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, I am conscious that I am your twenty-second Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your wisdom and experience are an inspiration to all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are striving for excellence in all that we do in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our goal is to be the best Diplomatic Service in the world: helping British people overseas, supporting our economy, keeping our country secure, and upholding freedom and human rights at all times. We do this with your example always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we are renaming in your honour the newly-restored old Home Office Library, which now houses our historians and the Knowledge and Information Management team, which will be called the Diamond Jubilee Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I am delighted to announce that as a mark of our country’s gratitude to you, an area of the Antarctic 437,000 square kilometres in size, nearly twice the size of the United Kingdom and more than a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory, will be given a name for the very first time. From today, in your honour, it will be forever known as Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are proud to serve a Queen who has achieved so much for our nation and who embodies the ideals of public service that we cherish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we thank you for your visit; for this proud and happy occasion that we will all remember for the rest of our lives, and which will be recorded for our successors in the plaque you are unveiling today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank everyone here and all the staff of Foreign and Commonwealth Office, all over the world for all their hard work on behalf of our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And now your Majesty to commemorate your visit today I invite you to unveil the plaque marking your Diamond Jubilee Year.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5731/Queen_s-visit--final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title="Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
