<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/foreign-affairs</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/foreign-affairs"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/foreign-affairs.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Foreign affairs"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T01:02:18+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55754</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T01:02:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T01:02:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-transfer-responsibility-for-security-in-sangin-to-us"/>
    <title>UK forces transfer responsibility for security in Sangin to US</title>
    <summary>ISAF has today announced that British forces in southern Afghanistan have handed responsibility for security in Sangin to US forces</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transfer of authority, first announced by the Defence Secretary in July this year, is the last move in the current rebalancing of ISAF forces across Helmand. It follows an increase in ISAF and Afghan security forces in Helmand over recent months and will ensure an equal distribution of ISAF forces amongst the Afghan population living there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handing over Sangin will allow UK forces to focus their effort in central Helmand where they will continue to deliver effective counter-insurgency operations, working alongside the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British forces have been in Sangin, a key economic and transport hub, since 2006. Alongside the ANSF, they have provided vital security for the local population on behalf of the Government of Afghanistan, enabling development and preventing the insurgency from using Sangin as a base from which to mount attacks across Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40 Commando Royal Marines, currently deployed with 4th Mechanized Brigade, have handed over to the US Marine Corps (USMC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;British forces have served in Sangin over the last four years and should be very proud of the achievements they have made in one of the most challenging areas of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The level of sacrifice has been high and we should never forget the many brave troops who have lost their lives in the pursuit of success in an international mission rooted firmly in our own national security in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The handover of Sangin by UK forces represents sound military rationale and reflects the increase of both ISAF and Afghan forces across Helmand over the course of the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;British troops will redeploy to central Helmand in support of ISAF’s main effort, where they will continue to lead the fight against the insurgency and assist in building a stable and secure Afghanistan that can stand on its own two feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Gordon Messenger, the Chief of the Defence Staff’s Strategic Communications Officer, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;British troops redeploying from Sangin are handing over a strong, forward-looking operation which has, over the last four years, ensured that the authority of the Afghan Government exists even in an area that the Taliban regard as their heartland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our troops operating in Sangin have been taking the fight to the Taliban and by doing so have reduced the threat of violence spreading elsewhere. The progress and momentum in central Helmand would not have been possible without their endeavour and sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is and will continue to be a challenging area because of its strategic importance to the Afghan Government, ISAF and the insurgency - that is why ISAF forces will remain there to build upon the progress already achieved by UK forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A member of the Police Mentoring Troop during a routine patrol around Sangin's bazaar " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5333/UK_forces_transfer_responsibility_for_security_in_Sangin_to_US-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A member of the Police Mentoring Troop during a routine patrol around Sangin's bazaar  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Si Ethell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The transfer of responsibility for Sangin to the USMC is the latest in a series of practical and sensible reconfigurations that have occurred as a result of the significant uplift in ISAF troops in Helmand over the last year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It allows British forces, with their Danish and Estonian allies, to focus their efforts in the critical central Helmand area, building on the strong momentum that has already been achieved there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Richard Mills, Commander of Regional Command (South West), the military headquarters responsible for Helmand and Nimruz provinces, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces have carved out a solid security bubble that we are moving US forces into. They are leaving solid professional relationships with the people and the ANSF in Sangin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will continue to build on the successes and continue to work with the local population and forces there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being an economic and transport hub, power lines route through Sangin, supplying power from the Kajaki hydroelectric station to central Helmand and Kandahar, and Sangin is one of the most fertile areas in Helmand. Building and maintaining security and governance in Sangin is therefore vital for the long-term stability and development of Helmand and the wider region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sangin has moved forward since 2006 with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• the reform of Sangin’s district governance with a new District Governor and senior staff appointed in March 2010. The new Governor is actively working with members of the UK-led Provincial Reconstruction Team and local community leaders to improve governance in Sangin and win the support of local tribal groupings, some of whom have previously supported the insurgency;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• over 850 shops trading in Sangin’s bazaar, twice as many as summer last year; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• the improvement of Route 611 from central Helmand through Sangin to Kajaki - increasing access to agricultural land and markets for local people; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• local administrators, supported by the Provincial Reconstruction Team, working to distribute grain and promote the production of legal alternatives to narcotics; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• trained Afghan medics at the new health clinic, which opened in October 2009, treating 300 patients per week - men, women and children from Sangin and its surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Paul James, Commanding Officer of 40 Commando Royal Marines, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s been a hard fight for 40 Commando Royal Marines in Sangin, but we have achieved much. We have sought to protect the local people and have worked hard to support the Afghan National Security Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our partners in the ANA and ANP [Afghan National Police] have improved tremendously. They have provided the security for the District Governor to spread the influence of the Afghan Government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The bazaar itself, central to the economy of the area, is thriving and a much more bustling place than when we arrived with new shops opening all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is still work to do, and we are confident that our American partners will build on what we have achieved. We have lost brave Marines, but we will do them proud and return home with our heads held high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British forces will redeploy to central Helmand where they will join their British colleagues who are operating alongside Afghan and other ISAF forces and where the UK-led Provincial Reconstruction Team is carrying out major governance and socio-economic development projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;District Governor of Sangin, Mohammad Sharif, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The attitude, service and sacrifice that has been paid by the Royal Marines has been exemplary and has set a very good example for the people of Sangin. As 40 Commando goes, they will be missed by the people of Sangin and they will be in our thoughts and minds forever as we will always remember their hard work and efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55753</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:58:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:58:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-support-afghan-operation-in-lower-gereshk-valley"/>
    <title>UK forces support Afghan operation in Lower Gereshk Valley</title>
    <summary>Afghan soldiers and police, supported by British troops, have completed an operation to clear insurgents from the Lower Gereshk Valley, in the north of Nahr-e Saraj district.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operation BIG FISH was planned at a meeting of Afghan security officials including the District Governor and the Chief of Police, which was attended by the Commander of Task Force Helmand, Brigadier Doug Chalmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security shura meets regularly to discuss the district’s security priorities and the allocation of police and army resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Rupert King-Evans, Fire Support Company Commander, 1st Battalion Grenadier Guards, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The operation was to clear insurgents, IED components and IED-making facilities from the Lower Gereshk Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The key point from this operation is that it was an Afghan operation supported by ISAF, and not the other way around. The Afghans planned the operation. We offered advice and, when they requested, we provided support for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task fell to the Afghan National Army (ANA) 3/215 Brigade, led by Brigadier General Sherin Shah. At dawn on the day of the operation, more than 400 Afghan warriors from the brigade flew into the contested area. By conducting several ‘dummy’ landings at various locations, the insurgents were kept on the back foot, and the Afghan forces achieved the element of surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Afghan warriors, accompanied by their British advisors, patrolled up the valley, clearing the area of insurgents and searching compounds for weapons and ammunition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Nathan Love from a Kandak Advisory Training Team said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sheer mass of Afghan force on the ground was enough to deter the enemy and show the people that the Afghans are leading. The Taliban saw this and most of them decided not to fight, so the ANA were able to find 14 of their IEDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An Afghan warrior sweeps for explosive devices during Operation BIG FISH" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5331/UK_forces_support_Afghan_operation_in_Lower_Gereshk_Valley-03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An Afghan warrior sweeps for explosive devices during Operation BIG FISH  [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the Afghan soldiers searching the area and keeping the local residents safe, it was a point of pride to be leading a major operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jawid Afghanyar, an ANA officer with the 6th Kandak, 3/215 Brigade, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have mine-defusing teams, infantry teams and many others bringing security and peace to the area. It has been a while since the Afghan National Security Forces have been in the area and the people now know that we will help make this area safe and secure, so the people here can continue their work in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British soldiers involved in mentoring the Afghan forces have seen them rise to a very high level of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major King-Evans concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s seriously impressive how well the Afghan Army is operating. They are really swept up. Their low-level tactics, skills and drills are excellent, and they conducted the operation almost as if they were ISAF themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They’ve shown the local population that the Government of Afghanistan and the Afghan National Army and Police are here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55752</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:55:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:55:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-praised-as-new-command-stands-up-in-south-west-afghanistan"/>
    <title>UK forces praised as new command stands up in South West Afghanistan</title>
    <summary>A new organisation has taken command of international forces in south western Afghanistan today, Monday 14 June 2010.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The changes, announced on 21 May, see Regional Command (South West), based in Helmand, overseeing Helmand and Nimruz provinces, while Regional Command (South) [RC(S)], headquartered in Kandahar, continues to control ISAF forces in Kandahar, Daykundi, Uruzgan and Zabul provinces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the majority of ISAF forces based in southern Afghanistan, the formation of the new headquarters permits commanders in the south to focus on geographically smaller areas, ensure greater partnering between the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF) and ISAF, and deliver the levels of security required for governance and development to continue to spread in the region. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Richard Mills of the United States Marine Corps is in charge of the new Command. He leads a combined force of some 27,000 personnel, with units drawn from eight nations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a distinct privilege for all of us to stand up Regional Command (South West),” he said. “We are truly building on the outstanding work of all that have served here in Helmand and Nimruz provinces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The establishment of Regional Command (South West) is a natural military progression based on the number of troops serving here and the priority placed on Helmand and Nimruz provinces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the first time that the US Marine Corps has led an ISAF Regional Command. The British officers serving in my coalition headquarters as well as Task Force Helmand have brought invaluable experience and knowledge to the command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are partnered with ANSF at all levels and conducting joint operations throughout Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tough fighting remains,” he added, “but I see evidence daily of progress that will bring about lasting stability across southern Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will be a significant year for the future of Afghanistan. Coalition forces, alongside our Afghan counterparts, will continue to support the Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan as it delivers legitimate governance, improved security and lasting economic development.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant General David Rodriguez, Commander of ISAF Joint Command, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The establishment of Regional Command (South West) significantly increases the ability of the Afghan National Security Forces to partner with the coalition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Mills praised the work of British forces in Helmand province:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I remain very much impressed by the momentum and achievements of RC(S) under General Carter,” he said. “My predecessors in the 2nd Marine Expeditionary Brigade and the British troops of Task Force Helmand have distinguished themselves in the service of the Afghan people here. Because of their efforts, real and tangible progress is being made here every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional Command (South), led by Major General Nick Carter, will continue to direct ISAF operations in the provinces of Kandahar, Zabul, Uruzgan and Daykundi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 30,000 troops continue to operate in RC(S). No troops have been realigned during the formation of the new command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55750</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-help-transform-helmand-hospital"/>
    <title>UK forces help transform Helmand hospital</title>
    <summary>A hospital in Helmand province has been completely transformed, thanks to the help of British forces.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Less than twelve months ago Gereshk District Hospital was in a poor state; all of the buildings were in need of urgent repair, there were no inpatients, the incinerator was broken, and medical waste littered the hospital grounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the Helmand Provincial Reconstruction Team (PRT), working with a Military Stabilisation Support Team (MSST), has completed 23 renovation projects at the site in Nahr-e Saraj (North).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hospital is now one of the leading medical facilities in Helmand, able to provide treatment to a much larger number of patients from Now Zad and Sangin - more than 20km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renovated hospital has a 24-hour accident and emergency ward, a maternity wing, and vaccination and dental clinics, as well as a drop-in service for more common ailments. All the services are free to patients thanks to the Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan (GIRoA) and non-governmental agencies, who manage the funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Abdul Latif is the Director of Health in Gereshk and has worked at the hospital for the last six years. He has worked closely with the MSST, PRT and GIRoA, and has been the driving force behind the renovation. All of the work has been carried out by Afghan contractors using local materials, and this has helped to boost the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Air Force Sergeant Karen Swallow is from the MSST, part of Task Force Helmand. She says the most significant change at the hospital has been in the maternity facilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Previously the maternity ward was what can only be described as a broom cupboard with two old beds side-by-side. Now, it’s a completely new building with up-to-date facilities giving privacy and respect to the women before, during and after their labour,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="nside the new maternity wing at Gereshk District Hospital " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5326/UK_forces_help_transform_Helmand_hospital-05.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;nside the new maternity wing at Gereshk District Hospital  [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Hamish Burke, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Latif says as a result they’re seeing more and more mothers at the hospital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Traditionally, most women give birth at home, but now the new maternity wing offers an ante and postnatal care facility, waiting rooms and bathrooms, and we have three female midwives and one female nurse working at the hospital,” he explained. “Increasingly, more women are taking advantage of the improved medical care rather than risking having their babies at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only the medical facilities that have been upgraded. A new incinerator, designed and built by an Afghan contractor, has been put in place so surgical rubbish is no longer left lying around, posing a health risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kitchen, which previously had no electricity and little equipment, now has lights and utensils, allowing the chef to prepare and store food for inpatients and staff. A new well has also been installed, along with a parking area, a mortuary, a new footpath and repairs to the boundary wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 (Artificer Quarter Master Sergeant) Mike Wright from the MSST said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everything has been completed to a high standard by the local contractors, providing a much needed improvement to services for the people of Gereshk. Without the dedication of the staff here to their hospital, the projects there would not have been such a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those treated at the hospital include victims of road traffic accidents, gunshot wounds and mine injuries from either insurgent-laid improvised explosive devices or legacy munitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding and better facilities mean that the medical care is no longer constrained to the hospital. Various outreach programmes are also run by the medical teams to ensure that provision is extended to the more rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Latif said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every day nurses from our hospital travel out into the district taking vaccines and health supplies to those who are unable to reach us. These health workers also spread information about basic hygiene and how important it is. The advice spread by word of mouth reaches far and wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Latif and the staff are keen to further expand the hospital and provide even better access to facilities for the local people. Sergeant Swallow is confident this will be achieved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This project has been the greatest success project which I have been involved in during my time with the MSST,” she said. “Dr Latif and his staff are fully committed to making further changes to the hospital, improving its service in the future. It is obvious that this facility will be sustained well after ISAF troops have vacated Afghanistan, which makes it the success story it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55748</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:47:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:47:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-forces-help-afghan-police-hold-community-party--2"/>
    <title>UK forces help Afghan police hold community party</title>
    <summary>UK forces have helped members of the Afghan Uniform Police hold a party for hundreds of people in Helmand province, Afghanistan</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 300 people from the local area attended the party, which was organised entirely by the Afghan Uniform Police (AUP), who also provided the security for the event - the largest gathering of its kind in the Babaji area of Lashkar Gah district for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entertainment was in the form of a band and traditional Afghan food was provided and served to the guests by the AUP. The band had travelled from Lashkar Gah and many of the police present had also come from areas outside the Babaji precinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘community concert’ marks a milestone in the continued success of the police to provide security and influence in the area. Within the last few months several ISAF checkpoints have been closed or handed over to the Afghan police and the final transition of Babaji to Afghan control is due to take place later this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Babaji bazaar, which has been closed for the last two years due to security concerns, has recently reopened - a sign that the local population now feel secure enough to return to a state of normality that has not existed in the region for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money for the event was provided by the Operations Coordination Cell (OCC), run by the Police Monitoring and Advisory Group, which is led by 1st Battalion The Princess of Wales’s Royal Regiment (1 PWRR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Paddy Munns, from 1 PWRR, is the Officer Commanding of OCC Babaji, and in the run up to the event he assisted the AUP precinct commander with planning the concert and the necessary security measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day, soldiers from Support Company, 1st Battalion The Yorkshire Regiment (1 YORKS), provided overwatch, but security at the event was provided solely by the Babaji AUP and the day went without incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Major Craig Powers, Officer Commanding Support Company, 1st Battalion The Yorkshire Regiment, dancing with Lieutenant Esmeri at the community concert  " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5324/UK_forces_help_Afghan_police_hold_community_party-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Major Craig Powers, Officer Commanding Support Company, 1st Battalion The Yorkshire Regiment, dancing with Lieutenant Esmeri at the community concert [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Munns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was a hugely successful occasion and provided a fantastic opportunity for the police to socialise with the local population and continue to build on the developing relationship between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A gathering of this size hasn’t happened in Babaji for over 10 years, so that is some measure of the success of the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The community concert was an excellent opportunity for the AUP, and they did themselves proud by organising the event. The AUP mixed in with the locals - dancing, socialising and serving them lunch. It allowed the AUP to show the people of Babaji that they are professional, competent and are here to serve the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band was hired from Lashkar Gah by the AUP and given a police escort to the venue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mangal, the band’s frontman, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I usually play at weddings and have never performed at a police-organised party. This is the first time I have seen such an event in Babaji. This would not have been possible during the last 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among those present were the Afghan Government’s interim municipal councillor Haji Abdul Gaffoor and Lieutenant Esmeri, the commander of the Babaji police precinct. Many of the local elders were also present, highlighting the influence of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those members of ISAF present at the concert entered into the spirit of the day with Major Craig Powers, Officer Commanding Support Company, 1 YORKS, encouraging Lieutenant Esmeri to join him and others dancing in front of the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babaji is part of the Lashkar Gah district, the security for which is the responsibility of the Queen’s Royal Hussars Battle Group aided by Support Company from 1 YORKS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55743</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:33:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:33:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-us-troops-work-together-to-train-afghan-police"/>
    <title>UK and US troops work together to train Afghan Police</title>
    <summary>British soldiers and US Marines have been working closely for the past six months to improve the capability of the Afghan National Police (ANP).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teams from The Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders, 5th Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland (5 SCOTS), and the 1st Marine Division of the United States Marine Corps (USMC) have been jointly responsible for the training of the ANP in Afghanistan’s Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canterbury-based 5 SCOTS, which recruits predominantly from central and western Scotland, are now in the final weeks of a seven-month deployment to Helmand province, during which time they have fulfilled the role of Police Development Advisory Training Team (PDATT) within Task Force Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Marines from the 1st Marine Division have formed a unit known as the Provincial Police Advisory Team (PPAT) and have worked alongside the 5 SCOTS troops, making improvements in police recruiting, training and operations throughout Helmand. Both the Jocks and the Marines are based in Helmand’s provincial capital Lashkar Gah. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Colonel John Klink of the United States Marine Corps' Provincial Police Advisory Team with Lieutenant Colonel Adam Griffiths, Commanding Officer of 5 SCOTS " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5315/UK_and_US_troops_work_together_to_train_Afghan_Police-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Colonel John Klink of the United States Marine Corps' Provincial Police Advisory Team with Lieutenant Colonel Adam Griffiths, Commanding Officer of 5 SCOTS [Picture: Corporal Pete George, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the 5 SCOTS PDATT has had responsibility for policing in the key central Helmand districts of Nad ‘Ali, Nahr-e Saraj and the city centre and outlying areas of Lashkar Gah, the US Marines have worked on improving the capabilities of the provincial police headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of this recent partnership, The Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders Regimental Museum researched the regimental archives to establish whether there was any record of them working together previously and discovered that the then 2nd Battalion Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders and the US 4th Marine Regiment served together in Shanghai in China from 1932 to 1933.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Argylls were deployed to China as an emergency battalion to ‘protect the foreign area from internal disorder and to defend it against external aggression’, as their mission was given at the time. Shanghai was split into various defence sectors controlled by different countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was held by US Marines, at the time the 4th Marine Regiment. The Argylls took over a sector close to the Marines and liaison officers were established within each headquarters. Just as the Argylls and the USMC worked successfully together in the 1930s, the modern-day partnership has seen great achievements in Helmand. Confidence amongst locals in the Afghan Police has evidently grown and the ability of the police to conduct operations unaided against the insurgency in Helmand has improved markedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ANP are now taking on more and more responsibility for providing security, as well as normal day-to-day policing, in the populated areas of Helmand, from the US and UK troops based there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subtle yet critical development in the campaign against the insurgency has been increasingly to view IED emplacement and other acts of violence against UK, US and Afghan troops as criminal acts rather than acts of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing them this way puts the emphasis on the Afghan Police to take primacy in the counter-insurgency effort. As such, crime scene exploitation, evidence-handling, and deeper understanding of powers of arrest and detention are now the focus of training the police and mentoring them on their day-to-day operations. Lieutenant Colonel Adam Griffiths, Commanding Officer of 5 SCOTS and the man responsible for leading the PDATT’s efforts throughout the deployment, commented on the work his battalion has done with the US Marines throughout the tour:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has very much been a joint effort working closely to develop the capacity of the ANP and, in particular, the Afghan Uniformed Police,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen demonstrable change over the past seven months and both the Jocks, in the form of the PDATT, and the Marines, as the PPAT, have worked hard to improve the accountability, sustainability and professionalism of the police here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a thoroughly enjoyable experience working with the US Marine Corps. Our antecedent regiments have history working together and it has been a joy to rekindle that relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To acknowledge the work done together during this tour of Afghanistan, Lieutenant Colonel Griffiths presented each member of the USMC PPAT with a ‘Glengarry’, the traditional formal headdress of the Scottish infantry soldier worn on ceremonial occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, Colonel John Klink of the USMC PPAT presented the Argylls with their divisional insignia and a USMC badge of rank, representing each of the 5 SCOTS soldiers’ and officers’ own rank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the reasons behind the recent success of the ANP in Helmand, General Hakim Angar, Helmand Chief of Police said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The foremost reasons are training and education. Now policemen better understand what is required of them and how to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have imposed strict discipline amongst our ranks and have rooted out practices which are contrary to the law. As I tell the people of Helmand, ‘the police and the people are one’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55740</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:22:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:22:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-us-navies-compare-training-for-afghanistan"/>
    <title>UK and US navies compare training for Afghanistan</title>
    <summary>As British and US troops are increasingly working side by side in Afghanistan, a group of Royal Navy personnel recently crossed the Atlantic to compare and contrast pre-deployment training between the UK and America</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The six Royal Navy instructors who visited America last week are based at the Pre-deployment Training and Mounting Centre in Portsmouth. They met their American counterparts at the US Army’s combat training centre at Fort Jackson in South Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to length of deployment and type of training, the US and the UK have their own ways of doing things and it was hoped that this visit might provide a knowledge-sharing opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Portsmouth most of the instructors are Royal Marines with operational experience, whereas the US Navy sailors are taught by the Army at one of eight military bases across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK around 1,000 sailors are trained every year as Individual Augmentees (IAs) who deploy to Afghanistan on a one-in-one-out basis, whereas in the US the total is nearer 40,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IAs can be sailors trained in a wide range of skills such as logistics, admin, intelligence or operations, and are able to join units already based in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK the maximum deployment period is six months, whereas in the US it is up to a year. In both cases sailors may be required to provide support to bases on the front line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although both countries are keen to learn from each other, the ultimate goal of the training is exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="American sailors participate in the US Navy Individual Augmentee combat training course at Fort Jackson, South Carolina " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5309/UK_and_US_navies_compare_training_for_Afghanistan-03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;American sailors participate in the US Navy Individual Augmentee combat training course at Fort Jackson, South Carolina  [Picture: Mass Communication Specialist 1st Class R Jason Brunson, US Navy 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the six Royal Naval instructors who visited Fort Jackson, officer-in-charge of the Portsmouth Mounting Centre, Lieutenant Commander Pat O’Callaghan, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The courses both run on the exact same principle - to get the sailors up to the standard that is required to work with land forces on the ground in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our course is slightly longer than the US, but they both cover all the fundamental aspects of pre-deployment training - cultural awareness, counter-IED, weapon-handling, medical trauma treatment, and how to protect themselves while on foot or vehicle patrols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There were a few differences on both sides - for example we use real life amputees in our scenarios whereas they use mannequins, but the US have a very good administrative system when it comes to issuing kit which we think we may also incorporate into our practices here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a navy’s traditional role involves working with ships on the water, a deployment to Afghanistan can be challenging for some IAs. Lt Cdr O’Callaghan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is something brand new for them. They are no longer on their ships and are instead drawing on all their military skills to survive out on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mounting Centre in Portsmouth trains groups of 80 personnel 12 times a year to ensure a constant rotation in the main operating bases in Afghanistan, the forward operating bases, the headquarters in Kabul and for those mentoring the Afghan National Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first two weeks the sailors take part in SA80 rifle training where they must produce consistently tight grouping on their targets at a range of 300 metres both in normal daylight and reduced light at night - the same requirement as that of Army personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once issued with their weapon, each serviceman must make sure they are confident with all the handling aspects by repeatedly stripping, cleaning and firing the rifle as it will be their constant companion for the duration of their tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the intensive two-week weapon course, each group is then taught vital survival skills such as a smattering of the local language, medical trauma treatment, an understanding of IEDs and mines, and also how to protect themselves on foot or vehicle patrols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week then follows at Longmoor training camp in Hampshire where the sailors put their newly-learnt skills into practice on exercise around a makeshift forward operating base - taking part in foot and vehicle patrols, coping with constant ambushes, and returning fire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55739</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:15:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:15:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-us-defence-secretaries-meet"/>
    <title>UK and US Defence Secretaries meet</title>
    <summary>Secretary of State for Defence, Dr Liam Fox, met with his US counterpart, Defense Secretary Robert Gates, in London yesterday for a wide-ranging discussion on defence issues affecting both countries.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a press conference following yesterday’s meeting Dr Fox said issues covered in his meeting with Mr Gates included progress in Afghanistan, the upcoming Strategic Defence and Security Review, reform of NATO and nuclear weapons in Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox and Secretary Gates both reinforced their commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said he thought hard about the issue before accepting the position of Defence Secretary last month, concluding there is still a national security imperative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that we cannot afford Afghanistan to lapse back into a failed state which will create a security vacuum which will contaminate the region and possibly well beyond it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to seeing it through to a resolution. By that I mean creating a stable enough Afghanistan to manage its own internal and external security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said British troops would stay until Afghanistan was ‘stable enough’ to ensure internal and foreign security and the nation was run by the Afghans for the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questioned whether British forces would move from Helmand to Kandahar at some point in the future Dr Fox said that UK forces had built up a strong understanding of the terrain and personalities unique to Helmand and that a move to Kandahar would be ‘quite a leap’ which would also incur a large cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded that it would therefore be ‘highly unlikely’ that any such move would happen and it is not something the UK Government would be proposing or indeed something that ISAF Commander, General Stanley McChrystal, has proposed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he added that the nature of the effort would inevitably change over time, with Secretary Gates making clear that July 2011 was the US target for the beginning of military withdrawal, dependent on ‘conditions on the ground’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secretary Gates paid tribute to the British contribution to the ISAF effort in Afghanistan and said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;British troops are demonstrating incredible courage on the battlefields of southern Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I told Dr Fox how much we in America appreciate his nation’s leadership in this effort and I offered my condolences for the nearly 300 British troops who have been lost in the conflict, including several just this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To paraphrase a poet from the Great War, British fighting men and women have more than done their bit and… had their share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Secretary of State for Defence, Dr Liam Fox, with his US counterpart, Robert Gates, at Lancaster House in London " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5307/UK_and_US_Defence_Secretaries_meet-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Secretary of State for Defence, Dr Liam Fox, with his US counterpart, Robert Gates, at Lancaster House in London  [Picture: Harland Quarrington, Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Gates said that the international community would have to stay committed to the country for many years to come, with civilian support increasing as the need for foreign combat troops becomes less acute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran was also a key feature of the discussions. Mr Gates said he was hopeful the United Nations Security Council would pass a resolution designed to prevent Iran developing nuclear weapons ‘very soon’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox was also optimistic in that regard and warned that if Iran were to become a nuclear power it would destabilise the entire region and ‘may well be the end of the NPT [Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty] as we know it’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Dr Fox said a new UN resolution backed by the entire global community would demonstrate to the Iranian leadership how ‘serious’ the situation was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both men also said that they agreed on the need for reform of NATO and would work together to achieve their aims in this area and Dr Fox said Britain would take lessons from the US when it decides on the future of Defence in the Strategic Defence and Security Review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55733</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:59:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:59:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-italian-defence-ministers-meet"/>
    <title>UK and Italian Defence Ministers meet</title>
    <summary>The UK's Defence and Foreign Secretaries today met with their Italian counterparts at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to discuss the ongoing working relationship of the two nations as part of the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) in Afghanistan</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Liam Fox and William Hague met with Italian Defence Secretary Ignazio La Russa and Foreign Minister Franco Frattini to highlight the UK’s appreciation for Italy’s contribution in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Italian national main effort is to support ISAF with over 3,000 personnel in Three Task Forces and, as part of the reinforcement promised by the end of 2010, an additional Task Force will be deployed to southern Afghanistan, taking the manning total to 4,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deployment has already started - one Company has arrived in theatre and is conducting familiarisation training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is thanks in part to this uplift that commanders on the ground have been able to rebalance the forces in Helmand province, including the eventual redistribution of UK troops from Sangin.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italy is also deploying some additional Carabinieri to Afghanistan to strengthen police mentoring and training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of 2010, Italy will be the fourth largest contributor (with France) to ISAF, with almost 4,000 troops deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s wide-ranging discussions included agreeing the importance of the outcomes of the Kabul Conference made earlier this week and investigating how progress can be made in the mission in Afghanistan over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also discussed the UK/Italian trade relationship. Italy is one of Britain’s largest trading partners, particularly in the defence industry sector, and will be an important partner in the commitment towards inward investment which is at the heart of the UK’s economic recovery plans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55728</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:42:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:42:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/50-ied-cache-found-by-uk-and-afghan-troops-in-helmand"/>
    <title>50-IED cache found by UK and Afghan troops in Helmand</title>
    <summary>Afghan soldiers working alongside British forces have dealt a heavy blow to the insurgency in central Helmand by discovering a deadly stash of bomb-making equipment and weaponry, including 50 improvised explosive devices (IEDs).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The weapons haul, retrieved from two bomb-making factories in northern Nad ‘Ali, is one of the largest made during 16 Air Assault Brigade’s six-month tour, and came as the unit prepared to hand over command of Task Force Helmand to 3 Commando Brigade on Saturday 9 April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;38kg of explosives, rocket-propelled grenade (RPG) launchers, bomb-making paraphernalia and drugs were among the items discovered during the joint Afghan National Army and UK operation, which also involved Estonian troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Military commanders believe the action will significantly disrupt the insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Matthew Cansdale, Officer Commanding the Brigade Reconnaissance Force, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is some of the most sophisticated equipment we’ve seen, and we found a large amount of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It appears that these people were highly skilled operatives who no doubt supplied their equipment to people across Helmand. Had it been left in the hands of the insurgents, it could have had truly devastating consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Items either removed for analysis or destroyed by the ISAF and Afghan forces included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• more than 50 pressure plate IEDs &lt;br&gt;
• strips of detonator cord&lt;br&gt;
• improvised detonator initiators&lt;br&gt;
• improvised detonators&lt;br&gt;
• demolition charges&lt;br&gt;
• 38kg of homemade explosives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• RPG warheads&lt;br&gt;
• 1kg of drugs&lt;br&gt;
• a variety of live ammunition (5.56mm, 7.62mm and pistol rounds), and various tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Small arms ammunition rounds and casings seized at the bomb-making factories " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5291/50-IED_cache_found_by_UK_and_Afghan_troops_in_Helmand2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Small arms ammunition rounds and casings seized at the bomb-making factories  [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Removing IEDs before they can be laid and denying the insurgents IED-making equipment is key to bringing peace and security to areas like this,” said Major Cansdale. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is extremely pleasing to know that this operation has reduced the threat to innocent locals and to our fellow soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghan and ISAF security forces have seized numerous weapons caches throughout Afghanistan since the beginning of the year. Joint patrols discovered most of the weapons caches in the southern part of the country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to coalition forces, the weapons and bomb-making materials seized include more than 32,000 pounds (14,500kg) of ammonium nitrate, 40 pounds (18kg) of magnesium, 5,550 feet (1,700m) of detonation cord and wire, 400 mortar rounds, 150 land mines, 400 hand grenades, 60 RPG launchers with 260 warheads, and 200 pressure plates. Various small arms were also discovered, including 200 AK-47 assault rifles with nearly 40,000 ammunition rounds.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caches yielded vast amounts of IED-making material, including blasting caps, saw blades, ball bearings, hundreds of pounds of shrapnel, and two 66-pound (30kg) barrels of homemade explosives, and suicide vests, various other explosives and unexploded ordnance were also removed from enemy hands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
