<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/further-education-and-skills</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/further-education-and-skills"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/further-education-and-skills.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Further education and skills"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60884</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-graduate-apprenticeships-for-the-professions-introduced"/>
    <title>Press Release: Graduate apprenticeships for the professions introduced</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graduate and post-graduate level apprenticeships will soon be available in subjects including law, accountancy and advanced engineering, Skills Minister Matthew Hancock announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next year, changes to the Specification of Apprentices Standards for England (SASE) will mean that level six and seven apprenticeships – equivalent to bachelors and masters degree level – are available for the first time, making vocational learning an attractive alternative to the traditional higher education route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are already a number of these top-level schemes in development, including in accountancy, law and human resources. BPP Law School is looking to develop a Legal Apprenticeship pathway which could be an alternative route to the legal profession and qualification as a solicitor. It is in discussion with the relevant regulatory body and sector skills council, Skills for Justice, to progress its proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister Matthew Hancock said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past, apprenticeships were restricted to only some trades, and some parts of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now we are introducing apprenticeships in all types of jobs, including a new route to the professions, to ensure everyone can reach their potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These new apprenticeships will help more young people to receive on-the-job training at top companies like BPP Law School, ensuring a vocational route to success in accounting, insurance, and the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director of BPP Professional Apprenticeships James Hammill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to improving social mobility and diversity in the work place by opening up some of the most prestigious professions and employers to school leavers as an alternative to the traditional route. Apprenticeships are an excellent way for employers to recruit talent early and design a structured training programme that incorporates technical learning as well as invaluable work based skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BPP Law School is based in eight UK cities: Birmingham, Bristol, Cambridge, Leeds, Liverpool, London, Manchester and Swindon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60195</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluation-of-the-deepened-co-location-trials"/>
    <title>Evaluation of the deepened co-location trials</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 jobcentres that took part in joint location trials with Next Steps.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 98. Presents findings from case study visits to 8 of the 22 Jobcentres that took part in the joint location trials with Next Step (now known as the National Careers Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It highlights key issues arising from the research with a view to contributing to the success of the wider roll out of joint location in Jobcentres in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56742</id>
    <published>2012-12-16T23:15:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-16T23:15:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-quality-of-further-education-and-skills-training"/>
    <title>Improving the quality of further education and skills training</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Introducing a new FE funding system, improving teacher training and apprenticeships
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The further education (&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt;) system – the colleges and training providers that teach vocational qualifications and skills – needs to guarantee students high quality teaching and courses to help students into jobs or university and create the skilled workforce employers need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve quality and efficiency in &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; and skills training, the government is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing a new funding system based on student loans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freeing colleges from central government control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; teacher training more professional&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing better careers advice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for funding post-16 learning in England is shared between the Department for Education (16-18 year olds) and the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (19 year olds and over).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, an independent review of further education, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.education.gov.uk/publications/eOrderingDownload/The%20Wolf%20Report.pdf"&gt;the Review of Vocational Education&lt;/a&gt; made a number of recommendations including that we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move to ‘per-student’ funding instead of ‘per-qualification’ funding, to make institutions more accountable to learners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the quality of apprenticeships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government then carried out a public consultation to invite opinions on these recommendations &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/new-challenges-new-chances-next-steps-in-implementing-the-further-education-reform-programme"&gt;New challenges, new chances: next steps in implementing the further education reform programme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the responses to the consultation, the government published its plans, in December 2011, for the &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; sector in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-investment-statement-for-2011-to-2014-new-challenges-new-chances" title="New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan"&gt;New challenges, new chances: further education system and skills reform plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will shortly publish an update on ‘New challenges, new chances’. This will explain the progress we have made in reforming the further education and skills system. We have already published a number of reports and plans on aspects of the system, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-for-sustainable-growth-strategy-document"&gt;Skills for Sustainable Growth&lt;/a&gt;, which sets out the national skills strategy for England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/11-1380-further-education-skills-system-reform-plan.pdf"&gt;Our plan for further education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/s/12-p172-skills-funding-statement-2012-2015.pdf"&gt;Skills Funding Statement 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;, which contains our budget for skills and the numbers of learners it will support for the next 2 years, set out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our strategy for investing £550 million in college facilities in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/f/12-1340-further-education-college-capital-investment-strategy-plan.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; College Capital Investment Strategy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jason Holt’s independent report on apprenticeships and small businesses, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/making-apprenticeships-more-accessible-to-small-and-medium-sized-enterprises-a-review-by-jason-holt"&gt;Making apprenticeships more accessible to small and medium-sized enterprises: a review by Jason Holt&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doug Richard’s independent report for the government on the future of apprenticeships, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-richard-review-of-apprenticeships"&gt;The Richard review of apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans to set up chartered status for the further education sector, to help institutions celebrate their success and reputation, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/chartered-status-for-the-further-education-sector-proposals-to-create-a-chartered-status-scheme-for-further-education-institutions-consultation"&gt;Chartered Status for the Further Education Sector&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="government/admin/publications/48201"&gt;Chartered Status Design Competition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the report by Lord Lingfield on how the further education sector can best serve its users’ needs, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/professionalism-in-further-education-final-report-of-the-independent-review-panel"&gt;Professionalism in Further Education: final report of the Independent Review Panel&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;advice for further education colleges and training providers on 24+ Advanced Learning Loans, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.practitioners.slc.co.uk/further-education.aspx"&gt;24+ Advanced Learning Loans Student Loans Company Learning Provider Services&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://readingroom.skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/sfa/24plusall_updated_guide_and_faqs_may_2012.pdf"&gt;SFA loans FAQs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ours and our partners’ plans to ensure that young people and adults get the advice they need on learning and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-careers-service-the-right-advice-at-the-right-time"&gt;National Careers Service: the right advice at the right time&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our proposals for piloting community learning trusts, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;Community Learning Trust prospectus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our plans for engaging 16 to 24 year-olds in education, training and work, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/16-24-education-training-and-work-strategy-and-reforms"&gt;Building engagement, building futures: our strategy to maximise the participation of 16-24 year olds in education, training and work&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/21/contents/enacted" title="Education Act 2011"&gt;Education Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier for colleges to make their own decisions. It means that &lt;abbr title="Further education"&gt;FE&lt;/abbr&gt; colleges can now borrow money without needing permission from the government. Colleges can also change the way they govern themselves, and those rated ‘outstanding’ by Ofsted no longer have to face routine inspections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukces.org.uk/"&gt;UK Commission for Employment &amp;amp; Skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/"&gt;National Apprenticeship Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://nationalcareersservice.direct.gov.uk/Pages/Home.aspx"&gt;National Careers Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/the-national-careers-council"&gt;National Careers Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56468</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:47:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/24-advanced-learning-loans-monthly-briefing-edition-7-november-december-2012"/>
    <title>24+ advanced learning loans. Monthly briefing: edition 7 - November/December 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Monthly update to help colleges and training organisations prepare for the introduction of student loans. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monthly update to help colleges and training organisations prepare for the introduction of student loans. Produced jointly with the Skills Funding Agency, the Student Loans Company and HM Revenue and Customs. Explains how the loans work and the policy behind them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55331</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:21:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boosting-skills-and-jobs-on-the-south-coast"/>
    <title>Boosting skills and jobs on the south coast</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Following the Autumn Statement, Vince Cable visited Southampton to launch two schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable was in Southampton to launch two key schemes to improve skills and create sustainable employment, following on from new investment launched in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;Chancellor’s Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He visited Eastleigh College to announce a new £550 million Further Education Capital Investment Fund to help improve college facilities across the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That investment  will be targeted towards colleges in the greatest need of help to improve facilities, improve efficiency and save money in the long term. Colleges will be able to apply for funding through the Skills Funding Agency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extra £310 million for the Regional Growth Fund to create and safeguard jobs was also announced in the Autumn Statement.  To date, £2.4 billion has been conditionally offered to businesses and intermediaries up and down the country – creating jobs and boosting the local economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south coast has benefited from a number of different Regional Growth Fund projects and programmes. The Solent LEP has been awarded £2m from the Regional Growth Fund to roll out the second phase of the successful Bridging the Gap Funding programme to Southampton and the Isle of Wight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other beneficiaries of Regional Growth Fund awards for the area include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southampton City Council has been awarded a further £5.3 million Regional Growth Fund in support of the ‘Platform for Prosperity’ project bringing the total to £10.9 million. The project entails the improvement and upgrade of the road infrastructure outside Eastern Docks and is expected to create or safeguard over 800 jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cobra Precision Engineering and Elite Care Homes are two of the first recipients of £100,000 of phase one of the Solent LEPs Bridging the Gap award. The grant will leverage close to £600,000 additional private investment and create and safeguard 12 jobs at the two firms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Solent Future’s project is a £13m Regional Growth Fund money investment from Round 3. Part of the funding will be utilised to ensure a sustainable future for the Advanced Manufacturing skills in the Solent workforce. This will bring together leading businesses, colleges and Universities at a world-class training centre on the Solent Enterprise Zone. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Portsmouth Naval Base Property Trust in Portsmouth secured £1.23 million of Regional Growth Fund to support two projects within the Historic Dockyard at Portsmouth. 
£750,000 will be used to develop the Cell Block Enterprise project which will support enterprise skills development and provide access to early stage funding with mentoring managed by the University of Portsmouth. The project aims to create over 440 jobs in the supply chain. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£475,000 will contribute to the development of the International Boatbuilding Training College (IBTC) which combines heritage conservation with apprenticeships and other training to develop transferrable skills. The project has also had initial support from the Heritage Lottery Fund which could result in a final grant of £3.9 million grant to help support the development of heritage skills for the future. Both projects will have a ten year economic life cycle. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;LINKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Dec/autumn-statement-2012"&gt;BIS: Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Vince-Cable-launches-schemes-for-skills-and-jobs-on-South-Coast-68482.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Vince Cable launches schemes for skills and jobs on South Coast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-550m-capital-investment-programme-will-transform-FE-colleges-68485.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New £550m capital investment programme will transform FE colleges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://skillsfundingagency.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Skills Funding Agency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56315</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T14:59:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluation-of-the-impact-of-capital-expenditure-in-further-education-fe-colleges"/>
    <title>Evaluation of the impact of capital expenditure in further education (FE) colleges</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report commissioned by BIS evaluate the impact of capital spending on key policy goals.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no.99. Report commissioned by BIS evaluate the impact of capital spending on key policy goals. Combines quantitative and qualitative research and builds on a previous study undertaken in 2008. Focuses on completed capital spending projects by FE colleges within England (total per college) between April 2001 and September 2011. Underlying data for tables and figure in this publication is available in a machine processable format: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/dataset/impact-of-capital-expenditure-in-further-education-colleges-evaluation"&gt;underlying data on the impact of capital expenditure in FE colleges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56073</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T10:47:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/skills-funding-statement-2012-2015"/>
    <title>Skills funding statement 2012 - 2015</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Confirms the budget available for the 2013-14 financial year for the further education (FE) sector. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Confirms the budget available for the 2013-14 financial year for the further education (FE) sector. Includes information for the Skills Funding Agency to set provider allocations for the 2013/14 academic year. The government is focusing investment on high quality provision that delivers good value for money, and its focus will remain on young adults, the low skilled and those who are unemployed. See also and the FE colleges capital investment strategy (URN 12/1340).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer, George Osborne, has delivered his 2012 Autumn Statement to Parliament.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60144</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-richard-review-of-apprenticeships"/>
    <title>The Richard review of apprenticeships</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports the findings from an independent review, carried out by Doug Richard, on what an apprenticeship should be, and how apprenticeships can meet the needs of the changing economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendations include redefining apprenticeships, focusing with greater rigour on the outcome of an apprenticeship, and using recognised industry standards to form the basis of every apprenticeship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also recommends ensuring that all apprentices reach a good level in English and maths before they can complete their apprenticeship, creating the right incentives for apprenticeship training through government funding, and encouraging greater diversity and innovation in training. Follows the call for evidence URN 12/914.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56984</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/prior-qualifications-of-learners-on-train-to-gain-provision-at-level-2-and-level-3-in-2010-to-2011"/>
    <title>Prior qualifications of learners on train to gain provision at level 2 and level 3 in 2010 to 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 84. Presents the findings of research into the highest prior qualifications levels of adult learners (aged 19 and over) who undertook full level 2 or full level 3 Train to Gain learning in November 2010. Covers some of the last groups of learners to be funded under Train to Gain. Aims to better understand the extent to which investment in Train to Gain has been directed towards up-skilling individuals with lower skill levels. Also explores the profile of learners undertaking learning under Train to Gain and those undertaking their first Level 2 learning, in demographics, employment status and income, and investigates why they take up Train to Gain learning. See also reports on prior qualifications of adults in classroom based learning (URN 12/P170) and in classroom based learning (12/P170).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
