<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/g8-2013</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/g8-2013"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/g8-2013.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "UK Presidency of G8 2013"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-01T09:18:16+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60959</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"/>
    <title>The UK's G8 priorities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK's G8 Presidency will be an economic G8 that deals with big issues in the global economy and prioritises trade, tax and transparency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK takes over the one-year Presidency of the G8 today (1 January) and will hold the annual leaders’ summit in Northern Ireland on 17 and 18 June. As the chair of the G8, the UK has a unique opportunity to lead in shaping the outcomes of the summit and taking concrete action with other G8 countries to address some of the world’s most pressing challenges, including important economic and foreign policy issues of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has announced that he will focus the G8 in 2013 on 3 key areas: open economies, open governments and open societies to unleash the power of the private sector by advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="trade"&gt;Trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no greater stimulus for growth in the world economy than trade and no more important battle than the fight against protectionism. The G8 has collective responsibility to drive forward trade liberalisation. Among G8 countries work is already on going to prepare a free trade agreement between the EU and Canada and work will start next year to begin free trade negotiations between the EU and Japan and the EU and US. An EU-US free trade agreement would be particularly significant – the EU and US together make up nearly a third of all global trade and an ambitious deal between the two could provide an enormous boost to jobs and growth. The G8 leaders’ summit will be an opportunity to show the importance of this ongoing work and to agree how to accelerate progress across our common trade priorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tax"&gt;Tax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will focus on strengthening international tax standards and working on greater international tax information exchange to tackle tax havens.  This will build on work that is already underway in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) and maintain the momentum set by the G20. And we will work with developing countries to enable them to collect tax that is due to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transparency"&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 has a long history of advancing the development agenda - and the UK’s G8 Presidency will be no different. The UK is meeting its commitment to spend 0.7 per cent of its gross national income on aid from 2013 and will hold other countries to account for their promises too. With this track record on aid, the Prime Minister plans to use the G8 Presidency to support the ‘golden thread’ of conditions that he sees as critical to the growth and prosperity of countries across the world. These include the absence of conflict, clamping down on corruption and ensuring strong and accountable government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency and accountability are vitally important to achieve these conditions. Too often, development at the G8 has been about rich countries doing things to poor countries. But at Lough Erne the G8 will focus on getting its own house in order and helping developing countries to prosper in the process. An example of this is mineral wealth. It’s important that developing countries rich in minerals see this as a blessing not a curse. The UK is already leading efforts in the EU that will require oil, gas and mining companies to publish key financial information for each country and project they work on. The UK’s G8 Presidency will push for greater transparency all around the globe so that revenues from oil, gas and mining are transparent. This should encourage greater accountability and ensure money doesn’t fuel conflict and corruption, but instead is used to provide better public services for citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined action on trade, tax and transparency during the UK’s G8 Presidency could lay the foundations of long-term growth and prosperity for generations to come and will support the development of open economies, open governments and open societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will also make progress across a range of vital global issues, including foreign policy challenges and supporting Arab Spring countries. The UK’s Presidency will also build on the Olympic Hunger Summit and the US’s New Alliance for Food Security and Nutrition, leading the way in the battle against hunger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this year the UK will also produce a comprehensive accountability report (CAR) that will show progress against key commitments made by the G8. The report is a concrete example of transparency and accountability at work, a central theme of the UK’s G8 Presidency, and an opportunity to hold G8 leaders to account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.linkedin.com/today/post/article/20121121130535-146036479-eyes-of-the-world-on-uk-again-for-g8-summit"&gt;Read the Prime Minister’s recent article on the G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60960</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:17:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue"/>
    <title>Lough Erne: G8 venue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year's G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2013 the UK will hold the Presidency of the G8. As part of the year-long Presidency there will be a G8 Summit of the 8 global leaders in June. The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year’s G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, in Northern Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing the G8 to Lough Erne will showcase to the world a modern Northern Ireland with huge potential for investment and tourism, demonstrating the growing confidence that exists in this part of the UK. It will highlight what Northern Ireland, its people and its businesses have to offer the global community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The venue of Lough Erne 2013 was also chosen because it creates the right conditions to encourage open and frank discussions between the G8 leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to welcoming my fellow leaders to Lough Erne and to showcase Northern Ireland to the world as a modern and dynamic part of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Northern Ireland’s transformation over the last 2 decades was made possible by the courage of so many people across sections of the community. Their determination and leadership has inspired the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60958</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:16:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/what-is-the-g8"/>
    <title>What is the G8?</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The G8 is a forum that brings together 8 global leaders to address global issues and tackle the most pressing global challenges.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The G8 (Group of 8) is made up of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Russia, the USA and the UK. The EU is represented by Jose Manuel Barroso, the President of the European Commission, and Herman Van Rompuy, the President of the European Council. The Presidency of the G8 rotates each calendar year and the country holding the G8 Presidency is responsible for hosting and organising the annual summit, with a number of preparatory meetings leading up to it. The summit is an opportunity for G8 leaders to have frank and open discussions about the important global issues of the day. In 2013 it will be the UK’s turn to shape the G8’s approach to these discussions with G8 leaders holding each other to account and agreeing concrete steps to advance growth and prosperity across the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="history-of-the-g8"&gt;History of the G8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1973 the world experienced its worst economic crisis since the Great Depression. The finance ministers of the USA, UK, France and West Germany met informally to talk about how they could solve the economic problems linked with the oil price shock. In 1974 Japan was invited to the meetings and in 1975 the French President brought these informal discussions to the leaders. He also invited Italy to what was the first G6 in Rambouillet, France. There was no army of political advisers in tow, just the leaders in a relaxed and private setting. This low-key formula was very successful and the leaders agreed to meet annually. A year later Canada joined and after the collapse of the Soviet Union, Russia became a full member in 1998. The EU has been part of the group since 1977, but does not hold a Presidency. Almost 40 years on, the G8 countries can provide guidance and stability in an unpredictable world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-presidency-involve"&gt;What does the Presidency involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 Presidency runs for 1 calendar year and rotates among the 8 member countries. The country chairing the Presidency is responsible for shaping the issues that leaders discuss at the G8 Summit and hosts a number of preparatory meetings leading up to the summit. It also acts as the spokesperson for the G8. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Presidency is an opportunity for the UK to influence the international debate on our global priorities, which include tax, trade and transparency. At the end of this year, the UK will hand over the Presidency to Russia for 2014. The Presidency will continue in its rotation to Germany in 2015, Japan in 2016, Italy in 2017, Canada in 2018, France in 2019, and the USA in 2020 before it returns to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-g8-do"&gt;What does the G8 do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 is a forum that provides the opportunity for its members to co-operate in addressing global challenges. The standards it sets, commitments it makes and steps it takes aim to drive prosperity and economic growth all over the world. Prime Minister David Cameron has said that this year the G8 will return to its roots, creating the right environment for frank and open discussions to promote growth and address global economic problems. There will be a short declaration aimed at holding G8 leaders to account and ensuring that good intentions become vital actions to advance growth and prosperity across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60961</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:14:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"/>
    <title>G8 events</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During the UK G8 Presidency 2013 there will be events in addition to the leaders' summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="g8-foreign-ministers-meeting"&gt;G8 foreign ministers’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 and 11 April 2013, the Foreign Secretary William Hague will host his counterparts from the G8 countries. They will meet for the G8 foreign ministers’ meeting at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to the UK’s G8 Presidency making headway on the serious challenges facing our global community today. Today the Prime Minister explained that by supporting the development of open economies, open governments and open societies we can harness the power of the private sector for everyone’s benefit. Our G8 priorities of advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency can only take place in an environment of political stability and peaceful international relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With my G8 foreign minister partners, I look forward to discussing and taking decisions on some of the most pressing foreign and security policy issues that we face. In particular I will be focusing on the Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative, a personal priority for me during the UK’s G8 Presidency and beyond, and ensuring that the G8’s Deauville Partnership provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g7-finance-ministers-and-central-bank-governors-meeting"&gt;G7 finance ministers’ and Central Bank governors’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 to 11 May 2013, the Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne and the Governor of the Bank of England Sir Mervyn King will host a spring meeting of the G7 finance ministers and Central Bank governors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Chancellor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to hosting colleagues from the G7 to Britain in the spring. This group remains an important institution and a key forum in which to grapple with the challenges that face the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This meeting will be a significant opportunity for the UK and our partners to take on these challenges and to show leadership in the fight to tackle the ongoing ramifications of the global financial and debt crisis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g8-leaders-summit"&gt;G8 leaders’ summit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G8 leaders’ summit will take place on 17 to 18 June 2013 at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue" title="Lough Erne Venue"&gt;Lough Erne in County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
