<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/higher-education</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/higher-education"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/higher-education.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Higher education"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61122</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-commenting-on-the-latest-ucas-2013-cycle-applicant-figures"/>
    <title>Press Release: Commenting on the latest UCAS 2013 cycle applicant figures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Department for Business, Innovation and Skills spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is too early to form a definitive picture about university applications for the 2013/14 academic year. Traditionally fewer than 50 per cent of applicants have submitted their applications by this point in the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that no one is put off applying to university because they do not have information about the student support available to them. Most new students will not pay upfront, there will be more financial support for those from poorer families and everyone will make lower loan repayments than they do now once they are in well paid jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/7150</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/widening-participation-in-higher-education--4"/>
    <title>Widening participation in higher education</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Encouraging more people from disadvantaged backgrounds to go to university</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-issue"&gt;The issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with the ability who wants to go to university should have the chance to do so, whatever their economic or social background. The government wants to get more young people from disadvantaged backgrounds into higher education – in particular into the country’s most selective universities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re providing financial support to help young people from low income families go to university so that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;students from families earning £25,000 or less get a full grant to help with living costs &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;under our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/widening-participation-in-higher-education--4/supporting-pages/the-national-scholarship-programme"&gt;National Scholarship Programme&lt;/a&gt;, universities will offer extra financial help to students from disadvantaged backgrounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Universities and colleges that charge the highest amounts - between £6,000 and £9,000 for full-time students – must now offer students more financial support under an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.offa.org.uk/access-agreements/"&gt;access agreement&lt;/a&gt;, which outlines what they will do to attract and support students from disadvantaged backgrounds. Universities will offer bursaries and other financial support, and carry out outreach work such as partnering with schools in disadvantaged areas of the country. Universities have to set up an agreement with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.offa.org.uk/"&gt;Office for Fair Access (OFFA)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2010 we published the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/coalition-documents"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, which stated our aim to ‘attract a higher proportion of students from disadvantaged backgrounds’ into higher education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2010 an independent review of the higher education funding system, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-browne-report-higher-education-funding-and-student-finance"&gt;Higher Education Funding and Student Finance in England&lt;/a&gt;, recommended increasing access to the UK’s top institutions for students from low income backgrounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review recommended that any university that charges higher tuition fees should increase financial support for students from low income families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2011 we carried out a consultation, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/higher-education-students-at-the-heart-of-the-system--2"&gt;Higher Education: students at the heart of the system&lt;/a&gt;, on whether to implement the reforms of the review, Higher Education Funding and Student Finance in England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the outcome of the consultation in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/higher-education-students-at-the-heart-of-the-system-and-new-regulatory-framework-for-higher-education-government-responses-to-consultations"&gt;Government response: students at the heart of the system&lt;/a&gt;. This outlines plans to increase financial support for students from low income families, through schemes such as the  &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-scholarship-programme-year-1"&gt;National Scholarship Programme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/7143</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-higher-education-system-more-efficient-and-diverse"/>
    <title>Making the higher education system more efficient and diverse</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Introducing a financially sustainable funding system and a diverse, competitive sector with a wide range of providers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure the system for funding universities is financially sustainable. We think this can be achieved by asking graduates - the people who benefit most from higher education - to pay more towards their education than they have in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to ensure higher education institutions provide innovative, high quality learning. We believe the way to do this is by making institutions compete to attract students and the funding they bring with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-higher-education-system-more-efficient-and-diverse/supporting-pages/introducing-a-financially-sustainable-funding-system-for-he"&gt;creating a new funding system for higher education&lt;/a&gt;, where graduates contribute more to their education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-higher-education-system-more-efficient-and-diverse/supporting-pages/creating-a-single-regulatory-system-for-publicly-funded-and-private-providers"&gt;creating a more diverse, competitive higher education sector&lt;/a&gt; by reviewing the way alternative providers can access funding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2010 the government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/coalition-documents"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt; stated our aim to create a more sustainable way of funding higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Independent Review of Higher Education Funding and Student Finance identified 3 problems with the existing funding system: the need for financial sustainability, wider participation and higher quality. Its report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/corporate/docs/s/10-1208-securing-sustainable-higher-education-browne-report"&gt;Securing a Sustainable Future for Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;, published in October 2010, looked at the case for a number of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The options considered were: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do nothing (keep current system with no reduction in government funding)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut the number of students &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce government funding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The June 2011 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/i/11-1050-impact-assessment-students-at-heart-of-system"&gt;Impact assessment: higher education - students at the heart of the system&lt;/a&gt; gives full details of these options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in June 2011 we ran a consultation, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/h/11-944-higher-education-students-at-heart-of-system"&gt;Higher Education: Students at the heart of the system&lt;/a&gt;, on proposals to create a more sustainable way of funding higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in June 2012 we published our response to the consultation: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/g/12-890-government-response-students-and-regulatory-framework-higher-education"&gt;Government response to consultation on students at the heart of the system.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently consulting on &lt;a href="NEEDS%20LINK"&gt;applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses&lt;/a&gt;. The deadline for responses is 23 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/8/contents"&gt;Higher Education Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; enabled universities to set their own tuition fees, known as ‘variable tuition costs’, which were introduced from academic year 2006 to 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1998/30/contents"&gt;Teaching and Higher Education Act 1998&lt;/a&gt; gives the Secretary of State power to make annual regulations setting out the support available to students going into higher education, and how and when student loans will be repaid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since academic year 2006 to 2007 a loan to cover the full cost of tuition has been available to eligible students studying at publicly funded providers, which is repaid only after the student has secured employment. This means that no eligible student is required to pay for their tuition up front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact-assessment"&gt;Impact assessment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010 we carried out an impact assessment on our proposals for higher education funding and student finance: &lt;a href="LINK%20NEEDED"&gt;Interim impact assessment: urgent reforms to higher education funding and student finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partner-organisations"&gt;Partner organisations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.offa.org.uk/"&gt;Office for Fair Access (OFFA)&lt;/a&gt; - an independent body that promotes fair access to higher education by monitoring ‘access agreements’. All English universities and colleges that want to charge higher fees must have an ‘access agreement’, which outlines what each institution will do to attract and support students from disadvantaged backgrounds &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/"&gt;Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE)&lt;/a&gt;, which administers public money for higher education teaching and research to universities and colleges. HEFCE helps ensure accountability and promotes good practice in the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.slc.co.uk/"&gt;Student Loans Company (SLC)&lt;/a&gt; - a non-profit making organisation that provides loans and grants to students in universities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.oiahe.org.uk/"&gt;Office of the Independent Adjudicator for Higher Education (OIA)&lt;/a&gt; - an independent body that runs a student complaints scheme in England and Wales&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ucas.ac.uk/"&gt;UCAS&lt;/a&gt;, which manages applications to higher education courses in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.qaa.ac.uk/Pages/default.aspx"&gt;Quality Assurance Agency for Higher Education (QAA)&lt;/a&gt; - an independent body that assures standards and improves the quality of higher education&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56392</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:19:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/further-education-fe-college-capital-investment-strategy"/>
    <title>Further education (FE) college capital investment strategy</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Outlines the government’s priorities for capital funding plans for the remainder of this Parliament in further education colleges</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outlines the government’s priorities for capital funding plans for the remainder of this Parliament and aspirations for future capital investment in further education (FE) colleges. Sets out key priorities, and it encourages colleges to develop coherent property strategies capable of a phased implementation to maximise the impact of capital grant availability. Also includes some FE college capital project case studies. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47199</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/applying-student-number-controls-to-alternative-providers-with-designated-courses"/>
    <title>Applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on the process of applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation aims to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to provide an overview of the shape and purpose of the new system for alternative providers that wish their students to be able to access student support from the Student Loans Company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to seek responses to specific proposals on student number controls, where we are consulting on options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to invite views, particularly from alternative providers, on aspects of how this will operate in practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher education white paper &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/h/11-944-higher-education-students-at-heart-of-system.pdf"&gt;Students at the heart of the system (PDF, 711 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; (June 2011) set out the government’s vision for how the higher education sector in England should become more diverse and responsive to the needs of students. A key plank of that strategy is to reduce the barriers which may artificially restrict the growth of alternative provision. Over time we wish to create a more level playing field of regulation between similar providers. As part of that process we are reforming the system of designation for student support purposes for alternative providers. We have been careful to set appropriate conditions to improve student protection while minimising bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/g/12-890-government-response-students-and-regulatory-framework-higher-education.pdf"&gt;Government response to the higher education white paper and associated technical consultation (PDF, 375 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;, published June 2012, stated that we would consult on the process of applying student number controls to alternative providers who have courses designated for student support purposes. This is part of a review of the existing course designation system for alternative providers, including introducing more robust and transparent requirements on quality assurance, financial sustainability and management and governance. An overview of our plans for the new course designation system is contained in chapter 1, with chapter 2 focusing on the student number control aspect of the new system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/a/12-1292-applying-student-number-controls-consultation.pdf"&gt;Applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses: consultation (PDF, 154 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/a/12-1292rf-applying-student-number-controls-form.doc"&gt;Applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses: consultation response form (DOC, 408 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56614</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/applying-student-number-controls-to-alternative-providers-with-designated-courses-consultation"/>
    <title>Applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses: consultation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respond by 23 January 2013. Consultation seeking views from higher education providers on controlling student numbers where they have courses designated for student support purposes. It aims to provide an overview of the new system for alternative providers that wish their students to be able to access student support from the Student Loans Company, to seek responses to specific proposals on student number controls, and to invite views on aspects of how this will operate in practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48213</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/applying-student-number-controls-to-alternative-providers-with-designated-courses-consultation-response-form"/>
    <title>Applying student number controls to alternative providers with designated courses. [Consultation] response form</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respond by 23 January 2013. Template for responses to consultation on controlling student numbers where they have courses designated for student support purposes (URN 12/1292).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61117</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:26:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ten-institutions-on-track-to-become-universities"/>
    <title>Ten institutions on track to become universities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will lead to the single biggest creation of universities since 1992. It follows the Government’s announcement in June that red tape barring some smaller institutions from being awarded the title of ‘university’ would be removed. Previously, institutions needed a minimum of 4,000 students to become a university. This has now been reduced to 1,000.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applicants being put forward to the Privy Council for formal approval are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Arts University College at Bournemouth &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bishop Grosseteste University College Lincoln &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harper Adams University College&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leeds Trinity University College &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newman University College, Birmingham &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norwich University College of the Arts &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Agricultural College &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University College Birmingham &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University College Falmouth &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University College Plymouth St. Mark &amp;amp; St. John &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These well-known and highly-regarded university colleges represent over 1,200 years of history between them. It is right to remove the barriers preventing high-quality higher education providers like these calling themselves universities simply because of their size.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that they have taken up the opportunity offered by our reforms. This will lead to the biggest creation of universities since 1992 and will enable more people to realise their aspiration of going to a university.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Westwood, Chief Executive of GuildHE, the organisation that represents the 10 institutions, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The minister’s recommendation that ten institutions have met the criteria to become universities recognises the quality, diversity and tradition that they bring to UK higher education.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Smaller and specialist institutions are long established - in most cases for longer than many UK universities - and often lead the league tables in areas such as teaching and employability. They also have a strong reputation and impact in their localities and sectors - contributing to economic growth and to stronger, more vibrant communities. Gaining university title is long overdue and it helps to provide greater choice for students and for businesses, while enhancing the quality and diversity of the UK’s higher education sector as a whole.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to advise the Privy Council to grant the institutions university title was made after careful consideration of their applications and advice from the Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government first proposed reducing the minimum number of students necessary to obtain university title from 4,000 to 1,000 in the 2011 higher education white paper, &lt;em&gt;Students at the heart of the system&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Notes to editors:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**1. **UNIVERSITY TITLE: CRITERIA AND PROCESS  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;**&lt;/em&gt;Criteria  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**An organisation wishing to apply for approval to use the title “university” must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have been granted powers to award taught degrees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Normally have at least 1,000 full time equivalent higher education students, of whom at least 750 are registered on degree courses (including foundation degree programmes), and the number of full time equivalent higher education students must exceed 55 percent of the total number of full time equivalent students &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be able to demonstrate that it has regard to the principles of good governance as are relevant to its sector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;**Process  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**The process for obtaining UT for institutions under Privy Council oversight is as follows:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applicant applies to the Privy Council for approval of a particular title. In exercising the power to consent to a change in any name the Privy Council must have regard to the need to avoid names which are or may be confusing  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applicants need to show evidence that the title they have selected is not confusing. They will be expected to have consulted stakeholders on their proposed title. The application should enclose the results of the consultation, together with proposed amendments to the institution’s governing documents  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Privy Council Office will seek advice from BIS, who assess the institution’s suitability for UT by judging it against the criteria listed above  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BIS will in turn seek advice from HEFCE on the student numbers and governance criteria. HEFCE will advise on student numbers through analysis of Higher Education Statistics Agency data and on governance issues will refer to recent audits of the institution’s framework of internal control, focusing on governance processes, audit arrangements, strategic and financial management arrangements, risk management processes, financial forecasts and sustainability frameworks   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the SoS considers that the institution meets the criteria for UT and that the proposed name is not confusing, BIS will write to the Privy Council Office advising them to approve amendments to the institution’s governing documents relating to a name change, thereby approving the title  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An organisation will only become a university when the Privy Council or Her Majesty the Queen approves its actual title by order or by letter.”  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work is underway across Government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the Government wants the economy to travel.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BIS’s online newsroom contains the latest press notices and speeches, as well as video and images for download. It also features an up to date list of BIS press office contacts. See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/newsroom"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/newsroom&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-information"&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Name
    BIS Press Office
Job Title&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Division
    Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills
Phone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fax&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email
    &lt;a href="mailto:bispress.releases@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;bispress.releases@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Name
    Emma Griffiths
Job Title&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Division
    Department for Business, Innovation and Skills
Phone
    020 7215 5982
Fax&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email
    &lt;a href="mailto:Emma.Griffiths@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Emma.Griffiths@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56270</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tracking-the-decision-making-of-high-achieving-higher-education-applicants"/>
    <title>Tracking the decision-making of high achieving higher education applicants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 86. Presents findings from research into the decision-making process of high achieving A level students. Analyses the attributes of high achieving applicants to higher education (HE) in comparison to the attributes of the wider applicant population. Examines the factors that contribute to the decision-making process of high achievers, and uses these to frame the admissions experiences of those who applied to the most selective HE and those who did not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56322</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-on-the-process-and-criteria-for-assessing-student-numbers-and-good-governance-for-non-hefce-funded-organisations-wishing-to-apply-for-the-title-of-university-and-university-college"/>
    <title>Guidance on the process and criteria for assessing student numbers and good governance for non-HEFCE funded organisations wishing to apply for the title of university and university college</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains how to apply for university and university college title, and the required report(s) on student numbers and/or good governance as part of a self-certification process. Intended for non-Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE) funded institutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
