<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/housing</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Housing"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16044</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:40:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/increasing-protection-for-homeowners"/>
    <title>Increasing protection for homeowners</title>
    <summary>Eric Pickles announces new safeguards to protect homeowners from having their homes taken by the council if they're left empty for while.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today announced that homeowners will be protected from having their homes taken against their wishes by councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect civil liberties, Mr Pickles has introduced powerful safeguards to restrict the use of Empty Dwelling Management Orders. Legislation came into force today that means people who leave their house empty for more than 6 months no longer risk having it seized by their local authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the previous government introduced Empty Dwelling Management Orders. They allowed councils to take over properties that had been empty for as few as 6 months even if they weren’t boarded up or where the occupant had died. Furniture and possessions were often taken and councils could even seize the property when it was for sale if they thought the asking price was unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers will now be limited to empty properties that have become magnets for vandalism, squatters and other forms of anti-social behaviour - blighting the local neighbourhood. A property will have to stand empty for at least 2 years before an Empty Dwelling Management Order can be obtained, and property owners will have to be given at least 3 months’ notice before the order can be issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils have previously used the orders to instigate action against homeowners that is inappropriate, including against people in vulnerable situations. Councils have, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempted to use the powers against a homeowner while she was caring for her injured daughter in France &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taken action against the house of a 96-year old howeowner as soon as he passed away in a nursing home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taken action against a divorcee, who faced action because he only lived in the property at weekends to visit his estranged children&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These new safeguards will ensure that responsible homeowners do not face having their properties seized. Mr Pickles said it is wrong that a bereaved family could face having their loved one’s home seized for a period if there is a delay in them deciding what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“An Englishman’s home is his castle and I’m proud to be able to help homeowners protect theirs from councils who are too draconian and heavy-handed in using their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government is standing up for the civil liberties and property rights of hard-working people. Those suffering the loss of a loved one should not have to endure the added indignity of having their home seized because of a delay in them deciding what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why I’ve introduced these safeguards that mean the rights of responsible homeowners will be protected, while allowing action to be taken against genuine derelict buildings which blight neighbourhoods.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move comes on top of government plans to bring back into use many of the 300,000 properties in England that have been empty for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils now have a new incentive to bring empty properties back into use through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, under which the government will match the Council Tax raised from any Council Tax collected from a property that previously stood empty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12712</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/offering-suitable-housing-to-homeless-people"/>
    <title>Offering suitable housing to homeless people</title>
    <summary>A consultation on the proposed draft Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 enables local authorities to end the main homelessness duty by arranging an offer of suitable accommodation in the private rented sector, without requiring the applicant’s agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed draft Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012 sets out those circumstances in which accommodation used for the private rented sector offer to end the main homelessness duty is not to be regarded as suitable.  It also looks at how best to strengthen requirements in relation to location and suitability, when local authorities secure accommodation for the use of households owed duties under the homelessness legislation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12789</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/english-indices-of-deprivation"/>
    <title>English indices of deprivation</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks user views on plans for the English indices of deprivation. Responses to this consultation will help inform the content, guidance and outputs of the indices, alongside other sources of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12788</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/evaluating-the-extent-of-rough-sleeping"/>
    <title>Evaluating the extent of rough sleeping</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document describes a set of proposed changes to the existing rough sleeping guidance. It also gives users of the rough sleeping figures and those involved in evaluating the scale of rough sleeping in their local area an opportunity to comment on the proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a public consultation and the Department for Communities and Local Government particularly welcomes responses from local authorities and the voluntary sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12775</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/new-homes-bonus"/>
    <title>New Homes Bonus</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the implementation of the &lt;em&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/em&gt; - which will provide a powerful, simple, transparent and permanent means of incentivising local authorities to increase their housing supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This follows the coalition agreement to provide incentives for local authorities to deliver sustainable development, including for new homes and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12759</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/leasehold-valuation-limits"/>
    <title>Leasehold valuation limits</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper contains proposals and the associated impact assessment for updating the property value limits which are used to determine whether certain rights are available to residential long leaseholders. These are rights for such leaseholders to remain in their properties as assured tenants when their lease comes to an end, to extend the lease of their leasehold house or to purchase the freehold of a leasehold house (enfranchise) on particular terms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12714</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-better-deal-for-mobile-home-owners"/>
    <title>A better deal for mobile home owners</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes a number of reforms to the park homes sector, aimed at tackling a number of complaints made by residents of some mobile home site operators. These can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking an owner’s sale of their home - without justifiable reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees, breaching site rules and stopping owners from improving their homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures are designed to ensure site operators who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already whilst the rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring compliance with site licence conditions by enabling the courts to impose unlimited fines on operators who do not manage their sites properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing local authorities to make a reasonable charge on site operators for their licensing services, which they are currently unable to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving local authorities the power to carry out works on sites in an emergency or where the site operator has been found guilty of a breach of the licence, and charge the cost back to them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the rules around the sale of mobile homes so that unscrupulous operators cannot interfere with owners selling to a qualifying buyer who they have chosen; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing legislation to improve other residents’ rights to reflect their status as home owners by, for example, allowing them to carry out home improvements without seeking permission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14476</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <summary>A statement of the impact that the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15152</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:52:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-allocation-of-housing-and-homelessness-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations</title>
    <summary>Letter to local housing authorities about the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations which came into force on 8 November 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2588/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 8 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations amend &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1294/contents/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) Regulations 2006&lt;/a&gt; in order to maintain the Government’s policy on eligibility for social hog and homelessness assistance in relation to non European Economic Area nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is making these amendments following a ruling in the Court of Justice of the European Union in the case of Zambrano (C-34/09).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wrote to chief housing officers about the new regulations on 17 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:36:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk announces new rules to house homeless people and help cut waiting lists.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
