<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/housing</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Housing"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64090</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-social-tenants-to-have-their-say-on-local-services"/>
    <title>Support for social tenants to have their say on local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk today launched a new training programme designed to put power firmly in the hands of social tenants.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He launched the £1.2 million Tenant Training and Support Programme to give residents the skills they need to hold their landlord to account, whether on their own, by setting up a tenant panel, or by taking over the management and maintenance of their homes and neighbourhoods themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boost in funding will offer a way for residents to ensure they get the service they deserve and that landlords offer the best possible value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said this new training programme would empower residents to take the first crucial step to having the necessary know-how to use their powers and take control in their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="empowering-tenants"&gt;Empowering tenants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/"&gt;Tenant Participation Advisory Service&lt;/a&gt;, the programme offers advice, training and support to tenants by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing tenants together from different neighbourhoods to discuss their experiences and inspire new tenant panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping individual tenants to engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offering face-to-face training with expert advisors for around 5,000 tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a tenant training programme to help them make the most of the powers they have, from accredited courses to local training systems and e-learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By doing this, new and existing social tenants will be equipped with the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be able to sign up to Community Cashback, which enables tenants to take over the management of their neighbourhood, from overseeing maintenance and minor repairs to signing up new contractors to run cleaning services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country want to use the powers they have to ensure their needs are reflected in the services they receive. But many simply lack the confidence to challenge the people in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why we’ve put this new tenant training scheme in place, helping make their voices heard and giving people the skills they need to ensure the changes that matter to them are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by playing this enhanced role tenants can help landlords improve the efficiency of local services and their work will help inspire even more communities to take control.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Meakin, Tenant Participation Advisory Service chair said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is exactly the programme we’ve all been waiting for. I urge any tenant who wants to be involved and make a difference in their community to get in touch and take advantage of the free support and training on offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples-of-effective-tenant-involvement"&gt;Examples of effective tenant involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helena Partnerships&lt;/em&gt; has set up the tenant-led customer excellence panel to challenge their landlord on performance and service delivery. It sets its own review programme, commissions mystery shoppers and has unfettered access to Helena’s performance and complaints information, customer surveys, activity-based costing and customer insight data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel carries out tenant-led peer reviews and hosts a series of webinars to engage with other organisations involved in scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works closely with Helena’s young inspectors - a group of under 25’s who play an active role in testing and challenging services while gaining transferable skills for employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel’s work has been responsible for a number of practical changes to Helena services to reflect the needs of tenants and delivered value for money savings, including tailored rent statements, extended repairs appointment times and changes to the complaints service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tower Hamlets, &lt;em&gt;Poplar HARCA&lt;/em&gt; (8,500 homes) is committed to helping social tenants to play a key role in their local housing. Recognising the benefits of tenant empowerment, the association enables democratically elected residents to monitor services on each of the association’s 12 estates, where they have delegated budgets enabling them to make community improvements. Additionally, tenant board members scrutinise the association’s policies and initiatives, challenging senior managers and making recommendations for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents can also use their local knowledge to try to resolve complaints about the association’s services. A youth empowerment board has been set up, comprising 30 young people drawn from across the estates, to ensure that the views of young people are heard. In total, over 300 residents are directly involved in decision making, performance monitoring and complaints handling at the association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding of almost £1.2 million will be made to the Tenant Participation Advisory Service to deliver a training and support programme. For further information on the programme visit their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/tenantcentral"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow DCLG’s Tenant Empowerment Team on Twitter (&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/TenantPower"&gt;@TenantPower&lt;/a&gt;) for all the latest news and updates on this programme and other activities to empower the lives of social tenants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61041</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T10:01:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/make-it-your-new-year-s-resolution-to-help-get-rough-sleepers-off-the-streets"/>
    <title>Make it your New Year’s resolution to help get rough sleepers off the streets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>People setting their New Year’s resolutions can now pledge to offer practical help to rough sleepers in 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk urged anyone wanting to get help for someone sleeping rough to use the new StreetLink hotline and website to ensure they are put in touch with the local agencies offering it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that while people want to offer help to those facing homelessness, they often don’t know where to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But StreetLink, run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway with support from the government, offers a “valuable alternative” to a cash handout for people sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those looking to offer help can call 0300 500 0914 or go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk" title="StreetLink"&gt;www.streetlink.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; to put those facing sleeping rough in touch with local charities and councils who can them get them long-term support and safe accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued this new and innovative service helps support the No Second Night Out initiative as it is extended across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London, where No Second Night Out has been adopted, 70% of rough sleepers have not spent more than one night on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The New Year offers many of us an opportunity to make a new start - StreetLink offers that opportunity to those facing the prospect of living on our streets and a valuable alternative to simply a cash handout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge anyone looking to set themselves a New Year’s resolution to use this service to ensure people sleeping rough in their area get the support they need to get off the streets and into a stable home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;Mark Prisk on rough sleeping and Streetlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/60136</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T13:00:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T13:00:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2"/>
    <title>Improving the rented housing sector</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>We're improving the quality and quantity of social homes for rent and encouraging investment in the private rented sector. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 1.8 million households on waiting lists for social housing. We must ensure people can get accommodation that meets their needs both in terms of quality and cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is improving the quality and quantity of properties for rent, both in the private and social sector. We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/social-housing-reform"&gt;allowing local flexibility&lt;/a&gt; on waiting lists, the types of tenancies and social tenants’ and landlords’ rights and responsibilities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping social landlords stop &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/social-housing-fraud" title="Social housing fraud"&gt;tenancy fraud&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/anti-social-behaviour-in-housing"&gt;anti-social behaviour&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing more affordable housing, including through a new model of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/providing-affordable-homes-for-rent"&gt;affordable rent&lt;/a&gt; that allows registered housing providers to charge no more than 80% of local market rent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/housing-revenue-account-reform-self-financing"&gt;housing revenue account subsidy system&lt;/a&gt; to a new, fair, locally controlled system where local authorities are responsible and accountable for their housing services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;funding local authorities to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/decent-homes-refurbishing-social-housing"&gt;refurbish their housing stock&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting tenants to play a bigger role in managing their accommodation through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/tenant-empowerment-programme"&gt;tenant empowerment programme&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging more investment in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt; through schemes like new loan guarantees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 21 November 2011, the Prime Minister, Deputy Prime Minister, and Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England,&lt;/a&gt; which set out the government’s actions to address the housing shortage, boost the economy, create jobs, and give people the opportunity to get on the housing ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We published a consultation on reforming social housing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-fairer-future-for-social-housing" title="A fairer future for social housing"&gt;Local decisions: a fairer future for social housing&lt;/a&gt; on 22 November 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New guidance for allocating social housing, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/allocation-of-accommodation-guidance-for-local-housing-authorities-in-england" title="Allocation of accommodation: guidance for local housing authorities in England"&gt;Allocation of accommodation: guidance for local housing authorities in England&lt;/a&gt; was published on 5 January 2012 to accompany changes in the Localism Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 9 June 2011 we published an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-rent-impact-assessment--2" title="affordable rent impact assessment"&gt;affordable rent impact assessment&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-rent-full-equality-impact-assessment--2" title="Affordable rent: full equality impact assessment"&gt;full equality impact assessment.&lt;/a&gt; This shows the costs and benefits of providing affordable housing under the new model as part of the Affordable Homes Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/" title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) is the national housing and regeneration agency for England (other than in London). It was established as an non-departmental government body on 1 December 2008. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s role includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with partners to  create homes, economic growth and jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing investment, including the Affordable Homes Programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;economic regulation of housing associations, safeguarding £43 billion of taxpayer investment in the sector and helping to secure more private investment for affordable housing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60137</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-200-million-build-to-rent-fund-will-boost-housebuilding"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk: £200 million Build to Rent fund will boost housebuilding</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new £200 million fund will boost the construction of new homes specifically for private rent, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Build to Rent fund aims to cut the risk for developers more traditionally used to building homes for sale who are looking to branch out into building homes for private rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By financing the construction of rental homes until they are built, let out and managed, the fund will give developers the freedom to build homes specifically for that market with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management companies will have the chance to invest in these new rental developments, and developers will then repay the investment from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the new fund, the Housing Minister described it as yet another step to support housebuilding which will help boost the economy, create jobs and strengthen the housing market by providing people with a broader housing choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reviving-the-rental-market"&gt;Reviving the rental market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that Build to Rent follows recommendations contained in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment" title="Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment"&gt;Montague report&lt;/a&gt; into rented homes earlier this year and will help address the varying level of quality across the nation’s private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of private rental landlords are small-scale, individual investors. This fund will redress the balance, by stimulating the market in private rented homes for large-scale housing organisations that will in turn help set a new benchmark for landlords across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kickstart this new, larger scale market for privately rented homes, the minister said that Build to Rent will fund ‘demonstration’ projects to show how it might work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expert taskforce will also work to boost investor awareness of the fund and offer practical support to those interested in this new market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A healthy rental housing market must have a broad range of choice across the board. But for it to grow and develop, we must first attract new investors. The Build to Rent fund will support this, helping to build homes specifically for private rent and breathing new life into the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by driving this market in housebuilding, the fund will also help create new jobs, build the homes that families need and local people want, and support economic growth across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor of London Boris Johnson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The private rented sector now houses a quarter of Londoners and has the potential to support the delivery of a huge number of new homes in the future. I welcome this funding and I will continue to make the case that investment in London’s housing infrastructure is one of the best ways to deliver much needed construction jobs and economic growth now, while at the same time laying the foundations for our economic growth for years to come.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greater London Authority will lead on assessing the expressions of interest for sites in London. Shortlisting decisions will be made by DCLG, the Homes and Communities Agency and the Greater London Authority. The Homes and Communities Agency will undertake due diligence, contracting and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £200 million Build to Rent Fund is now open for bids, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/private-rented-sector" title="Build to Rent Fund prospectus"&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt; has been published on the HCA website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fund has been developed to support purpose built, private rented demonstration schemes across England which have the potential to attract investors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/56814</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:51:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:51:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/ebbsfleet"/>
    <title>Ebbsfleet</title>
    <category>Case study</category>
    <summary>Over the next 20 years, more than 20,000 new homes will be built at Ebbsfleet, Kent, with builders on site as early as summer 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 29 August, the Department for Communities and Local Government announced a support package to unlock 22,600 new homes at Ebbsfleet, Kent over the next 20 years. Developers, Land Securities, have invested over £100 million in developing the site. However, plans have been delayed amid concerns over the cost and the need for further investment in transport improvements.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kent County Council and Dartford and Gravesham Borough Councils worked closely with the department, and with Department for Transport and the Highways Agency to reduce costs of the transport programme and to agree how funding could be unlocked.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, builders could be on site as early as summer 2013 with the first homes set to be completed by December 2013. The first phase of 1,500 homes at Eastern Quarry is expected to be completed by 2020, with a further 3,000 homes ready by 2030 to 2031. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern Quarry forms part of longer term plans which are expected to unlock the development of 22,600 homes and around 1 million metres squared of commercial development across the Kent Thameside region over the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/56810</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:49:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:49:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/cranbrook"/>
    <title>Cranbrook</title>
    <category>Case study</category>
    <summary>The new Cranbrook community in East Devon, has the capacity to deliver 6,000 new homes between 2012 to 2026.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Cranbrook community in East Devon, has the capacity to deliver some 6,000 new homes over the period 2012 to 2026. Almost a third of all housing required in the wider Exeter area is directly dependent on the successful delivery of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 1 of the development is already underway, funded by a £12 million repayable grant from a revolving infrastructure fund (RIF) managed by the Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) and being repaid on a roof tax basis. Using this funding the developer (the Cranbrook New Community Consortium) can build 1,120 homes by 2015, along with building the main access route into Cranbrook, the Clyst Honiton Bypass and a primary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investment"&gt;Investment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government investment of £20 million will provide: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£10 million for a new secondary school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£4 million for a second primary school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£6 million for infrastructure and services to create a new high street for the town centre and commercial areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This investment will ensure continuity of the scheme, securing the delivery of phase 2, while putting in place the capacity for up to 6,000 homes on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government’s investment, subject to due diligence, will directly unlock phase 2 and provide the infrastructure and school facilities that will give local partners the confidence to build an additional 2,380 homes by 2019.  It will also enable the developer to put in place enough infrastructure to support 6,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the housing, government investment will help create the confidence to bring forward the new town centre and support the realisation of the full ambition for the scheme. It will also provide employment (1,500 jobs) and retail space.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/56801</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:48:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:48:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/get-britain-building-bath-riverside"/>
    <title>Get Britain Building: Bath Riverside</title>
    <category>Case study</category>
    <summary>On the banks of the River Avon, the regeneration of Bath Riverside will transform Bath's western river front into a residential quarter.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set on the banks of the River Avon, the regeneration of this site has started to transform Bath’s western river front into a modern residential quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crest Nicholson is creating a vibrant new community of more than 2,000 homes, with some available for private sale, through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/affordable-home-ownership-schemes/first-buy-equity-loans"&gt;FirstBuy&lt;/a&gt; equity loan scheme, and for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="getting-on-the-ladder"&gt;Getting on the ladder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FirstBuy initiative helps first time buyers get a foot on the property ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FirstBuy is jointly funded by developers and the government, and works by enabling buyers to own their own home by only paying 80% of the purchase price. At Bath Riverside a 20% top up loan is offered by Crest Nicholson and the government, and buyers need a deposit of just 5% of the purchase price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Cocks, 25, had nearly given up hope of buying his own home until he became aware of FirstBuy on the properties already completed at Crest Nicholson’s Bath Riverside development. He has now moved in to his 1-bedroom apartment at the scheme and is relishing his new-found independence and the security of home ownership in Bath’s newest community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was living with my parents in Bradford-on-Avon but I have a 4 year old son who stays with me every other weekend, so that wasn’t an ideal situation”, explains Ben, who works in higher education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I had been renting previously, but it was impossible to save for a deposit while paying rent. I heard about the FirstBuy scheme after reading about it in the local press late last year, and noticed that it was available at Bath Riverside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without the FirstBuy scheme I would have found it pretty much impossible to get on the housing ladder,” said Ben. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unlocking-development"&gt;Unlocking development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also supporting developers with access to much needed finance through the Get Britain Building programme. Up to 16,000 homes on stalled sites across England will be built by March 2015 thanks to this programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second construction phase of 240 homes is currently underway, which has been supported by £2.8 million of investment from the Get Britain Building programme. A recoverable investment, the programme helps developers access finance, and to help bring forward marginal sites by sharing risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is run by the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;). Executive director Colin Molton said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bath Riverside is one of the most important developments in the South West, and I am pleased that we’ve been able to help keep Bath building and create quality new homes and safeguard jobs in the area.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A biomass central energy system, 2 new public parks, bike storage and easy access to the city centre along the towpaths, and brown and green roofs demonstrate the developer’s commitment to sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the support provided through Get Britain Building, the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; also invested around £2 million in vital infrastructure work which unlocked the first phase of development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/56796</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/get-britain-building-carlisle-park"/>
    <title>Get Britain Building: Carlisle Park</title>
    <category>Case study</category>
    <summary>Nearly 400 homes are set to be built on the site of a former tar distillery thanks to Gleeson Homes and HCA investment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new community of nearly 400 homes is set to be built on the site of a former tar distillery thanks to Gleeson Homes and investment from the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Croda Tar Distillery, on the border between Kilnhurst and Swinton, closed in the early 1990s. Over the past 2 decades the 31 acre site has lain derelict with the heavily contaminated site proving a challenge for developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2010 Gleeson identified the site, which is adjacent to the Sheffield &amp;amp; South Yorkshire Navigation Canal, as having great potential for new low cost homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with Rotherham Borough Council and remediation specialists, work is now underway to clean up the site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the clean-up has been completed Gleeson Homes will begin to transform the area into 381 new 2, 3 and 4 bedroom homes.  The developer will be making use of £2.2 million of investment from the Homes and Communities Agency’s (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Get Britain Building programme to start the first phase of 125 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craig Johns, Area Manager at the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development at Carlisle Park offers a real choice of quality homes to local residents where they want to live at a price they can afford. Our investment will ensure that a local firm will provide these homes which will help safeguard jobs in South Yorkshire.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development will feature a mix of first time buyer and family homes, set among public open space and children’s play areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Gamble, Gleeson Homes Group Land Director said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted that Carlisle Park is part of the Get Britain Building programme. The programme will help us to deliver the first tranche of 125 new homes which are built and priced to suit local people.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The project will also have a positive effect of the wider community with the creation of new jobs, apprenticeship opportunities for local young people and investment back into the local area.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recoverable investment, the Get Britain Building programme helps developers access finance, and to help bring forward marginal sites by sharing risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to 16,000 homes on stalled sites across England will be built by March 2015 thanks to this programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/57065</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:43:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:43:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/get-britain-building-herons-reach"/>
    <title>Get Britain Building: Heron's Reach</title>
    <category>Case study</category>
    <summary>The Get Britain Building programme is delivering new homes, safeguarding jobs and contributing to economic growth in Heron's Reach.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Difficult conditions in the local housing market caused building work at Heron’s Reach, a former mill near Saddleworth Oldham, to stall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help get work back on site, family-owned developer Wiggett Homes successfully applied for £1.5 million of development finance from the Get Britain Building programme. Work on the 41 homes began in August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites with just 15 homes could apply for the recoverable investment to restart their mothballed sites, and the programme was designed particularly to help small and medium-sized businesses (SMEs) get the necessary finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is being managed by the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) on behalf of the Department for Communities and Local Government. The programme is expecting to provide between 12,000 and 16,000 homes by March 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiggett Homes was the first &lt;abbr title="small and medium-sized business"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; in England to exchange contracts and restart work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phil Wiggett, a chartered surveyor by profession who set up Wiggett Construction in 1979, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Heron’s Reach development stalled some time ago so we’re pleased that the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is supporting us to deliver these 41 new homes. Work is underway on the next phase of construction which is a major boost to the economic regeneration of the area and will create new jobs and apprenticeships for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Trading has been difficult in these recessionary times and private housing for sale is still slow, but there is the odd green shoot and footfall is improving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Almost at the peak of the boom the company acquired a site at Knoll Mill, Greenfield, Saddleworth, near Oldham. With the land bought at the height of the market, the slow sales and falling house prices meant building work at the site stalled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now that we have sold the first phase of 16 new homes, and having been successful with Get Britain Building funding, workers are back on site and these new homes will be ready by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wiggetts has been impressed with how the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; dealt with the Get Britain Building funding. The people we dealt with had an in-depth knowledge of the industry, were very professional and dealt with our application quickly with the result that we are now back on site.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Executive Director for the North West, Deborah McLaughlin added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is great news that work is continuing at this vitally important project, which is delivering much needed high quality new homes and jobs for Oldham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s good to see that the Get Britain Building programme is delivering new homes, safeguarding jobs in our area and contributing to economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56906</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T14:39:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-funding-to-unlock-delivery-of-12-000-new-homes"/>
    <title>Government funding to unlock delivery of 12,000 new homes</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New government support for large housing sites will unlock the delivery of new homes and create thousands of jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intervention will accelerate building on 2 large sites in East Devon and near Milton Keynes; unlocking development and bringing forward construction to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £20 million injection of funding for the new town of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/cranbrook"&gt;Cranbrook&lt;/a&gt;, near Exeter, will enable local partners to bring forward the delivery of new homes included in the local plan, and create 1,500 jobs in the town that will include 6,300 homes and a new rail station with links to London and Exeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money will also unlock construction of a new high street and transport infrastructure needed to develop the town centre, as well as 2 new schools in the next phase of development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cranbrook, the minister met local construction apprentices who would work on the scheme. He said the government’s investment would create jobs for young people and bring a powerful economic boost to the area, while giving the consortium behind the new town the confidence and resources to drive forward its completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk with construction apprentices" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5640/Mark-Prisk-meets-apprentice.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk meets apprentices who will work on the new town at Cranbrook&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also revealed that the construction of 6,000 new homes on the Fairfield development in Milton Keynes will also be brought forward without the need for direct funding, following discussions with the developer behind the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intervention builds on the deal made earlier this year for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/ebbsfleet"&gt;Eastern Quarry&lt;/a&gt; development near Ebbsfleet in Kent, a site for over 22,000 homes, bringing total number of potential homes unlocked through these schemes to over 34,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the minister also pledged support for housing programmes near Wokingham, where £2.5 million will enable local partners to solve key transport issues in the town in order to unlock the potential for over 10,000 new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the government is making strong progress to boost house building despite the difficult economic circumstances, and he was in discussions with other schemes across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is serious about building more homes. That’s why we have been looking carefully at how we can accelerate large, planned housing schemes that already have the support of local people, but need help to move forward in the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I’m delighted that today I can announce our intervention will unlock the delivery of 12,000 new homes, and create thousands of jobs for local people. In the months ahead I will be announcing support for similar schemes. That means more investment, more jobs for our young people and more affordable homes for families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have set aside considerable funding to assist large housing programmes like Cranbrook, and I would urge anyone with similar proposals to come forward and contact my department.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East Devon District Council Leader Councillor Paul Diviani said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a unique opportunity here to create Cranbrook’s town centre as a shining exemplar of how all town centres can function!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Currently the town centre is a blank canvas; we are not restricted by existing buildings or street formations. With support from central government our vision of a town centre that is vibrant, attractive, welcoming, the beating heart of the new community, can become a reality much sooner than previously expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement is the first allocation of £225 million, earmarked by the Chancellor in last week’s Autumn Statement, for the delivery of 50,000 new homes in large, locally-supported housing programmes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding programme for planned, large-scale sites, administered by the Homes and Communities Agency, will be targeted at schemes that could deliver real benefits to their communities, but are struggling to move forward because the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside funding to unlock new construction, the schemes will receive a package of support, including help to facilitate close co-operation with the local council and community during planning and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-on-public-land"&gt;Progress on public land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said an expert review published today also demonstrates the government is taking the right steps to quickly release its previously-used, surplus land for building new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the recommendations in the report, led by the chairman of Berkley Group, Tony Pidgley, are already shaping measures being taken forward by the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date enough land has been sold to build up to 33,000 new homes, and last week’s Autumn Statement included a £290 million fund for the Home and Communities Agency to introduce measures that will quickly bring forward new sites for development, such as installing the right infrastructure so the land can be used for building new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Pidgley, chair of the Expert Advisory Panel said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a golden opportunity to deliver growth and great places. It’s surplus public land. It doesn’t need new legislation. All that’s required is a simple system to dispose of the land, alongside investment in infrastructure, and then the private sector can get on with building these much needed homes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further reaction to the funding support for Cranbrook: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the consortium partners - Hallam Land, Persimmon Homes and Taylor Wimpey - Mike Owen, project manager for Cranbrook, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were privileged to give Mark Prisk a tour of the development which gave him an insight into the brand new community being created. From the very start the development of Cranbrook has been about partnership and this announcement of funding support for phase 2 continues that process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without this phase 2 Cranbrook would have been delayed at the end of phase 1. Instead, we have certainty in the delivery of phase 2, we can move ahead now and commit with confidence to the next key stages of the project and delivering further community infrastructure and bringing forward much needed private and affordable homes. The success of Cranbrook to-date has been underwritten by the amenities and infrastructure that we have been able to provide. In turn this has enabled the creation a real community from day one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Will Mumford, Chair of Exeter and Heart of Devon Growth Board and cabinet member for Economy, Enterprise and Employment, Devon Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Cranbrook has been recognised for its successful delivery and for the additional funding to enable us to bring phase 2 forward. This keeps the project momentum going, will secure additional jobs and investment and is a resounding vote of confidence in the partnership approach.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Molton, Homes and Communities Agency Executive Director for the South and South West, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government has shown its commitment to housing and development as a major route to driving economic growth and we welcome the confidence ministers have shown in our ability to deliver its key initiatives, supported by new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s welcome news also that Cranbrook is rightly identified as a vanguard project which will help drive economic growth in the south west, by providing the essential investment needed to deliver the second phase of the project. This is a huge opportunity, and I know that our partners will grasp it to maximise delivery of new homes and growth in Exeter and East Devon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public land review published today can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/news&amp;amp;newsArticleID=6604&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;Berkley Group website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269488244/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
