<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/housing</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/housing.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Housing"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56640</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-funding-to-unlock-delivery-of-12-000-new-homes"/>
    <title>Government funding to unlock delivery of 12,000 new homes</title>
    <summary>New government support for large housing sites will unlock the delivery of new homes and create thousands of jobs, Mark Prisk announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intervention will accelerate building on 2 large sites in East Devon and near Milton Keynes; unlocking development and bringing forward construction to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £20 million injection of funding for the new town of Cranbrook, near Exeter, will enable local partners to bring forward the delivery of new homes included in the local plan, and create 1,500 jobs in the town that will include 6,300 homes and a new rail station with links to London and Exeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money will also unlock construction of a new high street and transport infrastructure needed to develop the town centre, as well as 2 new schools in the next phase of development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cranbrook, the minister met local construction apprentices who would work on the scheme. He said the government’s investment would create jobs for young people and bring a powerful economic boost to the area, while giving the consortium behind the new town the confidence and resources to drive forward its completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk with construction apprentices" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5640/Mark-Prisk-meets-apprentice.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk meets apprentices who will work on the new town at Cranbrook&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also revealed that the construction of 6,000 new homes on the Fairfield development in Milton Keynes will also be brought forward without the need for direct funding, following discussions with the developer behind the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intervention builds on the deal made earlier this year for the Eastern Quarry development near Ebbsfleet in Kent, a site for over 22,000 homes, bringing total number of potential homes unlocked through these schemes to over 34,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the minister also pledged support for housing programmes near Wokingham, where £2.5 million will enable local partners to solve key transport issues in the town in order to unlock the potential for over 10,000 new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the government is making strong progress to boost house building despite the difficult economic circumstances, and he was in discussions with other schemes across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is serious about building more homes. That’s why we have been looking carefully at how we can accelerate large, planned housing schemes that already have the support of local people, but need help to move forward in the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I’m delighted that today I can announce our intervention will unlock the delivery of 12,000 new homes, and create thousands of jobs for local people. In the months ahead I will be announcing support for similar schemes. That means more investment, more jobs for our young people and more affordable homes for families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have set aside considerable funding to assist large housing programmes like Cranbrook, and I would urge anyone with similar proposals to come forward and contact my department.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East Devon District Council Leader Councillor Paul Diviani said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a unique opportunity here to create Cranbrook’s town centre as a shining exemplar of how all town centres can function!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Currently the town centre is a blank canvas; we are not restricted by existing buildings or street formations. With support from central government our vision of a town centre that is vibrant, attractive, welcoming, the beating heart of the new community, can become a reality much sooner than previously expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement is the first allocation of £225 million, earmarked by the Chancellor in last week’s Autumn Statement, for the delivery of 50,000 new homes in large, locally-supported housing programmes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding programme for planned, large-scale sites, administered by the Homes and Communities Agency, will be targeted at schemes that could deliver real benefits to their communities, but are struggling to move forward because the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside funding to unlock new construction, the schemes will receive a package of support, including help to facilitate close co-operation with the local council and community during planning and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-on-public-land"&gt;Progress on public land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said an expert review published today also demonstrates the government is taking the right steps to quickly release its previously-used, surplus land for building new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the recommendations in the report, led by the chairman of Berkley Group, Tony Pidgley, are already shaping measures being taken forward by the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date enough land has been sold to build up to 33,000 new homes, and last week’s Autumn Statement included a £290 million fund for the Home and Communities Agency to introduce measures that will quickly bring forward new sites for development, such as installing the right infrastructure so the land can be used for building new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Pidgley, chair of the Expert Advisory Panel said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a golden opportunity to deliver growth and great places. It’s surplus public land. It doesn’t need new legislation. All that’s required is a simple system to dispose of the land, alongside investment in infrastructure, and then the private sector can get on with building these much needed homes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further reaction to the funding support for Cranbrook: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the consortium partners - Hallam Land, Persimmon Homes and Taylor Wimpey - Mike Owen, project manager for Cranbrook, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were privileged to give Mark Prisk a tour of the development which gave him an insight into the brand new community being created. From the very start the development of Cranbrook has been about partnership and this announcement of funding support for phase 2 continues that process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without this phase 2 Cranbrook would have been delayed at the end of phase 1. Instead, we have certainty in the delivery of phase 2, we can move ahead now and commit with confidence to the next key stages of the project and delivering further community infrastructure and bringing forward much needed private and affordable homes. The success of Cranbrook to-date has been underwritten by the amenities and infrastructure that we have been able to provide. In turn this has enabled the creation a real community from day one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Will Mumford, Chair of Exeter and Heart of Devon Growth Board and cabinet member for Economy, Enterprise and Employment, Devon Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Cranbrook has been recognised for its successful delivery and for the additional funding to enable us to bring phase 2 forward. This keeps the project momentum going, will secure additional jobs and investment and is a resounding vote of confidence in the partnership approach.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Molton, Homes and Communities Agency Executive Director for the South and South West, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government has shown its commitment to housing and development as a major route to driving economic growth and we welcome the confidence ministers have shown in our ability to deliver its key initiatives, supported by new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s welcome news also that Cranbrook is rightly identified as a vanguard project which will help drive economic growth in the south west, by providing the essential investment needed to deliver the second phase of the project. This is a huge opportunity, and I know that our partners will grasp it to maximise delivery of new homes and growth in Exeter and East Devon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public land review published today can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/news&amp;amp;newsArticleID=6604&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;Berkley Group website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56673</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:29:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-backs-new-rough-sleeping-helpline"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk backs new rough sleeping helpline</title>
    <summary>A new national hotline and website will connect rough sleepers with local help.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone looking to help rough sleepers this winter should contact a new service to get them long-term support, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke at the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt;, a new national hotline and website service that connects rough sleepers with the local help and advice they need to get off the streets and get their lives back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="StreetLink poster" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2025/streetlink_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said that while many want to help the people they see sleeping rough, they don’t know what to do. So the government has supported homelessness charities Homeless Link and Broadway to develop this new service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that StreetLink offers concerned members of the public a better option than handing out money or food, by directing rough sleepers to the help they need, and providing them with a “hand up, not a hand out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this service, the public can now turn their concern into practical action and take a direct step to help rough sleepers change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister urged people across the country to get behind StreetLink and call if they see someone in need this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the nights getting colder, many people will be wondering how they can help when they see someone facing a night on the streets. StreetLink will give them the chance to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new service will help rough sleepers across the country to connect with their local services, offering the help and advice they need to get back on track. So save the StreetLink number, 0300 500 0914, onto your phone, download the app or bookmark the webpage today. Your action could help a rough sleeper get out of the cold and into long-term support.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;StreetLink video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/54937</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:00:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-summit-to-end-rough-sleeping"/>
    <title>National summit to end rough sleeping</title>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister Mark Prisk on the launch of StreetLink and successful local steps to end rough sleeping.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of year, when the cold weather bites, it’s natural that people are concerned when they see people sleeping on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as you know better than most, this is not just an issue at Christmas; it’s a year-round problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it is not enough to offer a helping hand just during the season of good will. To really make a difference, we need to tackle the causes of rough sleeping, all the year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-action"&gt;Government action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the problems we face today, is a lack of affordable homes in the housing market. A market in which, for 15, maybe 20 years, we have seen just half the homes we actually need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, when this government came to power, we committed to building more homes, and more affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means unlocking substantial investment of £19.5 billion so we’re able to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes over this Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means a significant expansion of the private rented sector, to give tenants much greater choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it’s a sector that has often been overlooked, which is why we asked Sir Adrian Montague to carry out an independent review of the sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve now adopted his excellent report with a clear commitment, to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, so that we can deliver more new homes for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s often a debate about whether to focus on owner occupied homes, or the private rented sector, or affordable housing. But we need to deliver in all 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want there to be a bigger, better housing market, capable of providing people with more quality and more choice at affordable prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are building more homes, but we’re also determined to address all the issues that drive people towards homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we protected £400 million of funding, for tackling and preventing homelessness, over 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because homelessness is caused by the convergence of different problems, my predecessor Grant Shapps established the Ministerial Working Group that, for the first time, regularly brings ministers together from across Whitehall - from Health and Welfare, to Justice and even Defence - because we need to look at all the links between homelessness and for example, mental health, as well as some of the unique challenges which people face if veterans or former prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="homelessness-prevention"&gt;Homelessness prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve put the right building blocks in place, and today I want to discuss how else we’re moving forward, not least by focussing on prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular the new approach, through StreetLink to stop people slipping through the net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means tackling the underlying problems. And, (if people do turn to sleeping rough), early intervention to ensure they are swiftly helped off the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why, (on top of the £400 million funding for tackling homelessness), we announced an additional £70 million last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extra cash is ensuring vulnerable single people, (a high risk group), get early access to good housing advice, to prevent them becoming homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also looking to boost hostel provision, and supporting the national roll out of ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now after a really encouraging pilot in London (which we were able to support), this initiative is proving essential in ensuring people do not become caught up in a pattern of sleeping rough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s proved effective at providing a rapid response to new rough sleepers, by ensuring that no one has to sleep out for a second night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, tackling problems early is fundamental to the scheme’s success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m pleased that the momentum for ‘No Second Night Out’ is growing, with several more authorities adopting the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merseyside was quick off the mark, being the first area outside London to introduce their own initiative last February. 6 local authorities are now working in partnership, to really put an end to persistent rough sleeping they’ve had to endure right across the Liverpool city region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a commendable achievement and an example to other authorities - and you will hear more about how they delivered this when Councillor Anne O’Byrne speaks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="streetlink"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are many people beyond government (and the professionals) who also want to help. Often they see people sleeping rough, but they are not quite sure what they can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re concerned that giving money isn’t the best solution, but don’t know where else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, as a government, we decided to support your sector to develop a new approach, with the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk/"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt; today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how will it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for the general public StreetLink provides a central point of contact, that people who want to help rough sleepers can call. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minute anyone sees someone on their local street or town centre sleeping rough in their neighbourhood, they will be able to contact StreetLink and provide details on a confidential and secure basis, so vulnerable people can be found and connected to local services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the new approach is that it’s easy to use. StreetLink will be contactable by phone on 0300 500 0914, by using the website, the mobile website accessible by smartphone, or by using the StreetLink ‘app’, available for iphones and android devices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You maybe concerned that it’s difficult to do, but if I can get it on my mobile (and my wife will confirm), anyone can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it won’t just be about reporting problems: members of the public will also be able to see what action has been taken. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll be able to ask for email feedback from local services about the outcome of the information they’ve provided, and see the outcomes of their referrals on the StreetLink website, on a Google map that they can search by location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the first time, the public will be able to judge for themselves whether rough sleeping is being taken seriously and tackled effectively in their locality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does it mean for service providers - local authorities and your sector? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By involving the public, it will mean your outreach teams can help more people, because you will have better intelligence about what’s happening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homeless Link tell me that every local authority has agreed to accept referrals, with some already receiving and acting on the details provided by the public through the website, which has been live for over two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also supports your approach to helping rough sleepers. You, more than anyone, know that they need a hand-up, not just a handout. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the public will now be able to turn their concern into practical, effective action, and take a direct step to help vulnerable adults change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - it will help link up the different services helping rough sleepers. Callers in an area with a ‘No Second Night Out’ initiative or other rough sleeping helpline will be transferred directly to that scheme. In other areas StreetLink will refer the details to the local authority or local outreach team for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a smart, joined-up way of tackling the problem, and will have truly national coverage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to pay tribute to Homeless Link and Broadway for its development, using the support from government. It’s real partnership in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, most of us will struggle to understand what it is like to sleep on the streets. That’s why, when people see rough sleepers, they want to reach out and help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to engage with this issue, and ensure the right intervention is made, as early as possible. We need to break the habit to help people to turn their lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this must be a collaborative effort - including local authorities and the voluntary and charity sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me say a big thank you to all of you for the vital work you do. It’s tempting for the media to think it’s just a Christmas issue, but it’s 365 days a year. You are part of the reason we have one of the best safety nets in the world, to prevent and tackle homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted that, from today, StreetLink will strengthen this safety net. Everyone will now have an easy and effective way of helping change the lives of those who have been on the fringe, for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more to do, but I’m confident that, together, we can make a real difference to thousands of people, who are real in need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <summary>The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has appointed two non-executive members following open competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50195</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:04:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-boost-to-councils-and-communities-through-the-new-homes-bonus"/>
    <title>Boost to councils and communities through the New Homes Bonus</title>
    <summary>The New Homes Bonus scheme pays over £1 billion to councils backing growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Council efforts to get Britain building are to be rewarded with a multi-million pound &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus" title="New Homes Bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, Housing Minister Mark Prisk announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share a cash payout of £661 million, after delivering 142,000 new homes, including 58,000 affordable properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding also rewards councils for bringing 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s provisional allocation, to be paid in the 2013 to 2014 financial year, means councils will have received £1.3 billion through the New Homes Bonus scheme since its launch in April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This total recognises over 400,000 new builds and conversions, and over 50,000 empty properties being brought back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued that the New Homes Bonus had proved critical in ensuring communities see the benefit of housing growth in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For years, developers found themselves at loggerheads with communities unconvinced that their plans for growth would benefit them. But the New Homes Bonus is turning this around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The £1.3 billion paid out to councils to date has meant that now local people are able to see the rewards of new developments in their area - paving the way for thousands of much-needed, locally-supported homes to be delivered across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="getting-britain-building"&gt;Getting Britain building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils across the country have made the most of this additional funding to directly benefit their local communities. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Tyneside Council, which has allocated some of its New Homes Bonus funding towards a £3.1 million revamp of a library which overlooks a Georgian square in the heart of North Shields. The library scheme forms part of the regeneration of the square, which also includes the refurbishment of properties, bringing it back into residential use for the first time in decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warwick Council, which has entered in a 10-year partnership with the Waterloo Housing Group to deliver new affordable homes in the area, with all New Homes Bonus payments generated by additional new homes built recycled back into the scheme to deliver additional housing and bring empty homes back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uttlesford District Council is allocating some of its new Homes Bonus to fund a hi-tech shelter for teenagers in a new play park at Carver Barracks. Those using the shelter can generate their own power through crank handles located around the room, with the energy generated able to support the use of Bluetooth and MP3 players. The idea for the project came from a committee - The Rowney Community Park Fund - made up of soldiers’ wives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A full list of provisional allocations of New Homes Bonus for the 2013 to 2014 financial year can be found &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/28978/121210_Provisional_allocations_New_Homes_Bonus.xls" title="New Homes Bonus provisional allocations 2013 - 2014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/43074</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T11:54:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T11:54:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes"/>
    <title>Increasing the number of available homes</title>
    <summary>We're helping to get Britain building again, through schemes like the NewBuy Guarantee, New Homes Bonus and loan guarantees for developers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, there have not been enough homes to meet the needs of our growing and ageing population. From 2009 to 2010, only 115,000 new-builds were completed in England – fewer than any year in peace time since the 1920s and nearly a quarter of a million homes in England have stood empty for more than 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The housing market is also one of the biggest casualties of the 2008 global credit crunch and the government’s priority has been to rectify a situation where lenders couldn’t lend, so builders couldn’t build and buyers couldn’t buy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government wants builders, investors and local councils to increase the supply of both new-builds and repurposed empty homes. The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) schemes listed here should act together to increase housing supply by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;removing unnecessarily complex regulations &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing finance for projects that can’t proceed without it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping buyers who can’t afford to buy a home because they can’t afford the deposit &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve created a £570 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/get-britain-building" title="Get Britain Building"&gt;Get Britain Building&lt;/a&gt; investment fund for developers. This will help to build new homes on development sites that have stalled, haven’t started or are classified as being on hold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve identified enough formerly used, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/bringing-surplus-public-sector-land-back-into-use" title="Bringing surplus public-sector land back into use"&gt;surplus public sector land&lt;/a&gt; to support up to 100,000 new homes and are looking to sell this quickly to help get Britain building. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.savills.co.uk/contact/research-results.aspx?currentSitePageId=141274&amp;amp;keyword=case+for+housing&amp;amp;date=&amp;amp;country=" title="Savills: The Case for Housing: The impact of house building on the UK economy"&gt;2010 report by property group, Savills&lt;/a&gt; estimated that this could add 1% to the output of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus" title="New Homes Bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;. This is a grant to local councils for increasing the number of homes and their use. We are also pursuing other actions to bring &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes" title="Empty homes"&gt;empty homes&lt;/a&gt; back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also offering new loan guarantees for housing developers that are backed by government to encourage the building of more &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/providing-affordable-homes-for-rent" title="Providing affordable homes for rent"&gt;social&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector"&gt;privately rented&lt;/a&gt; housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re reducing regulations on house builders to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively"&gt;make the planning system more efficient and effective&lt;/a&gt;, and are offering finance options to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes" title="Self-builders"&gt;self-builders&lt;/a&gt; from a specially created fund of £30 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We help community groups to build new homes through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; which became law on 6 April 2012. It is now easier to bring vacant and underused public land back into use through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-reclaim-land" title="Community Right to Reclaim Land"&gt;Community Right to Reclaim Land&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also promoting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/community-led-design" title="Community-led design"&gt;community-led design&lt;/a&gt; which should lead to more building schemes being approved by local councils. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re helping buyers with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy Guarantee scheme&lt;/a&gt;, which started in March 2012 and allows buyers to get a mortgage on a new-build homes with only a fraction of the deposit they would normally require. More than 40 housing developers and 6 major lenders now offer the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils can also use &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/private-finance-initiatives" title="Private finance initiatives"&gt;private finance initiatives&lt;/a&gt; for housing refurbishment and regeneration, where other grants or funding wouldn’t have been enough to make the changes needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 21 November 2011 we published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;‘Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England’.&lt;/a&gt; This explained our plans to reform the housing market, including measures to stimulate house building and bring empty homes back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ran a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/new-homes-bonus" title="New Home Bonus"&gt;consultation on the design of New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt; between 12 November and 24 December 2010, receiving 470 responses. The final scheme design was published on 17 February 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, the government also consults local councils on the provisional allocations of New Homes Bonus, which are published towards the end of each calendar year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Build was introduced by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act 2011.&lt;/a&gt; The Act means that more decisions about housing are taken locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; works closely with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/" title="Home Builders Federation"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt; to find ways to encourage house building. We work with them on developing policy, particularly on NewBuy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cih.org/" title="Chartered Institute of Housing"&gt;Chartered Institute of Housing&lt;/a&gt; represents 22,000 housing professionals who work mostly in local councils, housing associations, arms-length management organisations and the private sector. They work with government to help ensure that housing policy takes into account the experience and expertise of their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukgbc.org/" title="UK Green Building Council"&gt;UK Green Building Council&lt;/a&gt;  is a membership organisation campaigning for a sustainable built environment. We work with them to develop environmental building standards and regulations to achieve zero carbon targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/" title="National Housing Federation"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; to develop and deliver policy on housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/" title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/a&gt; is the national housing and regeneration agency for England (other than in London). It plays an important role in increasing the supply of available homes, such as helping to bring empty homes and surplus public sector land back into use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18802</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T10:22:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-investment-in-local-growth-to-continue"/>
    <title>Government investment in local growth to continue</title>
    <summary>The Chancellor has announced a package of measures in his Autumn Statement that will help the department continue to boost local growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures will enable the country to build new homes, deliver key infrastructure and support vital jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new £474 million Local Infrastructure Fund that will support investment in key local projects will open up new development, including locally supported large housing sites and bring surplus public land back into use, delivering much needed new homes, businesses, infrastructure and local transport schemes. Plus a further £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures announced in the Autumn Statement and the September Housing and Planning package will support delivery of up to 120,000 homes. There will also be cash injections for local areas through a £1.5 billion borrowing arrangement for local enterprise partnerships and more money for the Regional Growth Fund. While small firms will continue to receive larger business rate tax breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-investment-in-local-infrastructure"&gt;New investment in local infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £225 million will be used to accelerate delivery of locally supported large housing sites, supporting around 50,000 homes. There are many locally supported large housing schemes in the development pipeline that can provide real benefits to local communities that are struggling to move forward because of the current economic circumstances. This fund will help unlock those stalled sites so they become shovel ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £190 million of the funding will be used to enable the quicker disposal of surplus public sector land for new homes. Alongside this, the Government will provide £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development. Government has identified enough land for over 106,000 homes and has already sold around 33,000. The Home and Communities Agency will become a single ‘shop window’ for land disposal so much needed homes can be built on these sites sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £60 million of this will be made available to support infrastructure in a limited number of enterprise zones. Building work has already begun on 20 zones and the majority have put in place simplified planning arrangements and secured private sector investment. The fund will help accelerate the infrastructure preparations so that new businesses can open and more new jobs are created as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from Lord Heseltine’s report which recommended devolution of more economic powers, local enterprise partnerships will be able to borrow up to £1.5 billion at cheap rates for nominated infrastructure projects. This puts partnerships and councils in much greater control over the levers of growth. They are already putting the Growing Places Fund to good use supporting 169 projects in the first 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will also pump an additional £350 million into the Regional Growth Fund, including a new £210 million to support jobs and growth across England - bringing the total fund to £2.6 billion. In addition, a new £170 million Department for Transport local transport pinch point fund, to unlock new development, homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="extra-support-for-business-continues"&gt;Extra support for business continues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to tackle the deficit there continues to be no real terms increases in business rates and inflation has fallen easing pressure further. The government will provide a further one year extension of the temporary doubling of small business rate relief to an estimated half a million business properties. In addition councils can now offer extra discounts to support local business and the 24 enterprise zones offer special 100% rate discounts to new firms that create local jobs. Postponing a revaluation will avoid local firms and local shops facing unexpected hikes in their business-rates bills over the next 5 years. Early estimates suggest that 800,000 premises faced a real-terms rise in their bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chancellor also announced a new temporary measure to extend the time period for the exemption from empty property rates, for newly built property for 18 months which will support construction. This will help promote regeneration and support high street renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="efficiency-savings-to-continue"&gt;Efficiency savings to continue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the government’s fiscal plans the new investment in the economy will, in part, be funded by some government departments’ resource budgets being reduced. The Department for Communites and Local Government has already become a smaller, streamlined, more flexible organisation. Its administration spending will reduce in real terms by 44% having reduced headcount by 37%. Arms length bodies have been reduced from 26 to 13 and the government office regions have been closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has been exempt from the reduction in 2013-2014 in recognition that local authorities are holding down budgets by comparable amounts by keeping council tax low in that year. This important concession will allow local authorities time in 2013-2014 to continue to protect frontline services by delivering reforms that will drive through further savings through transforming service delivery as demonstrated by the whole-place community budget pilots. Full details of local government funding for next year will be announced in the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement due later this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18653</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T14:58:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rough-sleeping-help-offers-winter-lifeline"/>
    <title>Rough sleeping help offers winter lifeline</title>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today that the "lifeline" support that rough sleeping services provide are vital at this time of year.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night the minister visited Westminster’s Cathedral Piazza, a rough sleeping hotspot, where he saw the outreach work of homelessness charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.passage.org.uk/"&gt;The Passage&lt;/a&gt; and the help provided by local hostels to get those at their lowest ebb back on the road to a stable, healthy lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister said that the services, from an offer of immediate help to long-term support, were a last line of defence in helping vulnerable people, especially as the temperature continues to drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was part of joint work between government, local authorities, homelessness charities and other agencies who work with the homeless to prevent rough sleeping and support those who fall through the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is investing £400 million over 4 years to help local authorities prevent and tackle homelessness, including rough sleeping, with an additional £70 million investment last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, on top of a pledge to roll out London’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt; service across the country, means that anyone facing losing their home and sleeping rough this winter will get the support they need and deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nobody should have to face the frightening prospect of a night on the streets, and we have some of the strongest homelessness protections in the world to help prevent it. But sometimes people fall through the cracks, which is why we have the emergency support in place to protect them, especially as the winter weather continues to bite. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The work I saw last night showed me the real issues faced by rough sleepers, and the important role local services play in helping them get their lives back on track. For many, they are a vital lifeline at the most difficult time, and the last line of defence, not only against the cold, but against a long-term life on the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16958</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-better-deal-for-mobile-home-owners"/>
    <title>A better deal for mobile home owners</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes a number of reforms to the park homes sector, aimed at tackling a number of complaints made by residents of some mobile home site operators. These can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking an owner’s sale of their home - without justifiable reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees, breaching site rules and stopping owners from improving their homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures are designed to ensure site operators who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already whilst the rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring compliance with site licence conditions by enabling the courts to impose unlimited fines on operators who do not manage their sites properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing local authorities to make a reasonable charge on site operators for their licensing services, which they are currently unable to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving local authorities the power to carry out works on sites in an emergency or where the site operator has been found guilty of a breach of the licence, and charge the cost back to them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the rules around the sale of mobile homes so that unscrupulous operators cannot interfere with owners selling to a qualifying buyer who they have chosen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing legislation to improve other residents’ rights to reflect their status as home owners by, for example, allowing them to carry out home improvements without seeking permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17313</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:51:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/funding-boost-will-help-stop-the-rot-of-empty-homes"/>
    <title>Funding boost will help "stop the rot" of empty homes</title>
    <summary>Don Foster has announced the opening of bidding for a share of £300 million. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funding will bring thousands of additional empty homes back into use across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communities minister pledged to “stop the rot” that empty homes can bring to blighted neighbourhoods and said that he “wants to go much further” in tackling the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the scheme 5,000 empty, and in many cases derelict, properties will be refurbished and put back onto the market over the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="extending-the-governments-commitment-to-tackling-empty-homes"&gt;Extending the government’s commitment to tackling empty homes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest figures show the number of empty homes dropped from 300,000 in 2009 to 259,000 in 2012, and today’s new funding is in addition to the £160 million ministers have already committed to bringing empty homes back into use. The government has also given councils greater powers to tackle empty homes locally including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allowing councils to charge up to 150% of the normal Council Tax rate on owners of the most problematic neglected homes from April 2013 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;applying the ‘New Homes Bonus’ to empty homes, with government matching Council Tax proceeds from newly inhabited properties pound for pound, doubling councils’ revenue from these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the most severe cases, enabling councils to take over the most problematic neglected homes through the use of Empty Dwelling Management Orders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the beginning of Empty Homes Week Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Empty homes blight communities, attract crime and rats and deprive people of available housing. What’s worse this is a vicious circle - one derelict home brings an area down and can lead to more and in places whole communities have been destroyed. I am determined quite literally to stop the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This extra money will help communities refurbish empty and abandoned homes, bring in new residents, provide desperately needed extra affordable housing for families and regenerate communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This significant cash injection will help thousands of families in housing need, but will also support local economic growth by providing work for local building firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of organisations including councils, housing associations, community and voluntary groups as well as high street regeneration groups - prioritising the 27 ‘Portas pilot’ towns and 326 town team partners - will be able to bid for a share of the funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are also considering future measures to bring not just homes but empty buildings generally back into use including making it easier to convert commercial into residential property and making more use of space above shops as homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TV presenter, architect, and Independent Empty Homes Adviser George Clarke said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Empty homes are a very serious problem for communities - they cause a loss of housing, produce an increase in crime and bring entire areas down. The government has shown it is equally serious about tackling this problem and I welcome this massive injection of extra cash that will help towns across the country tackle the blight of empty homes and regenerate communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Ireland, Chief Executive at the Empty Homes Agency, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The huge effort people have made this year to get empty homes back into use has been truly inspiring and created a major contribution to housing supply. This week we are celebrating what they have achieved and pushing for changes to make it possible for even more to be achieved next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homes and Communities Agency Chief Executive Pat Ritchie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tackling empty homes remains a key priority for the Agency. I welcome this additional funding, which has an emphasis on helping to bring empty commercial and non-residential back into use as affordable housing, and will build on the work we are already doing to bring long-term empty homes back into use through our Affordable Homes Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be working with our local partners to help meet local need and in doing so, support their efforts to tackle homelessness and regenerate neighbourhoods that are suffering from the blight of empty homes and help to prevent neighbourhood decline.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bidding guidance will shortly be published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk" title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;Homes and Communities Agency’s website&lt;/a&gt; for registered providers and at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.grantsadmin.co.uk" title="Grantsadmin"&gt;Grants admin&lt;/a&gt; for community and voluntary groups.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Empty homes figures can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/10605/1815794.xls"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government recently changed the threshold at which Empty Dwelling Management Orders take effect, maintaining councils’ powers to tackle the most problematic properties but preventing heavy handed use against homeowners. For more information see the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/pickles-acts-to-protect-the-rights-of-homeowners"&gt;news article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 150% council tax premium for empty homes is part of the measures within the Local Government Finance Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £300 million funding was part of the 6 September housing and growth package announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
