<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/international-aid-and-development</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "International aid and development"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-09T18:00:10+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64980</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T18:00:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T18:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"/>
    <title>UK hosts conference on Syrian-led political transition </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK meeting aims to galvanise international support for Syrian-led transition to a stable democratic country</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK is hosting a private meeting of the Syrian National Coalition, leading international partners and international experts on 9-10 January to consider how the international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the meeting a Foreign Office spokesperson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As announced by the Foreign Secretary to the Friends of Syria meeting in Marrakech on 12 December, the UK is intensifying its support for a Syrian-led transition process. With the escalating violence and suffering Syria has endured over the past 22 months, the international community has an important responsibility to ensure it is ready to help a future Syrian government achieve political transition and stability quickly. Therefore, it is vital that the international community is ready to react to change on the ground, which could happen suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64330</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/libya-operation-recognition-for-naval-air-squadron-personnel"/>
    <title>Libya operation recognition for Naval Air Squadron personnel</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy personnel from 815 Naval Air Squadron have received medals for their part in the NATO-led Libya operation in 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 4 servicemen from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; are among 1,500 Royal Navy personnel to receive medals for their part in the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;-led Libya operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aircrew and engineers, based at Royal Naval Air Station Yeovilton, were presented with &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; Operation Unified Protector medals for their participation in the Libya operation while serving with 217 Flight on board &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Decommissioned-Units/HMS-Liverpool" title="HMS Liverpool web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Naval Air Squadron personnel with their Operation Unified Protector medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5919/HMS_Liverpool_Flight_NATO_Medals_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: Lieutenant Alastair Crawford, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Lieutenant Craig Farquharson with their Operation Unified Protector medals [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The four who received medals for the operation were Lieutenant Alistair Crawford, Lieutenant Craig Farquharson, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Air Engineering Technician Matthew Parker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Crawford, from Yeovil, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;217 Flight and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool made a vital contribution to Operation Unified Protector, always at the forefront of helping to protect Libyan civilians and just show the flexibility of the Royal Navy and Fleet Air Arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer Perry, from Worcester, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud to have had the opportunity to help the Libyan civilians and put my years of experience to the best possible use. Medals are nice but that is the real reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They formed part of the high-profile &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; task force to provide maritime embargo operations and to control the no-fly zone to help protect the Libyan civilian population. The Flight were pivotal to the success of the maritime operation as they provided surface search and routine maritime patrols to counter the threat posed by pro-Gaddafi forces in laying mines in the vicinity of Libyan ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of the oldest warships in the Royal Navy, the team of aircrew and engineers regularly operated at high readiness, which required them to be on 15 minutes’ standby to launch over many nights, and all this achieved in spite of the sustained exposure to the harsh environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all of the problems they encountered, their aircraft flew over 270 hours in support of the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; mission, including 75 hours in August 2011 alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout their 8-month operational deployment, 217 Flight continually demonstrated an unquestionable commitment in support of the overall task group output. The engineering effort was pivotal to the exceptional aircraft availability enjoyed by &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool’s command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64191</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:59:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:59:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"/>
    <title>2013 should be ‘year of peace’ for people in the Middle East</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary says 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, he reaffirms UK’s support for a political transition in Syria. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today met Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States. Following the meeting the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to welcome Mr Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States, to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We discussed the Middle East Peace Process and agreed that 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation.  We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.  We agreed that Arab League and EU member states needed to assist the Palestinian Authority to overcome its current financial difficulties and that  Israel should fulfil its obligations to transfer customs revenues due to the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also discussed the situation in Syria, and efforts to achieve a political transition and an end to the violence. We reiterated our support for UN and Arab League Special Representative Brahimi’s efforts to advance a credible political solution to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK believes that President Assad can never recover legitimacy in the eyes of the Syrian people.  His latest promises of token reforms demonstrate his increasingly desperate attempts to hold on to power. As well as supporting a political transition the UK will continue our humanitarian assistance, our work to support those documenting human rights violations in Syria, and our non-lethal support for the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64188</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"/>
    <title>Minister “dismayed” at verdict in Bahraini activists’ appeal </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt, has called on Bahrain to guarantee its citizens’ fundamental liberties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court today upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. Commenting earlier, Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am deeply dismayed at the decision of the Bahraini Cassation Court to uphold the sentences of 13 political activists in today’s appeal hearing. At the time these individuals were sentenced, reports which were acknowledged by the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry suggested that some had been abused in detention, denied access to legal counsel and were coerced into confessing. I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bahrain-independent-commission-of-inquiry-bici"&gt;Minister comments on Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61173</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Ministers urge progress between Sudan and South Sudan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK, US and Norway say that Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan must seize the opportunity for peace now.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January. In a joint statement, Foreign Ministers from the ‘Sudan Troika’ are calling for the two countries to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint statement by Norwegian Foreign Minister Espen Barth Eide, United Kingdom Foreign Secretary William Hague and U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the news that the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January in a further effort to resolve outstanding issues between the two countries. We applaud the progress made at their Presidential Summit held in Addis Ababa at the end of September 2012, which demonstrated that a durable and equitable settlement is within reach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We commend the continuing valuable role of the African Union High-Level Implementation Panel led by former President Thabo Mbeki and the efforts of Ethiopian Prime Minister Hailemariam Desalegn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We regret that progress in implementing the Agreements signed on 27 September has stalled and in particular that the agreed security arrangements at the border are not yet in place. We call on the two leaders now to address concretely all outstanding issues and ensure that the armed forces of the two countries immediately withdraw from the demilitarised zone and deploy the Joint Border and Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM), in line with what has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We stress the importance of making progress in parallel on other parts of the relationship between the two countries. Full implementation of all agreements on their own terms and without preconditions or linkages between them, will help build confidence and benefit the people of the two countries. The restart of oil production and export will be particularly valuable for both economies and should not be held up by negotiation on other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We underline our support for the approach taken by the African Union to the question of Abyei. The proposal made by former President Mbeki is based on the Comprehensive Peace Agreement, including the Abyei Protocol. The proposal, adopted by AUPSC on October 24, sets out a clear path towards determining Abyei’s final status in accordance with agreements already signed by both parties, while protecting the rights of all communities and ensuring Abyei can become a model for cross-border cooperation and coexistence. We note in particular that the proposal provides for Abyei’s continuing special status as a bridge between the two countries with guaranteed political and economic rights for both the Ngok Dinka and Misseriya, whatever the outcome of the referendum. We urge the two countries to meet to elaborate on these rights and to move toward agreement on Abyei’s final status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision. We strongly urge them to seize the opportunity of the Summit meeting on 4 January to demonstrate their commitment to implement what they have agreed and make peaceful co-existence a reality.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60956</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"/>
    <title>Ministerial statement on UN sanctions against the M23, FDLR, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Legerero</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for Africa comments on vote agreeing sanctions against groups and individuals involved in the conflict in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds MP, the UK Minister for Africa, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome today’s agreement by the UN Security Council Sanctions Committee to add the Congolese rebel group, M23, to its list of sanctioned organisations and individuals. The Committee also agreed the listings of two M23 leaders, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Lugerero, as well as of the militia group Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR). The UK supports these measures as part of the international community’s response to the crisis in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). We remain committed to finding long term solutions which will end the cycle of violence in the DRC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops, that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR. It is also important that the DRC Government shows leadership in addressing the underlying causes of conflict in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, with its partners, will continue to seek ways to support the building of a sustainable peace in eastern DRC.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60865</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-new-settlement"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister condemns new settlement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister Alistair Burt statement: the approval of new units is a 'provocative action' contrary to Fourth Geneva Convention.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the announcements on 24 December that the Jerusalem District Planning Board issued approval for 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South, and that Ariel College is to be upgraded to university status thereby creating the first university in a settlement illegal under international law, Alistair Burt, Minister for the Middle East said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last week Foreign Secretary William Hague made clear our condemnation and deep disappointment at the approval of the East Jerusalem Ramat Shlomo plan. We also condemn the Jerusalem District Planning Board’s approvals for over 3150 units in Givaat Hamatos and 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South. These are further profoundly provocative actions that run contrary to the Fourth Geneva Convention. By taking these steps, despite the international community repeatedly raising our profound concerns, the Israeli Government is damaging Israel’s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also deeply disappointed in the decision to upgrade Ariel’s university centre. Ariel is beyond the Green Line in a settlement that is illegal according to international law. This decision will deepen the presence of the settlements in the Palestinian territories and will create another obstacle to peace. We reiterate our call on Israel urgently to reverse these decisions and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I spoke with President Abbas last week I expressed our appreciation for the measured response the Palestinian Leadership had been taking in response to Israel’s recent settlement announcements.  We utterly and unreservedly condemn the recent call for a third intifada and a suicide campaign by a Hamas official. Incitements to violence and terror are unacceptable. We welcome that President Abbas has publicly rejected the recent inflammatory statements by Hamas leaders, and that he has stated clearly the position of the legitimate Palestinian Leadership which has accepted the State of Israel in 1967 borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taken together, these further settlement announcements and comments deepen our worry for the region at such a crucial time, and demonstrate why we are convinced of the urgency for more positive indicators of change. Accordingly we continue to call on President Abbas and Prime Minister Netanyahu to show the strong leadership needed to achieve a return to negotiations for a two-state solution, which will bring a just and permanent solution to this conflict.  We repeat our hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
