<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/international-aid-and-development</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "International aid and development"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61173</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Ministers urge progress between Sudan and South Sudan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK, US and Norway say that Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan must seize the opportunity for peace now.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January. In a joint statement, Foreign Ministers from the ‘Sudan Troika’ are calling for the two countries to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint statement by Norwegian Foreign Minister Espen Barth Eide, United Kingdom Foreign Secretary William Hague and U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the news that the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January in a further effort to resolve outstanding issues between the two countries. We applaud the progress made at their Presidential Summit held in Addis Ababa at the end of September 2012, which demonstrated that a durable and equitable settlement is within reach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We commend the continuing valuable role of the African Union High-Level Implementation Panel led by former President Thabo Mbeki and the efforts of Ethiopian Prime Minister Hailemariam Desalegn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We regret that progress in implementing the Agreements signed on 27 September has stalled and in particular that the agreed security arrangements at the border are not yet in place. We call on the two leaders now to address concretely all outstanding issues and ensure that the armed forces of the two countries immediately withdraw from the demilitarised zone and deploy the Joint Border and Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM), in line with what has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We stress the importance of making progress in parallel on other parts of the relationship between the two countries. Full implementation of all agreements on their own terms and without preconditions or linkages between them, will help build confidence and benefit the people of the two countries. The restart of oil production and export will be particularly valuable for both economies and should not be held up by negotiation on other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We underline our support for the approach taken by the African Union to the question of Abyei. The proposal made by former President Mbeki is based on the Comprehensive Peace Agreement, including the Abyei Protocol. The proposal, adopted by AUPSC on October 24, sets out a clear path towards determining Abyei’s final status in accordance with agreements already signed by both parties, while protecting the rights of all communities and ensuring Abyei can become a model for cross-border cooperation and coexistence. We note in particular that the proposal provides for Abyei’s continuing special status as a bridge between the two countries with guaranteed political and economic rights for both the Ngok Dinka and Misseriya, whatever the outcome of the referendum. We urge the two countries to meet to elaborate on these rights and to move toward agreement on Abyei’s final status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision. We strongly urge them to seize the opportunity of the Summit meeting on 4 January to demonstrate their commitment to implement what they have agreed and make peaceful co-existence a reality.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60956</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"/>
    <title>Ministerial statement on UN sanctions against the M23, FDLR, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Legerero</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for Africa comments on vote agreeing sanctions against groups and individuals involved in the conflict in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds MP, the UK Minister for Africa, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome today’s agreement by the UN Security Council Sanctions Committee to add the Congolese rebel group, M23, to its list of sanctioned organisations and individuals. The Committee also agreed the listings of two M23 leaders, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Lugerero, as well as of the militia group Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR). The UK supports these measures as part of the international community’s response to the crisis in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). We remain committed to finding long term solutions which will end the cycle of violence in the DRC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops, that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR. It is also important that the DRC Government shows leadership in addressing the underlying causes of conflict in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, with its partners, will continue to seek ways to support the building of a sustainable peace in eastern DRC.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60865</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-new-settlement"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister condemns new settlement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister Alistair Burt statement: the approval of new units is a 'provocative action' contrary to Fourth Geneva Convention.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the announcements on 24 December that the Jerusalem District Planning Board issued approval for 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South, and that Ariel College is to be upgraded to university status thereby creating the first university in a settlement illegal under international law, Alistair Burt, Minister for the Middle East said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last week Foreign Secretary William Hague made clear our condemnation and deep disappointment at the approval of the East Jerusalem Ramat Shlomo plan. We also condemn the Jerusalem District Planning Board’s approvals for over 3150 units in Givaat Hamatos and 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South. These are further profoundly provocative actions that run contrary to the Fourth Geneva Convention. By taking these steps, despite the international community repeatedly raising our profound concerns, the Israeli Government is damaging Israel’s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also deeply disappointed in the decision to upgrade Ariel’s university centre. Ariel is beyond the Green Line in a settlement that is illegal according to international law. This decision will deepen the presence of the settlements in the Palestinian territories and will create another obstacle to peace. We reiterate our call on Israel urgently to reverse these decisions and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I spoke with President Abbas last week I expressed our appreciation for the measured response the Palestinian Leadership had been taking in response to Israel’s recent settlement announcements.  We utterly and unreservedly condemn the recent call for a third intifada and a suicide campaign by a Hamas official. Incitements to violence and terror are unacceptable. We welcome that President Abbas has publicly rejected the recent inflammatory statements by Hamas leaders, and that he has stated clearly the position of the legitimate Palestinian Leadership which has accepted the State of Israel in 1967 borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taken together, these further settlement announcements and comments deepen our worry for the region at such a crucial time, and demonstrate why we are convinced of the urgency for more positive indicators of change. Accordingly we continue to call on President Abbas and Prime Minister Netanyahu to show the strong leadership needed to achieve a return to negotiations for a two-state solution, which will bring a just and permanent solution to this conflict.  We repeat our hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
