<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/international-aid-and-development</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/international-aid-and-development.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "International aid and development"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56249</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice"/>
    <title>Iranian investigation into death of detained blogger is missed opportunity for justice</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger has failed to deliver justice.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marking the 40th day anniversary of the death of Sattar Beheshti, Foreign Officer Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is now forty days since the blogger Sattar Beheshti died in custody in Iran. I would like to use this occasion to extend my condolences to his family. That the Iranian authorities instigated an investigation into Sattar’s tragic death should have been a positive step. However, once again the authorities have failed to deliver justice. Neither Sattar’s family who have reportedly faced harassment and threats from the security services, nor Sattar’s countrymen and women have been given credible answers about the events that led to his death. Instead, the state-controlled media and the parliament have dismissed his death as a heart attack brought on by a fear of arrest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sattar was right to be afraid of the security forces and what could happen to him in jail. The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention. We are deeply disappointed that having taken the initiative to investigate,  Iran has been unwilling to hold those responsible to account. The sacking of the head of Cyber Police will not stop the security and detention forces from operating with impunity. Systemic change is needed to bring about a more transparent and accountable system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous statement on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reports-that-an-iranian-blogger-has-died-in-detention" title="Reports that an Iranian blogger has died in detention"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt on twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO" title="@AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55967</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-to-contribute-funds-to-courts-in-sierra-leone-and-cambodia--2"/>
    <title>UK to contribute funds to Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia</title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has announced UK funding for Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia to strengthen international justice.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on UK contributions to the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in a written ministerial statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce that in order to strengthen international justice and help secure accountability for some of the most horrific crimes against humanity in the last 50 years, the UK will make a voluntary contribution of £1,000,000 to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and a voluntary contribution of £600,000 to the international component of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s contribution will help ensure the Special Court for Sierra Leone is able to complete its work, and leave a lasting legacy for the people of Sierra Leone. On 30 May, the Court sentenced Charles Taylor, a former President of Liberia, to 50 years in jail for aiding and abetting war crimes. Taylor is the first former Head of State to be convicted by an international tribunal and the Court is currently hearing his appeal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia is delivering long awaited justice for millions of Cambodians through the trials of the most senior and responsible surviving members of the Pol Pot regime. The scale of the crimes committed and the number of victims makes it one of the most significant tribunals of its kind since Nuremberg. The Government’s contribution will help to prevent the collapse of the Court which has faced a significant shortfall in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International justice is central to foreign policy. It is essential for securing the rights of individuals and states, and for securing peace and reconciliation. Through the International Criminal Court, and the separate international tribunals, we are working to make clear that those responsible for the worst crimes will be held to account and that political leaders will not enjoy impunity. Our support to these institutions is an important element in our strategy to reduce conflict, promote stability and strengthen the rules based international system. In order to give Parliament a full accounting of this work we will, from this point forward, also provide an annual statement at the start of the financial year detailing our progress on this important issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/18790</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/strengthening-the-commonwealth--2"/>
    <title>Strengthening the Commonwealth</title>
    <summary>Using the Commonwealth to protect human rights and and support development.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth and its networks can act as effective partners in our work to protect and support human rights globally. Commonwealth membership is based on the shared values of democracy, human rights and the rule of law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth is also important in our work to contribute to the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/bkgd.shtml#mdgs"&gt;Millennium Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;, an agreement by all the world’s countries and leading development institutions to help the world’s poorest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/subhomepage/33247/"&gt;2011 Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting (&lt;abbr title="Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting"&gt;CHOGM&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; in Perth, Australia, which took place on 28-30 October 2011, the heads of the UK other governments agreed to a ‘Charter of the Commonwealth’. The charter identifies development for poorer countries, and improving human rights and democracy, as priorities for the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Secretary of State for International Development commissioned a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Documents/publications1/mar/multilateral_aid_review.pdf"&gt;Multilateral Aid Review (&lt;abbr title="Multilateral Aid Review"&gt;MAR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; to assess the value for money and impact provided by multilateral agencies that receive funding from the UK. The &lt;abbr title="Multilateral Aid Review"&gt;MAR&lt;/abbr&gt; found that the Commonwealth Secretariat has not fully achieved its potential to contribute to international development goals. Future funding now depends on the Commonwealth Secretariat reducing costs and becoming more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of these findings &lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt; ministers decided that &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Documents/publications1/mar/comsec.pdf"&gt;UK funding for the development programmes of the Commonwealth Secretariat&lt;/a&gt; should remain at 2010 to 11 levels for the 2011 to 12 and 2012 to 13 financial years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coalition’s 2010 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;Programme for Government&lt;/a&gt; set out the government’s aim to ‘strengthen the Commonwealth as a focus for promoting democratic values and development’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Commonwealth set up a review of the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group (&lt;abbr title="Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group"&gt;CMAG&lt;/abbr&gt;), a body established in 1985 to deal with serious violations of the Commonwealth’s political values. Their report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/files/245418/FileName/Strengthening-the-Role-CMAG_2011.pdf"&gt;Strengthening the role of the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group&lt;/a&gt;, found that giving &lt;abbr title="Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group"&gt;CMAG&lt;/abbr&gt; a bigger role would help establish the values of democracy, respect for human rights and the rule of law. The report was adopted by member states in September 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth launched the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.commonwealthconnects.org/"&gt;Commonwealth Connects&lt;/a&gt; website at &lt;abbr title="Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting"&gt;CHOGM&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2011. By 2013 the website will make information and communication technology widely available to Commonwealth citizens. It will provide a way to access information and resources from dozens of Commonwealth organisations and associations, and host a secure area for professionals across the Commonwealth to network, work together and share information, knowledge, good practice and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth was established by the Declaration of London in 1949, with King George VI as its head. The Declaration emphasised the freedom and equality of its member states, not just in their relationship to the Head of the Commonwealth as a “free association of [..] independent nations”, but also in their co-operative “pursuit of peace, liberty and progress”. When King George VI died, Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II assumed the role of Head of the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth is a unique association of 54 independent states (the newest of which, Rwanda, joined in 2009) consulting and co-operating in the common interests of their peoples and in international understanding. It comprises a diverse range of countries from all continents of the world (apart from Antarctica). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/"&gt;Commonwealth Secretariat&lt;/a&gt; is the main organisation of the Commonwealth. Its aim is to build stronger democratic institutions across the Commonwealth. It does this by providing training and technical assistance and sending teams of observers to countries’ elections by invitation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55763</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories"/>
    <title>Protecting and developing the overseas territories</title>
    <summary>Working with the Overseas Territories on the challenges they face and encouraging strong local economies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a broad responsibility to support the Overseas Territories and to ensure their security and good governance. Britain and territory governments share significant challenges: building more diverse and resilient economies; cutting public sector deficits; regulating finance businesses effectively; and protecting biodiversity and natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-overseas-territories-programme-fund"&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund supports the work of government to maintain the security, stability and prosperity of the Overseas Territories. This fund supports the economic, security, environmental and governance strategies in the government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/publications/overseas-territories-white-paper-0612/ot-wp-0612"&gt;white paper on the Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Where-we-work/Overseas-Territories/"&gt;Department for International Development (&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; provides budgetary support for Montserrat, Pitcairn and St Helena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Documents/publications1/op/ovseas-terr-dept-2011.pdf"&gt;Department for International Development’s Operational Plan 2011-2015&lt;/a&gt; explains how money is allocated to the territories and how expenditure is monitored for effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-and-climate-fund-darwin-plus"&gt;Environment and climate fund: Darwin Plus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government launched &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2012/10/17/2-million-a-year-overseas-territories-fund/"&gt;Darwin Plus: Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;, an environment and climate fund for the UK’s Overseas Territories, in October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fund consists of contributions from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;), and &lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;. The fund will disburse around £2 million per year dedicated to a range of environment and climate-related projects to improve long-term natural resource management in the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance and application forms for the fund are available on &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://darwin.defra.gov.uk/news/2012-10/darwin-plus/%20%E2%80%9CDarwin%20Initiative%E2%80%9D"&gt;Darwin Initiative website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="protecting-the-overseas-territories"&gt;Protecting the Overseas Territories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the UK’s main military tasks is to provide security to the nation and its overseas territories. The Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a security policy in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/1AD4AFE6-4946-4BAC-A3A6-7AFBF9AA25BF/0/overseas_territories.pdf"&gt;Overseas Territories: the Ministry of Defence’s contribution&lt;/a&gt;, which explains how the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; will protect the Overseas Territories from 2012 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-the-public-sectors"&gt;Supporting the public sectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have set up the Jubilee Programme to share experience between public servants in the territories and the UK by giving territory officials opportunities to train and work with colleagues in the UK, and vice versa, encouraging long-term partnerships between the territories and public bodies in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories are very diverse, with thousands of small islands, vast areas of ocean, but also, in Antarctica, land 6 times the size of the United Kingdom. They include one of the world’s richest communities, in Bermuda; the most remote community, in Tristan da Cunha and one of the smallest, with only 54 people living on Pitcairn Island. The total population of the territories is roughly a quarter of a million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 14 British Overseas Territories and most have a permanent resident population. The exceptions are the British Indian Ocean Territory and the British Antarctic Territory, and South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands, of which the latter have research stations. The Sovereign Base Areas on Cyprus have a resident population of Cypriot nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14 Overseas Territories are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/anguilla/"&gt;Anguilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/bermuda/"&gt;Bermuda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/british-indian-ocean-territory/"&gt;British Indian Ocean Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinbvi.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The British Virgin Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukincayman.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Cayman Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/falkland-islands/"&gt;The Falkland Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/europe/gibraltar/"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinmontserrat.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;Montserrat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/pitcairn-islands/"&gt;The Pitcairn, Henderson, Ducie &amp;amp; Oeno Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/st-helena/"&gt;Saint Helena&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/ascension-Island/"&gt;Ascension&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/tristan-da-cunha/"&gt;Tristan da Cunha (including Gough Island Dependency)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/south-georgia-south-sandwich/"&gt;South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas, Akrotiri and Dhekelia (on Cyprus)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://turksandcaicosislands.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Turks &amp;amp; Caicos Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can email enquiries about &lt;a href="enquiry.gibraltar@fco.gov.uk"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For enquiries about the Sovereign Base Areas, visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56411</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-for-peace-and-long-term-stability-in-the-middle-east-and-north-africa"/>
    <title>Working for peace and long-term stability in the Middle East and North Africa</title>
    <summary>The British government's humanitarian and diplomatic efforts in securing peace in the Middle East and North Africa.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Middle East and North Africa (&lt;abbr title="Middle East and North Africa"&gt;MENA&lt;/abbr&gt;)  is highly important to the UK. The change begun by the Arab Spring could bring a more open, inclusive and democratic society. This would be the greatest gain for human rights and freedom since the end of the Cold War. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Middle East and North Africa"&gt;MENA&lt;/abbr&gt; is home to some of the most long-running and high-profile foreign policy issues in the world, including the current Syria crisis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Middle East and North Africa"&gt;MENA&lt;/abbr&gt; matters for our prosperity, too. Trade between the UK and &lt;abbr title="Middle East and North Africa"&gt;MENA&lt;/abbr&gt; exceeded £30 billion in 2011, and millions of British tourists visit the region each year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="response-to-the-arab-spring-the-arab-partnership"&gt;Response to the Arab Spring: the Arab Partnership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/arab-partnership-programme-approach-2011-15"&gt;Arab Partnership&lt;/a&gt;, a joint Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Work-with-us/Funding-opportunities/partnerships/Arab-Partnership/"&gt;Department for International Development (&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;) plan&lt;/a&gt;, the government is providing support for political and economic reform in &lt;abbr title="Middle East and North Africa"&gt;MENA&lt;/abbr&gt;, helping the people of the region  build more open and accountable societies. This includes diplomatic support, working with international institutions like the G8 and EU, and £110 million over 4 years to help finance locally-led reform projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ongoing-support-in-libya"&gt;Ongoing support in Libya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK, together with international partners including the UN and the EU, is providing a range of assistance to the new Libyan government including strategic and practical advice and training in the security and justice sectors, support to improve economic and financial governance, and capacity building for the now flourishing Libyan civil society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has allocated approximately £5 million to a wide range of civil society projects since August 2011, including human rights training for lawyers and the judiciary. The money is used to fund projects that, for example, promote the participation of young people in the political transition process, support women’s rights groups which aim to secure women’s rights, and train former fighters to be domestic election observers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="finding-an-end-to-the-crisis-in-syria"&gt;Finding an end to the crisis in Syria&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is working with international partners to bring about an end to violence and achieve a managed political transition. We have already committed over £50 million to help &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Syria-crisis/"&gt;alleviate the humanitarian crisis&lt;/a&gt; and help the Syrian people prepare economically and politically for a new government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-middle-east-peace-process"&gt;The Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe that the Israeli-Palestinian conflict can be resolved through direct negotiations between the parties and urge both sides to avoid undermining the prospects for peace by working towards starting direct negotiation without pre-conditions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="stabilising-yemen"&gt;Stabilising Yemen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is providing Yemen with £196 million from 2012 to 2015. Most of this money will go to alleviate humanitarian suffering and to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://sfd.sfd-yemen.org/index.php"&gt;Social Fund for Development&lt;/a&gt; to improve rural infrastructure and expand social protection. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/yemen"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt; is supporting&lt;/a&gt; Yemen’s long-term development, stability and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arab Spring has shown that demands for political and economic freedom will spread widely by themselves, not because Western nations advocate these values, but because all people everywhere aspire to these freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/prime-minister%E2%80%99s-speech-to-the-national-assembly-kuwait/"&gt;speech to the National Assembly&lt;/a&gt; in Kuwait on 22 February 2011, the Prime Minister set out the UK’s approach to the Arab Spring, upholding universal values, rights and freedoms, with respect for the different cultures, histories and traditions of the countries in the region.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/50204</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-stability-throughout-the-western-balkans--2"/>
    <title>Promoting stability throughout the Western Balkans</title>
    <summary>Securing peace and creating the conditions for EU membership in the Western Balkans.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1990s saw the violent break-up of the former Yugoslavia and the beginning of the transition from communism in the region. The region has since started the long route to greater stability and prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stability in the Western Balkans matters; the region is on Europe’s doorstep and instability or conflict would affect the UK, including through migration and organised crime. The UK is therefore working to reduce the risk of conflict in the region, promote stability and reconciliation, and support reforms, as the region moves towards future EU and NATO membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a strong supporter of future EU and NATO membership for all countries of the Western Balkans (along with Iceland and Turkey). To reach this future in the EU and NATO, countries need to meet conditions for membership. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU accession process, leading to membership, requires serious reform efforts from the region, including on rule of law, organised crime and corruption, public administration, and economic reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is supporting these reforms with £3 million of Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office (FCO) programme funds for Albania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Kosovo, Macedonia, Montenegro, Serbia (and Turkey), for example funding judicial reform or media freedom projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also providing expertise supporting accession-related reforms from across the civil service as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twinning.org/en/page/the-european-union.html"&gt;EU twinning programme&lt;/a&gt;, means to help people understand the aims of the EU, to develop a stronger sense of European identity, and to bring the EU closer to its citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms reduce security threats to the UK and promote a strong environment for British business interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reconciliation is crucial for the region, following the conflict and atrocities of the past. Cooperation with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.icty.org/"&gt;International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia&lt;/a&gt;, the UN court of law dealing with war crimes that took place during the conflicts in the Balkans in the 1990s, remains important, as does the leadership in the region openly and honestly acknowledging the events of the past, such as the genocide in Srebrenica. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is also supporting conflict prevention efforts in the region, with around £10 million provided jointly from the FCO, Ministry of Defence and Department for International Development. The work is focused on Bosnia and Herzegovina and on Kosovo and includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UK troops joining, in December 2012, the regional reserve for the peacekeeping mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support for the Srebrenica prosecutions team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK judges hearing war crime cases in Kosovo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;projects to support ethnic minorities returning to rebuilt homes following the Kosovo war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK continues to support safeguards against instability in Bosnia and Herzegovina, particularly the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohr.int/"&gt;Office of the High Representative&lt;/a&gt;, the international institution responsible for overseeing implementation of civilian aspects of the Peace Agreement ending the war in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.euforbih.org/"&gt;EUFOR Althea peacekeeping operation&lt;/a&gt;, the EU’s military operation that launched on 2 December 2004 and has contributed to the maintenance of the safe and secure environment in Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="albania"&gt;Albania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albania is already a member of NATO and has made an application for EU membership. The UK encourages further progress on reforms, particularly rule of law and democracy, for Albania to move forward on towards their EU future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bosnia-and-herzegovina"&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK remains wholly and actively committed to Bosnia and Herzegovina as a sovereign, stable country with functioning state-level institutions. Significant political progress is needed if progress towards NATO and EU membership is to be made, but such progress will bring benefits to citizens throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="croatia"&gt;Croatia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Croatia will accede to the EU in July 2013. The European Commission’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/hr_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;Comprehensive Monitoring Report on Croatia’s state ofpreparedness for EU membership&lt;/a&gt;, published in October 2012, noted the progress made by Croatia in its preparations for accession. The commission also identified a number of areas where further improvements are necessary in order to fully meet all membership requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN06327"&gt;Croatia Accession Bill&lt;/a&gt; would allow the UK to ratify Croatia’s accession treaty. All existing EU member states must ratify the accession treaty before Croatia can join the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="kosovo"&gt;Kosovo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK recognised Kosovo’s declaration of independence in February 2008 and is a longstanding supporter of Kosovo’s independence, sovereignty and territorial integrity. The UK is a firm supporter of a stable, prosperous and multi-ethnic Kosovo making progress towards eventual EU and NATO membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="macedonia"&gt;Macedonia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports Macedonia’s progress towards EU and NATO membership. Since March 2002, the European Commission has reported regularly to the EU Council and Parliament on progress made by the countries of the Western Balkans region. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/pdf/key_documents/2012/package/mk_rapport_2012_en.pdf"&gt;2012 report&lt;/a&gt; describes the progress made by the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia in preparing for EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="montenegro"&gt;Montenegro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/fule/headlines/news/2012/06/20120629_en.htm"&gt;Montenegro opened accession negotiations&lt;/a&gt; with the EU in June 2012. The UK supports an early focus on rule of law issues in the negotiations, notably strengthening the judiciary and tackling organised crime and corruption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="serbia"&gt;Serbia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is a long-standing supporter of Serbia’s EU future and welcomed Serbia becoming an official EU candidate in March 2012. We urge Serbia to make further progress normalising its relations with Kosovo in order to meet the criteria for opening accession negotiations with the EU. Domestic reforms and regional cooperation remain important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/6929</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally"/>
    <title>Promoting human rights internationally</title>
    <summary>Promoting human rights, and political and economic freedom around the world.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people around the world are denied their human rights every day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government supports human rights, democracy and good governance around the world to increase Britain’s security, to protect British citizens overseas, and to secure political freedom globally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/supporting-pages/human-rights-and-democracy-programme-2012-13"&gt;Human Rights and Democracy Programme 2012 to 2013&lt;/a&gt; has allocated £6.5 million to support various projects, including those aimed at: preventing torture, abolishing the death penalty, increasing people’s freedom of expression, giving people freedom of religious belief, achieving gender equality and enabling them to take part in free elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a rel="external" href="http://fcohrdreport.readandcomment.com/"&gt;Human Rights 2011 &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; Report&lt;/a&gt; explains the Government’s work to create democratic societies and promote human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="democracy-and-the-rule-of-law"&gt;Democracy and the rule of law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government supports &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/supporting-pages/equality"&gt;democracy and the rule of law&lt;/a&gt; in a range of different ways. These include funding non-governmental organisations (&lt;abbr title="non-governmental organisations"&gt;NGOs&lt;/abbr&gt;) to increase citizen participation in political debate, reforming the European Court of Human Rights and working with regional and inter-governmental organisations and through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wfd.org/"&gt;Westminster Foundation for Democracy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-peoples-freedom-of-expression"&gt;Supporting people’s freedom of expression&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government supports freedom of expression, including on the Internet, and will continue to press countries that restrict access to online media to uphold their &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/supporting-pages/equality"&gt;international human rights commitments&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the right to freedom of expression applies, in principle, with equal force in cyberspace as elsewhere. We work with other countries to build a wider consensus about freedom of expression on the internet and to guard against the growing trend of political repression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK joined the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.minbuza.nl/en/appendices/the-ministry/final-declaration-coalition-freedom-online.html"&gt;Freedom Online Coalition&lt;/a&gt;, a coalition of like-minded states that shares information on violations of freedom of expression and other human rights online, and cooperates in supporting and protecting human rights online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="equality-and-non-discrimination"&gt;Equality and non-discrimination&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works to support &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/supporting-pages/equality-and-non-discrimination"&gt;equality and non-discrimination&lt;/a&gt; for all people, including gender equality; upholding the rights of minority groups and lesbian, gay and transgender people; supporting the freedom of religion and belief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preventing-torture"&gt;Preventing torture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is working with other countries and organisations to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/supporting-pages/preventing-torture"&gt;prevent torture&lt;/a&gt; by funding projects to make criminal justice systems fairer and developing national organisations that can effectively monitor places of detention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="abolishing-the-death-penalty"&gt;Abolishing the death penalty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government is working with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; to persuade other countries to abolish the death penalty. Our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/global-issues/human-rights/death-penalty-strategy-oct-11-15"&gt;Strategy for Abolition of the Death Penalty 2010-2015&lt;/a&gt; explains how the government persuades other governments to abolish the death penalty, funds projects to restrict the use of the death penalty and raises individual cases of British nationals sentenced to death overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Advisory Group of Human Rights, which consists of non-governmental experts, was created in 2010 by the &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; to give the Foreign Secretary the best possible information about human rights challenges; and for the Foreign Office to benefit from outside advice on the conduct of its policy. The group  discusses a wide range of human rights issues including those relating to conflict, security and counter-terrorism, the events of the Arab Spring, freedom of religion or belief, and business and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt; is the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;’s primary body for discussion and action on human rights issues.  The UK was an active member from its inception in 2006 until June 2011.  We will bid for re-election in 2013 and in the meantime will remain an active supporter of the Council. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also seek complementary action on human rights in other parts of the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, including through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/third/index.shtml"&gt;Third Committee of the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly&lt;/a&gt;, where all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; members can vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in The Hague, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.icc-cpi.int/Menus/ICC/Home"&gt;International Criminal Court (ICC)&lt;/a&gt; is the first ever permanent court with the jurisdiction to prosecute individuals accused of the most serious crimes of international concern: genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes. The Court was established by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://untreaty.un.org/cod/icc/index.html"&gt;Rome Statute for the International Criminal Court&lt;/a&gt;. The ICC is an independent international organisation, and is not part of the United Nations system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55440</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T17:48:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement"/>
    <title>Minister for Europe renews UK commitment to EU enlargement </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has set out the UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister gave a press briefing for European journalists today following his participation in the General Affairs Council meeting in Brussels on 11 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK remains a strong supporter of EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey. I’ve just returned from the General Affairs Council in Brussels where I was pleased to have a long discussion on EU enlargement. Its conclusions make clear the EU’s continued support for enlargement. This is important, and a message that I hope will be heard clearly in the accession and pre-accession countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is good for the EU and one of the EU’s greatest achievements. The European Union, alongside NATO, has been an instrument of peace and reconciliation that has helped spread democracy and the rule of law across our continent, and helped make armed conflict between EU members unthinkable. At the same time an enlarged Single Market, another of the key success stories of the EU, has opened up prosperity and opportunity to hundreds of millions of people. An outward-looking approach and a continuing commitment to enlargement should be seen by all EU Member States as signs of strength and vigour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enlargement is also good for wider security and prosperity across the continent. The accession of new Member States helps promote security, stability and prosperity across Europe, based on a firm foundation of democracy, human and civil rights, and respect for the law. The focus on good neighbourly relations is particularly important for a region such as the Western Balkans which saw conflict only two decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a respect for this firm foundation and its benefits which drives the UK’s scrutiny of progress and focus on conditionality. So the UK is clear that there will be no pause after Croatia’s accession. But equally there will be no movement without progress on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Foreign Secretary visited Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia and Kosovo in October. He set out clearly the UK’s support for each country’s EU future. But he stressed to the political leaders that they needed to take the necessary steps to deliver. I hope political leaders in all of the aspiring countries will do so and that we will see further progress being made towards the EU early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the UK remains committed to Turkey’s EU membership. We strongly believe that this would contribute to Europe’s prosperity and security, and the EU remains the strongest lever for reform in Turkey. We are focused on making real progress on the accession process in 2013 and we fully support the Irish Presidency in their desire to open a new acquis Chapter during their Presidency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=PressS&amp;amp;id=842001782" title="Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56355</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T12:46:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T12:46:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/apache-crews-receive-afghanistan-and-libya-campaign-medals"/>
    <title>Apache crews receive Afghanistan and Libya campaign medals </title>
    <summary>Soldiers who fly and maintain the Apache attack helicopter have celebrated their achievements on operations in both Libya and Afghanistan.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soldiers from the Wattisham-based 4 Regiment Army Air Corps (AAC) were on parade yesterday to be presented with campaign medals recognising their role in the NATO-led Libya operation in Summer 2011 and their service in Afghanistan earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2 deployments challenged the unit’s air and ground crews to carry out the Apache’s first operational missions in the salty sea air and confined spaces of a ship sailing off Libya, as well as supporting troops in the hot, high and dusty conditions of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Jacko Jackson, Deputy Commander of 16 Air Assault Brigade, presented 66 soldiers who served in the Libya campaign with NATO’s Non-Article 5 Operation UNIFIED PROTECTOR medals, which the Queen has granted special permission for military personnel to wear, and a further 44 Operational Service Medals for Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two operational honours awarded for actions during the Libya campaign - a Queen’s Commendation for Valuable Service for Major Mike Neville and a Mention in Despatches for Warrant Officer Class 1 Jonathan Lane - were also presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apaches from the regiment’s 656 Squadron flew sorties over Libya from HMS Ocean as part of NATO operations to protect civilians in support of United Nations Security Council Resolution 1973. On 22 missions between June and October 2011 the Apaches hit more than 100 targets, firing 99 Hellfire missiles and 4,800 30mm cannon rounds. Operation ELLAMY was the name of the British military’s contribution to the Libya campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Colonel Jacko Jackson presents soldiers with campaign medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4681/16x-2012-121-0181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Colonel Jacko Jackson, Deputy Commander of 16 Air Assault Brigade, presents soldiers of 4 Regiment Army Air Corps with their campaign medals [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soldiers from 4 Regiment AAC deployed to Afghanistan from January to September 2012, with the regiment’s 654 and 664 Squadrons each completing a four-month tour. As well as pinpoint strikes in support of ground troops, the Apache’s role is to escort other helicopters and land convoys and provide a near-all-weather surveillance capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jason Etherington, Commanding Officer of 4 Regiment AAC, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a very proud day as we join with our families to celebrate our achievements over an 18-month period with 2 very different but equally challenging operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fast-moving events in Libya saw a five-week exercise for 656 Squadron become a five-month operation, as they went from learning how to operate Apaches on board naval ships to flying operational missions for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taking off from a moving ship to fly over sea at night without lights into a high threat environment challenged the pilots, while the ground crew had to adapt to safely maintaining aircraft in the confined spaces of a ship. For 654 and 664 Squadrons it was a busy and demanding tour of Afghanistan that presented a very different environment, role and threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55806</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:22:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting </title>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has outlined the immediate responsibilities for the Friends of the Syrian People. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representatives from over 130 countries and international organisations met in Marrakesh for the fourth Friends of Syria meeting to support the Syrian National Coalition and the Syrian People. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the meeting the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank the Government of Morocco and H.M. King Mohammed VI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Twenty-two months ago the people of Syria asked for change. Their government responded by pounding cities into rubble, plunging four million people into desperate humanitarian need, and sowing fear and insecurity across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Friends of the Syrian people, we have done much to seek a peaceful end to the conflict. But we remain deeply disappointed by the failure of the international community to put its full weight behind the agreement made in Geneva six months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But in the United Kingdom we do not rule out any option to save lives. In addition, the Assad regime should not doubt our resolve, or miscalculate how we would react to any use of chemical or biological weapons against the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the Friends of the Syrian people, we have four immediate responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, we must increase our political support for and recognition of the Syrian National Coalition. I encourage other nations to recognise them as we have done in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The people of Syria need to feel the solid ground of a unified political alternative to the Assad regime. The National Coalition has now begun to offer that hope, and it is only right that we give them the recognition they deserve, and the support they need to survive and to prevail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Some countries have resisted the idea of a transition because they have seen no alternative to Assad’s leadership. Well now the world can see that there is an alternative, and I urge all countries including Russia and China to work with us to end the conflict. If they do, they will find us constructive partners, and I commend Special Envoy Brahimi for his efforts in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Second, I appeal to all countries here to give practical support to the Syrian National Coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom has given over £7 million of non-lethal support, including communication equipment and human rights training.  We will provide a further £1 million in communication support, and look to expand our assistance, through the leadership of the National Coalition, following the deployment of a UK Stabilisation Response Team to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the new Assistance Coordination Unit established in Cairo, which will be able to help co-ordinate  non-lethal assistance to the Syrian people including to the Local Coordination Committees inside Syria, and we call on all countries here to give it active support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we increase our support to the Syrian people we must also increase the pressure on Assad and his allies. I call again on all countries to implement sanctions, and to ensure that their territory is not used as a conduit for arms or assistance to the regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Third, we must ensure the international community is ready to provide rapid assistance to a future government in Syria in order to help a political transition succeed. We need to be ready to react to change on the ground, which could happen suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We look to the National Coalition to develop further detailed plans for achieving and implementing transition working with all Syria’s communities, and to uphold human rights and international law, including humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fourth and finally, we must do more to alleviate Syria’s humanitarian tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom has provided £53.5 million so far in humanitarian aid which is providing 100,000 people with food, blankets and warm clothing, and we have helped 30,000 sick and wounded people by funding hospitals, mobile clinics and training for health workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many other countries have given generously too, but it cannot be right that the UN appeal for Syria is still underfunded.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we gather in this beautiful city we should remember that 50% of all Syria’s refugees are children. The majority are not in school, are living in makeshift shelters in the depths of winter, and many have lost their families. They represent Syria’s future. Their safety, their education, and their ability to return to their home matter to Syria, and to the peace and security of the region. So I urge all countries to do more to help share the burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As part of our new initiative on preventing sexual violence in conflict, the UK has deployed experts to the region to provide training on documentation of sexual violence which we hope will support future prosecutions and care for survivors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We do not know how long the conflict in Syria will last. But uniting the international community around these efforts, helping the National Coalition to win the confidence of the Syrian people, planning for a peaceful future for the country and protecting the victims of the violence on whom that future will rest, is surely the right way to seek to end the conflict and stop the appalling loss of life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Friends of Syria meeting" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4802/friends-of-Syria-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/unog/website/news_media.nsf/%28httpNewsByYear_en%29/18F70DBC923963B1C1257A2D0060696B?OpenDocument" title="Final communiqué of the Action Group for Syria"&gt;Geneva Declaration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative" title="Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict Initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
