<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/law-and-the-justice-system</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/law-and-the-justice-system"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/law-and-the-justice-system.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Law and the justice system"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55664</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:22:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism"/>
    <title>Protecting the UK against terrorism</title>
    <summary>Preventing terrorist attacks on the UK, and on British people and businesses abroad.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a threat to the UK, British nationals and our interests abroad from terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of these threats come from outside the UK and cannot be resolved by concentrating efforts in the UK alone. The government is addressing these threats at their source overseas before they reach the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s Counter Terrorism Strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/counter-terrorism-strategy/"&gt;CONTEST&lt;/a&gt;, reduces the risk from international terrorism so that people can go about their daily lives freely and with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on 4 main actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent: to stop people from becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pursue: to stop terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protect: to strengthen our protection against terrorist attack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prepare: where an attack cannot be stopped, to mitigate its impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prevent"&gt;Prevent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to stop people becoming terrorists or supporting terrorism in the UK and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;responding to the ideological challenge of terrorism and the threat we face from those who promote it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventing people from being drawn into terrorism and ensuring that they are given appropriate advice and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with sectors and institutions where there are risks of radicalisation which we need to address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/prevent/prevent-strategy/"&gt;latest information on the Prevent strategy&lt;/a&gt; on the Home Office website. This includes the full text of the strategy and the outcomes of the Prevent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pursue"&gt;Pursue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/pursue/"&gt;Pursue&lt;/a&gt; strand of the strategy means working to detect and investigate terrorist networks and disrupt their activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving our ability to identify and understand the terrorist threat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disrupting terrorist activity and taking action to frustrate terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bringing terrorists to justice through prosecution – this  includes strengthening the legal framework against terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing international co-operation with partners and allies to strengthen our ability to work together to disrupt terrorist networks, for instance by using &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-the-uk-against-terrorism/supporting-pages/deportation-with-assurances"&gt;Deportation with Assurances&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="protect"&gt;Protect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/protect/"&gt;Protect&lt;/a&gt; strand means seeking to reduce the vulnerability of the UK and its interests overseas from terrorist attack. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing accurate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/"&gt;FCO travel advice&lt;/a&gt; on the threat from domestic and international terrorism, with advice for British companies abroad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting key foreign governments to develop their ability to protect areas such as aviation and maritime security, energy infrastructure, crowded places and ‘soft’ targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="prepare"&gt;Prepare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/uk-counter-terrorism-strat/prepare/"&gt;Prepare&lt;/a&gt; strand means working to mitigate the impact of a terrorist attack where it cannot be stopped. This includes work to manage an ongoing attack and recover from its aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preparing the FCO network to respond to terrorist attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting foreign governments to develop their own ability to respond to terrorism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advances in technology by both terrorists and organised crime groups create challenges to our national security. The UK’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/science-and-technology/science-and-technology-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;Science and Technology Strategy for Countering International Terrorism&lt;/a&gt; uses innovation, science and technology to reduce the risk to the UK and its interests overseas from international terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al Qaeda is weaker than at any time since 9/11. It has played no role in recent political change in North Africa and the Middle East. Its ideology has been widely discredited and it has failed in all its objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continued international pressure has further reduced its capability and the UK is working with other countries to weaken terrorist threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, al Qaeda continues to be a significant threat and other terrorist groups, some affiliated to al Qaeda, have become stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/counter-terrorism/"&gt;Home Office&lt;/a&gt; is responsible for keeping the UK safe from the threat posed by terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The determination of the government and everyone involved in the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games was to create a safe and secure event that the UK and the world could enjoy. We thoroughly tested our plans to see how government departments, police and emergency services could respond to a range of incidents.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The games’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/counter-terrorism/olympics/olympic-safety-security-strategy?view=Binary"&gt;safety and security strategy&lt;/a&gt; has helped communities become more resilient to crime and the threat from violent extremism, and relationships between police and other security agencies have improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the event of a terrorist incident, the Office for Security and Counter-Terrorism is responsible for activating and co-ordinating the Home Office response. We provide a crisis response 24 hours a day, 365 days of the year. The government’s response to all kinds of emergencies, including terrorism, is set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaem.com/regions/iaemeuropa/documents/UKConOps.pdf"&gt;Central government arrangements for responding to an emergency: concept of operations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55648</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T16:25:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T16:25:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-jets-arrive-at-raf-northolt-for-olympics-role"/>
    <title>Typhoon jets arrive at RAF Northolt for Olympics role</title>
    <summary>Typhoon fighter jets arrived at RAF Northolt today to take part in a major military exercise to test security for the forthcoming London Olympic Games.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time fighter planes have been stationed at RAF Northolt since the Second World War. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jets’ arrival marks the start of specialist training which will result in increased flying activity over London and the Home Counties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codenamed Olympic Guardian, the nine-day exercise will put airmen, soldiers and sailors through their paces in the skies over the South East. The exercise runs from 2 to 10 May, and it is likely that people will notice an increase in highly visible air activity (particularly on 5 and 6 May).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise will test the procedures military aircrews will use to intercept and communicate with aircraft breaching restricted airspace during the Olympics, and the actions they must take in response. Pilots entering restricted airspace can expect to be intercepted by Typhoon fighters or military helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air security plan for the Olympic Games builds on the Royal Air Force’s existing defence of UK airspace, which includes round-the-clock radar surveillance and Typhoon fighters held at high readiness every day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise integrates the additional forces being used to ensure the safety of the Olympics, as part of the Ministry of Defence’s role to ensure a safe and secure Games this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• the Typhoon fighters which arrived at RAF Northolt today&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• RAF Puma aircraft - together with Royal Navy and Army Lynx helicopters - carrying teams of RAF Regiment snipers to intercept aircraft in restricted airspace, and &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• airborne surveillance aircraft including RAF E-3D Sentry aircraft and Royal Navy Sea King ASaC (Airborne Surveillance and Control) helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An RAF Typhoon arrives at RAF Northolt" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4955/Typhoon_jets_arrive_at_RAF_Northolt_for_Olympics_role-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An RAF Typhoon arrives at RAF Northolt [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Steve Buckley, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the ground, the RAF is providing additional mobile ground radar systems (Type 101 radar), while the Army is deploying air observers and high velocity and Rapier missile systems, which also provide radar detection capability, to provide additional layers of radar coverage. A final decision on the deployment of these capabilities has yet to be taken by the Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Defence, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst there is no specific threat to the Games, we have to be ready to assist in delivering a safe and secure Olympics for all to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The fact that our state-of-the-art Typhoons will be stationed at RAF Northolt underlines the commitment of the Ministry of Defence and our Armed Forces to keeping the public safe at a time when the world will be watching us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Stuart Atha, Air Component Commander for Olympics Air Security, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we undertake this essential training, there will be a visible and audible presence of RAF Typhoon and military helicopters operating above Greater London and the Home Counties. There will also be flights occurring throughout the exercise period to allow pilots and other forces to become familiar with operating in the London and Home Counties airspace.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have sought to limit the amount of flying to the minimum required to ensure that our Forces are ready for their important role delivering air security for the Olympics, balancing this against the need for us to reduce disturbance to a minimum. But we hope that people will understand the need for this very important training, and we thank them for their continued strong support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council in a Written Ministerial Statement.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35569</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-highlights-risk-of-kidnap-to-british-nationals-in-sahel-region"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa highlights risk of kidnap to British nationals in Sahel region</title>
    <summary>Minister for Africa, Mark Simmonds, met members of the travel industry today to explain and emphasise the FCO’s travel advice on the Sahel region to British nationals, including the high risk of kidnap in certain areas of the Sahel and North Africa.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Simmonds detailed how the kidnap threat to western travellers in Mali and some neighbouring areas had grown as a result of instability in the region.  He reinforced how seriously the British Government takes the threat to British nationals overseas. Foreign Office officials asked the industry to highlight the risks and consider alternative options where travellers can still find adventure, but be safe too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Simmonds said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The British government takes the threat to British nationals overseas extremely seriously.  We urge tour operators, including rally organisers, to work with us to make sure that British nationals are fully aware of the serious risks involved in travelling to these areas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The terrorist groups Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb (AQ-M) and the splinter group, the Movement for Unity and Jihad in West Africa, pose the greatest kidnap threat. Since the recent coup in Mali, both groups have increased their operational reach and have proven capability to travel long distances to kidnap victims.  They have also been known to use criminal gangs to conduct attacks and pass hostages to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Attacks have taken place in Mali, Niger, Mauritania and Algeria. We also assess that they have operational reach into the north of Burkina Faso and southern Libya and I am sorry to say that the situation is likely to still get worse.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55174</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-supports-get-safe-online-week"/>
    <title>MOD supports 'Get Safe Online Week'</title>
    <summary>The MOD is backing 'Get Safe Online Week' in a bid to encourage both civilian and Service personnel to guard their personal information when using social media channels.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new document has been released by the Department in support of the campaign, providing guidance for staff on communicating using social media sites like Twitter, Facebook and YouTube so they don’t do or say things that bring themselves and their Service into disrepute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the awareness week, the MOD is rerunning videos from last year’s ‘Think Before You…’ campaign on our social media channels. ‘Think Before You…’ is a reminder that personal and operational security should be a primary concern and that social media merely provides a different context where sensitive details can be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff’s (CDS’s) Strategic Communications Officer said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Social media has enabled our personnel to stay in touch with their families and their friends no matter where they are in the world. We want our men and women to embrace the use of sites like Twitter, Facebook, LinkedIn and YouTube, but also want them to be aware of the risks that sharing too much information may pose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You don’t always know who else is watching in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD Headquarters has its own Facebook, YouTube and Twitter feeds and we see no reason to stop our personnel from tweeting or posting on their own walls. But the MOD has a responsibility to warn personnel of the risks they could be exposing themselves to, hence the launch of this new campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDS’s Strategic Communications Officer added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not want to scare Service personnel, families and veterans and we certainly do not want them to stop using social media. We are not here to gag people because we acknowledge the ubiquity and significant benefits that social media offers to people and the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of Facebook and Twitter and I use them on a regular basis. These channels are vital to communicating in a digital age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risks to Service personnel - and potentially their families - include posting details and locations of troop movements and operational events, locations and travel details of ships or aircraft, and people’s home addresses. If inadvertently released, information such as this could give the UK’s enemies the upper hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Get Safe Online Week’ runs from 22 to 26 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.getsafeonline.org/"&gt;Get Safe Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.blogs.mod.uk/onlinesecurity/"&gt;Personal Security Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hpKiIrYDLxg"&gt;Video: Personal Security Online 1 (Full)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6bXzU5Xe78Y"&gt;Video: Personal Security Online 2 (Teaser)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kUVKXSmsRHs"&gt;Video: Think Before You Share Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35309</id>
    <published>2012-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-09T19:10:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/airborne-supply-experts-train-for-rapid-reaction-role"/>
    <title>Airborne supply experts train for rapid reaction role</title>
    <summary>The supply and maintenance support provided to the British Army's Rapid Reaction Force has been put to the test on Exercise Active Chariot</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The role of Colchester-based 13 Air Assault Support Regiment Royal Logistic Corps (13 AA Sp Regt RLC) is to supply ammunition, food, fuel and spare parts to 16 Air Assault Brigade’s Air Assault Task Force (AATF), which is ready to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice to do anything from disaster relief to war-fighting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training in Norfolk placed troops six weeks into an operation, with heavy equipment having arrived in support of an initial airborne assault. The former RAF base at Sculthorpe had been established as a logistics base to supply infantry operations 30 miles (48km) away, near Thetford, with supply depots, workshops and accommodation set up in derelict hangars. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Vehicle mechanics of 7 Air Assault Battalion Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers at work during Exercise Active Chariot" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1562/Airborne_supply_experts_train_for_rapid_reaction_role2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Vehicle mechanics of 7 Air Assault Battalion Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers at work during Exercise Active Chariot
[Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Alistair Hamilton said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can insert logistics troops and supplies by parachute during the early phases of an operation and build from there. As more troops and kit arrive it makes for more complex logistical challenges as the demand for supplies rises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve been practising how supplies get to us, such as airborne drops from Hercules transport aircraft, how we get supplies forward using helicopters and lorries, and how we run distribution points to give the supplies to the troops that need them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rigging vehicles to be carried under helicopters is a key skill that troops have practised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Michael Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rigging is all about keeping a load balanced. We do a lot of classroom work to learn the principles and practise preparing different vehicles and loads, but there’s nothing like doing it with a helicopter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as their core logistic role the unit was tested with mock attacks on the base, including countering the threat of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (CBRN) weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Hamilton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has been good training to get all of our skills and drills right, but also to train the units we’re supporting in what we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 Field Company, 7 Air Assault Battalion Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers, which is responsible for maintaining the AATF’s vehicles, weapons and electronic equipment, also operated from Sculthorpe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit sent teams out to repair equipment in the field or bring it back to Sculthorpe for more complicated work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Corporal Tom Walker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve been given some tough repairs to do without the spares and tools there are in barracks. Our soldiering has been tested too, with guard duty in CBRN kit a new experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training was carried out in parallel with Exercise Active Eagle that tested the fieldcraft of 5th Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland, the AATF’s main infantry unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27456</id>
    <published>2012-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-italy-statement-on-counter-terrorism-co-operation"/>
    <title>UK-Italy statement on counter terrorism co-operation</title>
    <summary>Statement issued by UK Foreign Secretary William Hague and his Italian counterpart Minister Giulio Terzi.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Terzi and Foreign Secretary Hague discussed the continued threat facing the United Kingdom and Italy from terrorism, so tragically underlined by events in Nigeria two weeks ago.  We confirmed our intention to intensify our already close co-operation and consultation in this area and agreed to establish a UK-Italy High Level Group on terrorism to oversee this work. This Group will meet at senior official level, and will look at the full range of our co-operation on counter-terrorism and related issues, including counter-kidnap, piracy, radicalisation, Yemen, Somalia and Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we have agreed today to pursue the following areas of joint activity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the tragic deaths of Chris McManus and Franco Lamolinara in Nigeria two weeks ago, we will support further work to build regional capacity to tackle the kidnap threat posed by terrorist groups, who operate across borders and target victims regardless of nationality.  As a first step, the UK and Italy will consider how best to help strengthen Nigeria’s capacity to tackle the threat posed by terrorism, including through support to regional law enforcement and security co-ordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been at the forefront of the international effort to protect the people of Libya during their struggle for change, the UK and Italy share a common desire to help build a stable and secure future for that country. We will offer further support to the Libyan authorities to prevent terrorists from taking advantage of the proliferation of arms and fighters in Libya and the wider region following the Libyan conflict.  Identifying and understanding these threats will be essential in supporting Libya and its neighbours in their efforts to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Yemen, we have agreed to explore joint co-operation in the policing and justice reform sector.  As progress is made by the Government of Yemen in pushing Al Qaeda out of Yemen, it is important to ensure that civilian police fill the vacuum left behind.  The UK and Italy have important experience in this area.  The challenge is significant and we will work closely with our EU and other partners to support the Yemeni Government as they train police and improve justice capacity throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27416</id>
    <published>2012-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/joint-uk-italian-statement-on-hostage-rescue-operation-in-nigeria"/>
    <title>Joint UK-Italian statement on hostage rescue operation in Nigeria</title>
    <summary>UK and Italy reaffirmed that they will continue to work together closely in the fight against terrorism and hostage-taking.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;UK Foreign Secretary William Hague and Italian Foreign Minister Giulio Terzi di Sant’Agata met earlier today at the informal Foreign Ministers meeting in Copenhagen.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They discussed the recent hostage rescue operation in Nigeria following yesterday’s conversation between Prime Ministers Monti and Cameron.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague made clear that there had been a limited opportunity to secure the release of the two hostages whose lives were in imminent and growing danger.  Under these circumstances it was only possible to inform Italy once the operation was already getting underway.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Terzi expressed deep sorrow and disappointment over the tragic outcome of the operation and both ministers agreed on the urgency of sharing full information to facilitate the reconstruction and understanding of these events.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Ministers conveyed their solidarity and sympathy for the families of Chris McManus and Franco Lamolinara.  They reaffirmed that the UK and Italy will continue to work together closely in the fight against such horrific terrorism and hostage-taking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27233</id>
    <published>2012-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/kenya-travel-advice-update"/>
    <title>Kenya travel advice update</title>
    <summary>We advise against all but essential travel within 60km of the Somali border inland from the coastal strip, and to Garissa, due to continuing instability.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office has updated its travel advice for Kenya.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We advise against all but essential travel to within 60km of the Somali border, to coastal areas within 150km of the Kenya-Somalia border (this includes the Lamu area), to Garissa district and to low income areas of Nairobi, including all township or slum areas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kenyan authorities have alerted the public to a heightened threat from terrorist attacks in Nairobi. We believe that terrorists may be in the final stages of planning attacks. Attacks could be indiscriminate and target Kenyan institutions as well as places where expatriates and foreign travellers gather, such as hotels, shopping centres and beaches. We strongly advise British Nationals to exercise extra vigilance and caution in public places and at public events.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FCO Travel Advice is kept under constant review.  We will continue to monitor the situation closely and make further updates as necessary. Further details can be found in the updated &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/sub-saharan-africa/kenya1"&gt;travel advice on our website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27226</id>
    <published>2012-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-fac-report-on-piracy"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes FAC report on piracy</title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague has welcomed the Foreign Affairs Committee (FAC) report "Piracy off the Coast of Somalia".</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement today, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the FAC’s report into Piracy off the coast of Somalia. Somali piracy has grown into a major international problem, exacerbating the wider challenges we face in helping Somalia recover from conflict and drought. We will use the London Conference on Somalia to chart a way forward on the future political direction of Somalia, the vital humanitarian effort and the international community’s approach to tackling piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I particularly welcome the FAC’s clear support for our military engagement in the Gulf of Aden and in the wider Indian Ocean, for our position on establishing an extra-territorial Somali court, and policy of prosecuting pirates in local courts and our prisoner transfer agreements. Britain will continue to work with the UN, African Union, regional partners and the Somali people to build a stable Somalia and through our work with DFID to build sustainable alternative livelihoods for coastal communities in Somalia.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
