<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55268</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65m contract to refit Royal Navy's largest warship secures hundreds of UK jobs</title>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65M upgrade, the MOD announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on the helicopter carrier will secure more than 600 UK jobs. The warship was moored on the Thames during the Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;Devonport Royal Dockyard&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to her radar, gun, command system and living quarters. Around 1,200 metres of new pipe work will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter number 10 dock at Devonport Royal Naval Dockyard to begin her refit 
[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible, and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympic duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache attack helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12879</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories"/>
    <title>Protecting and developing the overseas territories</title>
    <summary>Working with the Overseas Territories on the challenges they face and encouraging strong local economies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a broad responsibility to support the Overseas Territories and to ensure their security and good governance. Britain and territory governments share significant challenges: building more diverse and resilient economies; cutting public sector deficits; regulating finance businesses effectively; and protecting biodiversity and natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-overseas-territories-programme-fund"&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories Programme Fund supports the work of government to maintain the security, stability and prosperity of the Overseas Territories. This fund supports the economic, security, environmental and governance strategies in the government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/publications/overseas-territories-white-paper-0612/ot-wp-0612"&gt;white paper on the Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Where-we-work/Overseas-Territories/"&gt;Department for International Development (&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; provides budgetary support for Montserrat, Pitcairn and St Helena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Documents/publications1/op/ovseas-terr-dept-2011.pdf"&gt;Department for International Development’s Operational Plan 2011-2015&lt;/a&gt; explains how money is allocated to the territories and how expenditure is monitored for effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="environment-and-climate-fund-darwin-plus"&gt;Environment and climate fund: Darwin Plus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government launched &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2012/10/17/2-million-a-year-overseas-territories-fund/"&gt;Darwin Plus: Overseas Territories Environment and Climate Fund&lt;/a&gt;, an environment and climate fund for the UK’s Overseas Territories, in October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fund consists of contributions from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;), and &lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;. The fund will disburse around £2 million per year dedicated to a range of environment and climate-related projects to improve long-term natural resource management in the Overseas Territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance and application forms for the fund are available on &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;DEFRA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://darwin.defra.gov.uk/news/2012-10/darwin-plus/%20%E2%80%9CDarwin%20Initiative%E2%80%9D"&gt;Darwin Initiative website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="protecting-the-overseas-territories"&gt;Protecting the Overseas Territories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the UK’s main military tasks is to provide security to the nation and its overseas territories. The Ministry of Defence (&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a security policy in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/1AD4AFE6-4946-4BAC-A3A6-7AFBF9AA25BF/0/overseas_territories.pdf"&gt;Overseas Territories: the Ministry of Defence’s contribution&lt;/a&gt;, which explains how the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; will protect the Overseas Territories from 2012 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-the-public-sectors"&gt;Supporting the public sectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have set up the Jubilee Programme to share experience between public servants in the territories and the UK by giving territory officials opportunities to train and work with colleagues in the UK, and vice versa, encouraging long-term partnerships between the territories and public bodies in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Overseas Territories are very diverse, with thousands of small islands, vast areas of ocean, but also, in Antarctica, land 6 times the size of the United Kingdom. They include one of the world’s richest communities, in Bermuda; the most remote community, in Tristan da Cunha and one of the smallest, with only 54 people living on Pitcairn Island. The total population of the territories is roughly a quarter of a million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 14 British Overseas Territories and most have a permanent resident population. The exceptions are the British Indian Ocean Territory and the British Antarctic Territory, and South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands, of which the latter have research stations. The Sovereign Base Areas on Cyprus have a resident population of Cypriot nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 14 Overseas Territories are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/anguilla/"&gt;Anguilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/north-central-america/bermuda/"&gt;Bermuda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/british-indian-ocean-territory/"&gt;British Indian Ocean Territory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinbvi.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The British Virgin Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukincayman.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Cayman Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/falkland-islands/"&gt;The Falkland Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/europe/gibraltar/"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinmontserrat.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;Montserrat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/asia-oceania/pitcairn-islands/"&gt;The Pitcairn, Henderson, Ducie &amp;amp; Oeno Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/st-helena/"&gt;Saint Helena&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/ascension-Island/"&gt;Ascension&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/tristan-da-cunha/"&gt;Tristan da Cunha (including Gough Island Dependency)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/south-america/south-georgia-south-sandwich/"&gt;South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas, Akrotiri and Dhekelia (on Cyprus)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://turksandcaicosislands.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;The Turks &amp;amp; Caicos Islands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can email enquiries about &lt;a href="enquiry.gibraltar@fco.gov.uk"&gt;Gibraltar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For enquiries about the Sovereign Base Areas, visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sbaadministration.org/home/index.html"&gt;Sovereign Base Areas website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12844</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-operational-readiness-to-provide-military-support-for-activities-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>Maintaining operational readiness to provide military support for activities in the UK</title>
    <summary>Civil authorities have resources to cope with a wide range of emergencies but if they lack capability or are overwhelmed by the scale of events they can ask the Ministry of Defence for assistance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is constantly refining its ability to provide an effective response to all types of emergencies and major crises at national, regional and local level. This means having a pre-planned, coordinated response from the emergency services, civil authorities and where appropriate, the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is an emergency or crisis situation in the UK, local emergency services provide the first response. Government departments or civil authorities can also call on the Ministry of Defence for military help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces support is officially known as Military Aid to the Civil Authorities (MACA). The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/36/contents"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; states that military support is available for major incidents when the capability or capacity of civilian authorities has been overwhelmed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no standing military forces for these tasks so support isn’t guaranteed and when it is provided the civil authorities normally have to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces can be brought in to deal with a range of situations including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural disasters - helping people in severe weather situations, such as flooding, where there is a need to protect human life, property and alleviate distress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network failure or disruption - including animal disease epidemics and public service-related industrial disputes that affect our safety or security, or disrupt transport or communications links&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;criminal or terrorist activity - where there is a need, providing specialist expertise in specific circumstances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bomb disposal - known officially as ‘explosive ordnance disposal’, this can be related to terrorism, or involve unearthing a bomb from World War 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue - helping people in danger, searching for sunken vessels or aircraft, carrying out underwater or mountain rescue tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK waters - protecting our territorial waters, ports, ships and energy installations from terrorist attack, protecting fisheries, preventing drug or people smuggling and dealing with pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK airspace - detecting and deterring aircraft approaching UK sovereign airspace and protecting UK and NATO monitored airspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of recent emergencies and crises that needed help from the armed forces include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing security for the 2012 Olympics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue operations during widespread flooding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping UK travellers stranded by the Icelandic ash cloud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;managing the disposal of infected cattle during the ‘mad cow’ disease outbreak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detailed information for civil authorities on handling crises is contained in the guidance &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-response-and-recovery"&gt;Emergency Response and Recovery&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-preparedness"&gt;Emergency Preparedness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/securing-britain-age-uncertainty-strategic-defence-and-security-review"&gt;Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR): Securing Britain in an age of uncertainty 2010&lt;/a&gt; sets out how the defence establishment will contribute effectively to civil crises and emergencies in the UK, balancing against other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-strategy-for-deploying-the-armed-forces-in-the-uk"&gt;The strategy for deploying the Armed Forces in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All defence operations including those in the UK must be authorised by the Defence Council. The Secretary of State for Defence is the government minister responsible for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and there is a single chain of command that connects to service personnel on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a crisis the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Deputy Chief of the Defence Staff (Military Strategy and Operations) and the Director General Security Policy give guidance to ministers and other government departments. In this way, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; acts as both a military HQ and a department of state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Contingencies Act 2004 (&lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) defines how organisations, particularly local responders, prepare for emergencies. In the event of an emergency in which the supply and distribution of the essentials of life to the community are extensively threatened, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt; can be used to invoke emergency powers on a local, regional or national basis. The full &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/civil-contingencies-act"&gt;text of the Act&lt;/a&gt; is available from the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to deploy service personnel would be authorised by the Defence Council and they may be given the power to requisition equipment and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 2 of the the Emergency Powers Act 1964, the Defence Council may authorise the temporary deployment of service personnel on urgent work of national importance. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1964/38/contents"&gt;Read the full text of the Act&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <summary>Opening up access to the Tipner site for businesses and visitors.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54835</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-monitoring-and-evaluation-framework"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport fund monitoring and evaluation framework</title>
    <summary>Expectations for the monitoring and evaluation of projects funded through the Local Sustainable Transport fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework sets out the department’s requirements from the monitoring and evaluation activity of Local Sustainable Transport fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) projects and the roles of the department and project teams in delivering these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework articulates which &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects are expected to fulfil which elements of monitoring and evaluation and provides project teams with the flexibility to collect evidence in a way that reflects the local variation of projects and data availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54827</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-draft-council-tax-reduction-schemes-prescribed-requirements-and-default-scheme-england-amendment-regulations-2012"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Draft Council Tax reduction schemes (prescribed requirements and default scheme) (England) (amendment) regulations 2012</title>
    <summary>This draft statutory instrument affects the upratings of default schemes and pension credit age schemes. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 7 September 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) confirmed its intention to update and align the premia/ applicable amounts in regulations for the default and pensioner schemes with current rates/ Department for Work and Pensions’ (&lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt;) autumn uprating. This would be done using Housing Benefit amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; said it would be working with &lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt; (again, in relation to the pension credit age and default schemes) to model the way in which non-dependent deductions would have been uprated had council tax benefit continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This draft statutory instrument effects these upratings and is being published ahead of the regulations being made, to give authorities early notice of the changes required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39721</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <summary>Royal Marines and Albanian forces recently joined together for an assault on an abandoned Soviet submarine base as part of Exercise Albanian Lion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham welcomes the ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ end of year review.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/34108</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T12:36:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-reduction-scheme-taking-account-of-universal-credit-income"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax reduction scheme - taking account of universal credit income</title>
    <summary>This document provides some worked examples of how default scheme universal credit provisions operate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In October 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government published a document setting out how the default scheme will take account of claimants receiving universal credit, and how these measures will help to support positive work incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to feedback from interested parties, this document now provides some worked examples of how default scheme universal credit provisions operate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <summary>A report setting out the progress the government is making to 'decentralise' power from Whitehall across the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
