<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16974</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-funding-arrangements"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: funding arrangements</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions for local council tax support schemes in England. This document sets out how the Government intends to distribute funding to support local schemes and seeks views on possible adjustments to allocations to avoid potential budgetary pressures in a few authorities. It is published alongside statements of intent for the key sets of regulations which will provide the legal framework for local schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16714</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: calculating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <summary>Consultation about how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16957</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-weston-transport-improvements"/>
    <title>Green light for Weston transport improvements</title>
    <summary>Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare has been given final approval today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will support economic growth in Weston-super-Mare and reduce congestion in the town centre. The work will also improve links between local roads and the M5 motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to increase capacity of the M5 Junction 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new link road for buses to access Worle railway station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bus priority measures at junctions and bus only sections to improve bus access to the south of Worle Station, linking it with regeneration areas at Weston Airfield and Locking Parklands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new 320 space car park with a bus interchange, drop-off and cycle facilities together with improvements to the north-side car park at Worle Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased capacity between the town centre and the regeneration areas through road widening and new routes for pedestrians and cyclists as well as bus priority measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great scheme that will support employment, reduce congestion and make it easier for people using public transport in and around Weston-super-Mare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £10.4 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country and the region needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Weston package scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work is currently planned to start in March 2013 with the package scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Weston package scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The package of measures, promoted by North Somerset Council, is scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16871</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:44:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-transport-bodies"/>
    <title>Guidance for Local Transport Bodies</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has announced its firm intention to devolve funding for local major transport schemes to Local Transport Bodies from 2015. The guidance sets out the necessary arrangement Local Transport Bodies will need to have in place to ensure value for money and sound decision making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16840</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T10:48:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/list-of-certifications-granted-for-approved-devices"/>
    <title>List of certifications granted for 'approved devices'</title>
    <summary>CCTV and evidence-recording equipment must be certified under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List of certifications granted by the Secretary of State for Transport for ‘approved devices’, CCTV and associated evidence-recording equipment, under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tma-part-6-certification-of-approved-devices"&gt;Civil traffic enforcement: certification of approved devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16882</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:46:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/housing-capital-receipts-exemptions-from-regulations"/>
    <title>Housing capital receipts: exemptions from regulations</title>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities applying to use receipts from the disposal of council housing assets in ways not prescribed in regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of receipts arising from the disposal of housing assets (ie assets held under part 2 of the Housing Act 1985 and for which account is made in the Housing Revenue Account) is governed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/1324/made"&gt;Local Authorities (Capital Finance and Accounting) (England) Regulations 2003 (as amended.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations require that, in short: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receipts arising from Right to Buy (and similar sales may be retained to cover the cost of transacting the sales and to cover the debt on the properties sold, but a proportion of the remainder must be surrendered to central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receipts arising from all other disposals may be retained in full provided they are spent on affordable housing, regeneration or the paying down of housing debt (each of which is defined in the regulations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, section 11(6) of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents"&gt;Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; (as inserted by section 174 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;) permits the secretary of state to enter into agreements with local authorities with the effect that any requirement imposed by these regulations does not apply, or is modified in its application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enter into such an agreement it is necessary for any interested authority to make an application to the secretary of state. This guidance sets out the Department for Communities and Local Government’s policy on such exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16890</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T14:26:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/weekly-collection-saved-as-government-scheme-delivers-for-6-million-families"/>
    <title>‘Weekly collection saved’ as government scheme delivers for 6 million families </title>
    <summary>Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles today announced that over 6 million families will keep getting a weekly bin service. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is thanks to the government’s £250 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/supporting-pages/bins-and-waste-collection"&gt;Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best 90 projects, from 85 councils, have today been selected from an over-subscribed scheme to share in the funding. Ministers are concerned that without the fund weekly bin collections could have all but disappeared by 2015, as is happening in other parts of the United Kingdom, such as Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Disraeli’s Public Health Act 1875 which first introduced a duty on local authorities to collect rubbish; this duty was enhanced by the Public Health Act 1936 obliging councils to collect household waste weekly. Weekly collections were the norm for decades, but started disappearing from 2000 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, 41 schemes will offer genuine rewards (such as shopping vouchers or loyalty points) for recycling so more families can go green without facing punitive fines and taxes, meeting an important coalition agreement pledge. It is hoped that such new schemes will encourage further take-up across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund was set up in February to support comprehensive and cost effective weekly collections that harness innovation, use new technology and spread reward schemes to increase recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils already receive funding for bin collections through central government formula grant and from the money raised locally via Council Tax: in total, council spending will be £114 million this year. A further 4 million households continue to provide weekly collections outside the support scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. Another survey found that two-thirds of the public thought government should mandate weekly collections; that weekly collections were better; and that problems with flies and smells were much worse with fortnightly collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government has already scrapped bin taxes plans via the Localism Act; reversed Audit Commission rules which marked down councils for not adopting fortnightly rubbish collections; and abolished Whitehall targets which created perverse incentives to downgrade waste collection services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will continue to work with Defra to spread best practice on weekly collections, challenge poor procurement or unpopular approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every Englishman has a basic right to have their household rubbish taken away each and every week - it is the most visible council service people get. Yet under the previous administration weekly bin collections halved while their Council Tax bills doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over 6 million families will breathe a sigh of relief tonight because we have put a stop to the fetid fortnightly rot and saved many weekly collections from extinction, all while increasing recycling rates by hundreds of thousands of tonnes to boot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Weekly Collection Support Scheme encourages councils to focus on 4 things: better weekly collections, cost effective bids, environmental improvements and better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment. 118 councils submitted final bids. For more information, see the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15038/Weekly_Collection_Support_Scheme_-_successful_bids.xls"&gt;list of 90 winning bids&lt;/a&gt;, which gives a short description of what each of the schemes will do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence: opinion research they carried out actually found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. (Ipsos-MORI, ‘Weekly or fortnightly: Public attitudes to waste collections’, July 2008.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fortnightly collections rose from just 13 councils across the United Kingdom in 2000 to 225 in 2008 (Alternate weekly collections conference, aspects of alternate weekly collection, July 2008). In Northern Ireland, as of 2010 to 2011, 92% of local authorities offer a fortnightly collection; in Scotland 72%, and Wales 77% according to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wrap.org.uk/" title="WRAP"&gt;WRAP’s&lt;/a&gt;, local authority waste and recycling information portal, statistics for 2010 to 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Sauce-Icaro attitudes to waste and recycling in Great Britain, December 2011 found that two-thirds (67%) agreed with the statement the government should mandate weekly collections. Weekly collections had higher satisfaction levels than fortnightly (83% compared to 74%). Reports of problems with flies and smells for fortnightly collections were more than double that for weekly (14% compared to 6%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What next: in the weeks to come the department will begin working with councils, the Local Government Association and Defra to support them to work together to procure the best deals as consortiums or groups to ensure value for money for the taxpayer. This means the department has provided a synopsis of each successful bid, but will not be disclosing further specific bid details as this would have an adverse effect on competition between prospective companies and potentially put local authorities in a disadvantageous position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16664</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T14:24:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-rewards-for-local-growth-under-new-scheme"/>
    <title>Greater rewards for local growth under new scheme</title>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis has set out how local retention of business rates will reward councils for local economic growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; creates a new model for funding local authorities from April 2013, linking their financial revenue to the decisions they take to support local firms and local jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government will retain a 50% local share of business rates and then keep a 50% share of any growth they generate, subject to a levy, providing a strong incentive to go for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new system could deliver around an extra £10 billion to the wider economy by 2020, and generate more business rate income for councils to help pay off the deficit and support frontline services that protect vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following consultation responses, the government has changed the approach to the levy to increase the rewards for growth. The maximum levy will now be 50p in the pound. This translates into very real benefits for authorities: after the central share and levy payments, at least 25p in each extra pound of business rates generated locally will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document also confirms the safety net for when councils experience unexpected drops in revenue will guarantee a real terms income from business rates of 92.5%. This means council income will never fall below 7.5% of its baseline funding level ensuring no area gets left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document confirms that the government will implement the majority of the technical proposals for the operation of the scheme set out in the summer consultation, together with changes to a number of detailed aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, after listening to councils, we are setting the central principles for how the new rate retention scheme will work next year. Ahead of the formal funding settlement next month this will give councils the certainty and security to begin planning their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The old flawed system of government handouts to local authorities encouraged a begging bowl mentality, with each council vying to be more deprived than its neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These reforms allow councils to stand tall, and rewards them for supporting local jobs and local firms. All councils, including the least prosperous, have the opportunity to gain from this system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation originally proposed a levy set at higher ratio. This would have meant that a district council with a business rates baseline of £100 million and a baseline funding level of £5 million would have been subject to a levy rate of 95p in the pound. So if the authority realised business rates growth of £2 million, £1 million of this would have been paid to the central share, £200,000 would have been paid to the county council, and £760,000 would have been paid in a levy, leaving the authority with £40,000 of growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s document confirms that levy rate will in fact be limited to 50p in the pound creating a much greater growth reward. This would leave that same authority with £400,000, ie 10 times more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"&gt;Business rates retention: policy statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/a-plain-english-guide-to-business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention: plain English guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates-retention"&gt;Written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16636</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-when-dwellings-should-not-be-liable-to-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: when dwellings should not be liable to the empty homes premium</title>
    <summary>Consultation about the government's proposals on homes that should not be charged the empty homes premium.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; allows a billing authority to charge an empty homes premium to provide a stronger incentive to get homes back into productive use and remove the blight of such properties on local neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premium was subject to a consultation, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"&gt;Technical Reforms to Council Tax&lt;/a&gt;’, which ended on 29 December 2011. The government published its response on 28 May 2012, which confirmed its intention to proceed with the premium and stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will not be payable until a dwelling has been empty and unfurnished for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the maximum premium that an authority will be able to charge will be 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation invited views on the government’s proposals on exceptions to the premium: dwellings which may otherwise be liable for the premium, but which are subject to circumstances that mean that it would not be appropriate for it to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary of responses was published on 21 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
