<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55970</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-for-everyone"/>
    <title>Transport for everyone </title>
    <summary>Putting accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker is calling on operators and local authorities to work with government to put accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help them to do this, the Department for Transport has published 2 action plans which set out priorities, as well as highlighting areas where action is in the pipeline or already underway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Transport for everyone’ outlines how operators, local councils and the Department can help to make it easier for people using public transport – particularly those with disabilities - to get to where they need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action plan builds on the success achieved in improving accessibility on public transport during the Olympics and Paralympics. At the heart of the plan is the importance of improving door-to-door journeys rather than addressing issues in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s equality action plan looks at how we can encourage a more inclusive transport network and underlines the importance of ensuring that policy makers at all levels are alive to the particular needs and concerns of different groups in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include affordability issues for young people and pensioners and the ability for all people to travel in safety and free from harassment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good transport system allows people to access jobs, opportunities and vital services - it needs to work for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the concerns that specific groups of people have about public transport and so we have pulled together ideas from across the transport sector on how these concerns can be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The action plans will help policy makers, as well as transport operators, to tackle problems head on and - more importantly - to level the playing field for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Sayce OBE, Disability Rights UK Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An accessible transport infrastructure is essential for what Disability Rights UK wants to achieve – disabled people playing a full and equal part in society. Over the past 20 years we have come a long way as our practical guide ‘Doing transport differently’ shows but there are still too many attitudinal, communication and physical barriers facing disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Action plan’ is a step change towards making further progress. We welcome the commitment that the Department for Transport will continue to work in partnership with disabled people and our organisations to ensure the most effective steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Accessibility action plan’ builds on the transport successes of the Olympic and Paralympic Games and aims to create a long lasting legacy of improved access and information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Olympic and Paralympic Games, public transport operators carried thousands of spectators with disabilities and work was done to ensure that the travelling public had easy access to information. One of the aims of the ‘Accessibility action plan’ will be to build on the Games Spectator Journey Planner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new planner would cover a wider geographical area and more types of transport as well as being made accessible to people with visual impairments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other measures outlined in the plan include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considering where £100 million of extra funding might be best spent in the long term to improve accessibility of railway stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible further amendments to the Blue Badge scheme to tackle abuse and fraud in this area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building on guidance for mobility scooters and powered wheelchairs to encourage training for those using this equipment &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Equality action plan’ sets out in one place what the department is doing to ensure people from all parts of society have the option to use public transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points addressed in the plan include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessibility to public transport for young people, older people and those living in rural areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety and personal security for women travellers, particularly at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling hate crime and bullying on buses and other public transport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promoting employment of under-represented groups within the transport industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both documents include lists of issues and the actions that have been, or will be, taken to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Accessibility action plan’&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;‘Equality action plan’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the interests of transparency and to enable as many people as possible to have their say, the ‘Equality action plan’ will be open for comment until 15 February. These will feed in to a final version of the document which will be published in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55824</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:34:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:34:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-13-december-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 13 December 2012</title>
    <summary>Several sets of figures including quarterly bus usage, port freight and vehicle licensing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) has published the following transport statistics: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/transport-statistics-great-britain-2012"&gt;transport statistics Great Britain: 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/quarterly-bus-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;quarterly bus statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/vehicle-licensing-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;vehicle licensing statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/national-travel-survey-2011"&gt;national travel survey: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agencys-motorway-and-a-road-network-october-2012"&gt;reliability of journeys on the Highways Agencys motorway and ‘A’ road network: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See statistics at &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; for details on all &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55866</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/accessibility-action-plan-and-equality-action-plan"/>
    <title>Accessibility action plan and equality action plan</title>
    <summary>Release of the accessibility action plan and equality action plan.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today pleased to be publishing the department’s accessibility action plan &lt;a href="/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Transport for Everyone: an action plan to improve accessibility for all’&lt;/a&gt;, and, for comment, a draft &lt;a href="/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;equality action plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has already been achieved in making transport more accessible, and the accessibility action plan seeks to address the challenges that remain. In doing so, we also want to draw on the success of the Olympic and Paralympic Games which demonstrated what can be done to provide those using our public transport system with a positive experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility action plan focuses not only on improving physical accessibility, but also on providing better information for the traveller, and on improving attitudes and behaviour, especially towards disabled passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying our priorities in the action plan, we have worked with a large number of representative organisations, individuals, transport operators and local authorities. I am grateful for the support and input that they have provided.  We want transport to be accessible by all and the plan moves us further towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equality action plan presents some of the activities we are undertaking to meet our duties under the equalities legislation, and provides an initial set of priorities for promoting equality and well-being, based on the evidence we have gathered and the engagement we have already had with transport organisations and other interested parties. We are seeking comments on this initial draft and will publish a final version following further engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56454</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-03T22:04:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/proportion-of-urban-trips-under-5-miles-taken-by-i-walking-or-cycling-ii-public-transport"/>
    <title>Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles taken by (i) walking or cycling (ii) public transport</title>
    <summary>Impact indicator, disaggregated by region, published annually from May 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="type-of-indicator-impact-indicator"&gt;Type of indicator: Impact indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-england-data-are-also-available-for-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: England (data are also available for Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-region-and-country"&gt;Information broken down by: Region and country&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2011, 39% of urban trips under 5 miles in England were taken by walking or cycling and 9% were taken by public transport.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles taken by (i) walking or cycling; (ii) public transport: England, 2010 and 2011 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Walking or cycling&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Public transport&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;All modes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;37%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;For urban trips under 5 miles in England:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;39% were taken by walking or cycling in 2011 compared with 37% in 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9% were taken by public transport in 2011, compared with 10% in 2010. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London was the region with the highest proportion of walking or cycling and public transport trips, 43% and 22% respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The region with the lowest proportion of walking or cycling trips was the West Midlands (32%). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The South West had the lowest proportion of public transport trips (4%).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/nts99-triips-and-distance-travelled-per-person-per-year"&gt;Proportion of urban trips under 5 miles by main mode: England, 2007 to 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proportions of walking or cycling and public transport trips are calculated using the number of trips under 5 miles as reported in the National Travel Survey by residents living in urban areas (settlements of over 3,000 population). Data are available by region and county.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: annual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: 13 December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: July 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Travel Survey (NTS) collects data on personal travel in Great Britain. The NTS reports on trends in personal travel including key questions on how, why and when people travel for all age groups. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/national-travel-survey-statistics"&gt;Further information and statistics from the NTS.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: email &lt;a href="mailto:national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; or telephone 020 7944 3097&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55926</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65 million contract to refit HMS Ocean</title>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65 million upgrade, securing more than 600 UK jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The warship was moored on the Thames during the London 2012 Olympic Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at Devonport Royal Dockyard in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project, securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to the ship’s radar, gun, command system and living quarters. In addition, around 1,200 metres of new pipework will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter Number 10 Dock at Devonport Royal Dockyard to begin her refit [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympics duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12844</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-operational-readiness-to-provide-military-support-for-activities-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>Maintaining operational readiness to provide military support for activities in the UK</title>
    <summary>Civil authorities have resources to cope with a wide range of emergencies but if they lack capability or are overwhelmed by the scale of events they can ask the Ministry of Defence for assistance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is constantly refining its ability to provide an effective response to all types of emergencies and major crises at national, regional and local level. This means having a pre-planned, coordinated response from the emergency services, civil authorities and where appropriate, the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is an emergency or crisis situation in the UK, local emergency services provide the first response. Government departments or civil authorities can also call on the Ministry of Defence for military help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces support is officially known as Military Aid to the Civil Authorities (MACA). The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/36/contents"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; states that military support is available for major incidents when the capability or capacity of civilian authorities has been overwhelmed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no standing military forces for these tasks so support isn’t guaranteed and when it is provided the civil authorities normally have to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces can be brought in to deal with a range of situations including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural disasters - helping people in severe weather situations, such as flooding, where there is a need to protect human life, property and alleviate distress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network failure or disruption - including animal disease epidemics and public service-related industrial disputes that affect our safety or security, or disrupt transport or communications links&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;criminal or terrorist activity - where there is a need, providing specialist expertise in specific circumstances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bomb disposal - known officially as ‘explosive ordnance disposal’, this can be related to terrorism, or involve unearthing a bomb from World War 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue - helping people in danger, searching for sunken vessels or aircraft, carrying out underwater or mountain rescue tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK waters - protecting our territorial waters, ports, ships and energy installations from terrorist attack, protecting fisheries, preventing drug or people smuggling and dealing with pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK airspace - detecting and deterring aircraft approaching UK sovereign airspace and protecting UK and NATO monitored airspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of recent emergencies and crises that needed help from the armed forces include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing security for the 2012 Olympics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue operations during widespread flooding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping UK travellers stranded by the Icelandic ash cloud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;managing the disposal of infected cattle during the ‘mad cow’ disease outbreak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detailed information for civil authorities on handling crises is contained in the guidance &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-response-and-recovery"&gt;Emergency Response and Recovery&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-preparedness"&gt;Emergency Preparedness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/securing-britain-age-uncertainty-strategic-defence-and-security-review"&gt;Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR): Securing Britain in an age of uncertainty 2010&lt;/a&gt; sets out how the defence establishment will contribute effectively to civil crises and emergencies in the UK, balancing against other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-strategy-for-deploying-the-armed-forces-in-the-uk"&gt;The strategy for deploying the Armed Forces in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All defence operations including those in the UK must be authorised by the Defence Council. The Secretary of State for Defence is the government minister responsible for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and there is a single chain of command that connects to service personnel on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a crisis the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Deputy Chief of the Defence Staff (Military Strategy and Operations) and the Director General Security Policy give guidance to ministers and other government departments. In this way, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; acts as both a military HQ and a department of state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Contingencies Act 2004 (&lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) defines how organisations, particularly local responders, prepare for emergencies. In the event of an emergency in which the supply and distribution of the essentials of life to the community are extensively threatened, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt; can be used to invoke emergency powers on a local, regional or national basis. The full &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/civil-contingencies-act"&gt;text of the Act&lt;/a&gt; is available from the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to deploy service personnel would be authorised by the Defence Council and they may be given the power to requisition equipment and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 2 of the the Emergency Powers Act 1964, the Defence Council may authorise the temporary deployment of service personnel on urgent work of national importance. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1964/38/contents"&gt;Read the full text of the Act&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <summary>Opening up access to the Tipner site for businesses and visitors.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56472</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-monitoring-and-evaluation-framework"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund monitoring and evaluation framework</title>
    <summary>Expectations for the monitoring and evaluation of projects funded through the Local Sustainable Transport Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework sets out the department’s requirements from the monitoring and evaluation activity of Local Sustainable Transport Fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) projects and the roles of the department and project teams in delivering these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework articulates which &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects are expected to fulfil which elements of monitoring and evaluation and provides project teams with the flexibility to collect evidence in a way that reflects the local variation of projects and data availability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54827</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-draft-council-tax-reduction-schemes-prescribed-requirements-and-default-scheme-england-amendment-regulations-2012"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Draft Council Tax reduction schemes (prescribed requirements and default scheme) (England) (amendment) regulations 2012</title>
    <summary>This draft statutory instrument affects the upratings of default schemes and pension credit age schemes. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 7 September 2012, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) confirmed its intention to update and align the premia/ applicable amounts in regulations for the default and pensioner schemes with current rates/ Department for Work and Pensions’ (&lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt;) autumn uprating. This would be done using Housing Benefit amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; said it would be working with &lt;abbr title="Department for Work and Pensions"&gt;DWP&lt;/abbr&gt; (again, in relation to the pension credit age and default schemes) to model the way in which non-dependent deductions would have been uprated had council tax benefit continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This draft statutory instrument effects these upratings and is being published ahead of the regulations being made, to give authorities early notice of the changes required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39721</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <summary>Royal Marines and Albanian forces recently joined together for an assault on an abandoned Soviet submarine base as part of Exercise Albanian Lion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
