<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/64074</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/dclg-draft-statistics-plan-for-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>DCLG draft statistics plan for 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on the Department for Communities and Local Government's proposals for collecting and publishing official statistics in 2011 to 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft statistics plan describes the Department for Communities and Local Government’s proposals for collecting and publishing official statistics over the period April 2011 to March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;users’ reactions to our proposals and their views on whether our planned deployment of resources will meet their needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggestions for the development of any new statistics, products or services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggestions for any further reductions in the amount of data we collect and publish (beyond those already submitted in the context of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/single-data-list"&gt;‘single data list’&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information from users about the particular uses to which they put our statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/61057</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:28:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:28:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people"/>
    <title>Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>We want local councils to provide more information on how they are spending public money and about the decisions they make.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public should be able to hold local councils to account about the services they provide. To do this, people need information about what decisions local councils are taking, and how local councils are spending public money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If councils publish their data in open formats with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/information-management/government-licensing/about-the-ogl.htm" title="The National Archive: open government licences"&gt;open licences,&lt;/a&gt; people will be able to use and reuse the data for many different purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="publishing-council-spending-and-salaries-online"&gt;Publishing council spending and salaries online&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) has asked all local councils and fire and rescue authorities in England to publish spending information over £500 online. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve created guides on publishing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localtransparency.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: guides to publishing data"&gt;local spending data,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localsalaries.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: senior salaries"&gt;senior salary information&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localnewcontracts.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: new contracts &amp;amp; tenders"&gt;new contracts.&lt;/a&gt; The guidance was produced by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt;, working with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/blog/local-public-data-panel" title="Data.gov.uk: Local Public Data Panel"&gt;Local Public Data Panel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils must now produce &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/publishing-details-of-local-council-pay-and-jobs" title="Publishing details of local council pay and jobs"&gt;policy statements about staff pay&lt;/a&gt;, including senior and lower-paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="peoples-rights-to-see-council-accounts"&gt;People’s rights to see council accounts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have 20 days a year to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/peoples-rights-to-see-council-accounts" title="People's rights to see council accounts"&gt;inspect town hall accounts&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-government-transparency-code"&gt;Local government transparency code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve drawn up a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-data-transparency-code" title="Local authority data transparency code"&gt;code of recommended practice for local authorities on data transparency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-council-publicity"&gt;Local council publicity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve introduced a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/recommended-code-of-practice-for-local-authority-publicity" title="Recommended code of practice for local authority publicity"&gt;publicity code for local councils in England&lt;/a&gt;. The code provides guidance on the content, style, distribution and cost of local authority publicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reforming-local-audit"&gt;Reforming local audit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are replacing the Audit Commission with new local arrangements for auditing local councils. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;local bodies will be able to appoint their own auditors from an open and competitive market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oversight by the National Audit Office, Financial Reporting Council and professional accountancy bodies will make sure that high standards of auditing continue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="local-procurement"&gt;Local procurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re encouraging all councils to make regular use of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/contracts-finder" title="Contracts Finder"&gt;Contracts Finder,&lt;/a&gt; a tool that helps match up providers and bidders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made it easier for small and medium-sized companies to bid for contracts by removing the need for bidders to complete a pre-qualification questionnaire to tender for contracts under £100,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="accountability-system-statement-for-local-government"&gt;Accountability system statement for local government&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; publishes an annual &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accountability-system-statement-for-local-government--2" title="Accountability system statement for local government"&gt;‘Accountability system statement for local government’&lt;/a&gt;. This sets out the funding systems, laws and guidance that apply to local councils and fire and rescue authorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="demonstrating-the-benefits-of-local-transparency"&gt;Demonstrating the benefits of local transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In partnership with the London Borough of Lambeth, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; has developed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lambeth-in-numbers.co.uk/" title="Lambeth in Numbers"&gt;Lambeth in Numbers&lt;/a&gt; to demonstrate how better access to information can help people to understand and solve problems in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be using this demonstration project to stimulate further debate in Lambeth and other local council areas about open data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://openlylocal.com/" title="Openly Local"&gt;Openly Local&lt;/a&gt; project now makes use of the data provided by more than 140 local councils. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publishing more council information will also put the voluntary sector and small businesses in a stronger position to bid for contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gathering-better-financial-information-from-local-government-to-help-make-public-services-more-efficient"&gt;Gathering better financial information from local government to help make public services more efficient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask local authorities in England to report &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/quarterly-revenue-outturn" title="Quarterly revenue outturn"&gt;revenue expenditure and forecast outturn&lt;/a&gt; every 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also published the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/single-data-list" title="Single data list"&gt;single data list&lt;/a&gt;. This is a list of all the datasets that local government must submit to central government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with HM Treasury requirements, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; collects returns from English local authorities for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/local-data-for-whole-of-government-accounts" title="Whole of Government Accounts"&gt;Whole of Government Accounts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sir Bob Kerslake, Permanent Secretary of &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;, published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accountability-adapting-to-decentralisation--2" title="Accountability: adapting to decentralisation"&gt;report on the transparency of local public services&lt;/a&gt; in September 2011. The report recommended ways to make sure that local councils are transparent and accountable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this report, all government departments started to publish annual ‘accountability system statements’ about the money they provide to local bodies. These statements demonstrate to Parliament that appropriate checks on spending are still in place following the move to a more local approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-authorities-data-transparency-code" title="Local authorities data transparency code consultation"&gt;consulted on the draft local government transparency code&lt;/a&gt; in early 2011. The consultation was published in February 2011 and the responses to the consultation were published in September 2011. In October 2012, we &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/improving-local-government-transparency" title="Improving local government transparency"&gt;consulted on updating the code and making it mandatory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the draft Local Audit Bill in July and August 2012. This Bill will abolish the Audit Commission and put in place new local arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-authority-publicity-code" title="Local authority publicity code consultation"&gt;consulted local authorities about our draft revised Publicity Code&lt;/a&gt; in 2010. The Communities and Local Government Select Committee also undertook a short inquiry looking at the draft revised Code. Their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmcomloc/666/666.pdf" title="The Communities and Local Government Select Committee report: proposed code of recommended practice on local authority publicity"&gt;report (PDF 4.2MB)&lt;/a&gt; was published on 27 January 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public accountability of local government is covered in several Acts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Eliz2/8-9/67" title="Public Bodies (Admission to Meetings) Act 1960"&gt;Public Bodies (Admission to Meetings) Act 1960&lt;/a&gt; opened up meetings to the public, allowing members of the public and press to attend meetings of councils and certain other public bodies &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1972/70" title="Local Government Act 1972"&gt;Local Government Act 1972&lt;/a&gt; requires councillors to declare their interests, and councils to publish agendas, documents and reports &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1980/65/section/96" title="Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980: section 96"&gt;Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980: section 96&lt;/a&gt; established a public register of land and buildings owned by local councils. The aim of the register is to identify government land and buildings which are not being fully used &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1985/43" title="Local Government (Access to Information) Act 1985"&gt;Local Government (Access to Information) Act 1985&lt;/a&gt; provides public access to local authority meetings, reports and documents.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/1991/351/contents/made" title="Local Authorities (Members’ Allowances) Regulations 1991"&gt;Local Authorities (Members’ Allowances) Regulations 1991&lt;/a&gt; requires local authorities to publish the recommendations made by their independent remuneration panel, their scheme of allowances and the actual allowances paid to any member of the authority in any given year &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1992/14" title="Local Government Finance Act 1992"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 1992&lt;/a&gt; allows members of the public to obtain information about local domestic rating lists &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/36/contents" title="Freedom of Information Act 2000"&gt;Freedom of Information Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; allows people to request copies of information held by public authorities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/22/contents" title="Local Government Act 2000"&gt;Local Government Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; provides people with access to information held by local authority executives, like leaders and elected mayors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can download the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm83/8393/8393.pdf" title="Draft Local Audit Bill"&gt;‘Draft Local Audit Bill’ (PDF 1.54MB)&lt;/a&gt; from the Parliament website. This Bill will establish new local audit arrangements to replace the Audit Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partner-organisations"&gt;Partner organisations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re supporting the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/blog/local-public-data-panel" title="data.gov.uk: Local Public Data Panel"&gt;Local Public Data Panel,&lt;/a&gt; an independent panel of experts on open data and transparency chaired by Professor Nigel Shadbolt. The panel was set up to make local public services better understood and more accessible. Its members include local authorities, community activists and web developers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61052</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:11:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-application-process-and-bidding-guidance"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process and bidding guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance on the Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These documents were produced to support the Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process. They were published and made available to all project teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61045</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:11:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-project-summaries"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund project summaries</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Local Sustainable Transport Fund project summary information.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has awarded Local Sustainable Transport Fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport Fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) funding in 3 streams. Tranche 1 and key component projects were awarded in July 2011. This was followed by 2 funding announcements in May and June 2012, for large projects above £5 million and tranche 2 of smaller projects. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64108</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/action-on-council-tax-a-helping-hand-to-residents-cost-of-living-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>Action on Council Tax a helping hand to residents cost of living, says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Communities Secretary hailed new rules for 2013 that mean taxpayers can now choose to pay their bill over 12 months rather than 10.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move will lower average band D council tax instalments by an average of £24 per month for 10 months and helps tax payers manage their finances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legislation passed by the government means that in 2013 council tax payers can now request to pay their bills over a longer period of time, lowering their monthly bills, and so easing the financial burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has already &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/third-year-of-council-tax-freeze-announced"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; support for local authorities in England to help them freeze council tax in 2014-15 for a third year and assist in keeping bills down. The government has set aside £450 million as part of the Autumn Statement package to help support local authorities. Taxpayers living in an average band D home in England could save up to £72 compared to a 5% increase, while the cumulative effect of the 3 freezes is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils will also be able to publish online the detailed supporting information that until now they have had to supply with council tax bills in hard copies. While residents still have the legal right to request hard-copy documents, the online versions will enable authorities to cut costs, improve efficiencies and help the environment through a decrease in the use of paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are also urging councils to follow the example of utility companies in offering discounts to those customers who pay online or through direct debit facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We know many people are worried about their cost of living expenses and we’ve already acted to freeze council tax in the past 2 years after bills doubled under the last administration. We have now offered councils a third freeze deal, which could have a combined effect potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have also changed the rules so hard working council residents can choose to pay their annual bills online or spread their payments over 12 months instead of 10. These sensible measures will make paying easier giving tax payers a little more room for manoeuvre and bring down their monthly outgoings by around £24 for most of the year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Billing authorities collect and enforce council tax as per the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/1992/613/contents/made"&gt;Council Tax (Administration and Enforcement) Regulations 1992&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/3038/contents/made"&gt;Council Tax (Demand Notices)(England) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt;. For each financial year, billing authorities must issue demand notices (the bill) setting out the amount that is due and how it is to be paid. From April 2013, the demand notice will inform bill payers of their right to pay in 12 instalments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government consulted on its technical reforms to council tax between 31 October and 29 December 2011. The government’s response can be found on the 
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"&gt;consultation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has set aside £450 million over two years as part of the Autumn Statement package to help support local authorities in freezing their council tax in 2013-14.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60858</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>"Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New style local settlement to reward striving councils with more income.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles spelled out 50 sensible savings, a Council Tax freeze and a fair funding deal as the “right road” for councils to protect residents and local services, as a major shake up of local finance was initiated today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister signalled the watershed moment for councils as he unveiled a new look local government finance settlement that will reward councils that strive to improve their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dramatic shift in spending power from Whitehall to the town hall means an estimated 70% of council income will now be raised locally compared to 56% under the centrally distributed ‘begging-bowl’ formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013 councils can channel this greater local control into encouraging local jobs and local firms via a new business rate retention incentive that rewards them for growth. It could potentially add £10 billion to the economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, councils account for a quarter of all public spending - with English councils still spending £114 billion - so it is vital they continue to play their part tackling the inherited budget deficit by making sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help councils in that regard a document containing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;50 practical ways to make sensible savings&lt;/a&gt; was published today. It shows how a culture change by councils can unearth significantly more taxpayer savings and help make services more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must keep doing their bit to tackle the inherited budget deficit because they account for a quarter of all public spending and still get through over £114 billion of taxpayers money each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement is a fair funding deal that will reward councils ready to strive for their communities and gives them another year to get their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must do 3 things to get on the right road for their residents: put our fair funding deal to work; do every single one of our 50 ways to save; and accept our Council Tax freeze offer. Councils that cry wolf without having done all of this are letting their residents down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils that put their thinking caps on now can save precious taxpayer pennies next year by cutting out waste and transforming frontline services that vulnerable people rely on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s fair funding deal arms councils with an average spending power of £2,240 per household. Local authorities have been protected from further spending reductions for 2013 to 2014. Overall the average spending power reduction for councils in 2013 to 2014 is expected to be limited to just 1.7% per household, less than last year’s comparable figure of 3.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe this important concession gives councils the time they need to transform service delivery, build up their local business rate income, improve procurement and comprehensively complete the suggested 50 savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total start-up funding assessment for councils 2013 to 2014 apportions £26 billion in a fair and sustainable way that ensures the smallest reductions for the councils most reliant on government support. More weighting has been given to areas with the highest levels of assessed need. For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is setting aside an extra £450 million over the next 2 years to help local government in England to freeze their Council Tax, equivalent to a 1% rise. A third year’s combined Council Tax freeze is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government confirmed today that where a council rejects the freeze, the majority will have to secure electoral agreement through a ‘local tax lock’ referendum to hike band D bills by more than 2%. Smaller authorities with a track record of low Council Tax will be given slightly more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘50 ways to save’ include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing back offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting Community Budgets to bring staff and money together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using transparency to cut waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clamping down on corporate charge cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting special spending controls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling the £2 billion of local fraud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising £16 billion of non-school reserves creatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve collection rates to reduce the £2.4 billion of uncollected Council Tax across England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage direct debit and e-billing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve property management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close subsidised council canteens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing senior pay and posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut spending on consultants and agency staff which had risen to £4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stop translating documents into foreign languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut expensive travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce printing costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hire out the town hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; for the full list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 20 December 2012, the day after the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement, Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis MP hosted a teleconference call for local authorities and fire &amp;amp; rescue services, fielding more than 25 questions from 200 callers. You can listen to the call &lt;a rel="external" href="http://bit.ly/Ul5u6X"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 to 2014 spending power calculation includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£26.07 billion start up funding assessment (which includes £10.9 billion of locally retained business rates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£23.9 billion in Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£859 million for NHS funding to support social care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£661 million via New Homes Bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£240 million for 2013 to 2014 Council Tax freeze grant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition local authorities will also benefit from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£112 million via the Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£33.5 million via New Burdens for Council Tax Support in 2013 to 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/spending-power-by-local-authority"&gt;Spending power data by local authority for 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;No authority will see a spending power reduction of more than 8.8% because of decisions taken by ministers to make an efficiency support grant available. The ‘per household’ figures are calculated using total spending power a combination of the new start up funding assessment and Council Tax, and the number of dwellings by Council Tax band for each administrative area in England. The counts are calculated from data for England extracted from the Valuation Office Agency’s database on 12 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;plain English guide&lt;/a&gt; to cut through Whitehall jargon and explain the new settlement system is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a period of statutory consultation on the settlement which runs to 15 January 2013. Ministers will then finalise their proposals and the settlement for 2013 to 2014 will be debated in Parliament in February in time for councils to set their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement committed the government to relinquishing control over excessive Council Tax increases and giving that democratic power directly to local communities. This was legislated for through the Localism Act. The government has today published the Council Tax principles it is proposing for 2013 to 2014. Council Tax increases would trigger a referendum, if they exceed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2% for most principal authorities; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 (which ever is higher) in the case of shire district councils, police and crime commissioners and fire and rescue authorities that set the lowest quartile of Council Tax in their class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final principles for 2013 to 2014 will be set out in a report for the approval of the House of Commons early next year, at the same time as the final report on the local government finance settlement. No equivalent principles are being proposed for town and parish councils for 2013 to 2014, although they may in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical data for the 2013-14 Local Government Finance Settlement can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;Local Government Finance site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have been protected with savings back loaded to allow time for sensible savings; they have also benefited from the protection to local government in 2013 to 2014. In addition the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, has been asked to carry out a review to pinpoint ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money. The government intends to announce the breakdown of £140 million of capital grant money to fire and rescue authorities. The money for 2013 to 2015 will be distributed by a combination of formula and for projects to fire and rescue authorities that have been successful through bidding. All fire and rescue authorities will receive some capital funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60312</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T10:57:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-2014-draft-regulations-on-membership-contributions-and-benefits"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme 2014: draft regulations on membership, contributions and benefits</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on the provisions relating to membership, contributions and benefits which come into force in April 2014.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks responses from interested parties on draft regulations for the new Local Government Pension Scheme to come into force in April 2014. This consultation only covers the core elements of the new scheme, in particular, the provisions relating to membership, contributions and benefits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second consultation exercise covering the remainder of the new scheme will follow shortly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60592</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:38:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-statutory-burdens-equality-impact-assessments"/>
    <title>Reducing statutory burdens: equality impact assessments</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Letter from Brandon Lewis to all leaders and chief executives of local authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance on the production of equality impact assessments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60241</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:25:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-258-million-sea-king-helicopter-support-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £258 million Sea King helicopter support contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MOD has agreed a £258 million contract to support Sea King helicopters, which will sustain 500 jobs across the UK.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; fleets of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-Mk5" title="Sea King Mk5"&gt;Sea Kings&lt;/a&gt; are best known for providing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/UK/Search-and-Rescue" title="Search and Rescue"&gt;Search and Rescue&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt;) services in the UK and Falkland Islands. They can also be used to carry troops and provide airborne surveillance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extension to the Sea King Integrated Operational Support (&lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt;) contract will ensure continued technical and maintenance support for the 90-strong helicopter fleet for the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD originally signed the &lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt; arrangement with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.agustawestland.com/" title="AgustaWestland"&gt;AgustaWestland&lt;/a&gt; in 2005 and this is the final phase of the deal which is expected to sustain around 500 jobs at AgustaWestland’s UK headquarters at Yeovil, in the industry supply chain and at several &lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt; bases across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5786/45153254g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter is pictured on an operation over Helmand Province, Afghanistan (stock image) [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This phase of the contract will provide support until Sea King is retired from service in 2016 and replaced by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin MK1"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Sea King helicopter fleet has been in service for over 40 years providing a vital capability in air/sea rescue and surveillance. This maintenance agreement, securing 500 jobs across the UK, demonstrates our commitment to keeping this aircraft in top condition until it is retired from service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy Captain Tony Gray, Defence Equipment and Support Sea King Team Leader, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing this contract ensures value for money for the taxpayer while maintaining the provision of search-and-rescue helicopters around the UK, 24-hours-a-day throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60769</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T21:19:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bus-subsidy-per-passenger-journey"/>
    <title>Bus subsidy per passenger journey</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Bus subsidy per passenger journey input indicator.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-input-indicator"&gt;DfT Business Plan input indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-england"&gt;Geographical coverage: England&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-region---data-are-available-for-london-english-metropolitan-areas-as-a-group-and-english-non-metropolitan-areas-as-a-group"&gt;Information broken down by: Region - data are available for London, English metropolitan areas (as a group), and English non-metropolitan areas (as a group)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2011/12, the average level of subsidy (direct from central government) per passenger journey was 9.2 pence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="table-for-net-government-support-for-local-bus-services-and-concessionary-travel-per-passenger-journey-by-metropolitan-area-status-england-annual-from-200405"&gt;Table for Net government support for local bus services and concessionary travel per passenger journey by metropolitan area status: England, annual from 2004/05&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Most recent data&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Subsidy per Journey (2010/11 prices)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.2p&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.2p&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Percentage change&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.5 %&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complete set of data is available at: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/bus05-subsidies-and-concessions"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/bus05-subsidies-and-concessions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#10"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2011/12 the average level of subsidy (direct from central government) per passenger journey was 9.2 pence. This decreased (adjusted for inflation) from 10.1 pence in 2004/05. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;English non-Metropolitan areas had the highest level of subsidy per passenger journey (15.8 pence in 2011/12), London had the lowest level of subsidy per passenger journey (4.8 pence in 2011/12) while English Metropolitan areas were in-between (10.7 pence in 2011/12). Comparisons between London and the rest of the country should be made with care – see note in Background Information below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower subsidy per passenger journey will indicate better value for the public purse. However, this could arise as a result of reductions in the most heavily subsidised services – many of which are routes in rural areas which would be unprofitable without public subsidy. Reductions to these services would improve the ‘headline’ measure but would risk making rural communities more isolated. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The figures exclude expenditure on capital projects (e.g. bus lane priority schemes) which benefit the bus industry directly or indirectly. Outside London, the local bus industry is deregulated, but London runs an entirely tendered bus market under the oversight of Transport for London. Given the different market structures, comparisons between London and the rest of country should be made with considerable care.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The indicator is calculated by dividing the total Bus Service Operators’ Grant by the total passenger journeys on buses (this will include concessionary journeys). Further information is available in the measurement template (above). &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: annual&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;last updated: 20 December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;next update: December 2013&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats#bus-statistics"&gt;The full guidance notes on DfT bus statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/bus-statistics"&gt;Related bus statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/statistics-on-public-attitudes-to-transport"&gt;Research on attitudes to bus travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2011-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: Matthew Tranter, &lt;a href="mailto:bus.statistics@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Bus statistics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
