<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17266</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:36:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localising-support-for-council-tax-guidance-note-on-administrative-matters"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: guidance note on administrative matters </title>
    <summary>Guidance note on administrative elements of the Council Tax reduction schemes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The administrative elements will in future operate under existing Council Tax provisions in the Local Government Finance Act and related regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This note will provide clarity for local authorities on how some administrative elements will be dealt with under these provisions, where these are not covered in the Default Scheme and Prescribed Requirements Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:55:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis on early intervention pilots and neighbourhood community budgets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T16:10:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <summary>Council-led early intervention pilots are showing it is possible to radically rework public services so those in need get better help.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16782</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T14:12:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T14:12:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2"/>
    <title>Giving local authorities more control over how they spend public money in their area</title>
    <summary>We're handing back control to councils, and letting them share in the financial benefits of generating growth in their areas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England’s local government finance system is one of the most centralised in the world. This means that local authorities don’t have the autonomy and flexibility they need to make sure public money is spent on the things that matter in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that local authorities are better placed to make decisions about the needs of their local communities than central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-services-support-grant"&gt;Local Services Support Grant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2013, local councils will be able to decide how most of their grants from central government should be spent in their area. The only exceptions are schools funding and the new public health grant. The new
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/local-services-support-grant" title="Local Services Support Grant"&gt;Local Services Support Grant&lt;/a&gt; is a single grant paid by central government to individual councils to help support and protect local services. Councils can decide themselves how they wish to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="protecting-funding-in-areas-that-are-most-reliant-on-central-government-funding"&gt;Protecting funding in areas that are most reliant on central government funding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some areas are more dependent than others on central government funding, because they have a higher proportion of people who pay lower levels of Council Tax. The 2012 to 2013 local government finance settlement includes measures to protect those councils most reliant on central government funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="business-rates-retention"&gt;Business rates retention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re introducing a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/business-rates-retention" title="business rates retention scheme"&gt;business rates retention scheme&lt;/a&gt; from 2013 to 2014. This will allow councils to keep a share of growth in business rates in their area and reduce their dependency on central government grant funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community Budgets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/community-budgets" title="Community Budgets"&gt;Community Budgets&lt;/a&gt; are a new way for local public service providers to work more effectively together. Community Budgets allow providers of local services to contribute to a shared fund, so they can co-ordinate their work more effectively and efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="investment-in-buildings-land-vehicles-and-machinery"&gt;Investment in buildings, land, vehicles and machinery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils need to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/investment-in-local-government-capital-assets" title="Investment in local government capital assets"&gt;invest in their capital assets&lt;/a&gt;, including buildings, land, vehicles and machinery. We will ensure that the system gives councils the resources and flexibilities to make this investment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="localising-council-tax-support"&gt;Localising Council Tax support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013, councils in England will design their own &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support" title="Localising Council Tax support"&gt;Council Tax support schemes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-government-resource-review"&gt;Local government resource review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government set up a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN06030" title="Review of local government resource"&gt;review of local government resources&lt;/a&gt; in March 2011 to consider how to give local councils more control over their money. The first phase of the review considered how local authorities could promote local economic growth by allowing them to keep at least a proportion of the locally generated business rates (the tax paid by businesses to local councils). This would replace the current formula grant arrangements which are a combination of business rates, revenue support grant and police grant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second phase of the local government resource review looked at extending financial autonomy to communities and local people through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/community-budgets" title="Community Budgets"&gt;Community Budgets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-government-funding"&gt;Local government funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities fund their activities from 3 main sources: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grants from central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Council Tax &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other locally generated fees and charges for services &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Central government funding for local councils is announced each year in the annual local government finance settlement. In 2012 to 2013, the finance settlement includes formula grant. For 2012 to 2013 formula grant is £28 billion, an average reduction of 7.2% on the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) ran a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax" title="Localising Council Tax support consultation"&gt;consultation on proposals to localise support for Council Tax&lt;/a&gt; between 2 August and 14 October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also ran a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-funding-arrangements" title="Localising Council Tax support: funding arrangements"&gt;funding consultation&lt;/a&gt; from 17 May to 12 July 2012. The consultation paper explained how the government intends to distribute funding to support local schemes. It included proposals to adjust the way money is allocated to authorities, to make sure all authorities have what they need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base" title="Localising Council Tax support: Council Tax base"&gt;consultation paper on the Council Tax base&lt;/a&gt; and funding for local precepting authorities. Precepting authorities are councils from other levels of local government such as a county or parish councils and other agencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/business-rates-retention" title="Business rates retention"&gt;consulted on our proposals for a business rates retention scheme&lt;/a&gt; in summer 2011. We set out our proposition for a new business rate retention scheme on 19 December 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also regularly meets and consults with representatives from local councils and other organisations involved in local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/localgovernmentfinance.html" title="Local Government Finance Act"&gt;Local Government Finance Act&lt;/a&gt; gained Royal assent on 31 October 2012. It provides a legal basis for business rates retention and localising Council Tax support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities must have regard to the ‘Prudential code for capital finance in local authorities’ when carrying out their duties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in England and Wales under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents" title="Local Government Act 2003"&gt;Part 1 of the Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Scotland under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/asp/2003/1/part/7" title="Local Government in Scotland Act 2003"&gt;Part 7 of the Local Government in Scotland Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Northern Ireland under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/nia/2011/10/enacted" title="Local Government Finance Act (Northern Ireland) 2011"&gt;Part 1 of the Local Government Finance Act (Northern Ireland) 2011&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="localising-council-tax-support-1"&gt;Localising Council Tax support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2885/contents/made" title="Council Tax Reduction Schemes (Prescribed Requirements) (England) Regulations 2012"&gt;The Council Tax Reduction Schemes (Prescribed Requirements) (England) Regulations 2012 (SI 2012/2885)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2886/contents/made" title="The Council Tax Reduction Schemes (Default Scheme) (England) Regulations 2012 (SI 2012/2886)"&gt;The Council Tax Reduction Schemes (Default Scheme) (England) Regulations 2012 (SI 2012/2886)&lt;/a&gt; were made on 16 November 2012, and laid before Parliament on 22 and 23 of November 2012 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prescribed Requirements regulations prescribe requirements for all local Council Tax reduction schemes and come into force on 27 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note for Prescribed Requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedules 1 to 6 apply to pensioners (as defined) only &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schedules 7 to 8 apply to all applicants (ie working age and pensioners)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Default Scheme Regulations, which prescribe the default Council Tax reduction scheme which will apply to any council which has not made its on scheme on or before 31 January 2013, comes into force on 18 December 2012.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Default Scheme Regulations contain provisions about applicants in receipt of an award of universal credit, and we will be publishing a further guidance note on this approach, with worked examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information go to the supporting page, &lt;a href="/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;Localising Council Tax support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Group runs the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/community-budgets" title="Community Budgets website"&gt;Community Budgets website&lt;/a&gt;, which includes news, resources and weekly updates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17108</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:08:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"/>
    <title>Cash boost to get England cycling</title>
    <summary>An extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cities, towns and villages across England are set to benefit from an extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure.  The new funding was announced today by Transport Minister Norman Baker, at a conference in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new funding will help people take to two wheels.  Projects could include better cycle facilities at railway stations, improved cycle links, or projects to improve the layout of road junctions to make them more cycle-friendly. Previous investment has seen some great projects making a real difference in communities, including better cycle routes from residential areas to schools to encourage the next generation of cyclists to cycle more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference in Leicester, attended by Public Health Minister Anna Soubry and Norman Baker, explores how councils’ health and transport officials can work better together to deliver better options for cycling and walking in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is great for your health, the economy, and for the environment so we are determined to make it easier for people to cycle whether for leisure, getting to the shops or as part of their commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the success of the Olympics, there is a huge appetite for more cycling provision from the travelling public and we need to capitalise on this enthusiasm at local and national level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are investing £20 million in cycling infrastructure and getting councils to bring an end to silo working in their offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public Health Minister Anna Soubry said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being active helps us stay healthy and protects against life threatening conditions such as heart disease, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a great way for adults to get their recommended 150 minutes of physical activity each week and this funding will help encourage more people to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million announced today is in addition to £30 million already announced for similar projects this year which drew in an additional £15 million in matched funding from local sources.  The projects to be funded will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"&gt;written statement&lt;/a&gt; was laid in Parliament this morning &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence today also published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nice.org.uk/"&gt;guidance on public health for local authorities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17109</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T09:50:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Additional funding for cycling infrastructure</title>
    <summary>An additional £20m for existing infrastructure projects to support cycling.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has today made available an additional £20m for our existing infrastructure projects to support cycling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will increase the total available for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Community Linking Places Fund (in addition to the £15m announced on 7 February 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving cycle safety at junctions (in addition to the £15m announced on 26 June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Community Linking Places Fund is primarily for improvements to cycling and walking infrastructure, facilities and links. This includes improving access to the rail network by bicycle. In addition the fund aims to support jobs, enhance access to employment and encourage greater use of more environmentally friendly transport.   Projects currently being supported were announced on 6 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment in junctions - for use by English local authorities outside London - will help to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured, or are deemed to be at greater risk.  Local authorities are currently submitting bids for funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand from local authorities, Sustrans and train operating companies, who are delivering the infrastructure, has been high.  An increase of £20m to the total funding available will allow the Government to support more high quality proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the projects to be supported under the additional funding will be published early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"&gt;Cash boost to get England cycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17022</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-revenue-expenditure-and-financing-england-2010-to-2011-individual-local-authority-data--5"/>
    <title>Local authority revenue expenditure and financing England: 2010 to 2011 individual local authority data</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data in the above spreadsheets have been used to compile the final outturn estimates of local authority revenue expenditure and financing for the financial year April 2010 to March 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of the original final outturn statistical release (4 April 2012), the data in these spreadsheets have been revised on 27 November 2012. The changes over the previously published figures are generally small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16974</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-funding-arrangements"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: funding arrangements</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions for local council tax support schemes in England. This document sets out how the Government intends to distribute funding to support local schemes and seeks views on possible adjustments to allocations to avoid potential budgetary pressures in a few authorities. It is published alongside statements of intent for the key sets of regulations which will provide the legal framework for local schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16714</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: calculating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <summary>Consultation about how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
