<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/local-government</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/local-government.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Local government"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16424</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:37:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-authorities-in-england-2011-12-update"/>
    <title>National non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England 2011-12 (update)</title>
    <summary>Details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An updated statistical release giving details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12 was published on 20 November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provided updated information on figures that were announced on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-councils-in-england-2011-to-2012"&gt;15 August 2012&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the net rate yield (after allowances for changes in respect of previous years and reliefs) increased by 9.1% to £21 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contribution to the pool (net rate yield after allowances for collection costs including losses) also increased by 9.2% to £20.7 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 2007-08 and 2011-12 the contribution to the pool from the local lists increased by £3.5 billion or 21%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London accounts for 29% of the contribution to the national pool while having only 15% of the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16427</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2012-in-england"/>
    <title>Council Taxbase 2012 in England</title>
    <summary>Estimate of the number of properties liable for council tax.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2008 to 2012 updating those &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2011-in-england"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; previously issued on 16 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="number-of-dwellings"&gt;Number of dwellings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In England there were 22.4 million dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list liable for council tax as at 10 September 2012. This is an increase of 1% compared with 2011 and an increase of 3% compared with 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of dwellings on the valuation list that are exempt from council tax increased by 2% compared with 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;35% of all exemptions from council tax are class C (short term vacant dwellings). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A further 27% of all exemptions are class M or N (student related exemptions). Of these, class M exemptions have increased by more than 48% in the period 2008 to 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of class L exemptions (unoccupied dwellings repossessed by a mortgage lender) again fell between September 2011 and September 2012 to 9,400, the four consecutive annual fall. There are now 6,500 (or 41%) fewer class L exemptions than the peak in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7.7 million dwellings were entitled to a discount as a result of being occupied by single adults. This represents 33% of all dwellings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.7 million Band A dwellings (50% of all dwellings liable to Band A council tax) were entitled to a single adults discount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The total number of dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list in England as at 10 September 2012 was 23.2 million, an increase of 143,000, or 1% compared with 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="empty-properties"&gt;Empty properties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 2011 and 2012 the number of long-term empty dwellings subject to a discount fell by 28,000 (or 22%). In the same period the number of long-term empty dwellings not subject to a discount increased by 8,000 (or 5%). This gives a net reduction of 20,000, or 7%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2011 and 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of long term empty dwellings that were subject to a discount has fallen by 86,000, or 47%, between 2008 and 2012. In the same period the number of long term empty dwellings that do not receive a discount has increased by 18,000 or 13%. This gives a net reduction of 68,000, or 21%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2008 and 2012. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since the introduction of the New Homes Bonus in the summer of 2010 a large number of authorities have taken the opportunity to review the empty properties and second homes in their area. A number have also altered the level of discount awarded with many abolishing the discount for empty properties altogether.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16406</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:18:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-walsall-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <summary>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16401</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:19:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-blackpool-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council</title>
    <summary>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16121</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:53:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:53:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-15-november-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 15 November 2012</title>
    <summary>Annual bus release and concessionary travel statistics for the last 2 years.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport on Thursday 15 November published the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/annual-bus-statistics-2011-12"&gt;Annual bus statistics 2011/12&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/concessionary-travel-statistics-england-2011-12-and-2012-13"&gt;Concessionary travel statistics 2011/12 and 2012/13&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15105</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T12:52:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"/>
    <title>Low carbon bus calculator</title>
    <summary>This toolkit can be used to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (LCEB).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the benefits of purchasing a low carbon bus will be different for each operator and will depend on the way in which the bus in service is used. So, Department for Transport economists have produced a transparent, user-friendly toolkit to be used by bus operators and local authorities to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (&lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;). Your assessment should always compare the &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; to an equivalent diesel bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit allows you flexibility in changing the input assumptions to those most relevant to you. You will be able to assess the financial implications of purchasing a &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;, based on the fuel savings on offer (as advised by &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturers or experienced in trials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet tool is intended to provide indicative estimates only and &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; does not vouch for the accuracy of such estimates. Please note that the Department for Transport does not accept any liability for any decisions that may be taken on the basis of such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit will be routinely updated and refined. Details of any updates or changes that are made will be outlined in the ‘Intro’ worksheet of the toolkit. We therefore encourage you to visit this website regularly and download the toolkit to ensure you are using the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15610</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:23:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/business-rates--2"/>
    <title>Business rates</title>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Brandon Lewis on business rates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 18 October, the government announced our intention to postpone the next business rates revaluation in England from 2015 to 2017. Clause 22 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; currently before the House of Commons will deliver upon this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the recent Westminster Hall debate on business rates and during the second reading debate on the Bill, ministers committed to provide more information on the analysis which has informed the government’s position to assist parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full assessment would require a revaluation, which in itself would cost £43 million and take a significant amount of time. However, the Valuation Office Agency have today published their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/corporate/News/2012/newsRelease_November_2012.html"&gt;high level estimates of non-domestic rental and rating assessment movements for England&lt;/a&gt; as at January 2012; it provides an illustration of the potential impact those rateable values would have had on business rate bills. The Agency’s analysis is based on professional judgements informed by limited rental market evidence up to January 2012. The analysis has been prepared independently of ministers and published in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last revaluation was based on April 2008 valuations and rents set at the height of an unsustainable property boom. Since then, the economy and property market have faced exceptional changes. Rents have fallen since that property boom. Some groups have assumed that falling business rents would entail falling business rates. However, this is not the case. While aggregate rateable values have fallen, this would automatically be offset at the revaluation by a higher rating multiplier. Firms would just be required to pay a higher proportion of their rateable value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency’s estimates are based on an increase in the multiplier of 16%. My department has actually forecast an increase of 20%, as a consequence of inflation and the adjustment required to the multiplier for appeals; in this context, in practice, the losers would be likely to be even greater than those presented in the Agency’s paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Agency’s analysis suggests that 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates at a 2015 revaluation. This compares to 300,000 seeing reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sectors would have faced big hikes including petrol stations (+28% tax paid), the self-catering industry such as caravan parks (+29% paid), hotels (+6% tax paid), theatres (+25% tax paid), and pubs (+11% tax paid). The retail sector overall would have seen a tax rise of 1% above inflation, and food retail and convenience stores in particular would have faced significant tax increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given business rates are the third biggest outgoing for local firms after staff and rent, such changes would invariably feed through to more expensive prices for family’s weekly shop, more expensive pints in pubs and a significant hit on Britain’s tourism trade. Indeed, as Community Pubs Minister, I am very aware of the concern expressed by honourable members on the pressures being faced by local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revaluations should be revenue-neutral, and equally, postponing the revaluation will be revenue-neutral. Overall the revaluation would not change the total business rates paid in England, so some sectors and locations would have seen reductions at 2015. During recent parliamentary exchanges, it was unfairly suggested that that this change was being done to assist southern parts of England at the expense of other parts of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that offices in central London would have seen by far the greatest reductions in tax paid if the 2015 revaluation had gone ahead (a fall in aggregate rateable value that is one of the reasons why the multiplier has to be increased by so much to make up for the lost revenue). There are complex variations by both locality and by sector in different parts of the country, but what is clear is that there would be far more losers than winners across the country as a whole. In making this decision, ministers are seeking to support the national interest and the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that as a very direct form of taxation, business rates are not popular. Local government finance is too often opaque and confusing. However, we are acting in an open and transparent manner. This independent evidence shows that by postponing the 2015 revaluation, we will protect local firms and local shops from sharp changes in business rates bills at a time when we want to ensure the economy is growing. It will provide business with a stable economic environment in which to invest and support jobs for the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of the document will be placed in the Library together with a copy of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"&gt;Impact Assessment for the Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <summary>The legal minefield that can pressure councils into giving large pay offs to chief executives they want to dismiss is to be ended.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13532</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:58:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/changes-to-the-audit-commission-board"/>
    <title>Changes to the Audit Commission Board</title>
    <summary>The Department for Communities and Local Government has launched a recruitment process to find 3 new board commissioners. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of appointment for 7 commissioners comes to an end on 31 December 2012. The Secretary of State has taken the decision, with support from the chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Audit Commission"&gt;Audit Commission&lt;/a&gt;, to offer reappointment 4 of the existing board members, and a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publicappointments.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Public Appointments website"&gt;recruitment exercise&lt;/a&gt; has commenced to find 3 new members of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new commissioners will work alongside other board members to achieve an efficient and effective closedown and, in the lead up to closure, oversee the smaller Commission’s remaining duties and the transfer of continuing functions to other bodies. The full programme of reforms to local audit and inspection, and the closure of the Commission, will bring in a more localist approach and are expected to save £650 million in public money over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16425</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:02:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:02:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people"/>
    <title>Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people</title>
    <summary>We want local councils to provide more information on how they are spending public money and about the decisions they make.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public should be able to hold local councils to account about the services they provide. To do this, people need information about what decisions local councils are taking, and how local councils are spending public money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If councils publish their data in open formats with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/information-management/government-licensing/about-the-ogl.htm" title="The National Archive: open government licences"&gt;open licences,&lt;/a&gt; people will be able to use and reuse the data for many different purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="publishing-council-spending-and-salaries-online"&gt;Publishing council spending and salaries online&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) has asked all local councils and fire and rescue authorities in England to publish spending information over £500 online. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve created guides on publishing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localtransparency.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: guides to publishing data"&gt;local spending data,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localsalaries.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: senior salaries"&gt;senior salary information&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://localnewcontracts.readandcomment.com/" title="Local transparency: new contracts &amp;amp; tenders"&gt;new contracts.&lt;/a&gt; The guidance was produced by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt;, working with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/blog/local-public-data-panel" title="Data.gov.uk: Local Public Data Panel"&gt;Local Public Data Panel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils must now produce &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/publishing-details-of-local-council-pay-and-jobs" title="Publishing details of local council pay and jobs"&gt;policy statements about staff pay&lt;/a&gt;, including senior and lower-paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="peoples-rights-to-see-council-accounts"&gt;People’s rights to see council accounts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have 20 days a year to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/peoples-rights-to-see-council-accounts" title="People's rights to see council accounts"&gt;inspect town hall accounts&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-government-transparency-code"&gt;Local government transparency code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve drawn up a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-data-transparency-code" title="Local authority data transparency code"&gt;code of recommended practice for local authorities on data transparency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-council-publicity"&gt;Local council publicity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve introduced a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/recommended-code-of-practice-for-local-authority-publicity" title="Recommended code of practice for local authority publicity"&gt;publicity code for local councils in England&lt;/a&gt;. The code provides guidance on the content, style, distribution and cost of local authority publicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reforming-local-audit"&gt;Reforming local audit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are replacing the Audit Commission with new local arrangements for auditing local councils. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;local bodies will be able to appoint their own auditors from an open and competitive market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oversight by the National Audit Office, Financial Reporting Council and professional accountancy bodies will make sure that high standards of auditing continue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="local-procurement"&gt;Local procurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re encouraging all councils to make regular use of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/contracts-finder" title="Contracts Finder"&gt;Contracts Finder,&lt;/a&gt; a tool that helps match up providers and bidders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made it easier for small and medium-sized companies to bid for contracts by removing the need for bidders to complete a pre-qualification questionnaire to tender for contracts under £100,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="accountability-system-statement-for-local-government"&gt;Accountability system statement for local government&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; publishes an annual &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accountability-system-statement-for-local-government--2" title="Accountability system statement for local government"&gt;‘Accountability system statement for local government’&lt;/a&gt;. This sets out the funding systems, laws and guidance that apply to local councils and fire and rescue authorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="demonstrating-the-benefits-of-local-transparency"&gt;Demonstrating the benefits of local transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In partnership with the London Borough of Lambeth, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; has developed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lambeth-in-numbers.co.uk/" title="Lambeth in Numbers"&gt;Lambeth in Numbers&lt;/a&gt; to demonstrate how better access to information can help people to understand and solve problems in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be using this demonstration project to stimulate further debate in Lambeth and other local council areas about open data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://openlylocal.com/" title="Openly Local"&gt;Openly Local&lt;/a&gt; project now makes use of the data provided by more than 140 local councils. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publishing more council information will also put the voluntary sector and small businesses in a stronger position to bid for contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gathering-better-financial-information-from-local-government-to-help-make-public-services-more-efficient"&gt;Gathering better financial information from local government to help make public services more efficient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask local authorities in England to report &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/quarterly-revenue-outturn" title="Quarterly revenue outturn"&gt;revenue expenditure and forecast outturn&lt;/a&gt; every 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also published the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/single-data-list" title="Single data list"&gt;single data list&lt;/a&gt;. This is a list of all the datasets that local government must submit to central government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with HM Treasury requirements, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; collects returns from English local authorities for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/local-data-for-whole-of-government-accounts" title="Whole of Government Accounts"&gt;Whole of Government Accounts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sir Bob Kerslake, Permanent Secretary of &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;, published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accountability-adapting-to-decentralisation--2" title="Accountability: adapting to decentralisation"&gt;report on the transparency of local public services&lt;/a&gt; in September 2011. The report recommended ways to make sure that local councils are transparent and accountable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this report, all government departments started to publish annual ‘accountability system statements’ about the money they provide to local bodies. These statements demonstrate to Parliament that appropriate checks on spending are still in place following the move to a more local approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-authorities-data-transparency-code" title="Local authorities data transparency code consultation"&gt;consulted on the draft local government transparency code&lt;/a&gt; in early 2011. The consultation was published in February 2011 and the responses to the consultation were published in September 2011. In October 2012, we &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/improving-local-government-transparency" title="Improving local government transparency"&gt;consulted on updating the code and making it mandatory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on the draft Local Audit Bill in July and August 2012. This Bill will abolish the Audit Commission and put in place new local arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-authority-publicity-code" title="Local authority publicity code consultation"&gt;consulted local authorities about our draft revised Publicity Code&lt;/a&gt; in 2010. The Communities and Local Government Select Committee also undertook a short inquiry looking at the draft revised Code. Their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmcomloc/666/666.pdf" title="The Communities and Local Government Select Committee report: proposed code of recommended practice on local authority publicity"&gt;report (PDF 4.2MB)&lt;/a&gt; was published on 27 January 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public accountability of local government is covered in several Acts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Eliz2/8-9/67" title="Public Bodies (Admission to Meetings) Act 1960"&gt;Public Bodies (Admission to Meetings) Act 1960&lt;/a&gt; opened up meetings to the public, allowing members of the public and press to attend meetings of councils and certain other public bodies &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1972/70" title="Local Government Act 1972"&gt;Local Government Act 1972&lt;/a&gt; requires councillors to declare their interests, and councils to publish agendas, documents and reports &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1980/65/section/96" title="Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980: section 96"&gt;Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980: section 96&lt;/a&gt; established a public register of land and buildings owned by local councils. The aim of the register is to identify government land and buildings which are not being fully used &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1985/43" title="Local Government (Access to Information) Act 1985"&gt;Local Government (Access to Information) Act 1985&lt;/a&gt; provides public access to local authority meetings, reports and documents.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/1991/351/contents/made" title="Local Authorities (Members’ Allowances) Regulations 1991"&gt;Local Authorities (Members’ Allowances) Regulations 1991&lt;/a&gt; requires local authorities to publish the recommendations made by their independent remuneration panel, their scheme of allowances and the actual allowances paid to any member of the authority in any given year &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1992/14" title="Local Government Finance Act 1992"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 1992&lt;/a&gt; allows members of the public to obtain information about local domestic rating lists &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/36/contents" title="Freedom of Information Act 2000"&gt;Freedom of Information Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; allows people to request copies of information held by public authorities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/22/contents" title="Local Government Act 2000"&gt;Local Government Act 2000&lt;/a&gt; provides people with access to information held by local authority executives, like leaders and elected mayors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can download the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm83/8393/8393.pdf" title="Draft Local Audit Bill"&gt;‘Draft Local Audit Bill’ (PDF 1.54MB)&lt;/a&gt; from the Parliament website. This Bill will establish new local audit arrangements to replace the Audit Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partner-organisations"&gt;Partner organisations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re supporting the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk/blog/local-public-data-panel" title="data.gov.uk: Local Public Data Panel"&gt;Local Public Data Panel,&lt;/a&gt; an independent panel of experts on open data and transparency chaired by Professor Nigel Shadbolt. The panel was set up to make local public services better understood and more accessible. Its members include local authorities, community activists and web developers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
