<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/national-security</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "National security"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has welcomed Sir John Holmes' review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60044</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-announces-reduction-in-uk-troop-numbers-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prime Minister announces reduction in UK troop numbers in Afghanistan</title>
    <summary>UK force levels in Afghanistan are to reduce to around 5,200 by the end of 2013, the Prime Minister announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="Number 10"&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt; told &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/" title="UK Parliament"&gt;Parliament&lt;/a&gt; that UK forces would shift from mentoring Afghan troops at battalion level to brigade level next year. This reflects the progress made in Helmand and the increasing ability and confidence of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;) to lead security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown, agreed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-security-council" title="National Security Council"&gt;National Security Council&lt;/a&gt; this week, is in line and consistent with both UK military advice and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;North Atlantic Treaty Organization&lt;/a&gt; strategy agreed at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/events_66529.htm" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization Summit, Lisbon 2010"&gt;Lisbon Summit in 2010&lt;/a&gt;, under which &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) forces continue to operate across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK forces will end combat operations by the end of 2014. It is part of transition to an enduring commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement comes as the previously announced reduction of UK force levels from 9,500 to 9,000 is being achieved with service personnel due to arrive home in time for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed work on how force levels will reduce in 2013 is ongoing and will be conducted in line with operational requirements and the transition process which remains on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Afghan forces increasingly take the lead, UK combat operations will give way to an increasing focus on training and advising. By the end of 2013, it is expected that UK forces will not routinely need to mentor Afghan forces below brigade level, allowing the reduction in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real progress being made on the ground in Helmand province will allow us, on current planning, to reduce British troops to around 5,200 by the end of 2013. This is a direct result of the success of the Afghan National Security Forces in assuming a lead role in delivering security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The phased process of transition of security responsibility agreed at the Lisbon Summit is well advanced and on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have consistently said that there will not be a cliff-edge reduction in troop numbers at the end of 2014. This gradual drawdown is firmly in line with the planning of our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; partners and the advice of military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces will continue to operate alongside their Afghan counterparts, albeit in lower numbers, until our combat operations cease at the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There remain huge challenges ahead for the Afghan people. Our combat mission is drawing to a close, but our commitment to the Afghan people is long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Afghan National Army" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5775/JMOCCCT-2012-014_Op_Horhari_Afghan_004.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Afghan National Army take part in an operation in Helmand province (stock image) [Picture: Sergeant Steve Blake RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir David Richards, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Army and Police have greatly improved in the past years. Their capability has increased so that today they enjoy the trust of some 84 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As they develop, and in agreement with the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, the efforts of our Armed Forces will continue to shift from a combat role to one that focuses on training, advice and assistance. That will allow us to make appropriate and measured reductions in our force levels in line with the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; plan and our Chicago commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These drawdown plans are based on military advice and following discussion with General Allen [Commander &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces]. I am confident that the progress we have seen in Helmand and across Afghanistan can be maintained and that we can complete the tasks we have been set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be in the position where we are now able to commit to reducing UK force levels to around 5,200 by the end of next year is testament to the professionalism and courage of those personnel who have served, and continue to serve, in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We must remember that the UK’s commitment to the operation in Afghanistan will continue beyond the end of 2014 as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/" title="Department for International Development"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [Department for International Development] and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign Office&lt;/a&gt; continue to build the government and nation while the UK’s pledge to support the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, including training the military’s officers, will be ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significant progress in Afghanistan continues with 75% of the Afghan population now being secured by the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; and at least 80% of all patrols being &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;-led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 80 UK bases at the start of the HERRICK 16 deployment this April, only 32 remain active with the others having been handed over to Afghan forces or closed. Afghan National Army numbers in Helmand province now stand at about 18,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57526</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-protector-takes-to-the-ice-for-a-charity-santa-run"/>
    <title>HMS Protector takes to the ice for a charity Santa run</title>
    <summary>HMS Protector's ship's company have taken to the ice in Antarctica dressed as Father Christmas in support of the ship's affiliated charity.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Santas, accompanied by Rudolph, were gathered at 10am for a gentle warm-up led by the Executive Officer, Commander Don Mackinnon, who is currently in command for this Antarctic patrol, before it was ‘on your marks, get set… ho ho ho’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Santa run was conducted on ice in the waters surrounding Deception Island, a dormant, water-filled caldera volcano; one of only two known in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking through a sheet of snow-covered ice before coming to a planned stop, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Ice-Patrol-and-Survey-Ships/HMS-Protector" title="HMS Protector"&gt;HMS Protector&lt;/a&gt; took position and disembarked her personnel to test the ice conditions and drill ice core samples to ensure the ice was safe, before Protector’s eager Father Christmasses followed via the ship’s accommodation ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amid perfect weather conditions, and under the watchful eye of two seals that had taken up post next to the ship, they completed their run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5743/protector2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line, ready for the off [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annually, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.each.org.uk/" title="East Anglian Children's Hospice"&gt;East Anglian Children’s Hospice&lt;/a&gt; conducts nine Santa runs across Essex and East Anglia throughout the festive period, raising thousands of pounds for the charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is traditional for Royal Naval ships to adopt a charity from their affiliated town so that they can fundraise whilst away from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the work that HMS Protector conducts in Antarctica, she has formed a close liaison with a number of organisations in the Cambridge area (amongst them the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.antarctica.ac.uk/" title="British Antarctic Survey"&gt;British Antarctic Survey&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.spri.cam.ac.uk/" title="Scott Polar Research Institute"&gt;Scott Polar Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;) and as such is affiliated to the City of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector has been affiliated with the East Anglian Children’s Hospice since August 2012. The East Anglian Children’s Hospice provides support to families and care for children and young people with life-threatening conditions across Cambridgeshire, Essex, Norfolk and Suffolk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) Royal Navy" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5744/protector3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) gets off to a flying start [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing care and support wherever the family wishes, in families’ own homes, in the community or at the hospices, their care teams help children and their families with the emotional and physical challenges they face, helping them to make the most of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Don Mackinnon stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With 21 hours of daylight in every 24, our working day in Antarctica tends to be a long one. Yesterday for example our first boat group departed the ship at 0830 [8.30am] in the morning and the last one finally got back at 2300 [11pm] that night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With that sort of work pace it’s nice to be able to take a break from operations now and again, and do something both for fun, and also to help our affiliated charity at the same time. Father Christmas’s traditional home might be the North Pole… but as you can see, he has helpers that visit the other one too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector is currently in the Antarctic in order to support an international team conducting formal &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ats.aq/e/ats.htm" title="The Antarctic Treaty"&gt;Antarctic Treaty&lt;/a&gt; inspections of sites across the Peninsula, whilst maintaining a UK Sovereign presence in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5745/protector4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses lie on the ice to spell out EACH [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Led by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/a&gt; and with the support of the British Antarctic Survey and observers from HMS Protector, the international Antarctic Treaty team is inspecting a number of scientific stations, historic sites, cruise vessels and yachts in the Antarctic Peninsula region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector will be operating in and around Antarctica until April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59902</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements </title>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague condemns decision to build new settlements in East Jerusalem.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK condemns the decision by the Jerusalem District Planning Board to give approval for a plan to build 1,500 housing units in the East Jerusalem neighbourhood of Ramat Shlomo, and is extremely concerned by reports that the Board is considering giving the approval to a further 5000 housing units in East Jerusalem this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on yesterday’s announcement the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Israeli settlements are illegal under international law, and I condemn this decision. It is deeply disappointing that despite the international community repeatedly raising our concerns, Israel continues to press ahead with plans to expand them.  Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties.  This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.  If implemented, it would make a negotiated two-state solution, with Jerusalem as a shared capital, very difficult to achieve.  We  urge Israel to reverse this decision and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity”
.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57532</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:49:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-joy-for-old-soldier-who-finally-got-his-medal"/>
    <title>Christmas joy for old soldier who finally got his medal</title>
    <summary>A former soldier from Lancashire has received the only service medal he was ever entitled to… 42 years late</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Army veteran Joe McKenna, 72, who volunteers at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/" title="Duke of Lancaster's Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum"&gt;Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Preston, left the military in 1970 just months before his Northern Ireland service medal was minted and eventually decided to track down his medal after years of attending parades where he was the only veteran not wearing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Bob Dixon, from 2 Medical Regiment and a fellow volunteer at the museum, offered to help Joe claim his honour. Sergeant Major Dixon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had been helping some visitors at the museum with enquiries about their service medals and so I offered to help Joe too. I got all the paperwork together, went around to his house, and we filled in the documents before sending them off to the MOD Medal Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We got a reply within 2 months, the quickest I’ve ever known; I think the turnaround was so fast because he still lives at the same address that appeared on his service papers back in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe enlisted in the Loyal Regiment, a forebear to the North West’s current infantry regiment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/3477.aspx" title="The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;The Duke of Lancaster’s&lt;/a&gt;, almost exactly 51 years ago and served in Kenya, Swaziland, Cyprus and Malta as well as in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern Ireland service medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5711/Joe_smedal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Joe McKenna's Northern Ireland service medal [Picture: Sergeant Mark Garry, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After he left the Army as a Lance Corporal in 1970, Joe worked for more than 30 years as an &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; driver, married Josie, with whom he had his children Sandra and Peter, and is now a grandfather of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said until recently the distractions of day-to-day life meant he just never got around to claiming what was his: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was only when I was marching at the Armed Forces Day parade in Preston last summer when I thought ‘I’m getting on a bit now and I should really get my medal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think my son would like to have it when I’m gone; he and my daughter think that it is marvellous that it’s finally here. It’s the best Christmas present ever and it makes me very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe’s wife Josie added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It really was something special to see his face when he received the medal; it was as if all his Christmases had come at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe now plans to wear his medal at his regiment’s Kimberley Day service and parade in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57555</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:23:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-sutherland-returns-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Sutherland returns in time for Christmas</title>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Sutherland has returned to the UK after a successful six-month deployment in the Middle East and Indian Ocean.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship was greeted by cheering and waving families and friends wearing festive hats and holding banners with loving messages at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;HM Naval Base Devonport&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth on Saturday 15 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship’s Culdrose-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopter flight arrived back separately at the Helston air station on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Sutherland" title="HMS Sutherland"&gt;HMS Sutherland&lt;/a&gt; has been busy conducting anti-piracy and terrorism patrols as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/Combined-Maritime-Forces" title="Combined Maritime Forces"&gt;Combined Maritime Forces&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring the sea lanes and waters east of Suez and off the Horn of Africa are safe for seafarers to conduct their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship conducted boarding operations on suspect vessels and also reassurance visits to build relationships with mariners and obtain information on pattern of life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="AS(ME) Dale Plumpton kissing Terri Layden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5729/Sutherland5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Able Seaman (Marine Engineering) Dale Plumpton receives a welcome home kiss from Terri Layden [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crew also exercised with coalition and allied forces in the region to strengthen ties and improve methods of working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland’s Commanding Officer, Commander Al Wilson, said it was a ‘magic’ time to come home at Christmas. He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The huge variety and diversity of task that Sutherland has fulfilled whilst on operations illustrates the inherent flexibility of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; in protecting and promoting UK interests worldwide, whether it is preventing piracy or terrorism at sea or strengthening bonds with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, I could not have achieved this without an efficient, capable and highly motivated ship’s company and, as always, I am highly proud of what my team has achieved over the last 6 months whilst remaining cheerful and utterly professional throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My team and myself are now looking forward to spending Christmas at home with our loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Navy personnel on board HMS Sutherland" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5730/Sutherland4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Petty Officer on board HMS Sutherland waves to the waiting families on the dockside as the ship comes into port [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Able Rate (Communication Information Specialist) Peter Hodgkin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland is my first ship and I joined her 3 months prior to deploying on operations. With this being my first deployment and first time away from the UK I was nervous, but excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There have been some tough times, but overall I have really enjoyed it, especially the team spirit of the ship and all the good work that we have achieved on operations. My most memorable moment was helping out at an orphanage in Tanzania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having handed over duties to sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;HMS Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; at the end of November, the crew of HMS Sutherland is now looking forward to spending Christmas at home and time with families and friends before a busy 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57066</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:32:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-secretary-welcomes-defence-reform-annual-report"/>
    <title>Defence Secretary welcomes Defence Reform annual report</title>
    <summary>The Defence Secretary has welcomed Lord Levene's review of progress towards implementing the recommendations of the Defence Reform Review. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a letter to the Secretary of State, Lord Levene congratulated the Department on strong progress made against the 53 recommendations since the publication of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2" title="Defence Reform Report, June 2011"&gt;Defence Reform Report&lt;/a&gt; in June 2011 and said that he believes the programme is being run with genuine urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full report, with the new annex by Lord Levene, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome Lord Levene’s recognition of the strong progress made to date in implementing his recommendations, and his confidence that we can deliver transition to a new operating model for the Ministry of Defence in April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some of the key changes of Defence Reform are already complete, such as strengthened top-level decision-making and the focus on strategic direction from a newly-constituted Defence Board, which I chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-joint-forces-command-established--2" title="Read more about the establishment of the Joint Forces Command"&gt;The Joint Forces Command has been established&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14926288" title="Read more about the appointment of the first Commander of the UK's Joint Forces Command"&gt;first Commander appointed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many other recommendations are on track for delivery by April 2013, including the delegation of financial and military capability management to give the Service Chiefs greater accountability and freedom to manage their resources and plan for future capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A few recommendations will take longer to complete: I acknowledge that there is more to do in some areas, such as development of the Whole Force Concept and the delivery of improved Management Information, and I value Lord Levene’s continued interest and focus on these important changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am confident, though, that by April [2013] we will have gone a long way towards achieving the aim of the Defence Reform programme: a smaller more professional MOD that is better at supporting the Armed Forces now, and looking forward to Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57040</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:26:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/video-hms-edinburgh-sends-home-festive-cheer"/>
    <title>VIDEO: HMS Edinburgh sends home festive cheer</title>
    <summary>The sailors of HMS Edinburgh have created a musical message for their loved ones back home as they prepare to spend Christmas on deployment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 260 sailors serving on board &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-42-Destroyers/HMS-Edinburgh" title="HMS Edinburgh"&gt;HMS Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; will spend the festive season on board the Portsmouth-based warship while she sails the South Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a bid to spread some Christmas cheer the personnel have donned their smartest Santa outfits and created a video for their loved ones set to The Darkness’ Christmas Time (Don’t Let The Bells End):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jEz0dfCrqaI" title="HMS Edinburgh Christmas Video"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video features scenes from around the ship with sailors wearing Santa hats, Christmas cracker outfits and elf costumes waving hello to family and friends from thousands of miles away at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the crew have also made videos to send back to their home towns - the full selection can be seen on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/royalnavyofficial" title="Royal Navy Official YouTube channel"&gt;Royal Navy’s official YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of HMS Edinburgh, Commander Nick Borbone, who will be away from wife Joanne and children Barney, 9, Eddie, 6, and Amy, 5, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will be strange not being there on Christmas Day and I will miss seeing them, but they have lots of friends and family to keep them entertained and I will call them to see how they are getting on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a tough time of year to be away, but I expect there will be a good festive spirit on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last of the Royal Navy’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-42-Destroyers" title="Type 42 destroyers"&gt;Type 42 destroyers&lt;/a&gt;, HMS Edinburgh is halfway through a six-month deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a historic milestone for both the ship and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; as it will be the last time a Type 42 destroyer deploys on operations as they make way for the new-generation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Edinburgh is undertaking a range of tasks across the length of the Atlantic in support of British interests. Her tasking will see her supporting counter-narcotics efforts in the West African region as well as providing reassurance to UK territories and dependencies worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Borbone will be the last commanding officer of a Type 42 destroyer. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a real privilege. HMS Edinburgh might be the last of the class but she remains a capable ship with a highly-trained and motivated ship’s company that is determined to preserve the fine tradition that the Type 42s have established in 30 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57046</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T17:56:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council--2"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and the General Affairs Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Europe Mr David Lidington said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I attended the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, the Foreign Secretary attending the initial part before handing over to me.  I attended the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council was chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council was chaired by the Cypriot Presidency, the Deputy Minister for European Affairs, Ambassador Andreas Mavroyiannis, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Dr. Erato Kozakou-Markoullis.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commissioners Füle (Enlargement and European Neighbourhood Policy) and Georgieva (International Cooperation, Humanitarian Aid and Crisis Response) were also in attendance for some of the discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A provisional report of the meetings and all Conclusions adopted can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/foraff/134152.pdf" title="Provisional report"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch, Ministers discussed the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. There was a widely shared view that  the EU should focus on human rights, including the role and freedom of NGOs; push Russia to end its restrictive trade practices in order to comply with its World Trade Organisation obligations; press for implementation of the agreement on Siberian overflight royalties; and reaffirm the importance of the Third Energy Package. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers considered the need for re-engagement by the international community on the Middle East Peace Process in 2013 over lunch.  Ministers agreed Conclusions calling for the parties to return to negotiations without precondition with international support; expressing deep dismay at and strong opposition to recent Israeli announcements on settlements; calling on Israel to avoid undermining the financial situation of the Palestinian Authority; and urging the Palestinians not to build on their change in UN status in a way that would undermine a return to talks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council debated the latest developments in Syria, ahead of the next meeting of the Friends of Syria group in Marrakech on 12 December. During lunch, ministers exchanged views with Ahmed Moaz Al-Khatib, President of the National Coalition for Syrian Revolutionary and Opposition Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed Conclusions on Syria, expressing their concern at the deteriorating situation, and the need for greater protection of civilians.  The Conclusions state that ‘the EU accepts [the National Coalition for Syrian Revolutionary and Opposition Forces] as legitimate representatives of the Syrian people’.  The Conclusions reiterated that “if concerns about war crimes and crimes against humanity are not adequately addressed on a national level, the International Criminal Court should deal with the situation”, and called upon the United Nations Security Council “to urgently address the situation in Syria in all aspects”.
Ministers expressed their concern about the situation in Egypt, ahead of the planned referendum on 15 December.  They agreed that it was in the EU’s interest to see a democratic, inclusive, economically-sound Egypt, and noted the need for strong EU engagement with Egypt, based upon mutual accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers discussed the situation in Libya.  The High Representative stated that there had been a number of positive developments in Libya, politically and economically, and that the EU now needed to develop co-operation in border management and security.  Ministers welcomed the Fact Finding Mission, which had demonstrated significant Libyan political will to engage. Ministers noted that the EU needed to build on and sustain contacts with the Libyan authorities and UN so that international efforts were coordinated and met Libyan requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers had a short discussion on Western Balkans issues. This was one of a series of Western Balkans related meetings building up to the General Affairs Council discussion of the Enlargement Conclusions.  The High Representative briefed ministers on the latest developments in the Belgrade-Pristina Dialogue, noting that the successful opening of two crossing points was a significant step in terms of Integrated Border Management implementation. Member States welcomed the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this issue.
The need to maintain a credible EU perspective for Macedonia was also raised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="council-conclusions"&gt;Council Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I anticipated in my pre-Council statement, Ministers agreed Conclusions without discussion on Ukraine and the Democratic Republic of Congo.  In addition, Ministers approved the Crisis Management Concept for a Common Security and Defence Policy military mission aimed at providing training and advice to the Malian Armed Forces; and the revised Crisis Management Concept for the EU Training Mission for Somalia.  In light of the DPRK’s recent announcement of its plan to launch a satellite, in breach of UN Security Council Resolutions, the Council agreed Conclusions expressing deep concern, urging the DPRK not to conduct the launch, and signalling the need for an international response, potentially including sanctions, were the launch to go ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed without discussion a number of others measures, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Azerbaijan Cooperation Council, to take place on 17 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Georgia Cooperation Council, to take place on 18 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Armenia Cooperation Council, to take place on 17 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adoption of a decision on the signing, on behalf of the European Union, of a protocol to the Partnership and Cooperation Agreement with the Republic of Armenia, which will allow the participation of Armenia in EU programmes. It forwarded the draft decision on conclusion of the protocol to the European Parliament for its consent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A review of the list of persons, groups and entities subject to EU restrictive measures with a view to combating terrorism, according to common position 2001/931/CFSP. No changes were made to the measures, which currently affect 11 persons and 25 groups and entities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of preparations for the annual review of EU restrictive measures against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adoption of the implementation plan for the EU advisory and assistance mission for security reform in the Democratic Republic of Congo (EUSEC RD Congo) for the period until 30 September 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A provisional report of the meeting and all Conclusions adopted can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/ueDocs/cms_Data/docs/pressData/EN/genaff/134235.pdf" title="Provisional report"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC discussed the issue of the appointment of nine additional judges for the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union.  The Presidency presented their proposals, suggesting a rotating system between Member States with a weighted allocation.  I emphasised the importance of sufficient representation of judges from a common law background and stressed the need to ensure that the proposals were budget neutral.  There was no consensus on this issue which will be revisited next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission presented the main priorities for this year’s Annual Growth Survey, stressing that Member States must “stay the course” on fiscal consolidation and structural reforms if the EU is to achieve long-term, sustainable growth. The incoming Irish Presidency then outlined their roadmap for handling the process in Council, focussing on the importance of bilateral dialogue and multilateral surveillance to resolve Member States’ concerns relating to country specific recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council-and-february-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council and February European Council&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency announced the agenda for the February European Council, which is due to focus on trade and external relations. The outcome of the December European Council will be covered in the Prime Minister’s statement to the House of Commons and the Leader of the House of Lords’ statement to the House of Lords.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC endorsed the programme of the incoming Trio of Presidencies; Ireland, Lithuania and Greece. The programme covers a broad range of priorities for the next 18-month period. For Ireland, the key was strengthening Economic and Monetary Union, implementing agreed reforms to economic governance, and securing financial stability including Banking Union. Ireland also looked for progress on the Multiannual Financial Framework and related dossiers.  They underlined the importance of measures which have the potential to improve competitiveness and create jobs and growth.  Finally they also want to see progress on third country trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC discussion focussed on Macedonia, Serbia and Kosovo. The Council agreed a package of Conclusions on enlargement including important steps forward for several countries, which rightly recognise their progress so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council made its commitment to Macedonia’s EU path clear with the Council taking a possible decision on opening accession negotiations during the next Presidency, based on a report to be presented by the European Commission in spring 2013 on progress relating to good neighbourly relations and movement on the name issue. This is an important and valuable opportunity for Macedonia to move further forward next year, and we look forward to a positive decision to open accession negotiations soon. I welcome, in that regard, the Commission starting preparatory work. Likewise the government is pleased that the Commission will propose negotiating directives to take forward Kosovo’s EU path with a Stabilisation and Association Agreement, once Kosovo meets the short term conditions. This will be a significant step forward for Kosovo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The High Representative briefed again on the EU-led Dialogue between Serbia and Kosovo. I set out the UK government’s continued firm support for Serbia’s EU future. The Council undertook to review during the first half of next year progress on the conditions the Council has agreed for Serbia to open accession negotiations, including progress in the Dialogue and irreversible progress on the parallel structures in northern Kosovo, as reiterated by the High Representative. The Council was clear that it wanted to see Serbia moving to the next stage as soon as they have met the conditions to do so. The recent steps taken in the EU-led Dialogue between Serbia and Kosovo had shown that both countries can move forward and deal with difficult issues, enabling them to continue on their European paths. I welcomed the steps taken by the parties so far and I endorsed the Council’s commendation for Prime Ministers Dacic and Thaci: they had approached their recent discussions in a statesman like and courageous manner. The Council expected the two sides to continue and accelerate their work in addressing all aspects of the relations between them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusions on Bosnia and Herzegovina set out the Council’s concern about the slow progress being made in Bosnia and Herzegovina and stalled reforms there; and the risk that Bosnia and Herzegovina will lag further behind her neighbours unless the political leaders deliver on the actions they have agreed.  The GAC called on the Bosnian leaders to act, in the interests of their citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council Conclusions also covered Albania, reflecting recent progress and underlining the need to further intensify efforts as identified by the Commission. The successful conduct of Parliamentary elections in 2013 will be a crucial test for the smooth functioning of the country’s democratic institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council adopted forward-looking Conclusions on Turkey which will allow the accession process to be taken forward in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council looked forward to Croatia’s accession and welcomed progress made by Iceland and Montenegro. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to update Parliament on future Foreign Affairs Councils and General Affairs Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
