<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/national-security</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "National security"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56853</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:05:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/female-officer-cadet-wins-sandhursts-sword-of-honour"/>
    <title>Female Officer Cadet wins Sandhurst's Sword of Honour</title>
    <summary>A female officer has become just the fourth woman in history to win Sandhurst's prestigious Sword of Honour.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The top accolade from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/training_education/training/17057.aspx" title="Royal Military Academy Sandhurst"&gt;Royal Military Academy Sandhurst&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Officer Cadet Sarah Hunter-Choat, who received the award during her commissioning at the Sovereign’s Parade on Friday 14 December.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted Sword of Honour is presented to the best overall Officer Cadet out of 200 in the senior term and is personally chosen by the Academy’s Commandant, Major General Timothy Evans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 200 cadets have their performance rigorously monitored throughout the year. Then, going into the final phase of their training, the 3 top candidates, termed ‘blade runners’, are carefully scrutinised then brought before the Commandant for a final interview. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat received the Sword of Honour from Defence Secretary Philip Hammond, who represented Her Majesty The Queen at the Sovereign’s Parade. It has been 6 years since a female officer won, when Angela Laycock was commissioned into the Royal Engineers in December 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat’s success follows in her parents’ footsteps. Her father Brigadier Tony Hunter-Choat had a long, distinguished military career, starting out in the French Foreign Legion before commissioning into the British Army, while her mother is a former RAF officer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56877</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-palestinian-refugee-camp-bombing-in-damascus"/>
    <title>UK condemns Palestinian refugee camp bombing in Damascus</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the attack by the Syrian regime which killed at least 20 people yesterday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of Syrian government air strikes on the Yarmouk refugee camp in Damascus, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I condemn the Syrian regime’s aerial bombardment of the Yarmouk Palestinian refugee camp in Damascus, which killed at least 20 people yesterday. They are among four hundred Syrians killed across the country this weekend in yet another tragic reminder that the Assad regime continues to attack its own people with brutality and without remorse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Syrian government actions have already driven hundreds of thousands of Syrian civilians from their homes into neighboring countries. The senseless targeting of Palestinian refugees, who had hitherto looked to Syria for shelter and protection, will only exacerbate the risk of contagion across the region. Our objective remains an end to the violence and a transition to a more democratic and stable Syria.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56977</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-to-auction-off-radio-spectrum"/>
    <title>MOD to auction off radio spectrum</title>
    <summary>The Ministry of Defence is planning to auction some of its radio spectrum in the first direct sale of its kind by a government department.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radio spectrum refers to the radio waves over which all wireless communication takes place, including radio, television, radar, satellite, mobile voice and data. Under plans announced today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to auction around 200 Megahertz (&lt;abbr title="Megahertz"&gt;MHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) of its spectrum usage rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes as market demand for extra spectrum is mounting, fuelled by the sharp rise in the use of spectrum-hungry devices such as smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale will give private operators the chance to buy more spectrum to support the introduction of fourth-generation mobile services to people in cities, towns and villages across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively the spectrum could be used by fixed-line operators to provide wireless access to broadband services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum being sold by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is all below 15 Gigahertz (&lt;abbr title="Gigahertz"&gt;GHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is regarded as the most useful and valuable part of the radio spectrum because of its wide range of applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of all spectrum below 15GHz is held by the public sector and is used for a broad range of services including defence, emergency services, transport and science. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; holds around three-quarters of all publicly-held spectrum and one-third of all spectrum below 15GHz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome this opportunity to free up much-needed spectrum. We hope that the sale will help drive the roll-out of new generation networks and universal access to broadband, both of which are vital to the UK’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale follows the announcement made in the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/spend_index.htm" title="Spending Review"&gt;2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; that at least 500MHz of public spectrum below 5GHz will be released by 2020 for new mobile communications uses. The spectrum to be sold off is being cleared of military users to contribute towards this target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are expected to start at the end of 2013, with the auction completed by the summer of 2014. Ahead of this, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to produce an Industry Brochure in early spring 2013 and to host an Industry Day in early summer 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56828</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:30:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-brize-norton-counting-down-to-christmas"/>
    <title>RAF Brize Norton counting down to Christmas</title>
    <summary>As people tuck into Christmas dinner, it will be business as usual for RAF personnel deployed overseas or at RAF stations across the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we take a closer look at how &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;RAF Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt; in Oxfordshire prepares for the festive season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-boss"&gt;The boss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAF Brize Norton is the largest station in the RAF and has approximately 6,000 Service personnel and 1,400 MOD civil servants and contractors. It is the home of the Air Mobility Squadrons and the ‘gateway to operations’ as the main airport used for deploying UK troops worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The station never sleeps and supports operations around the world 24/7, 365-days-a-year. Station Commander Group Captain Steve Lushington and his family will be serving Christmas dinner to the junior ranks on the big day. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the festive season gets into full swing, for personnel at RAF Brize Norton work continues as normal. The support to operations is paramount; even during the festive period personnel are still required to be on duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pilots and engineers on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/216squadron.cfm" title="216 Squadron"&gt;216 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/99squadron.cfm" title="99 Squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; maintain their high readiness state, personnel continue to control from the tower, operations staff continue to plan missions and taskings, all supporting tri-Service personnel across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Captain Steve Lushington" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5706/Brize1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Group Captain Steve Lushington, Station Commander at RAF Brize Norton [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/c17aglobemaster.cfm" title="C-17 Globemaster"&gt;C-17 Globemaster&lt;/a&gt; is a huge, heavy-lift transport aircraft operated by 99 Squadron. It can carry troops and all types of cargo around the world, including transporting &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/merlin.cfm" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/chinook.cfm" title="Chinook"&gt;Chinook&lt;/a&gt; helicopters direct to the front line in Afghanistan to provide support to ground troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stuart Lindsell is the Officer Commanding 99 Squadron and has volunteered to cover Christmas duties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The squadron is 300-plus-strong and moves an immense amount of personal mail and parcels from families and loved ones. It’s rewarding for us to know that we are helping to play a part in connecting Service families who are separated over the Christmas period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s very much ‘business as usual’ for 99 Squadron; we have crews covering aeromed standby, a crew based in the Middle East ready for normal tasking. The squadron engineers stand ready to generate an aircraft at short notice should an aeromed mission be called and they will also be manning the engineer control desks as normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best way to look at it is hopefully Christmas Day itself will be quiet, but Christmas Eve, Boxing Day and to that extent the New Year period are no different to any other time of year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festive season can bring wintry conditions and, a couple of years ago, when the UK was gripped by sub-zero temperatures and heavy snowfalls, in the thick of it were 99 Squadron who battled to get troops home for Christmas. Wing Commander Lindsell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Snow and ice are certainly not ideal flying conditions to say the least but as a station we are better off than we were when the wintry conditions of 2010 hit. We did manage to get everyone home but it was certainly a challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="snow-and-ice-operations"&gt;Snow and ice operations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Corporal John Oliver" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5707/Brize3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Corporal John Oliver from the Airfield Support Mechanical Transport section [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal John Oliver will also be on standby during Christmas and works at the Complete Equipment Schedule Store at Airfield Support Mechanical Transport that, amongst other things, makes sure vehicles are in working order. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve spent the last 2 months preparing and bringing online all the snow and ice prevention vehicles as they are not used during the summer months; we inflate their tyres, fill the vehicle up with whatever fluid it needs, test it and carry out daily inspections to make sure they are ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it was horrendous snow the main vehicle we would use is the airfield snow clearing vehicle or the compact jet sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicles are equipped to plough snow, break up compact ice and blow snow, broken ice or other debris to the side. Corporal Oliver continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is to make sure we have a serviceable fleet of vehicles to meet the minimum required to clear the airfield. It’s a priority to clear the runway and certain bays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Getting the airfield cleared is very important for the ‘airbridge’, especially for those personnel that want to get home in the last couple of days before Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="air-movements-squadron"&gt;Air Movements Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5708/Brize4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson getting into the festive spirit at a check-in desk in the air terminal [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal Emma Hopkinson works on the passenger check-in desk in the air terminal for the Air Movements Squadron. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s like a civilian airport. The difference is, if I went for a job in a civilian airport I would only just be either a check-in girl, departures, or elsewhere in the building, whereas here at Brize we have to multi-task and do everything - one minute I could be behind the check-in desk, then I could be on the check-through or departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We see the whole process through and make sure that nobody is left behind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked what it’s like checking in troops knowing they will be away for Christmas, Corporal Hopkinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is no different at Christmas, the process is still the same, it’s the personalities and how people are with you, and how you are with them - I try and be a bit more jolly! I’ve done Iraq, Afghanistan and Ascension Island at Christmas, so I know what it’s like being away at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Hopkinson will be on shift during the Christmas period but sets aside a day in the new year to have a ‘Christmas Day’ with her family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I remember one year my mum bought a second turkey and it stayed in the freezer until February! I go to college and have met a lot of people and they are surprised I’m working Christmas Eve and Christmas Day - they ask ‘are you open?’ and I say yes! it’s a 24/7 camp, and it’s the same for New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="christmas-presence"&gt;Christmas ‘presence’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5709/Brize5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as 'Kev the Rev', will be working over the New Year period [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like the station itself, the chapel is open 24/7, and for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/chaplains/" title="RAF Chaplains"&gt;RAF chaplains&lt;/a&gt; the run-up to Christmas is always busy. Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as ‘Kev the Rev’, will be working over the New Year period, but last year was on duty over Christmas. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because our senior chaplain was away on ops, I joined other officers on station and helped serve Christmas lunch in the Junior Ranks Mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a great experience, my wife was with me and some personnel brought family along. There was that family feel, the military family; everyone was in very good spirits as the portions of potatoes were getting bigger and bigger!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We often think about the people who are deployed at home or overseas, but it’s harder for the families left behind. Service people will make the most of it, no matter what, and I’m sure they get an extra mince pie or an extra bit of turkey and will make the most of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s the families left behind and the kids that don’t have their mum or dad with them on Christmas Day that find it hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best gift at Christmas is ‘presence’. For those who have had loved ones away last year, they will know that having loved ones around is the best gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If not ‘presence’, instantaneous communication such as emails and Skype is great; however, people underestimate e-blueys and handwritten letters - they have that personal touch which means so much to people and always makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56779</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:14:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-portland-sets-sail-after-27-million-refit"/>
    <title>HMS Portland sets sail after £27 million refit</title>
    <summary>HMS Portland is on her way to Plymouth after a £27 million 50-week refit at Rosyth dockyard in Fife, Scotland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With more than 260,000 man-hours invested in the almost year-long project, the 133-metre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Portland" title="HMS Portland"&gt;HMS Portland&lt;/a&gt; has returned to sea bristling with the latest high-tech equipment, maintaining its role at the cutting-edge of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 19 major system and capability upgrades have been undertaken on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates" title="Type 23 frigates"&gt;Type 23 frigate&lt;/a&gt;, including the installation of new anti-submarine warfare sonar, full upgrade of the ship’s computer systems, an overhaul of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Weapons-Systems/Seawolf" title="Seawolf"&gt;Seawolf&lt;/a&gt; missile system, replacement of guns, refurbishment of the galley and upgrades of accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship sailed underneath the famous Forth Bridges having had a total exterior makeover too, with 15,000 litres of paint having been applied to her hull and superstructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Sarah West, Commanding Officer of HMS Portland, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very much looking forward to getting this fantastic ship back to sea to put her through her paces. In tandem with the MOD and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, the crew has spent many long months working hard to return HMS Portland to fighting form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Portland " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5675/NE120458002g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Portland sails from Rosyth following her refit [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Arthur, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ship is equipped for the many future challenges which greet the modern fleet and we are ready to be with her every step of the way. It is an exciting moment returning a warship to sea after refit - we know that HMS Portland is in great shape for regaining full operational readiness early next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has benefited from close partnership between Babcock, the MOD, ship personnel and the team under the Surface Ship Support Alliance, resulting in the refit programme being delivered on time and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babcock project manager Russell Glancy said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have successfully met the challenges of this project, and applied our experience from previous Type 23 refits, along with strong partnering, to ensure delivery of this upgrade and maintenance programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Portland will undertake a further 3 months of sea trials and training before returning to the fleet as a fully operational ship, prepared at any time to take on duties worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3,500-tonne Type 23 frigates, of which there are 13 in the fleet, are flexible and adaptable ships which protect the UK’s interests both in home waters and further afield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical deployments will include anything from the fleet ready escort, which is the UK’s high readiness ship, to counter-narcotics, piracy and terrorism patrols and the ship can provide humanitarian intervention and security when required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57013</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T23:46:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/chief-of-the-defence-staff-general-sir-david-richards-speech-to-the-royal-united-services-institute-rusi-17-december-2012"/>
    <title>Chief of the Defence Staff General Sir David Richards speech to the Royal United Services Institute (RUSI), 17 December 2012</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you Lord Hutton for your kind introduction.  It is good to see so many friends and colleagues here and may I take the opportunity to thank you all for your strong support to the Armed Forces.  It is hugely appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am feeling slightly cautious this evening.  Our senior Defence Attaché in the Americas tells me that in the Aztec calendar today is the Day of the Lizard.  They say:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘The warrior must be like the lizard, who is not hurt by a high fall but, instead, immediately climbs back to its perch.  These are good days to keep out of sight; bad days to attract attention.’&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So perhaps today isn’t the best time to be standing before you!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In honouring my commitment to this august organisation that plays such an important role in the life of UK Defence, I want to take the opportunity to examine where we are today, what deductions we should draw, and what we are doing to ensure we are prepared for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are all aware of how much change there has been over the past two years.  We have begun to introduce the SDSR, balanced the books and turned a corner in Afghanistan.  Yet much of the world seems less stable and more dangerous than was the case even two years ago; a harsh world in which intra-state conflict can be confused by and for new forms of inter-state conflict.  A world in which governance vacuums present opportunities for extremist groups to perpetrate large-scale violence and disruption, especially as precision-strike capabilities, cyber instruments and bio terror weaponry become inevitably more accessible.  And this in a period when economic fragility makes us both more vulnerable and less able to respond in a confident and timely manner, a reality aggravated by the huge cost differentials between western forces and non-state opponents. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this is demanding much from all of us and is changing the shape and capabilities of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together with my fellow Chiefs I have been examining, as you would expect, how we should best use what we have and what we need for the future.  We have to be hard-nosed realists; accepting we have less than we would wish but that we are still required to protect this nation’s interests through the projection of military force.  We cannot shrug our shoulders and hope the problem will go away.  We have to be ready to fight and fight effectively, often not on our own terms and accepting the constraints we are under.  I have brought this together in a piece of work I will be sharing in the future called How We Will Fight.  And I will look at some of its key deductions in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should be under no illusions; the Armed Forces of tomorrow, like those of today, will be engaged in operations around the world.  They will require the best of their generation as they always have.  People who can think flexibly and with imagination.  As Einstein said, “imagination is more important than knowledge”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These operations will not be carbon copies of Afghanistan or Libya.  But they will require the same skill and dedication that these operations, and all the others we have engaged in since the Cold War, have demanded.  They will require the strength and indeed guile that our Army, Navy and Air Force are famous for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the battle-winning reputation, proven resilience and technological edge of the past decade, I hope you won’t notice some of the tasks the Armed Forces will be doing.  They will be performing a key part of our developing military strategy – deterrence.  Preventing conflict, you may recall, is rightly a principal task of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will come back to this theme later but it is worth remembering that your Armed Forces are often most effective when they are not in the headlines.  Few operations, exercises or training missions are widely reported but each one communicates that we are strong, credible and reliable.  This deters our enemies and reassures our friends.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we should be proud of our nation’s record in this respect.  The relative peace we have enjoyed here in the UK for the past 70 years is not an accident.  It is in large part the result of the quiet work of diplomats building friendships, the skill of our financiers and businessmen in making our economy strong, and the courage of our Armed Forces in deterring and when necessary overcoming threats.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is an example of this lesson.  With our partners in NATO/ISAF and the ANSF we have been more successful than many, regrettably, recognise.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have recently returned from a visit there and, I can tell you, we are meeting the tasks laid on us.  Over the past decade we have:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	closed Al Qaeda’s bolthole ;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	helped underpin a more stable government;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	overseen elections;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	trained an Army and police force;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	and put a country that suffered 30-years of war into a position where industry, education and the rule of law are beginning to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;True, there is a long way to go.  The presidential elections in 2014 will be hugely important.  But we are heading in the right direction and we have proved what can be done with the right resources and with the right support.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I look forward to 2013 seeing us increasingly transition to an Afghan lead as we move from mentoring battalions to supporting brigades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Afghan Army now enjoys the support and trust of 84 percent of the country, only 3 percent less than the British Army in this country.  That is a fantastic achievement, by them and ISAF.  It recognises the integral part they are playing in turning the destiny of a country away from violence and onto a path of peace.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am proud of what our Service men and women have achieved in Afghanistan.  Alongside partners in DFID and the Foreign Office we have given Afghans a chance they couldn’t have dreamt of only a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our operation in Afghanistan does not stand alone.  It is linked to Pakistan and India and the wider region.  In my recent trip to Islamabad, a city I have got to know well, I was very encouraged by the helpful attitude of civilian and military leaders to reconciling the Taliban.  The Taliban, like us, are focussed on Afghanistan’s presidential poll and the end of our combat operations in 2014.  They know that the window of opportunity to play a role in their country’s future is closing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every day the Afghan Army and Police grow in capability and legitimacy.  Every day the government is better able to serve its people and thus better able to marginalise the Taliban.  Now, surely, the time is ripe to take risk in order to find that elusive political solution 10 years of military effort and sacrifice has sought to create the conditions for?  But in order to pull this off, it is vital that Afghan confidence in the West’s long-term commitment to their country is retained.  Why, should this be lost, would they stay the course themselves let alone fight to protect us in 2014 when, absent successful reconciliation, we will be at our most vulnerable?  And why should the Taliban reconcile, if they thought we were ‘cutting and running’?  Retaining Afghan confidence is the campaign’s centre of gravity.  And for the UK, retaining our influence and status within NATO and amongst key allies, is another reason for getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While achieving our goals in Afghanistan, British Armed Forces have been active elsewhere around the world.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Libya we fought in support of a people who wanted to be free from tyranny.  We joined allies from around the world built around a NATO core.  Together, we supplied the air force and the navy.  The people themselves were the army.  They made the change happen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the seas off Somalia we are playing our part in an operation that is controlling the spread of piracy.  Alongside navies from around the world, including Pakistan, India and China, reinforcing the benefit of cooperation.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Closer to home we have also been proud to play our part in HM the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations.  And my fellow Chiefs and I were delighted to receive so many letters of support for the actions of our Regular and Reserve Service men and women during the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It reminded all of us in uniform of the level of support that we enjoy amongst the people of this country.  We are very grateful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this has happened as we have been going through reforms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past two years we have implemented some of the most radical changes to the Ministry of Defence and to the Armed Forces in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SDSR shrank the size of the Armed Forces and changed the governance of the department.  And whilst we are aware that the Autumn Statement has further implications, a balanced budget means we can start from a firm base and better demonstrate what is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new Armed Forces Committee mandates the Chiefs to resolve problems in the interests of Defence as a whole.  It exploits collective military judgment and balances single service requirements in private allowing the CDS to go to the Defence Board with the underpinning authority of a combined Joint service view.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AFC, the Defence Strategy Group chaired jointly by John Thomson the PUS and me, and the new style Defence Board chaired by Philip Hammond enable the MOD to be more agile and decisive in responding at the strategic level to developing threats and trends.  The world is not a safe place.  Some threats to our interests and allies are long term but some are very present.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The immediate danger of the collapse of the Syrian regime is one.  We will support our allies in the region and would all like to see a diplomatic solution but cannot afford to remove options from the table at this stage.  Should chemical weapons be used or proliferate, both President Obama and Prime Minister Cameron have made it clear that a line would have been crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And Syria is linked to Iran.  The regime is backed by Tehran so the fall of Assad’s dictatorship will impact the Iranian government.  What that means for the stability of the region is as yet unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my recent trip to the Manama Dialogue I was struck by the issues that came up.  Our host, Crown Prince Salman of Bahrain, emphasised the threat of nuclear proliferation.  North Korea’s missile test last week aggravates this risk. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kenyan and Ugandan armed forces have been exemplary in bringing order to Somalia but this has not been without cost.  Both have sustained losses, and the retaliation of terrorist groups has endangered Kampala, Nairobi and the Kenyan coast.  We must continue to support both countries, as well as the fledgling Somali government. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To the west, Mali is a major cause for concern.  As still is Yemen, despite President Hadi’s laudable efforts. 
So What?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now reducing these short and long term threats, our task is to evolve a force capable of meeting, with allies, various complex tasks.  By the early 2020s, these plans result in a powerful Joint force that, on the basis of a balanced budget from Planning Round 12, should be able to meet the requirements laid on it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has not been easy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the Secretary of State, building on the work of the SDSR, has ensured that the department is able to squeeze the most from the resources available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2020 we will have kit that many of my fellow NATO Chiefs of Defence, saddled with much more sclerotic budgets than we, are envious of:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	A World Class Carrier Capability with the JSF – Lightning II – on board;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	Type 45 destroyers on patrol;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	Type 26 frigates in production;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	Astute class submarines;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	Chinook Mk 6 bringing the total Chinook fleet to 60;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;f.	Typhoon Tranche 3, as well as the Lightning II;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;g.	Atlas and Voyager air transport and air-to-air refuelling aircraft, underpinned by our now larger C17 fleet;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;h.	Scout vehicles, upgraded Warrior, Challenger, and Apache to give the Army better reconnaissance, mobility and firepower;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i.	Rivet Joint and other critical ISTAR platforms that will ensure we have better situational awareness than ever.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;j.	And much more emphasis on Cyber, to which I will return shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But our most decisive asset will remain our Service men and women.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the private sector puts it, we must look after the ‘talent’. As I see equipment around the world parked with no-one to operate it. Great equipment without talented people counts for little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must ensure our people have the intelligence and confidence to treat the unexpected as an opportunity to exploit.  They must be capable of informed, independent action; of what has been described as a ‘brains-based approach’ to operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have all heard the common refrain that we must do more with less.  Well, to be frank, that is what we are doing.  At the strategic level, a brains-based approach means deciding to act only when we must and then doing it well, not always kinetically.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This type of thinking has shaped the work I have started on ‘How We Will Fight’.  Assuming the approach I have just outlined, I and my fellow Chiefs have designed our forces to:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	act jointly and with allies, but able to act alone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	be well equipped, but not tied to platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	adapt as the environment changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But we must prioritise.  And as spending has tightened, we must be ruthless in our requirements and getting the most from them.  Effectively targeting limited resources is, in large part, the art of military command in war and in peace through force design.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new UK Joint Expeditionary Force is an expression of this.  The JEF promises much greater levels of integration than previously achieved especially when combined with others, as is already happening with our French allies in the Anglo/French Combined JEF.  The JEF must be genuinely synergistic.  It is the building block to future alliances and independent action.  And we would hope that allies such as Denmark and Estonia, who have fought with distinction in a British formation in Afghanistan, will want to play key roles within the British element of the CJEF.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What it offers is clear: an integrated joint force with capabilities across the spectrum at sea, on land and in the air.  A force that can confidently be allocated a specific slice of the battle space in an allied operation or act alone.  It will be the basis of all our combined joint training.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the capability to ‘punch’ hard and not be a logistical or tactical drag on a coalition, we will be especially welcomed by our friends and feared by our enemies. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF will be of variable size; a framework into which others fit.  It will be the core of the UK’s contribution to any military action, whether NATO, coalition or independent. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together with critical C2 elements such as HQ ARRC and the emphasis placed on the maritime component HQ at Northwood, the JEF is designed to meet our NATO obligations. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Libyan campaign, Jordan, Qatar and the United Arab Emirates were able to play a vital role by bringing their regional expertise into the command structure of a NATO operation.  This provided greater military and political reach.  I look forward to the alliance, perhaps in part through the vehicle of the JEF, working more with non-member states.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Britain’s JEF will be capable of projecting power with global effect and influence.  Nowhere is more important to us than our friends in the Middle East and Gulf and in line with clear political intent we would expect, with other initiatives, for JEF elements to spend more time reassuring and deterring in that region. 
The Royal Navy&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me briefly examine how the How We Fight work affects the single services, starting with the Royal Navy.  As the Prime Minister has put it, the Navy “keeps the arteries of trade of the global economy from hardening.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy will continue to grow in importance.  As our carrier capability comes into service it will be a key part of our diplomatic, humanitarian and military strategy.  Prepared to overcome the toughest military challenges.  This is its raison d’être.  But I know it will be used for much more.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Americans demonstrated through their deployment to Aceh and Haiti that aircraft carriers have huge strategic impact supporting people around the world.  Seeing US military personnel, ships and helicopters playing such a critical role boosted the standing of the US in the world’s most populous Islamic country and undermined extremist rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard power is an essential element of soft power.  In this respect especially, numbers, or mass, still matter.  We must resolve the conundrum at the heart of Bob Gates quip about ‘exquisite technology’.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the future, the Chief of the Naval Staff and I have a vision for a Navy which procures ships differently allowing us to have more, not fewer platforms. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must resist the pressure that has shrunk the number of platforms.  Clearly that will mean rethinking the Navy, including examining the case for ships that may have a limited role in general war.  But this is not new ¬¬¬– remember the corvette over the ages – and is similar to the utility of light and heavy land forces, tailored to task.  And in so doing we will ensure seamanship skills and leadership qualities, so much in demand by our friends and allies, flourish into the long term.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy’s maritime and amphibious components, with 3 Commando Brigade Royal Marines at the core of the latter, will be at the heart of Britain’s JEF.  As the concept develops we will look to acquire ships that range from top-end war fighting elements through potentially to more vessels tailored to discrete but important tasks, to be deployed on a range of routine non-warfighting duties.&lt;br&gt;
The British Army&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army too is changing.  Once we come out of the combat role in Afghanistan at the end of 2014, it will cease to be on permanent rotation with the burdens that imposes.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army will maintain a hard power war-fighting capability while creating the strategic influence, support and engagement ability essential to modern operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the Navy, these land forces must be equipped to pack a punch but war fighting is not all they’re for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conflict prevention, to which I will return in a moment, is not just sensible strategy; it is a military operation requiring appropriately configured and equipped forces. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army 2020 reforms are a fundamental re-set for the Army, making the best of a regular force a fifth smaller than when I commanded it only three years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we will retain three high-readiness manoeuvre brigades, we will also have ‘adaptable brigades’ to sustain enduring operations and routinely develop partnerships and knowledge around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though more conceptual work is needed, given the importance of the region and clear Prime Ministerial intent, I envisage two or more adaptable brigades forming close tactical level relationships with particular countries in the Gulf and Jordan, for example, allowing for better cooperation with their forces.  Should the need arise for another Libya-style operation, we will be prepared.  This would greatly enhance our ability to support allies as they contain and deter threats and, with our naval presence in Bahrain, air elements in the UAE and Qatar, and traditional but potentially enhanced roles in Oman, Kuwait and Saudi Arabia, would make us a regional ally across the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Africa, brigades would be tasked to support key allies in the east, west and south whilst another might be given an Indian Ocean and SE Asian focus, allowing for much greater involvement in the FPDA, for example. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we are to influence, we must know what drives our friends and how to motivate them.  This is not something that can be done on the eve of an operation.  As these adaptable brigades develop links with countries around their region, this will create opportunities for soldiers and officers to progress their careers through linguistic and cultural specialism.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Defence Engagement Strategy, prepared with the Foreign Office, will provide what I have often referred to as a ‘strategic handrail’ for engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will require tough decisions.  If we are to invest properly in some relationships, others will naturally get less attention.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if we get this right ¬– and we will – we will have deeper links to specific regional partners giving them the confidence to deal with their own problems and, when appropriate, to act in partnership with us.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I have described puts military flesh on the bones of welcome, NSC endorsed, national strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all comes as we are increasing the Reserves and integrating them closer with the Regular forces.  This will do more to increase our own capacity and ability to help friends and allies.
The Royal Air Force&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turning now to the Royal Air Force.  The rate of technological advance is most keenly felt on air platforms.  This is understandable.  These are complex fully networked combat and ISTAR platforms.  This intelligence cuts the time between understanding and reacting.  It allows us better to out-think and out-act our opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, lift, both tactical and global, reduces the number of reserves we need to keep, giving the Armed Forces a flexibility that was unimaginable just a few decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding and exploiting the opportunities technology presents will be decisive in maintaining our advantage – in sufficient numbers – into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remotely piloted air systems and novel anti-air defences have changed our understanding of both what it means to fight and defend.  We must not allow sacred cows – such as the indispensability of on-board pilots – to rule the day.  The Chief of the Air Staff is leading the change.  By giving ‘wings’ to UAV pilots the Royal Air Force is recognising the capability of the platform and skill of the pilot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is a reflection of how early we are in this process of transition that we still refer to remotely-piloted air systems or unmanned aerial vehicles.  How long was it before we stopped referring to the horseless carriage?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all three Services, their role within an integrated CJEF will be the driving force in their force development and training.  Whoever the enemy, wherever the threat, we will need partners.  Building them now is an investment in our own future and our capacity to succeed quickly should war break out.
Cyber&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is a new environment within which we must learn to manoeuvre with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today Facebook, with around a billion users, is the third most populous country in the world.  It exemplifies one of the most extreme changes we have seen in the past decades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberspace is the nervous system of our global economy.  We are reliant on the internet and other networked systems for every aspect of our lives.  It allows bewildering speed of action and global reach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, just as crime has become e-crime, spying has increasingly become cyber espionage.  We have seen nations, their proxies and non-state actors use this new space for terrorism and conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though not conventional assaults, the hostile cyber attacks on Estonia in 2007, Georgia in 2008 and Burma in 2010 were damaging.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, there have been unprecedented levels of cyber attack over the past 24 months.  Israel has reported over 44 million attempts to disrupt its government websites during recent tension around the Gaza strip.  STUXNET demonstrated a new class of threat aimed at process control systems at the heart of modern infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without doubt, actions in cyberspace will form part of any future conflict.  Communication and the control of infrastructure and systems has become a new environment through which combatants will further their objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our immediate priority must be to ensure our networks are secure and defensible, working with partners in industry and around the country to drive up standards and ensure we have robust protocols in place.  This builds on the excellent work done under the National Cyber Security Strategy but Defence has particular challenges as a department, as Armed Forces and through the contractors and partners with whom we work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am determined that the Armed Forces should understand cyberspace, and how it will shape future conflict, as instinctively as we understand maritime, land and air operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will mean changes in the way we operate: new doctrine; new capabilities; new structures, with Joint Forces Command at their heart.
It will mean a new approach to growing and developing the talent we need to operate in this new, electronic, environment.  Like our Secretary of State, I see an important role for reserves in this domain. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="winding-up"&gt;Winding Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In examining each environment separately I hope I have highlighted some of the key issues on the Chiefs’ plate and how we must respond to them.  But the most important is developing an integrated Joint model.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF is neither the 1980s Canadian model nor, whilst there are some apparent similarities, is it a British version of the US Marine Corps.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of the UK armed forces relies heavily on the different skill-sets and ethos of each single Service.  Each adapted for its environment, and evolving as times and technology change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But a joint conceptual approach, based on lessons from the real world, embedded through force development, in training, on operations and though the cohering glue of modern C3I and cyber is vital to delivering the military capability the nation requires.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is about ensuring single Service skills meld into joint action so that the whole is greater than the sum of the parts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF won’t mean we can do more with less; it will mean, through the synergy it provides, that we get the most from what we have.  And doubtless there will be some roles that we continue to leave to others, notably the USA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I close let me draw some lessons from my 41 years in uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some constants which may seem obvious in this room but are often over looked:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	The need for military force to influence, secure and protect is as great as ever.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	I joined an Army that was geared to defend Britain by fighting in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	Today life is more complex but the principle is the same.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	9/11, and the 7/7 bombings in London show that we cannot choose our battlefields as we once did.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	The world is not a safer place and the distinction between home and abroad is strategically obsolete.  Today it is part of a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We cannot just stand by and hope we are ignored and danger passes us by.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the Foreign Secretary said in September last year: “the country that is purely reactive in foreign affairs is in decline”. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responses may be based on either soft or hard power, but to divorce the two is strategic blindness.  Soft power is not a substitute for strength.  On the contrary, it is often based on the credible threat of force, either to support a friend or deter an enemy.  Hard power and soft power are intertwined.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is not enough to provide aid or speak kindly.  Our friends want to know we are there when it counts, not just fair-weather friends.  This is the confidence hard power brings.  It drives equipment sales and thus industrial growth, as well as diplomatic treaties, just as it has for centuries.  But hard power also does more than this: it dissuades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deterrence doctrine has fallen out of fashion so perhaps you will allow me to recall some of the elements.  Sun Tzu’s famous maxim is: “Supreme excellence consists in breaking the enemy’s resistance without fighting”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Too often this is seen as clever posturing on the eve of battle.  It is not.  Training, equipping and partnering with allies enhance the aura of British power.  They give us presence on the world stage and ensure that we are not tested.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is worth being clear: when the Armed Forces train we do not just do it to be ready, we do it to be seen to be ready.  When we succeed on operations, we do not just win a battle.  We prove that we can win a war.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a very real sense, everything the Armed Forces do deters and reassures.  With enough numbers, enough equipment and with good leaders at every level, Britain is a credible threat to our enemies and a reassuring friend to our allies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is cheaper than fighting and more credible than talk.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading the record of how the Soviets saw the Falklands War demonstrates this admirably.  What many saw as post-colonial folie de grandeur, the Soviet leadership, rightly, saw as proof that the British Armed Forces were united with their government and people – Clausewitz’s famous trilogy – and more than a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was far from the only factor, but the increase in Soviet defence spending in the 1980s which ended up contributing to the collapse of the Warsaw Pact was partly due to clarity of their failure to impose their will in neighbouring, occupied countries while Britain could liberate territory some 8,000 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Chief of the Defence Staff I do not wear the burdens of office any more lightly than my predecessors.  I have set out some of my concerns for the coming years and some of the ways we will think and act to meet them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the Prime Minister’s chairmanship, The National Security Council, on which I am privileged to sit, considers all the big strategic issues that I have listed and more.  It is a hugely welcome addition to Whitehall, directing and bringing clarity to national strategy and coordinating cross-government action. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the nature of the world is such that what will later seem obvious, today is opaque and unpredictable.  How will Europe emerge from the Euro crisis?  How will the Arab Spring conclude?  How will global warming affect water supplies?  And what of cyber?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After all, grand strategy, while providing a guide to action in peacetime, is also about being prepared and balanced for what we can never know.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ensuring we have enough left in the bag while actively deterring, and when required defeating, aggression against us and our friends, enough left to succeed against those ‘unknown unknowns’, is ultimately what I and my fellow Chiefs are paid for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;END&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56611</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-welcomes-new-counter-terrorism-centre-in-uae"/>
    <title>UK welcomes new counter terrorism centre in UAE</title>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has welcomed the opening of a Centre of Excellence on Countering Violent Extremism in Abu Dhabi.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the broad experience and expertise of the 30 Global Counter-Terrorism Forum (GCTF) founding member nations, the Centre will lead global research on the drivers of terrorism, deliver training to address these, and identify practical, operational initiatives to reduce the threat from terrorism. It was launched at the third ministerial meeting of the GCTF in the United Arab Emirates (UAE), which was attended by representatives from all member nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tunisia, where he is on an official visit, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s launch in Abu Dhabi of the Centre of Excellence for Countering Violent Extremism (CVE) is an important milestone in the global fight against terrorism. In particular I welcome the leadership that His Excellency Foreign Minister Abdullah bin Zayed has shown and the Emirati commitment to host the Centre and make it a reality. The UK will continue to give it our full support. We have nominated an expert to serve as a Member of the International Steering Board and are seconding a Director of Training &amp;amp; Capacity-Building into the Centre’s senior management team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to do our utmost to tackle the root causes of terrorism by ensuring a collaborative international approach to the common threat of terrorism. The Global Counter Terrorism Forum offers us an excellent platform from which to address this constantly changing challenge, drawing on the expertise and experience of its members”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thegctf.org/web/guest/about" title="Global Counter-Terrorism Forum"&gt;Global Counter-Terrorism Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56641</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:36:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-more-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet more Millies heroes</title>
    <summary>Last week, The Sun honoured courageous Service personnel at their Military Awards. Here we bring you interviews with two more winners.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-1---operation-olympics"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 1 - Operation Olympics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympians Victoria Pendleton and Greg Rutherford presented the first of two Judges’ Special Recognition Awards to the Armed Forces for their contribution to the London 2012 Olympics. At its height, more than 17,500 personnel stepped in when G4S were not able to provide sufficient guards for all the venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victoria said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone I’ve met has been incredible; individuals who’ve achieved so much. I feel in awe because all I did was ride round in circles on a wooden track with a bike with no brakes and one gear and this is real life. I can’t not be moved and it makes me feel very proud to be British.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear the military personnel treasured their experiences. Senior Aircraftwoman Afyah Bubb, an RAF medic who volunteered to be part of the security team at the Olympic Park, saw it as a ‘once-in-a-lifetime opportunity’. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were there to do a job but I unexpectedly got the chance to see Ellie Simmonds break some swimming records which was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Brian Fahy added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were really proud to be part of the Games this summer and see the superb performance of our athletes. Who wouldn’t want to be part of the greatest show in town?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic long jump gold medallist Greg Rutherford said backstage: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m hugely proud of the Armed Forces; the whole evening has been a massive highlight and getting involved feels out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5637/award_for_headley_court.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team with their Special Recognition Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a light-hearted moment, Greg joked that he hadn’t packed enough tissues. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I get emotional so easily and seeing videos of these incredible people moves me to tears every time. It’s completely surreal to be here; I’ve got friends in the Armed Forces including my best friend who is now going through training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to be invited to such a prestigious night, and to show our respect and thanks to these guys is an honour. The troops came in with happy smiley faces and gave high fives and absolutely saved the day! A huge thank you, you were absolutely spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-2---complex-trauma-team-headley-court"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 2 - Complex Trauma Team, Headley Court&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second Judges’ Special Recognition Award honoured the Complex Trauma Team at the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/Militarymedicine/Pages/HeadleyCourt.aspx" title="Headley Court"&gt;Headley Court&lt;/a&gt;. It is the remarkable skill and dedication of the 110-strong Trauma Team that help many critically wounded soldiers overcome life-changing injuries so they can get back to leading active lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex trauma manager Anne Brannagan received the award on behalf of Headley Court from actor Kevin Spacey who congratulated and shook hands with each of the 10 team members on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Clare Walton, Commanding Officer at Headley Court, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kevin Spacey was just very complimentary, it was great, and to have someone of his level of superstardom even know who we are is lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony tonight (14 December) on ITV1 at 2100hrs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56576</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:51:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:51:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-police-launch-defence-road-safety-week-road-show"/>
    <title>MOD Police launch Defence Road Safety Week Road Show</title>
    <summary>MOD police officers are aiming to drive up awareness about road safety by travelling more than 1,000 miles (1,600km) across the UK this week visiting defence communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of Defence Road Safety Week a Ministry of Defence Police (MDP) Road Show will take a mobile police station to different MOD establishments under the banner of its Home Front Community Safety Partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiative supports National Road Safety Week, promoted by Brake, the road safety charity, and both events run from Monday 21 November to Sunday 27 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDP Community Safety Manager for the North East, Sergeant Gavin Alcroft, who is managing the initiative for the MDP, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This will be the sixth year we have carried out a national road show event. We provide information on road safety but we also have equipment on board that allows us to carry out interactive activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We show high impact road safety films and we encourage visitors to take a Highway Code quiz with the chance to win a goody bag!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The national theme of Road Safety Week 2011 is ‘Too Young to Die’ and it focuses on the fact that road crashes are sudden, violent events that can rip families apart by ending lives too soon and causing life-changing injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of those affected are young and these casualties send shock waves through families and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDP Community Safety Manager for Scotland, Sergeant George Smart, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These casualties are preventable as they are often caused by factors such as driving too fast, overtaking dangerously, driving while using a mobile, driving whilst over the limit, drug driving, driving when tired or failing to use a seat belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest official figures show that there were 1,850 road casualties in the UK overall in 2010 - a reduction of 17 per cent on 2009. Within the MOD, road casualty trends and statistics are down too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="PC Colin Everett helps get the road safety message across at RAF Wittering" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5612/MOD_Police_launch_Defence_Road_Safety_Week_Road_Show_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;PC Colin Everett helps get the road safety message across at RAF Wittering [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, 37 military personnel were killed in on and off duty road traffic incidents. The statistics show that Armed Services personnel are twice as likely to be killed in a road traffic incident as their civilian counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Moate, of the Defence Road Safety Team, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the first six months of 2011, six out of the ten MOD fatalities recorded were of personnel riding motorcycles. These statistics cover any MOD employee killed as a result of a road traffic accident, irrespective of circumstance, and include passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everything that we can do to help lower this figure through extra training and workshops, using the support of local authorities and the police, is time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDP have Community Police Officers and Community Safety Officers stationed across the country who can be contacted for information on road safety activities and initiatives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to remain focused on raising awareness of road safety and promoting safer driving across the Defence Estate,” said Sergeant Alcroft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are keen to target attitudes to driving and road use - on and off duty - for military personnel, particularly the younger element, as well as raising awareness in Service families of those important safety messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although the national theme is important, we are also mindful of local issues and problems. Where these are identified, they are targeted by our local officers, so please approach them if you have concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road show is scheduled to carry out visits to the Defence Munitions centres at Beith and Longtown, MOD St Athan, the Atomic Weapons Establishment at Aldermaston and HM Naval Base Clyde - covering defence communities in Scotland, England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
