<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/national-security</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/national-security.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "National security"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-02T10:31:30+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56526</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T10:31:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T10:31:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation"/>
    <title>Countering weapons proliferation </title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Securing global safety by preventing countries and terrorists access to the materials needed for weapons of mass destruction.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of weapons of mass destruction (&lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;) poses a threat to the UK and the international community. Indiscriminate trade in conventional arms and the use of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear (&lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt;) weapons and ballistic missiles raises serious humanitarian and security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working around the world to champion and implement UK policies as set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the spread of &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; weapons and ballistic missiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK works with international partners and through organisations such as the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, G8, NATO and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce terrorists’ ability to create, obtain or use &lt;abbr title="chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear"&gt;CBRN&lt;/abbr&gt; materials and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the FCO’s tools to combat these threats is our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/counter-proliferation-programme"&gt;Counter-Proliferation Programme&lt;/a&gt;. In the financial year 2012 to 13, the value of the programme is £3 million. This funding is used to support projects around the world which increase political will or technical capacity to reduce the threat of weapons proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-counter-proliferation-strategy"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-counter-proliferation-strategy-2012-2015"&gt;National Counter-Proliferation Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in March 2012. The strategy’s main aims are to deny terrorists the materials and expertise to make and use &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;; to stop countries such as Iran and North Korea from obtaining &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt; or advanced conventional weapons; and to build up the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/About/"&gt;International Atomic Energy Agency (&lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; and other organisations and treaties that help us meet our goals through the international community and which help to protect global security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chemical-weapons"&gt;Chemical weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK supports the destruction of remaining chemical weapons stocks and works to encourage full national implementation of the Chemical Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;) by all countries. The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/the-chemical-weapons-convention"&gt;Chemical Weapons Convention&lt;/a&gt; bans the development, production, stockpiling and use of chemical weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biological-weapons"&gt;Biological weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has signed up to the global implementation of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/04FBBDD6315AC720C1257180004B1B2F?OpenDocument"&gt;Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention (&lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of the convention is to help prevent states acquiring or keeping biological and toxin weapons, and prevent them ever being used by states or terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Biological and Toxin Weapons Convention"&gt;BTWC&lt;/abbr&gt; doesn’t have a verification system like that of the &lt;abbr title="Chemical Weapons Convention"&gt;CWC&lt;/abbr&gt;. Participating countries are required to submit relevant data and declarations, or confidence-building measures, to the United Nations Office for Disarmament Affairs. This increases openness and gives participating countries confidence that others are complying with the convention. The UK’s confidence building measures are published on the the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.unog.ch/80256EE600585943/%28httpPages%29/CEC2E2D361ADFEE7C12572BC0032F058?OpenDocument"&gt;Implementation Support Unit website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nuclear-weapons"&gt;Nuclear weapons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-towards-nuclear-disarmament"&gt;working towards nuclear disarmament&lt;/a&gt;. The UK is one of 189 states that have signed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/supporting-pages/nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty"&gt;Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. The treaty aims to stop the spread of nuclear weapons and ultimately eliminate them. The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; has three equally important ‘pillars’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to work towards non-proliferation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to champion nuclear disarmament &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="nuclear-security"&gt;Nuclear security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK will continue work to strengthen international nuclear security including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;securing fissile material in Kazakhstan, in a joint project with the US &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to build a central store for spent radioactive sources in Ukraine  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to create new jobs for 3,000 former weapons scientists in Russia and other former Soviet Union countries  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;assisting many other countries through our collaboration with the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; on its Nuclear Security Fund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will continue to offer funding and expertise for physical nuclear security upgrades and help support the strongest possible security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are supporting the full implementation of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/N04/328/43/PDF/N0432843.pdf?OpenElement"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Resolution 1540&lt;/a&gt;, which requires all states to refrain from supporting non-government agents from developing, acquiring, manufacturing, possessing, transporting, transferring or using nuclear, chemical or biological weapons and their delivery systems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="state-programmes"&gt;State programmes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the international legal framework, conventions and treaties, some countries have active programmes to develop and produce &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. Of particular concern is Iran’s nuclear programme; the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea’s nuclear programme and willingness to provide weapons to other countries; and Syria’s possession of chemical and biological weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK works through various international organisations to seek peaceful means to reduce the threat from these programmes and the networks that support them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="arms-trade-treaty"&gt;Arms Trade Treaty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a legitimate arms trade, there is also an urgent need for more effective and coherent international regulation of that trade. The UK is working to achieve an international arms trade treaty to provide clearer and more effective control of the illegal arms trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; conference in July 2012 was unable to adopt an Arms Trade Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;). However, the UK will continue to play a leading role in future negotiations to help to secure one. An &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to reduce the flow of weapons from legitimate trade to the illicit market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; process towards an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt; and submissions from states (including the UK’s views on an &lt;abbr title="Arms Trade Treaty"&gt;ATT&lt;/abbr&gt;) are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/first/63/documentation.shtml"&gt;United Nations General Assembly website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="export-licensing"&gt;Export licensing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has joined other governments around the world to pursue &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/3849543/eu-arms-export"&gt;collective implementation of export controls&lt;/a&gt; to prevent the proliferation of &lt;abbr title="weapons of mass destruction"&gt;WMD&lt;/abbr&gt;. The 4 main export control regimes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mtcr.info/english/index.html"&gt;Missile Technology Control Regime&lt;/a&gt;, which controls the proliferation of missile systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/Leng/default.htm"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt;, which controls the supply of nuclear related technologies and materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.australiagroup.net/en/index.html"&gt;Australia Group&lt;/a&gt;, which seeks to ensure that exports do not contribute to the development of chemical or biological weapons &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt;, which promotes greater responsibility in transfers of conventional arms and dual-use goods and technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read further details about the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/international-non-proliferation-and-arms-control-regimes"&gt;international non-proliferation and arms control regimes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s regulatory authority responsible for assessing and issuing strategic export licences to UK exporters is the Export Control Organisation (ECO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS). Read more about the UK’s policies and procedures for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/controlling-defence-security-and-dual-use-strategic-exports--2"&gt;controlling defence, security and dual-use strategic exports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (&lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;) was borne out of fear that the Cold War era would lead to a nuclear arms race and is still the basis of the international nuclear non-proliferation regime. All states are now party to it apart from India, Israel, Pakistan and South Sudan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt; provides for a Review Conference every 5 years, both to review developments over the previous 5 years and to look ahead to the future. At the last &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/conf/npt/2010/"&gt;Review Conference in 2010&lt;/a&gt; a series of action plans were agreed to enhance implementation of the treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iaea.org/"&gt;The International Atomic Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt; was set up as the world’s ‘Atoms for Peace’ organisation in 1957 within the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; family, and supports the &lt;abbr title="Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty"&gt;NPT&lt;/abbr&gt;. The agency is at the centre of international efforts to address Iran’s nuclear dossier and to ensure the benefits of safe and secure peaceful nuclear energy are accessible to everyone, not just to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thenuclearsecuritysummit.org/eng_main/main.jsp"&gt;Seoul Nuclear Security Summit&lt;/a&gt; assembled 53 countries, the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, the &lt;abbr title="International Atomic Energy Agency"&gt;IAEA&lt;/abbr&gt; and Interpol, to continue work to secure vulnerable nuclear material around the world within 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 24 December 2008 in the &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; General Assembly, 133 States voted in favour of a draft resolution ‘Towards an Arms Trade Treaty’. There was a clear majority view that, working together, the international community can shape an Arms Trade Treaty into an effective legally binding mechanism to regulate the international trade in arms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our detailed guides on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/sanctions-embargoes-and-restrictions"&gt;Sanctions, embargoes and restrictions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/current-arms-embargoes-and-other-restrictions"&gt;Current arms embargoes and other restrictions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the Common Foreign and Security Policy (&lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt;), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; applies restrictive measures in pursuit of the specific &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; objectives set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/treaties/index.htm"&gt;Treaty on European Union&lt;/a&gt; (see particularly Article 11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; External Action website&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of restrictive measures adopted in the framework of the &lt;abbr title="Common Foreign and Security Policy"&gt;CFSP&lt;/abbr&gt; that are currently in force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/sc/committees/list_compend.shtml"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council Sanctions Committees website&lt;/a&gt; contains links to the latest versions of all &lt;abbr title="United Nations"&gt;UN&lt;/abbr&gt; Security Council targeted sanctions lists. The individuals and entities included in these lists are subject to the relevant measures imposed by the Security Council, and all member states are obliged to implement these measures. Each separate list is maintained by the relevant Security Council Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60956</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"/>
    <title>Ministerial statement on UN sanctions against the M23, FDLR, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Legerero</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for Africa comments on vote agreeing sanctions against groups and individuals involved in the conflict in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds MP, the UK Minister for Africa, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome today’s agreement by the UN Security Council Sanctions Committee to add the Congolese rebel group, M23, to its list of sanctioned organisations and individuals. The Committee also agreed the listings of two M23 leaders, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Lugerero, as well as of the militia group Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR). The UK supports these measures as part of the international community’s response to the crisis in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). We remain committed to finding long term solutions which will end the cycle of violence in the DRC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops, that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR. It is also important that the DRC Government shows leadership in addressing the underlying causes of conflict in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, with its partners, will continue to seek ways to support the building of a sustainable peace in eastern DRC.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/60314</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:23:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:23:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/establishing-stability-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Establishing stability in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>How the UK is helping Afghanistan to become a more secure nation with international support. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in Afghanistan for one overriding reason - to protect our national security by helping the Afghans take control of their own. We are helping Afghanistan develop the ability to maintain its own security and prevent the return of international terrorists, such as al Qaeda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, Afghanistan is supported by a range of international partners to develop its security, governance, infrastructure, economy and ability to provide essential services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is a top UK foreign policy priority and it is our defence main effort. We are one of more than 60 countries helping the Afghan Government establish the conditions to be able to protect its citizens, provide for their basic needs and determine the country’s future, eventually without significant help from the international community. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinafghanistan.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Embassy in the capital Kabul&lt;/a&gt; provides a focus for the UK’s work in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="military-support"&gt;Military support&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s military activities in Afghanistan are conducted under a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/1974%282011%29"&gt;UN Mandate&lt;/a&gt; as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/"&gt;International Security Assistance Force (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. We are the second largest contributor to this coalition of 50 nations and the majority of our armed forces in Afghanistan operate in the southern province of Helmand. &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; conducts operations alongside the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;), mainly the Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training the Afghan Army and Police so that they are capable of independent operations and can protect the population and provide a basic civilian policing service, will be crucial to ensure Afghanistan’s long-term stability and prevent terrorists from finding a safe haven there. As well as carrying out combat operations, &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; provides training, mentoring, advice and support to the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-transfer-of-responsibility-for-security-to-afghanistan-by-2014"&gt;The transfer of responsibility for security to Afghanistan by 2014&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shared aim of President Karzai and the members of the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; is that the transfer of responsibility for security to the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; is completed across the whole country by the end of 2014, when the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; mission is due to end.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature and size of the UK’s presence in Afghanistan is changing. President Karzai and &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; members have agreed to this process of change - known as ‘Transition’ - whereby full responsibility for security and governance is taken on by the Afghans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transition has already started in large areas of Afghanistan, including Helmand Province. Over three-quarters of Afghanistan’s population now live in these areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, established in 2002, is made up of the Afghan National Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;), the Afghan Air Force (AAF) and the Afghan National Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;). These groups are mentored and trained by &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces and other specialists from the international community, for example British Police Officers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; are growing in size and capability. By 2013 we expect them to be approximately 352,000 strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; now leads 80% of conventional operations and carries out 90% of its training. As its capability grows it is increasingly taking responsibility for more specialist tasks such as dealing with Improvised Explosive Devices (roadside bombs) and route clearance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015 &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; will start a new, and smaller, non-combat mission in Afghanistan based on training, assisting and advising the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;. This will take place alongside international community activities that will continue to support Afghanistan’s development in other areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK support for Afghanistan’s long-term development beyond 2014 was confirmed in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-enduring-strategic-partnership-document-between-the-uk-and-afghanistan"&gt;Enduring Strategic Partnership&lt;/a&gt; agreement signed by the Prime Minister and President Karzai of Afghanistan in January 2012. It reaffirmed both countries’ commitment to a continuing partnership and friendship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the agreements made at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/official_texts_87595.htm"&gt;Chicago Summit&lt;/a&gt; in May 2012 the UK will contribute £70 million per year from 2015 to 2017 for the development of the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Police"&gt;ANP&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our Armed Forces will be involved in supporting the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; through a new Afghan National Army Officer Academy in Kabul. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="economic-and-social-projects"&gt;Economic and social projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are helping Afghanistan to become a more viable state that can increasingly meet its population’s needs from its own resources. This work includes support for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://projects.dfid.gov.uk/project.aspx?Project=201023"&gt;economic and social development&lt;/a&gt; and helping the Afghan Government implement its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/afghanistan-ministry-of-counter-narcotics-national-drug-control-strategy"&gt;National Drug Control Strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK agreed to maintain our development assistance of £178 million a year until 2017 at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Tokyo-Conference-on-Afghanistan-8-July-2012/"&gt;Tokyo Conference&lt;/a&gt; in July 2012. This support will help the Afghan Government to reduce extreme poverty, create jobs and achieve long-term economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s development assistance is led by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/Where-we-work/Asia-South/Afghanistan/"&gt;Department for International Development&lt;/a&gt;. It concentrates on 3 main areas to increase stability and reduce poverty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving security and political stability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stimulating the economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping the Afghan Government deliver basic services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.stabilisationunit.gov.uk/"&gt;Stabilisation Unit&lt;/a&gt; deploys civilian experts such as police officers, prison governors, barristers and governance experts to Afghanistan to help the Afghan Government and its people in these 3 main areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan’s development into a more viable state is a long-term task that will continue to face many challenges. Our efforts are not designed to create a perfect Afghanistan but one that is able to maintain its own security and prevent the return of international terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-provincial-reconstruction-team"&gt;The Provincial Reconstruction Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.helmandprt.com/"&gt;Provincial Reconstruction Team (&lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Team"&gt;PRT&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; is a UK-led, multinational effort of the UK, US and Danish governments. It works with &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Regional Command South West, helping the Afghan Government establish improved governance and development across Helmand Province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As agreed by President Karzai and the international community, all &lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Teams"&gt;PRTs&lt;/abbr&gt; across Afghanistan will close by the end of 2014, in keeping with developing Afghan sovereignty and transition.  This includes Helmand.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the remainder of its presence in Helmand, the &lt;abbr title="Provincial Reconstruction Team"&gt;PRT&lt;/abbr&gt; will focus on supporting the Government of Afghanistan reach inclusive political settlements backed by good governance, strong rule of law and sustainable development in line with the Government of Afghanistan’s national ministry strategies, standards and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is in Afghanistan because the country had become a base for terrorists that threatened our country and the rest of the world. The Taliban government gave al Qaeda safe haven in Afghanistan and this allowed terrorists to plan and carry out attacks around the world, most notably the 9/11 atrocities in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taliban were given the opportunity to help bring the leaders of al Qaeda to account. When they refused to do so, action was taken by members of the international community to remove them from control of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The al Qaeda training camps and Taliban regime that provided them safe haven were dismantled in the months after 9/11. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="political-settlement"&gt;Political settlement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stability of Afghanistan will not be achieved by security activities alone and we are supporting Afghan efforts to achieve a political settlement that will secure peace and stability. The Prime Minister, Foreign Secretary and others are actively involved in trilateral talks with their Afghan and Pakistani counterparts. Everyone is committed to this and we have all called on the Taliban to break from al Qaeda and participate in a peace process. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60865</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-new-settlement"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister condemns new settlement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister Alistair Burt statement: the approval of new units is a 'provocative action' contrary to Fourth Geneva Convention.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the announcements on 24 December that the Jerusalem District Planning Board issued approval for 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South, and that Ariel College is to be upgraded to university status thereby creating the first university in a settlement illegal under international law, Alistair Burt, Minister for the Middle East said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last week Foreign Secretary William Hague made clear our condemnation and deep disappointment at the approval of the East Jerusalem Ramat Shlomo plan. We also condemn the Jerusalem District Planning Board’s approvals for over 3150 units in Givaat Hamatos and 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South. These are further profoundly provocative actions that run contrary to the Fourth Geneva Convention. By taking these steps, despite the international community repeatedly raising our profound concerns, the Israeli Government is damaging Israel’s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also deeply disappointed in the decision to upgrade Ariel’s university centre. Ariel is beyond the Green Line in a settlement that is illegal according to international law. This decision will deepen the presence of the settlements in the Palestinian territories and will create another obstacle to peace. We reiterate our call on Israel urgently to reverse these decisions and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I spoke with President Abbas last week I expressed our appreciation for the measured response the Palestinian Leadership had been taking in response to Israel’s recent settlement announcements.  We utterly and unreservedly condemn the recent call for a third intifada and a suicide campaign by a Hamas official. Incitements to violence and terror are unacceptable. We welcome that President Abbas has publicly rejected the recent inflammatory statements by Hamas leaders, and that he has stated clearly the position of the legitimate Palestinian Leadership which has accepted the State of Israel in 1967 borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taken together, these further settlement announcements and comments deepen our worry for the region at such a crucial time, and demonstrate why we are convinced of the urgency for more positive indicators of change. Accordingly we continue to call on President Abbas and Prime Minister Netanyahu to show the strong leadership needed to achieve a return to negotiations for a two-state solution, which will bring a just and permanent solution to this conflict.  We repeat our hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60863</id>
    <published>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-forces-mark-christmas-in-helmand"/>
    <title>British Forces mark Christmas in Helmand </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British forces in southern Afghanistan mark Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;British forces serving in southern Afghanistan have been marking Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province today (25 December).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities took place as the troops completed a full day of operational duties.  Many soldiers from the UK-led Task Force Helmand spent the day on patrol in support of the Afghan security forces, yet still most found time to open presents and ring home – and enjoy a freshly-prepared Christmas lunch with all the trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-post"&gt;Christmas post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last-minute festive cheer was provided by the Post and Courier Squadron as tonnes of mail arrived at a number of forward locations, delivered by Chinook helicopter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing last minute festive cheer on Christmas morning, 78 sacks of post (1 tonne) arrived by helicopter in Main Operating Base (&lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) Lashkar Gah – home to the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; (‘Black Rats’) headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5819/Xmas_post_delivery_helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province, Afghanistan&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a chilly Christmas morning, in &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; over 100 soldiers and civilians took part in the ‘Lash Dash’ 5km run around the base.  Many completed the course in fancy dress, with proceeds from the event split between two charities: the Lashkar Gah Orphanage and The Black Rat Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the male and female winners were Danish soldiers. The Brits fared better in the fancy dress competition with Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant’s General Corps, Royal Military Police) winning by running dressed as a well-wrapped Christmas present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5818/LashDash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant General Corps, Royal Military Police) won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="working-day"&gt;Working day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, is another working day for all military here in Helmand. As the sun rose on Christmas morning, troops from the Royal Dragoon Guards and the Royal Military Police set off on patrol to the Provincial Police Headquarters to train Afghan Police. The ‘train the trainer’ course sees Afghan Police qualifying to teach police skills. This will allow British troops to step back as the Afghan Security Forces take the lead in training their own forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-lunches-and-all-the-trimmings"&gt;Christmas lunches and all the trimmings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full Christmas lunch, including all the trimmings, was served in the cookhouses of Camp Bastion, &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; Lashkar Gah and patrol bases across Helmand. Even the troops manning the security towers or sangars surrounding Camp Bastion were not forgotten and enjoyed personal deliveries of hot food.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5820/Xmas_dinner_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Baldwin kitchen manager from KBR in Camp Bastion said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is the full Christmas celebration for the troops in Bastion.  This includes a traditional Christmas lunch consisting of roast beef, pork, turkey, sprouts, roast potatoes and pudding and mince pies. We are cooking for roughly about 4,000 people - ranging from 140 joints of beef, 200 turkeys, 120 gammons – that’s what it take to feed these guys.  Also using 40 boxes of brussel spouts, 150 bags of potatoes, it’s on a massive scale.  It also includes litres of gravy, tomato soup – it’s a big operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="presents-for-all-serving-personnel"&gt;Presents for all serving personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5821/Xmas_presents_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing a little Christmas cheer to forces overseas every year is the UK based charity called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4uThanks!"&gt;uk4uThanks!&lt;/a&gt;  This is an organisation funded by money donated by members of the public. The presents (affectionately known as the ‘square stocking’) act as a gift from the nation to all those serving in the UK Armed Forces overseas away from their families and loved ones on Christmas Day.  The boxes, containing a host of goodies from business sponsors and bought with money donated from members of the public, were delivered in time to be opened on Christmas Day.  Much speculation abounds as to the contents of the boxes and it is never a disappointment as much thought is put into providing amusing and useful gifts away from home at Christmas time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
