<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65293</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-to-receive-cash-boost-for-choosing-development"/>
    <title>Communities to receive cash boost for choosing development</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles announces new cash incentives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities that tackle the legacy of inadequate house-building and choose to accept new housing will benefit directly from new generous cash incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods that take a proactive approach by drawing up a neighbourhood development plan, and securing the consent of local people in a referendum, will receive 25% of the revenues from the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; arising from the development that they choose to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cash boost will be paid directly to parish and town councils and can be used to back the community’s priorities for example to re-roof a village hall, refurbish a municipal pool or take over a community pub. Neighbourhoods without a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood development plan&lt;/a&gt; but where the levy is still charged will still receive a capped 15% share of the levy revenue arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities without a parish or town council will still benefit from this incentive, with the local planning authority retaining it and spending it in accordance with the wishes of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of hectoring people and forcing development on communities, the government believes that we need to persuade communities that development is in everyone’s interest. Incentives are key to getting the homes built that we both need for today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital this country increases the number of homes it builds to meet the needs of its increasing population. The failure of previous administrations to build enough homes, latterly despite the credit boom, led to a severe housing shortage that has been made worse by the rapid increase in the number of households. The number of people living alone has rocketed, and immigration has led to an influx of 1.7 million people into England in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to tackle this housing shortage and make best use of what we already have the government has invested £160 million to deal with the 250,000 homes empty for more than 6 months - 50,000 fewer then in 2009. This money combined with a share of £300 million announced in September’s housing growth package, will help put more than 15,000 empty homes back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also made clear that planning should encourage the effective use of land, including brownfield land that is not of high environmental value. The majority of all new homes - 76% of those completed in 2010 - were built on brownfield land. But this will not be enough and some undeveloped land will need to be made available for house-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a simple choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. We can shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or we can accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land and resolve that we will make these decisions locally and build beautiful places like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is determined to persuade communities to accept more house-building by giving them a tangible share of the benefits it brings. By undertaking a neighbourhood plan that makes space for new development, communities can secure revenues to make the community more attractive for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is an important way to make sure that development has the backing of the community. It is right that the areas that have organised themselves to bring forward a neighbourhood plan and have taken the plan through all the stages of the neighbourhood planning (including a successful examination and referendum) should be rewarded for their positive, pro-active approach to delivering growth. This is why they are entitled to an extra 10% of the levy arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy amount passed to neighbourhoods reflects the rates the local planning authority set for the levy. These charge a rate or different rates for development in the local area in pounds per square metre. The neighbourhood funding element will be calculated based on the levy receipts from the relevant development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The levy’s charges will become due from the date that a chargeable development is commenced. The neighbourhood funding element will be passed to parish or community councils in accordance with a timetable agreed between the local planning authority and the local council.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the money is transferred to a parish council (in England) or a community council (in Wales) they will decide how the money will be spent - although they will be expected to work with the local planning authority. Where the money stays with the local planning authority (in areas without a parish or community council) the local planning authority will engage with the communities where the development has happened to agree how best to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In areas that have not been subject to neighbourhood planning there will be a cap of £100 per council tax dwelling on the neighbourhood funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We aim to have these incentives in place from Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We previously &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;consulted&lt;/a&gt; on allowing councils the choice whether to spend their levy receipts on affordable housing but given other ongoing policies to support housing, we are not proposing to make this change at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also going to enable a mayoral development corporation to impose a Community Infrastructure Levy charge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64958</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T15:15:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-on-the-pre-application-process-for-major-infrastructure-projects"/>
    <title>Guidance on the pre-application process for major infrastructure projects</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This guidance sets out the requirements and procedures for the pre-application process and consultation for major infrastructure projects.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is the result of merging and expanding reworked versions of the local authority guidance and the pre-application guidance that went out to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/pre-application-process-for-planning-applications"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; on 13 April 2012. By merging these, we are avoiding unnecessary repetition of the description of common processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new guidance sets out the necessary requirements and procedures and gives clarity on the scope and scale of the consultation required at the pre-application stage. It covers all the main processes required by an applicant prior to the submission of an application, including the pre-application consultation, Environmental Impact Assessment, Habitats Regulations Assessments, and advice on drafting a Development Consent Order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60988</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T11:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T11:25:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cutting-red-tape-will-save-homeowners-240-on-diy-electrical-jobs-says-don-foster"/>
    <title>Cutting red tape will save homeowners £240 on DIY electrical jobs, says Don Foster</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government moves to scrap the requirement to get simple and low risk electrical works approved will save money for householders. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government moves to scrap the requirement for householders to get simple and low risk electrical works approved by their local council will save ‘DIYers’ £240 each, and in some cases even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduced just before Christmas, these changes will come into force in April 2013 and will avoid the need for householders to seek council approval for simple jobs such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding a socket to a kitchen, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;installing a new security light or a lawnmower socket in the garden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under current rules obtaining council approval for such jobs costs around £240 each time, or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riskier jobs such as work near baths and showers, installing new circuits and house rewires will continue to require approval from councils’ building control departments or be carried out by an electrician registered to approve their own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lots of people will have made it a new year resolution to fix or improve their home’s electrics, but they are often put off by the bureaucratic costs. I am cutting red tape to allow people to get on with making simple and safe improvements without having to spend hundreds of pounds on getting the council’s approval. Safety is the number one concern though and riskier jobs will always need to be signed off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also urged people to stay safe and continue using common sense saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I urge anyone who is either inexperienced at DIY or in doubt as to what they are doing to always consult a professional. Using a competent electrician is the simplest way to ensure you and your family remain safe. That’s why I’ll be working with industry and others to see what more we can do to get this simple message across.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also acknowledged that many people - mainly married men like him - were going to lose an excuse for not getting on with their list of jobs around the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are part of a package of measures to clarify and update the building regulations that will also save businesses £50 million a year. Taking over 400,000 electrical jobs out of the system annually contributes to savings to electrical firms of around £14 million per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The changes to electrical safety were included in a package of deregulatory measures &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations" title="Written Ministerial Statement by Don Foster on changes to the building regulations regime in England"&gt;announced to Parliament&lt;/a&gt; on 18 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety" title="Consultation on building regulations -electrical safety"&gt;consultation in January 2012&lt;/a&gt; sought views on electrical safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The deregulation package also delivers other savings to business including:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;bringing together currently separate guidance on how to design stairs and ramps so they are both safe and accessible - saving £4.4 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;updating fire safety guidance for lighting diffusers - saving £26.3 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;making the building control system more efficient and to extending the scope of competent person schemes - saving £6 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60871</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T12:58:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T12:58:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"/>
    <title>Changes to Temporary Stop Notices consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on proposals to improve councils' power to tackle unauthorised development.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation is on the proposal to revoke Statutory Instrument 2005/206 under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/206/contents/made"&gt;Town and Country Planning (Temporary Stop Notice)(England) Regulations 2005&lt;/a&gt;. The regulation currently restricts councils use of Temporary Stop Notices on unauthorised sites where a caravan is used as a main residence. This can discourage local councils from serving stop notices where it may be beneficial to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this consultation would give local councils greater freedom to make a decision on the basis of local circumstances and on whether serving Temporary Stop Notices in respect of caravans used as main residences is appropriate. It will remain for local councils to consider the consequences of taking enforcement action and whether the action is necessary and proportionate in the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60870</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T10:54:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T10:54:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/streamlining-information-requirements-for-planning-applications"/>
    <title>Streamlining information requirements for planning applications</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on proposed changes to reduce information requirements for planning applications.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out proposals relating to information requirements for planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These proposals include changes to secondary legislation on information requirements for outline planning applications, and a requirement that local authorities update their local lists of information requirements at least every 2 years. It also sets out proposed changes to the standard application form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60830</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-freedom-for-local-councils-to-prevent-unauthorised-traveller-sites--2"/>
    <title>Greater freedom for local councils to prevent unauthorised traveller sites</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposals to give councils more freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites have been published for consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be given greater freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites being set up and prevent long, drawn-out stalemates like Dale Farm, under proposals published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="temporary-stop-notices"&gt;Temporary Stop Notices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals would allow councils greater freedom to use temporary stop notices in relation to caravans that are in breach of planning control, and are used as a person’s main residence. This would be backed up with the potential for heavy fines of up to £20,000 on indictment or an unlimited fine on summary conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the current system councils are constrained as to when they can use these powers against caravans that are main residences, which can result in long delays and high costs to stop unauthorised development of this kind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long a small minority have abused the planning system, often at the expense of local communities who are forced to put up with unauthorised development in their area. This government believes in fair play, with everyone abiding by the same rules. These proposals will assist local councils in taking effective action against those who don’t.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-powers"&gt;Stronger powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporary Stop Notices enable councils to take action with immediate effect against unauthorised development without having to wait three days for a Stop Notice, or 28 days for an enforcement notice to come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to the outcome of the consultation, today’s proposals would remove restrictions on the use of temporary stop notices so councils can act quickly against new unauthorised sites, and save on the costs of enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60950</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:56:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"/>
    <title>Planning practice guidance should be simpler</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An external review of planning practice guidance has recommended rationalising advice and making it easier to use.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review group, led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system but did not review planning policy. They were not tasked with revaluating green belt policy or other countryside protections, which continue to be safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that the existing guidance is unwieldy in its current form and recommends that it be shorter but retain key elements, and be more accessible to be useful to everyone using the planning system. They stated that guidance is important to ensuring planning decisions are properly informed but should not place undue burdens on users of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that a vast range of materials are being considered guidance, and that ‘living documents’ intended to be updated on a regular basis had not been amended since publication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; to consider the group’s recommendations was launched today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is very clear that the old way of doing things is no longer fit for purpose. We have made recommendations for a modern web-based resource that is clear, up-to-date, coherent and easily usable, not just by planners and developers, but the public too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very grateful to the group for all the work they have done on this. We will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and I would urge other users of the planning system to have their say by responding to the consultation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group consists of Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones. They are sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;External review of government planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;Review of planning practice guidance - consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt;, Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/57081</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:00:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:00:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment"/>
    <title>Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the environment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009 buildings accounted for about 43% of all the UK’s carbon emissions. Buildings and other developments can also damage the environment, through poor waste management or inefficient use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the natural and built environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have included policies in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to explain how developments should be planned to reduce carbon emissions and protect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce carbon emissions from buildings, we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are requiring local planning authorities to make sure that new developments are energy efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will require all new homes to be zero carbon from 2016 and are considering extending this to include all other buildings from 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/green_deal/green_deal.aspx" title="Green deal"&gt;green deal&lt;/a&gt; to enable people to pay for home improvements over time using savings on their regular energy bills &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have improved &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/energy-performance-of-buildings" title="Energy Performance Certificates"&gt;Energy Performance Certificates&lt;/a&gt; to make them more informative and user-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/code-for-sustainable-homes" title="Code for sustainable homes"&gt;Code for Sustainable Homes&lt;/a&gt; which provides a single national standard for the design and construction of sustainable new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect trees we have simplified the system for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/tree-preservation-orders" title="Tree preservation certificates"&gt;tree preservation orders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work with the 9 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/aggregate-working-parties" title="Aggregate working parties"&gt;aggregate working parties&lt;/a&gt; who provide technical advice about the supply and demand for aggregates such as sand, gravel and crushed rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is responsible for developing town and country planning policy and rules that affect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policies on planning and the environment are set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework-and-the-environment" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012 following extensive public consultation. The framework is an important part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more easy to understand, and to promote sustainable growth. It replaced and simplified a series of earlier planning policy statements and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the government’s policy to revoke existing regional strategies outside London. However, any final decision on this must take account of assessments of, and consultation on, the possible environmental effects. We are updating the earlier environmental reports and undertaking further consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/abolition-of-regional-strategies"&gt;written ministerial statement&lt;/a&gt; made by Baroness Hanham on 25 July 2012 sets out the background and explains why the reports are being updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All EU member states must follow the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive. This requires that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all properties (homes, commercial and public buildings) must have an Energy Performance Certificate when sold, built or rented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger public buildings must display a Display Energy Certificate &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all air-conditioning systems over 12kW must be regularly inspected by an Energy Assessor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60403</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:57:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"/>
    <title> Review of planning practice guidance</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on the conclusions and recommendations of the review of planning guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"&gt;21 December 2012&lt;/a&gt; the government welcomed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;report of the review of planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt; led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the review group’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60325</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:58:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"/>
    <title>External review of government planning practice guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Conclusions and recommendations of the review of planning guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"&gt;21 December 2012&lt;/a&gt; the government welcomed the report of the review of planning practice guidance led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, and announced a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;short consultation&lt;/a&gt; on the review group’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group’s report makes recommendations as to the scope and form of practice guidance that should be provided in future by government to support effective planning; what new or updated practice guidance should be published, with clear priorities; and what guidance should be cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
