<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16257</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-review-of-planning-appeal-procedures"/>
    <title>Technical review of planning appeal procedures</title>
    <summary>This consultation proposes changes to improve the planning appeals procedures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published: 1 November 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to make the planning appeals process faster and more transparent, improve consistency and certainty in decision taking timescales. The proposals will bring cost and time benefits for those appealing decisions and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:36:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <summary>Proposed new powers will make it easier for hard working families to make home improvements.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14476</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:39:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill: impact assessment</title>
    <summary>A statement of the impact that the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures in the Growth and Infrastructure Bill will help to remove unnecessary bureaucracy that can hinder sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment provides a statement of the impact that the Bill will have on businesses, local government and communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14388</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation"/>
    <title>Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation</title>
    <summary>This consultation proposes changes to increase permitted development rights for extensions to homes and business premises.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes changes to increase permitted development rights for extensions to homes and business premises in non-protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to amend the Town and Country Planning (General Permitted Development) Order 1995 to allow homeowners and businesses to make larger extensions to their homes and business premises without requiring a planning application, and to allow quicker installation of broadband infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please submit your views using the questionnaire below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/15671</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:14:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:14:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development"/>
    <title>Giving communities more power in planning local development</title>
    <summary>Giving local people and councils more say about development through neighbourhood planning, Local Plans and the community infrastructure levy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want people to be able to influence decisions about new and modified buildings and facilities in their area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have the right to get involved in development decisions that affect them but in practice they have often found it difficult to have a meaningful say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give people more control over the development of their local area, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving communities the power to set the priorities for local development through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning" title="Neighbourhood planning"&gt;neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requiring local planning authorities to draw up clear, up-to-date &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/local-plans" title="Local Plans"&gt;Local Plans&lt;/a&gt; that conforms with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, meets local development needs and reflects local people’s views of how they wish their area to develop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils the power to raise money to support local infrastructure through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy"&gt;community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils new powers to stop unwanted development on gardens (so-called ‘garden grabbing’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a commitment in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf" title="Coalition agreement"&gt;coalition agreement (PDF 475KB)&lt;/a&gt; to give people more power over development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 introduced new powers for people to make neighbourhood plans and neighbourhood planning orders, with reduced interference from central government. These new powers are in addition to existing opportunities for community involvement, which are already part of the planning system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/neighbourhood-planning-regulations--2" title="Neighbourhood planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed regulations for neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; between October 2011 and January 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt; between October and December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-planning-regulations" title="Local planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the regulations which govern the process by which local councils prepare their development plans&lt;/a&gt; between July and October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neighbourhood planning provisions are contained in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/637/contents/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (General) Regulations 2012"&gt;Neighbourhood planning legislation&lt;/a&gt; came into effect in April 2012. Further legislation covering the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2031/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (Referendums) Regulations 2012"&gt;referendum stage of neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 2 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/987/contents/made" title="Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2011.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/2918/contents/made" title="The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011"&gt;The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 7 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16128</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:10:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:10:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient"/>
    <title>Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient</title>
    <summary>Ensuring that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date, safe and effective. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building regulations contain the rules for new and altered buildings to make them safe and accessible and limit waste and environmental damage. People carrying out building work must usually arrange for their work to be checked by an independent third party to make sure that their work meets the required standards. In some cases the installer can certify themselves that their work complies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building practices, technology and construction techniques are constantly evolving. We need to make sure that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (DGLC) is &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/review-of-building-regulations" title="Review of Building Regulations"&gt;reviewing building regulations in England&lt;/a&gt; to make sure they continue to be up to date and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to provide effective building regulations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing guidance that builders must comply with called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/approved-documents" title="Approved Documents"&gt;Approved Documents&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overseeing and supporting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/building-control-system" title="Building control system"&gt;building control organisations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorising competent person self-certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;producing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-circulars"&gt;circulars&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-divisional-circular-letters" title="Building regulations: divisional circular letters"&gt;divisional circular letters&lt;/a&gt; to formally tell interested parties about changes to building regulations policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-research"&gt;publishing research&lt;/a&gt; to provide a scientific basis to underpin the regulations   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adjudicating in disputes between people carrying out building work and a building control body through processes called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/determinations-and-appeals" title="Determinations and appeals"&gt;determinations and appeals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the secretariat for the &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/organisations/building-regulations-advisory-committee" title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England "&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England (&lt;abbr title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England"&gt;BRAC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; by March 2013, which advises the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government on the exercise of his or her power to make building regulations and on other related subjects in England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first set of national building standards were introduced with The Building Regulations 1965. These were a set of prescriptive standards that had to be followed.
The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1984/55" title="The Building Act - Legislation website"&gt;Building Act 1984&lt;/a&gt; brought fundamental changes to the building regulations regime. It introduced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;functional performance standards, set in terms of what was adequate, reasonable or appropriate, supported by statutory guidance in the Approved Documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;competition into the building control sector through the addition of private sector approved inspectors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes were introduced to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the standards more flexible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the system more efficient and effective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, there have been further changes to the legislation and the supporting guidance. These have sought to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the overall quality of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the effectiveness of the building regulations system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce any unnecessary burdens on those who use the system &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="building-regulations-2010-and-building-approved-inspectors-etc-regulations-2010"&gt;Building Regulations 2010 and Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and all amendments to both, were revoked from 1 October 2010, and are no longer in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; consolidated the Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and incorporated all of the amendments made since 2000. The regulations were also renumbered and reordered to make them easier to use and with a more logical structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/718/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012(SI 2012/718)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2012. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011(SI 2011/1515)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 15 July 2011.  These should be read in conjunction with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has published the following circulars which help to explain the regulations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2011-circular-02-2011"&gt;Circular (02/2011)&lt;/a&gt; explains the amendments made by the Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-and-building-regulations-2010-circular-07-2010"&gt;Circular (07/2010)&lt;/a&gt; explains the 2010 regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16103</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:08:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:08:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively"/>
    <title>Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively </title>
    <summary>We're simplifying the planning process to make it quicker and easier to build new homes, to develop new places and redevelop neglected land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes planning decisions can take too long. This can slow down or prevent people building new homes, creating new places and bringing disused or neglected land and buildings back into productive use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that the planning rules or poorly managed planning processes do not unnecessarily prevent or delay development. We want to simplify planning approval processes and make our policies and guidance simpler and easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speed up the planning approval process, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;provided a National Planning Policy Framework, the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;government’s view of what sustainable development means in practice&lt;/a&gt; for the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced, or is introducing, a range of other measures to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/speeding-up-the-planning-process" title="Speeding up planning decisions"&gt;speed up planning decisions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To speed up planning for nationally significant infrastructure projects (such as wind farms or motorways) we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are reforming the infrastructure planning process to  make sure it remains efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;want to extend the scope of the major infrastructure planning system to include new categories of commercial and business development so that, where they’re of sufficient significance, they can be determined at a national level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to ensure that the planning system stays effective and up to date.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make decisions about planning casework, compulsory purchase orders and land transaction cases through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abolished the Infrastructure Planning Commission on 1 April 2012, so that decisions on national infrastructure proposals are now made by ministers advised by the Planning Inspectorate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/called-in-planning-decisions-and-appeals" title="Called-in planning decisions and appeals"&gt;‘call-in’ planning decisions and appeals&lt;/a&gt; to be decided by the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oversee and support local planning authorities’ plan-making and decision-taking functions, mainly by providing planning laws, national planning policy and guidance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement set out the government’s commitment to publish and present to Parliament a simple and consolidated national planning framework covering all forms of development and setting out national economic, environmental and social priorities by April 2012. On 27 March 2012 the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; (the ‘Framework’) was published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework was produced following an extensive consultation with Parliament and the public.
The final Framework retains all of the most important elements of the draft Framework published in July 2011, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making sure the local plan - produced by communities - is the keystone of the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making planning much simpler and more accessible, reducing over 1,000 pages of often impenetrable jargon into around 50 pages of clearly written guidance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a presumption in favour of sustainable development that means that development is not held up unless to approve it would be against our collective interest &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;guaranteeing strong protections for the natural and historic environment, and requiring improvements to put right some of the neglect that has taken place &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;raising design standards so that the requirements for design are the most exacting yet &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve consulted on various aspects of planning reform, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allowing planning obligations to be renegotiated &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renegotiation-of-section-106-planning-obligations" title="Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations"&gt;Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations consultation&lt;/a&gt; to help get stalled development projects back on track&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating new opportunities to reuse existing buildings for sustainable development &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/reusing-existing-buildings-permitted-development-rights"&gt;New opportunities for sustainable development and growth through the reuse of existing buildings consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/streamlining-information-requirements-for-planning-applications"&gt;simplifying information requirements for planning applications&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; introduced a number of changes to the planning system, including transferring decisions on major infrastructure projects from the Infrastructure Planning Commission to ministers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further changes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2008/29/contents"&gt;Planning Act 2008&lt;/a&gt; will be introduced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-working-with"&gt;Who we are working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities prepare development plans, based on consultation with local communities, which set out their overall plans for development in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities are also responsible for development management. This includes making planning decisions, complying with the law about publicising, consulting on and determining most applications for planning permission, taking into account the opinions of local people and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also offer pre-application advice to prospective developers and enforce planning laws in their area. 
Appeals against refusal of planning permission and inquiries are dealt with by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/planning-inspectorate" title="Planning Inspectorate"&gt;Planning Inspectorate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.planningportal.gov.uk/" title="The Planning Portal"&gt;Planning Portal&lt;/a&gt; includes advice on planning permission, online applications and guidance on how the system works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on planning for major infrastructure projects can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://infrastructure.planningportal.gov.uk"&gt;Planning Inspectorate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16131</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:01:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:01:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment"/>
    <title>Improving the energy efficiency of buildings and using planning to protect the environment</title>
    <summary>We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the environment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009 buildings accounted for about 43% of all the UK’s carbon emissions. Buildings and other developments can also damage the environment, through poor waste management or inefficient use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to reduce carbon emissions from buildings and make sure that planning policies help to protect and improve the natural and built environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have included policies in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-planning-policy-framework--2" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; to explain how developments should be planned to reduce carbon emissions and protect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce carbon emissions from buildings, we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are requiring local planning authorities to make sure that new developments are energy efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will require all new homes to be zero carbon from 2016 and are considering extending this to include all other buildings from 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have introduced the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/tackling/green_deal/green_deal.aspx" title="Green deal"&gt;green deal&lt;/a&gt; to enable people to pay for home improvements over time using savings on their regular energy bills &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have improved &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/energy-performance-of-buildings" title="Energy Performance Certificates"&gt;Energy Performance Certificates&lt;/a&gt; to make them more informative and user-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/code-for-sustainable-homes" title="Code for sustainable homes"&gt;Code for Sustainable Homes&lt;/a&gt; which provides a single national standard for the design and construction of sustainable new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help protect trees we have simplified the system for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/tree-preservation-orders" title="Tree preservation certificates"&gt;tree preservation orders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work with the 9 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/aggregate-working-parties" title="Aggregate working parties"&gt;aggregate working parties&lt;/a&gt; who provide technical advice about the supply and demand for aggregates such as sand, gravel and crushed rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is responsible for developing town and country planning policy and rules that affect the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policies on planning and the environment are set out in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-buildings-and-using-planning-to-protect-the-environment/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework-and-the-environment" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, published in March 2012 following extensive public consultation. The framework is an important part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more easy to understand, and to promote sustainable growth. It replaced and simplified a series of earlier planning policy statements and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="impact"&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the government’s policy to revoke existing regional strategies outside London. However, any final decision on this must take account of assessments of, and consultation on, the possible environmental effects. We are updating the earlier environmental reports and undertaking further consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A written ministerial statement made by Baroness Hanham on 25 July 2012 sets out the background and explains why the reports are being updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All EU member states must follow the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive. This requires that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all properties (homes, commercial and public buildings) must have an Energy Performance Certificate when sold, built or rented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger public buildings must display a Display Energy Certificate &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all air-conditioning systems over 12kW must be regularly inspected by an Energy Assessor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <summary>Don Foster welcomed a huge response from neighbourhood groups interested in using new powers to save local assets or take over services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16084</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report on the revocation of the North East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the North East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S5 from the Northumberland County and National Park Joint Structure Plan First Alteration relating to the green belt at Morpeth. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the Coalition Agreement to safeguard green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note:&lt;/strong&gt; Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
