<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17814</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/statutory-consultee-performance-and-award-of-costs"/>
    <title>Statutory consultee performance and award of costs</title>
    <summary>Proposals to amend guidance on awards in appeals and other planning proceedings.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes to amend guidance in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/costs-awards-in-appeals-and-other-planning-proceedings-circular-03-2009"&gt;Circular 03/09: Costs Awards in Appeals and Other Planning Proceedings&lt;/a&gt; in relation to statutory consultees and their advice at appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also announced clarifications to the guidance in relation to local councils and their development plan, and in relation to ensuring evidence submitted at appeal is manifestly accurate and truthful. The government is also requiring the 5 main statutory bodies to report on, and be accountable for their performance on dealing with planning applications as part of their individual Improvement Plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of responses was published on 18 December 2012. The report above summarises the key issues raised and provides a revised addendum to circular 03/09.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/57427</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:14:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:14:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"/>
    <title>Building regulations: access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7</title>
    <summary>Overview of the consultation on changes to the building regulations system and details of various technical aspects of the regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilet and regulation 7, and is section 1 of 4, relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 1 provides an overview of the consultation package as a whole as well as proposals on a number of areas including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;replacing the currently referenced standards in part A (structure) with the new British Standards based on Eurocodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligning the existing guidance in Approved Document C (site preparation and resistance to contaminants and moisture) with the most up-to-date radon maps to ensure the safety provisions are targeted appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarifying the guidance on access statements in Approved Document M (access to and use of buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalising the guidance supporting parts M, K and N (access, protection from falling, collision and impact and glazing respectively) to remove unnecessary costs on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making minor changes to the technical guidance in Approved Document B (fire safety) to resolve practical problems in the application of requirement B2 (internal fire spread (linings))&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the intention to take forward the repeal of the fire protection provisions in the Local Acts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting out the non-regulatory approach proposed in relation to domestic security and changing places toilets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="draft-approved-documents"&gt;Draft Approved Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published alongside this section of the consultation is a draft version of a new Approved Document K (protection from falling, collision and impact). Not only does this reflect the proposed changes resulting from the rationalisation of parts K, M and N, it also seeks consultees’ views on the proposed new style of Approved Documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new style has also been applied to a draft revised Approved Document regulation 7 which can be found in the main consultation document as annex I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="other-consultation-sections"&gt;Other consultation sections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/57426</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:14:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:14:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"/>
    <title>Building regulations: electrical safety</title>
    <summary>Section 3 of the consultation on changes to the building regulations, covering electrical safety in homes (part P).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out detailed proposals on part P, and is section 3 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise. It includes proposals to reduce the cost associated with the provisions governing electrical safety in the home whilst not undermining safety benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/57425</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:13:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:13:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"/>
    <title>Building regulations: the building control system</title>
    <summary>Consultation about changes to the building regulations building control system.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on the building control system, and is section 4 of 4 relating to the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 4 includes proposals on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving local authority building control processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving private sector approved inspector arrangements, including removing the warranty link rule&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extending the competent person self-certification schemes framework and introducing specialist third-party certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing ‘appointed persons’ to act as compliance co-ordinators on construction sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;section 2: part L (conservation of fuel and power)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/57422</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:12:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:12:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"/>
    <title>Building regulations: conservation of fuel and power</title>
    <summary>Consultation about changes to the building regulations that relate to the energy efficiency of buildings (part L).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the detailed proposals on part L of the building regulations. It is section 2 of 4 of the 2012 building regulations consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes proposals for tighter carbon dioxide emission standards for new homes and non-domestic buildings, to take the next step towards zero carbon standards, plus tighter performance standards for works to existing buildings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper also contains proposals to introduce, on a phased basis, requirements for additional energy efficiency improvements to be carried out when other specified works (eg extensions) are planned and Green Deal finance is available as an option to meet the up-front costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other consultation sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;section 1: introduction to the consultation package and proposals on parts A, B, C, K, M and N, access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;section 3: part P (electrical safety - dwellings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;section 4: the building control system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles has announced a new multi-million pound cash boost to help more communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by The Right Honourable Don Foster MP on changes to the building regulations regime in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57041</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:45:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-planning-authorities-on-implementing-planning-requirements-of-the-eu-waste-framework-directive-2008-98-ec"/>
    <title>Guidance for local planning authorities on implementing planning requirements of the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC)</title>
    <summary>A guidance note to ensure compliance with the EU Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Waste Framework Directive (2008/98/EC) (‘the Directive’) provides an overarching legislative framework for the management of waste across Europe. This guidance note provides advice on the measures required by local planning authorities to ensure compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance is aimed primarily at waste planning authorities, but it highlights the main legal and policy provisions of relevance to all planning authorities, and the action we expect them to take to assist them in ensuring compliance with the directive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be read alongside the government’s planning policy for waste management, currently set out in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;Planning Policy Statement 10&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/planning-for-sustainable-waste-management-a-companion-guide-to-planning-policy-statement-10"&gt;companion guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56834</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the north west plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919154703/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationnwrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the north west regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56622</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/guidance-will-help-support-development-and-get-infrastructure-built"/>
    <title>Guidance will help support development and get infrastructure built</title>
    <summary>Updated guidance will ensure the Community Infrastructure Levy is effective in supporting development and getting key infrastructure built. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance has been revised with the active participation of councils and developers to provide certainty on key issues. It has been updated to reflect reforms to the planning system and will help councils looking to introduce the levy, as well as providing clarity to those paying the levy about how it works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; ensures there is no double charging to developers by clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance reflects existing best practice and ensures councils in the process of developing proposals do not need to start their levy setting process from the beginning. Support will be available to councils who choose to review their levy as a result of the new guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ensures a robust evidence base is used for assessing levy rates and provides advice on the 2012 regulations that improve the operation of the levy. The guidance also makes clear that there is no obligation for councils to charge the levy, and that they can set a low or zero rate if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Government has worked actively with councils and developers to get this guidance right and make clear how we expect the levy to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The guidance ensures that councils who have already adopted their levy will not need to do anything new and only councils developing levy rates will need to consider this new guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will continue to listen to issues being raised, such as the need for greater clarity at an earlier stage on how the levy will be spent. We will also be considering the suggestion to move the 2014 date when councils will be limited in their use of pooled Section 106 planning obligations for infrastructure that can be funded by the levy. The government expects to consult on further regulatory changes in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy has the potential to raise an estimated £1 billion a year of funding by 2016 to support growth locally. It gives councils more choice and flexibility in how they fund the infrastructure that their communities want and need, and provides developers with much more ‘up front’ certainty about the amount of money they will be expected to contribute for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Peace from the British Property Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development industry has raised a number of concerns about the Community Infrastructure Levy. We have been closely involved in the development of this document and are pleased that it clearly sets out what local authorities must do when they are looking to charge the levy. These revisions should help support development by ensuring the levy is being implemented effectively. We look forward to continuing our work with the department on other Community Infrastructure Levy issues next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Mike Jones, Leader, Cheshire West and Chester Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils are keen to continue work with the development industry in a positive and productive way that enables much needed development to take place in a way that is fair and equitable to developers and to local people. Discussions on the Community Infrastructure Levy have been conducted in this spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Builders Federation Executive Chairman Stewart Baseley said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been closely involved in the process to improve the Community Infrastructure Levy guidance. We are pleased that it assists in clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations and sets out the importance of robust evidence and transparency when deciding on levy rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recently introduced changes to ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged the Community Infrastructure Levy. Applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents (via a Section 73 planning application) without having to pay another levy on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
