<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <summary>The flag representing the historic county of Lancashire has been hoisted above Whitehall to coincide with the county day on 27 November.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16962</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents</title>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on which consents could be brought within the scope of an expanded ‘one stop shop’ for major infrastructure.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 6 September 2012, the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister set out a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;major package of reforms to housing and planning&lt;/a&gt; to help create conditions for economic growth. This announcement included a commitment to ‘work to extend the principle of a one-stop-shop for non-planning consents for major infrastructure’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this consultation is to seek views from interested bodies on what consents should be moved within the scope of an expanded ‘one stop shop’ for major infrastructure and on proposals for streamlining the current list of statutory consultees that developers are required to consult before applying for a development consent order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"&gt;extend the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16960</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects</title>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on the proposal to extend the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime to business and commercial projects.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To help speed up planning decisions for the most complex projects and to increase choice for developers, the government proposes to extend the scope of the Planning Act 2008 so that a wider range of development can be brought within the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime. This will allow developers of nationally significant business or commercial projects to apply to the Secretary of State for the option of using the streamlined planning regime set out in the Planning Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views about the proposal to extend the nationally significant infrastructure regime and, in particular, about the types and forms of business and commercial projects to be prescribed in regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"&gt;expand and improve the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16971</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:52:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:52:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient"/>
    <title>Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient</title>
    <summary>Ensuring that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date, safe and effective. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building regulations contain the rules for new and altered buildings to make them safe and accessible and limit waste and environmental damage. People carrying out building work must usually arrange for their work to be checked by an independent third party to make sure that their work meets the required standards. In some cases the installer can certify themselves that their work complies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building practices, technology and construction techniques are constantly evolving. We need to make sure that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (DGLC) is &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/review-of-building-regulations" title="Review of Building Regulations"&gt;reviewing building regulations in England&lt;/a&gt; to make sure they continue to be up to date and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to provide effective building regulations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing guidance that builders must comply with called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/approved-documents" title="Approved Documents"&gt;Approved Documents&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overseeing and supporting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/building-control-system" title="Building control system"&gt;building control organisations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorising competent person self-certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;producing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-circulars"&gt;circulars&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-divisional-circular-letters" title="Building regulations: divisional circular letters"&gt;divisional circular letters&lt;/a&gt; to formally tell interested parties about changes to building regulations policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-research"&gt;publishing research&lt;/a&gt; to provide a scientific basis to underpin the regulations   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adjudicating in disputes between people carrying out building work and a building control body through processes called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/determinations-and-appeals" title="Determinations and appeals"&gt;determinations and appeals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the secretariat for the &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/organisations/building-regulations-advisory-committee" title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England "&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England (&lt;abbr title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England"&gt;BRAC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; by March 2013, which advises the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government on the exercise of his or her power to make building regulations and on other related subjects in England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first set of national building standards were introduced with The Building Regulations 1965. These were a set of prescriptive standards that had to be followed.
The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1984/55" title="The Building Act - Legislation website"&gt;Building Act 1984&lt;/a&gt; brought fundamental changes to the building regulations regime. It introduced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;functional performance standards, set in terms of what was adequate, reasonable or appropriate, supported by statutory guidance in the Approved Documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;competition into the building control sector through the addition of private sector approved inspectors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes were introduced to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the standards more flexible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the system more efficient and effective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, there have been further changes to the legislation and the supporting guidance. These have sought to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the overall quality of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the effectiveness of the building regulations system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce any unnecessary burdens on those who use the system &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of July 2010 we ran an exercise to identify what changes are needed to ensure the building regulations continue to operate effectively in the future. We invited ordinary people, businesses and local authorities to submit their ideas about what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These views helped us decide the priority areas for further work and led to the development of a detailed package of proposals for changes to the building regulations. The proposals were contained in a consultation published on 31 January 2012 in 4 sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;section 1: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation overview and proposals on various technical aspects of the regulations&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 2: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;energy efficiency of buildings (Part L)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 3: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;electrical safety in homes (Part P)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 4: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;changes to the building control system&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, the Cabinet Office’s Red Tape Challenge has also looked at the potential to reduce the amount of regulation in this area. The next steps will be incorporated into our response to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="building-regulations-2010-and-building-approved-inspectors-etc-regulations-2010"&gt;Building Regulations 2010 and Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and all amendments to both, were revoked from 1 October 2010, and are no longer in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; consolidated the Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and incorporated all of the amendments made since 2000. The regulations were also renumbered and reordered to make them easier to use and with a more logical structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/718/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012(SI 2012/718)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2012. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011(SI 2011/1515)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 15 July 2011.  These should be read in conjunction with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has published the following circulars which help to explain the regulations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2011-circular-02-2011"&gt;Circular (02/2011)&lt;/a&gt; explains the amendments made by the Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-and-building-regulations-2010-circular-07-2010"&gt;Circular (07/2010)&lt;/a&gt; explains the 2010 regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16956</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:39:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/measures-to-reduce-bureaucratic-barriers-to-growth-and-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Measures to reduce bureaucratic barriers to growth and infrastructure</title>
    <summary>An expansion of the ‘one-stop-shop’ approach for considering nationally significant infrastructure projects will help boost growth and jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;, currently being considered in Parliament, will help the country compete on the global stage by introducing a comprehensive series of practical reforms that will reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals in the Bill include reducing the number of different consents infrastructure developers require. The government is also consulting on a new streamlined ‘one-stop-shop’ service and on reducing the number of bodies developers need to consult on every application. The proposed reforms will deliver a swifter, more efficient planning process while ensuring interested parties can continue to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms will also open up the fast-track planning process used for nationally significant infrastructure projects to additional types of nationally significant development. It will be open for the first time to business and commercial projects that are important to delivering growth and prosperity and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new types of developments that could be considered under the nationally significant infrastructure system include: manufacturing and major tourism and leisure proposals, office development such as research and development facilities, and warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers would be allowed to request that their application for these nationally significant business projects be determined through the infrastructure planning system which ensures decisions are made within 12 months from the beginning of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations on these two proposed reforms to the major infrastructure planning process were issued today. (See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects"&gt;extending the regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents"&gt;expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital we secure investment in new nationally significant infrastructure and commercial development, and that quicker and better planning decisions are made, if we are to help boost the economy and create the new jobs we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning delays help no one. They bring uncertainty for local people and local firms and can deter new investment all together. By streamlining the planning process to make it quicker and easier for these national significant projects to be decided we can ensure sustainable development gets underway without delay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reforms have already given significant additional powers to councils and communities so they can decide on the scale and location of development in their areas. With this power comes a responsibility to ensure that local planning decisions are efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will also give planning applicants the ability to apply directly to the Planning Inspectorate where there is clear evidence that a council’s planning service is performing very poorly and failing to administer a proper service for both applicants and local residents.  A consultation recently published sets out how these proposals would work, including the basis for assessing performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16917</id>
    <published>2012-11-24T11:13:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-24T11:13:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively"/>
    <title>Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively </title>
    <summary>We're simplifying the planning process to make it quicker and easier to build new homes, to develop new places and redevelop neglected land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes planning decisions can take too long. This can slow down or prevent people building new homes, creating new places and bringing disused or neglected land and buildings back into productive use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that the planning rules or poorly managed planning processes do not unnecessarily prevent or delay development. We want to simplify planning approval processes and make our policies and guidance simpler and easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speed up the planning approval process, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;provided a National Planning Policy Framework, the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;government’s view of what sustainable development means in practice&lt;/a&gt; for the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced, or is introducing, a range of other measures to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/speeding-up-the-planning-process" title="Speeding up planning decisions"&gt;speed up planning decisions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To speed up planning for nationally significant infrastructure projects (such as wind farms or motorways) we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are reforming the infrastructure planning process to  make sure it remains efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;want to extend the scope of the major infrastructure planning system to include new categories of commercial and business development so that, where they’re of sufficient significance, they can be determined at a national level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to ensure that the planning system stays effective and up to date.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make decisions about planning casework, compulsory purchase orders and land transaction cases through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abolished the Infrastructure Planning Commission on 1 April 2012, so that decisions on national infrastructure proposals are now made by ministers advised by the Planning Inspectorate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/called-in-planning-decisions-and-appeals" title="Called-in planning decisions and appeals"&gt;‘call-in’ planning decisions and appeals&lt;/a&gt; to be decided by the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oversee and support local planning authorities’ plan-making and decision-taking functions, mainly by providing planning laws, national planning policy and guidance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement set out the government’s commitment to publish and present to Parliament a simple and consolidated national planning framework covering all forms of development and setting out national economic, environmental and social priorities by April 2012. On 27 March 2012 the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; (the ‘Framework’) was published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework was produced following an extensive consultation with Parliament and the public.
The final Framework retains all of the most important elements of the draft Framework published in July 2011, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making sure the local plan - produced by communities - is the keystone of the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making planning much simpler and more accessible, reducing over 1,000 pages of often impenetrable jargon into around 50 pages of clearly written guidance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a presumption in favour of sustainable development that means that development is not held up unless to approve it would be against our collective interest &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;guaranteeing strong protections for the natural and historic environment, and requiring improvements to put right some of the neglect that has taken place &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;raising design standards so that the requirements for design are the most exacting yet &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve consulted on various aspects of planning reform, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allowing planning obligations to be renegotiated &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renegotiation-of-section-106-planning-obligations" title="Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations"&gt;Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations consultation&lt;/a&gt; to help get stalled development projects back on track&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating new opportunities to reuse existing buildings for sustainable development &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/reusing-existing-buildings-permitted-development-rights"&gt;New opportunities for sustainable development and growth through the reuse of existing buildings consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/streamlining-information-requirements-for-planning-applications"&gt;simplifying information requirements for planning applications&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; introduced a number of changes to the planning system, including transferring decisions on major infrastructure projects from the Infrastructure Planning Commission to ministers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further changes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2008/29/contents"&gt;Planning Act 2008&lt;/a&gt; will be introduced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-working-with"&gt;Who we are working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities prepare development plans, based on consultation with local communities, which set out their overall plans for development in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities are also responsible for development management. This includes making planning decisions, complying with the law about publicising, consulting on and determining most applications for planning permission, taking into account the opinions of local people and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also offer pre-application advice to prospective developers and enforce planning laws in their area. 
Appeals against refusal of planning permission and inquiries are dealt with by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/planning-inspectorate" title="Planning Inspectorate"&gt;Planning Inspectorate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.planningportal.gov.uk/" title="The Planning Portal"&gt;Planning Portal&lt;/a&gt; includes advice on planning permission, online applications and guidance on how the system works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on planning for major infrastructure projects can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://infrastructure.planningportal.gov.uk"&gt;Planning Inspectorate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16667</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:33:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-performance-and-the-planning-guarantee"/>
    <title>Planning performance and the Planning Guarantee</title>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on planning performance and the Planning Guarantee.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation links to the Government’s proposals, contained within Clause 1 of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, to introduce legislation to give applicants the choice of submitting planning applications direct to the secretary of state, where the local planning authority is underperforming.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on what measures to use to identify an authority’s performance, how to identify underperformance and how to identify improved performance and related measures to underpin the Planning Guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16388</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-west-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the West Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194311/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationwmrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the West Midlands regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16257</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-review-of-planning-appeal-procedures"/>
    <title>Technical review of planning appeal procedures</title>
    <summary>This consultation proposes changes to improve the planning appeals procedures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published: 1 November 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to make the planning appeals process faster and more transparent, improve consistency and certainty in decision taking timescales. The proposals will bring cost and time benefits for those appealing decisions and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:36:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <summary>Proposed new powers will make it easier for hard working families to make home improvements.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
