<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-30T15:15:40+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/17411</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T15:15:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T15:15:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development"/>
    <title>Giving communities more power in planning local development</title>
    <summary>Giving local people and councils more say about development through neighbourhood planning, Local Plans and the community infrastructure levy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want people to be able to influence decisions about new and modified buildings and facilities in their area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have the right to get involved in development decisions that affect them but in practice they have often found it difficult to have a meaningful say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give people more control over the development of their local area, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving communities the power to set the priorities for local development through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning" title="Neighbourhood planning"&gt;neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requiring local planning authorities to draw up clear, up-to-date &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/local-plans" title="Local Plans"&gt;Local Plans&lt;/a&gt; that conforms with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, meets local development needs and reflects local people’s views of how they wish their area to develop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils the power to raise money to support local infrastructure through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy"&gt;community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils new powers to stop unwanted development on gardens (so-called ‘garden grabbing’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a commitment in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf" title="Coalition agreement"&gt;coalition agreement (PDF 475KB)&lt;/a&gt; to give people more power over development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 introduced new powers for people to make neighbourhood plans and neighbourhood planning orders, with reduced interference from central government. These new powers are in addition to existing opportunities for community involvement, which are already part of the planning system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/neighbourhood-planning-regulations--2" title="Neighbourhood planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed regulations for neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; between October 2011 and January 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt; between October and December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-planning-regulations" title="Local planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the regulations which govern the process by which local councils prepare their development plans&lt;/a&gt; between July and October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neighbourhood planning provisions are contained in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/637/contents/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (General) Regulations 2012"&gt;Neighbourhood planning legislation&lt;/a&gt; came into effect in April 2012. Further legislation covering the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2031/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (Referendums) Regulations 2012"&gt;referendum stage of neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 2 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/987/contents/made" title="Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2011.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/2918/contents/made" title="The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011"&gt;The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 7 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2975/contents/made"&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 29 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17341</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T13:09:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T13:09:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely environmental effects of revoking the South West Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194318/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationswrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the South West regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South West regional planning guidance and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report proposes to retain the saved structure plan policy S6 from the ‘Somerset and Exmoor National Park joint structure plan’ relating to the green belt in North East Somerset. Removing this policy before the council has adopted a local plan which defines green belt boundaries could put green belt land at risk from unwanted development. This is in line with the coalition agreement to safeguard the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17304</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-green-belt-statistics-for-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Local authority green belt statistics for England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <summary>Statistics on designated green belt land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on the extent of the green belt in England were released under the auspices of the UK Statistics Authority on 30 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The extent of the designated green belt land in England in 2011/12 was estimated at 1,639,410 hectares, about 13% of the land area of England. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall there has been a decrease of 130 hectares from the revised 2010-11 green belt. This is due to three authorities who have adopted new plans in which they have changed the boundaries of the green belt. This represents a decrease of less than 0.01% per cent in the total green belt area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since these statistics were first compiled for 1997, there has been an increase in the area of green belt after taking account of the redesignation of some green belt as part of the New Forest National Park in 2005.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17243</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:33:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/town-and-country-planning-association-conference-speech"/>
    <title>Town and Country Planning Association conference speech</title>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Planning Minister Nick Boles about beautiful urban landscapes and affordable homes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;England is famous for the beauty of its landscapes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Yorkshire Dales to the South Hams, from the Weald of Kent to the Cumbrian Lakes, England glories in countryside of which generations of man and nature are joint authors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes - together with the greater drama of their Celtic cousins - that draw visitors to these islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes that our most popular institution and your sister organisation, the National Trust, was set up to preserve in perpetuity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of England is its finest asset and, for each of us, our most precious inheritance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative in both name and spirit, as a West Country boy and a Lincolnshire MP, as the son of a former director general of the National Trust and the brother of 1 of its conservation managers, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that nothing would do more to improve the health and happiness of the British people than if more of them got to spend more of their lives surrounded by beauty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty lifts, calms, excites, inspires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more intoxicating than any narcotic, more soothing than any therapy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Britain becomes more prosperous, we must insist that it becomes more beautiful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the beauty we seek, and the landscapes we treasure, are not only to be found in our open spaces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the loveliest scenery in Britain is to be found in our villages, cities and towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take you on a journey, which starts in my constituency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, the river Welland has snaked its way through the low contours of Lincolnshire from its source in Northamptonshire’s Hothorpe Hills.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enters Lincolnshire at the point where 4 counties meet and passes through countryside that is pleasant but hardly memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wandering painter or poet would not give this stretch of the Welland valley a second look, were it not for the landscape of Lincolnshire limestone that is the town of Stamford.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is not just 1 of England’s most beautiful towns; it is 1 of its finest bits of scenery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man-made. Built from stone and timber frames and slate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the aesthetic equal of our most splendid hills, lakes and rivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did this landscape come from?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it spring fully formed from the mind of some 17th century master planner, the brainchild of a Lincolnshire Haussman?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is, as the Royal Commission for Historic Monuments pronounced, ‘a town of discrete buildings’, each 1 unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earls of Exeter from nearby Burghley House provided long leases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the local community of wool, leather, cloth and hemp merchants, apothecaries and solicitors indulged themselves with a great variety of stone window surrounds, doorways, eaves, corner and chimney details.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did so within a broad set of rules set out in the London manuals of Rome educated James Gibbs but almost always used local architects and builders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford was the spontaneous product of human initiative, haphazardly executed and totally unplanned, motivated by the desire for profit, the love of God and that age-old urge that keeps makeover shows in business, the desire to make your house nicer than your neighbours’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop is north of the border, in Great Britain’s first New Town.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by contrast, was an example of municipal town planning at its boldest and most inspired.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the economic stagnation into which Edinburgh had slipped after the Act of Union, in 1752 the Provost, George Drummond, launched an architectural competition to design a new cityscape of wide streets, crescents and squares, featuring symmetrical terraces of town-houses as well as purpose-built shops and public gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-six year old James Craig won the competition and, in 4 stages between the 1760s and the 1850s, he, Robert Adam, William Chambers and William Playfair all stayed loyal to the original vision and developed their own variations on a Greek revival theme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In building their New Town, Edinburgh’s town councillors not only restored commercial and cultural vigour to Scotland’s capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also created 1 of the most beautiful landscapes in the British Isles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who can resist the melancholy charm of a walk in the rain around Charlotte Square and through Ainslie Place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would wager that the Facebook pages of recent visitors to Scotland contain at least as many photographs of Bute House and Moray Place as they do of Loch Lomond or Glencoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Stamford in the early 1600s, and in Edinburgh 150 later, beauty came about as a result of the natural human urge to get together with one’s neighbours to build a place in which it would be a pleasure to live and work, to raise a family and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same generous set of instincts that, another hundred and fifty years later, inspired Ebenezer Howard to build Letchworth Garden City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I am skating on very thin ice telling members of the Town and Country Planning Association anything about the Garden City movement, when your association was founded to promote just that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do want take a moment, as a layman, lacking all planning qualifications, to say why, like the Prime Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister, I believe that we have so much to learn from Ebenezer Howard and his garden cities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genius of Letchworth, like so many of the most appealing towns and cities, lies as much in the spaces between the buildings as in the buildings themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By resisting the temptation to cram as many houses as possible onto the available land and adopting their golden rule of twelve houses to the acre, Letchworth’s architects, Barry Parker and Raymond Unwin allowed room for the organic intermingling of nature and architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings are buttressed by front and back gardens, the roads are lined with broad verges and trees, the town is criss-crossed with footpaths and patchworked with allotments and parks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ebenezer Howard himself put it, “Parks and gardens, orchards and woods, are being planted in the midst of the busy life of the people, so that they can be enjoyed in the fullest measure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letchworth and the other garden cities work as living, breathing urban communities because, as an Ebenezer Howard put it, they combine “the advantages of the most energetic and active town life, with all the beauty and delight of the country.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way most English people want to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find a way to build places like this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has been holding us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only been planning minister for a few months but I have observed the debate about housing and planning for over ten years and I think I know what is wrong.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trapped in a vicious circle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at the new housing estates that have been bolted on to their towns and villages in recent decades and observe that few of them are beautiful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not to put too fine a point on it, many of them are pig-ugly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Harrisons Wharf in Purfleet that I visited last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure the flats inside are nice enough but they occupy an overbearing and unbroken slab of dismal brickwork that is an insult to the community it borders, cutting it off from a stretch of the River Thames which, in Victorian times, attracted day-trippers from London keen to take a pleasant walk along banks of the river.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since new housing estates are all too often soulless and formulaic, and those who will inhabit them will add to the pressure on local roads, primary school places and doctor’s appointments, existing residents oppose any proposal to build new houses on green field sites, even when the land is of low environmental quality.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities respond to the wishes of local voters by putting too few sites into their local plans. And this drives the cost of development land up to stratospheric levels (roughly £3 million an hectare in the South East and East of England by 2010.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers respond by stuffing as many units as they can onto any site and, in an attempt to make the properties affordable, skimp on room size, architectural features, vernacular materials, communal spaces and landscape design.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, because we don’t build beautifully, people don’t let us build much. And because we don’t build much, we can’t afford to build beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the coalition, and my personal mission as planning minister, is to help us break out of this vicious circle once and for all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get back on to that confident, progressive path, which created Stamford, Edinburgh New Town and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to build beautiful and affordable places once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have we done to bring this about? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles’ first step, in June 2010, was to scrap John Prescott’s blanket density target of 30 dwellings per hectare and to stop the garden grabbing that was destroying the precious green spaces that make Britain’s cities so pleasant to live in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government then embarked on a root and branch reform of the planning system and the creation of the National Planning Policy Framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mammoth task which had to be masterminded by a minister with a mammoth brain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my predecessor, Greg Clark, is blessed with exactly that - as well as the unfailing patience and politeness required to bring the good ship Reform to dock with most of those interested in planning and development still on board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Framework establishes a few clear principles, which it is now my job to drive through.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That local councils should take charge of development in their areas by drawing up local plans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that alongside the power to plan comes the responsibility to provide new houses to meet people’s aspirations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their local plans, councils must bring forward enough land to meet the objectively assessed housing needs of their area over the next 5 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they do so, they will be able to protect precious open spaces against speculative development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Secretary of State and I will back them to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they fail to take their responsibilities seriously, the presumption in favour of sustainable development will fill the vacuum and make the vital decisions that they are ducking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Framework, Grant Shapps introduced the New Homes Bonus, which gives local councils additional money for every new home for which they give planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in what I believe will turn out to be our most revolutionary step, the government launched neighbourhood planning through which villages, parishes and other neighbourhoods can take control of their future and decide for themselves how and where development should take place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be talking more about our ambitions for neighbourhood plans after the Autumn Statement.
So the government has acted to ensure that more land is brought forward for development and that local communities have an incentive to welcome new housing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now for planners, architects and developers, large and small, to seize the opportunity we have created and start designing beautiful places, which local people will welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, on the edge of Bishops Castle in Shropshire, Bob Tomlinson and Carole Salmon set out to create a new, contemporary village, a friendly place that people would want to live.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was The Wintles, 1 of the most exciting and enchanting collection of new houses anywhere in England.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses are all different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are unashamedly contemporary but incorporate vernacular features in a bold and imaginative way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a wide range of both natural and manufactured materials and make a priority of the spaces between the buildings (both private and communal) and the planting of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wintles did not get everything right first time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which experiment ever does?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not as integrated into the rest of Bishops Castle as some long-standing residents would like. And, to replicate it on a large scale, one would need to find a way to build houses that are just as beautiful and just as sustainable but cost less to build.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Bishops Castle I believe that the Living Village Trust created a model for our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which Ebenezer Howard would be proud.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which, once again, we build beautiful new urban landscapes full of affordable houses surrounded by green spaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be our goal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T12:38:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <summary>The flag representing the historic county of Lancashire has been hoisted above Whitehall to coincide with the county day on 27 November.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16962</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents</title>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on which consents could be brought within the scope of an expanded ‘one stop shop’ for major infrastructure.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 6 September 2012, the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister set out a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;major package of reforms to housing and planning&lt;/a&gt; to help create conditions for economic growth. This announcement included a commitment to ‘work to extend the principle of a one-stop-shop for non-planning consents for major infrastructure’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this consultation is to seek views from interested bodies on what consents should be moved within the scope of an expanded ‘one stop shop’ for major infrastructure and on proposals for streamlining the current list of statutory consultees that developers are required to consult before applying for a development consent order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"&gt;extend the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16960</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:10:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects"/>
    <title>Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects</title>
    <summary>Consultation seeking views on the proposal to extend the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime to business and commercial projects.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To help speed up planning decisions for the most complex projects and to increase choice for developers, the government proposes to extend the scope of the Planning Act 2008 so that a wider range of development can be brought within the nationally significant infrastructure planning regime. This will allow developers of nationally significant business or commercial projects to apply to the Secretary of State for the option of using the streamlined planning regime set out in the Planning Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views about the proposal to extend the nationally significant infrastructure regime and, in particular, about the types and forms of business and commercial projects to be prescribed in regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a separate consultation we are seeking views on proposals to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents"&gt;expand and improve the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16971</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:52:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:52:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient"/>
    <title>Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient</title>
    <summary>Ensuring that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date, safe and effective. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building regulations contain the rules for new and altered buildings to make them safe and accessible and limit waste and environmental damage. People carrying out building work must usually arrange for their work to be checked by an independent third party to make sure that their work meets the required standards. In some cases the installer can certify themselves that their work complies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building practices, technology and construction techniques are constantly evolving. We need to make sure that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (DGLC) is &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/review-of-building-regulations" title="Review of Building Regulations"&gt;reviewing building regulations in England&lt;/a&gt; to make sure they continue to be up to date and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to provide effective building regulations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing guidance that builders must comply with called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/approved-documents" title="Approved Documents"&gt;Approved Documents&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overseeing and supporting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/building-control-system" title="Building control system"&gt;building control organisations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorising competent person self-certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;producing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-circulars"&gt;circulars&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-divisional-circular-letters" title="Building regulations: divisional circular letters"&gt;divisional circular letters&lt;/a&gt; to formally tell interested parties about changes to building regulations policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-research"&gt;publishing research&lt;/a&gt; to provide a scientific basis to underpin the regulations   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adjudicating in disputes between people carrying out building work and a building control body through processes called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/determinations-and-appeals" title="Determinations and appeals"&gt;determinations and appeals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the secretariat for the &lt;a href="https://whitehall-admin.production.alphagov.co.uk/government/organisations/building-regulations-advisory-committee" title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England "&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England (&lt;abbr title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England"&gt;BRAC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; by March 2013, which advises the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government on the exercise of his or her power to make building regulations and on other related subjects in England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first set of national building standards were introduced with The Building Regulations 1965. These were a set of prescriptive standards that had to be followed.
The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1984/55" title="The Building Act - Legislation website"&gt;Building Act 1984&lt;/a&gt; brought fundamental changes to the building regulations regime. It introduced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;functional performance standards, set in terms of what was adequate, reasonable or appropriate, supported by statutory guidance in the Approved Documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;competition into the building control sector through the addition of private sector approved inspectors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes were introduced to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the standards more flexible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the system more efficient and effective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, there have been further changes to the legislation and the supporting guidance. These have sought to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the overall quality of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the effectiveness of the building regulations system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce any unnecessary burdens on those who use the system &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of July 2010 we ran an exercise to identify what changes are needed to ensure the building regulations continue to operate effectively in the future. We invited ordinary people, businesses and local authorities to submit their ideas about what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These views helped us decide the priority areas for further work and led to the development of a detailed package of proposals for changes to the building regulations. The proposals were contained in a consultation published on 31 January 2012 in 4 sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;section 1: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation overview and proposals on various technical aspects of the regulations&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 2: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;energy efficiency of buildings (Part L)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 3: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;electrical safety in homes (Part P)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 4: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;changes to the building control system&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, the Cabinet Office’s Red Tape Challenge has also looked at the potential to reduce the amount of regulation in this area. The next steps will be incorporated into our response to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="building-regulations-2010-and-building-approved-inspectors-etc-regulations-2010"&gt;Building Regulations 2010 and Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and all amendments to both, were revoked from 1 October 2010, and are no longer in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; consolidated the Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and incorporated all of the amendments made since 2000. The regulations were also renumbered and reordered to make them easier to use and with a more logical structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/718/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012(SI 2012/718)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2012. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011(SI 2011/1515)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 15 July 2011.  These should be read in conjunction with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has published the following circulars which help to explain the regulations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2011-circular-02-2011"&gt;Circular (02/2011)&lt;/a&gt; explains the amendments made by the Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-and-building-regulations-2010-circular-07-2010"&gt;Circular (07/2010)&lt;/a&gt; explains the 2010 regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16956</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:39:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/measures-to-reduce-bureaucratic-barriers-to-growth-and-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Measures to reduce bureaucratic barriers to growth and infrastructure</title>
    <summary>An expansion of the ‘one-stop-shop’ approach for considering nationally significant infrastructure projects will help boost growth and jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;, currently being considered in Parliament, will help the country compete on the global stage by introducing a comprehensive series of practical reforms that will reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals in the Bill include reducing the number of different consents infrastructure developers require. The government is also consulting on a new streamlined ‘one-stop-shop’ service and on reducing the number of bodies developers need to consult on every application. The proposed reforms will deliver a swifter, more efficient planning process while ensuring interested parties can continue to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms will also open up the fast-track planning process used for nationally significant infrastructure projects to additional types of nationally significant development. It will be open for the first time to business and commercial projects that are important to delivering growth and prosperity and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new types of developments that could be considered under the nationally significant infrastructure system include: manufacturing and major tourism and leisure proposals, office development such as research and development facilities, and warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers would be allowed to request that their application for these nationally significant business projects be determined through the infrastructure planning system which ensures decisions are made within 12 months from the beginning of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations on these two proposed reforms to the major infrastructure planning process were issued today. (See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects"&gt;extending the regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents"&gt;expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital we secure investment in new nationally significant infrastructure and commercial development, and that quicker and better planning decisions are made, if we are to help boost the economy and create the new jobs we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning delays help no one. They bring uncertainty for local people and local firms and can deter new investment all together. By streamlining the planning process to make it quicker and easier for these national significant projects to be decided we can ensure sustainable development gets underway without delay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reforms have already given significant additional powers to councils and communities so they can decide on the scale and location of development in their areas. With this power comes a responsibility to ensure that local planning decisions are efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will also give planning applicants the ability to apply directly to the Planning Inspectorate where there is clear evidence that a council’s planning service is performing very poorly and failing to administer a proper service for both applicants and local residents.  A consultation recently published sets out how these proposals would work, including the basis for assessing performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16917</id>
    <published>2012-11-24T11:13:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-24T11:13:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively"/>
    <title>Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively </title>
    <summary>We're simplifying the planning process to make it quicker and easier to build new homes, to develop new places and redevelop neglected land.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes planning decisions can take too long. This can slow down or prevent people building new homes, creating new places and bringing disused or neglected land and buildings back into productive use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that the planning rules or poorly managed planning processes do not unnecessarily prevent or delay development. We want to simplify planning approval processes and make our policies and guidance simpler and easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speed up the planning approval process, the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;provided a National Planning Policy Framework, the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;government’s view of what sustainable development means in practice&lt;/a&gt; for the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduced, or is introducing, a range of other measures to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/speeding-up-the-planning-process" title="Speeding up planning decisions"&gt;speed up planning decisions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To speed up planning for nationally significant infrastructure projects (such as wind farms or motorways) we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are reforming the infrastructure planning process to  make sure it remains efficient &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;want to extend the scope of the major infrastructure planning system to include new categories of commercial and business development so that, where they’re of sufficient significance, they can be determined at a national level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to ensure that the planning system stays effective and up to date.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make decisions about planning casework, compulsory purchase orders and land transaction cases through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abolished the Infrastructure Planning Commission on 1 April 2012, so that decisions on national infrastructure proposals are now made by ministers advised by the Planning Inspectorate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/called-in-planning-decisions-and-appeals" title="Called-in planning decisions and appeals"&gt;‘call-in’ planning decisions and appeals&lt;/a&gt; to be decided by the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oversee and support local planning authorities’ plan-making and decision-taking functions, mainly by providing planning laws, national planning policy and guidance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement set out the government’s commitment to publish and present to Parliament a simple and consolidated national planning framework covering all forms of development and setting out national economic, environmental and social priorities by April 2012. On 27 March 2012 the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; (the ‘Framework’) was published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework was produced following an extensive consultation with Parliament and the public.
The final Framework retains all of the most important elements of the draft Framework published in July 2011, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making sure the local plan - produced by communities - is the keystone of the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making planning much simpler and more accessible, reducing over 1,000 pages of often impenetrable jargon into around 50 pages of clearly written guidance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a presumption in favour of sustainable development that means that development is not held up unless to approve it would be against our collective interest &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;guaranteeing strong protections for the natural and historic environment, and requiring improvements to put right some of the neglect that has taken place &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;raising design standards so that the requirements for design are the most exacting yet &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve consulted on various aspects of planning reform, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allowing planning obligations to be renegotiated &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renegotiation-of-section-106-planning-obligations" title="Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations"&gt;Renegotiation of Section 106 planning obligations consultation&lt;/a&gt; to help get stalled development projects back on track&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating new opportunities to reuse existing buildings for sustainable development &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/reusing-existing-buildings-permitted-development-rights"&gt;New opportunities for sustainable development and growth through the reuse of existing buildings consultation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/streamlining-information-requirements-for-planning-applications"&gt;simplifying information requirements for planning applications&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; introduced a number of changes to the planning system, including transferring decisions on major infrastructure projects from the Infrastructure Planning Commission to ministers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further changes to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2008/29/contents"&gt;Planning Act 2008&lt;/a&gt; will be introduced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-we-are-working-with"&gt;Who we are working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities prepare development plans, based on consultation with local communities, which set out their overall plans for development in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local planning authorities are also responsible for development management. This includes making planning decisions, complying with the law about publicising, consulting on and determining most applications for planning permission, taking into account the opinions of local people and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also offer pre-application advice to prospective developers and enforce planning laws in their area. 
Appeals against refusal of planning permission and inquiries are dealt with by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/planning-inspectorate" title="Planning Inspectorate"&gt;Planning Inspectorate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.planningportal.gov.uk/" title="The Planning Portal"&gt;Planning Portal&lt;/a&gt; includes advice on planning permission, online applications and guidance on how the system works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on planning for major infrastructure projects can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://infrastructure.planningportal.gov.uk"&gt;Planning Inspectorate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
