<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15764</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/draft-national-planning-policy-framework"/>
    <title>Draft National Planning Policy Framework</title>
    <summary>A consultation on the draft National Planning Policy Framework: proposals to make the planning system less complex and more accessible</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft National Planning Policy Framework was published for consultation. This is a key part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more accessible, and to promote sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15804</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/development-rights-for-small-scale-renewable-and-low-carbon-energy-technologies-and-electric-vehicle-charging-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Development rights for small-scale renewable and low-carbon energy technologies and electric vehicle charging infrastructure</title>
    <summary>A consultation on the introduction of permitted development rights for small scale renewable and low carbon technologies in domestic and non-domestic settings.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sought views on government proposals to introduce permitted development rights for small scale renewable and low carbon technologies in domestic and non-domestic settings. It also sought views on introducing permitted development rights and deemed advertisement consent in relation to electric vehicle charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15362</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-traveller-sites"/>
    <title>Planning for traveller sites</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation on the government’s draft planning policy for traveller sites ended on 3 August, and a new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be published as soon as possible, following due consideration of the consultation responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also consulting on the draft &lt;em&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/em&gt; until 17 October. As part of this consultation, we welcome views on the consistency of the draft Framework with the draft planning policy for traveller sites, and any other comments about the government’s plans to incorporate planning policy on traveller sites into the final National Planning Policy Framework. The new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be reviewed in the light of all comments received and incorporated into the final National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the consultation on the National Planning Policy Framework, the government would welcome responses to the following question:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13410</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-east-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking  the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East Midlands Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East Midlands Regional Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13408</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking  the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the South East Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South East Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices. This includes whether or not to retain the Oxfordshire structure plan policy H2, covering development at Upper Heyford, until a revised plan is adopted by the relevant local planning authority (Cherwell District Council).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13406</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <summary>Consultation about transferring some planning functions from the Homes and Communities Agency to Milton Keynes Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13404</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-yorkshire-and-the-humber-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the Yorkshire and the Humber regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary>Consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking  the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12791</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-better-use-of-energy-performance-certificates-and-data"/>
    <title>Making better use of energy performance certificates and data</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Energy performance certificates (EPC) and display energy certificates (DEC) have an important role to play in supporting our carbon reduction aims by providing vital information about the energy efficiency of buildings in England and Wales and advice about measures to improve their energy performance. To enhance their contribution, we are consulting on a number of measures to help improve the effectiveness of EPCs and to make better use of energy performance data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12784</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-town-and-country-planning-environmental-impact-assessment-regulations-2010"/>
    <title>The town and country planning environmental impact assessment regulations 2010</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper covers the consolidation of the 1999 environmental impact assessment regulations, as amended, and explains amendments for screening changes and extensions. It also explains the requirement for the competent authority to provide reasons for screening decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12779</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-schools-development"/>
    <title>Planning for schools development</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation document invites views on the government’s proposals to make changes to the general permitted development order to give a permitted development right for change of use planning permission for schools development. The purpose of the proposals set out in this document is to support the Department for Education’s policy on new free schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
