<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T17:04:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56381</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T17:04:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:04:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/no-hidden-costs-to-home-improvement"/>
    <title>No hidden costs to home improvement</title>
    <summary>Homeowners will not face red tape when building conservatories and extensions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government today announced that anyone looking to improve their home through measures such as building a conservatory will not be subject to any rules requiring them to carry out additional building works on other parts of the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals for ‘consequential improvements’ - whereby work on one part of a home would trigger a requirement to carry out energy efficiency improvement works throughout, such as the installation of loft or cavity wall insulation - would in fact deter many people from having any work done in the first place, ministers believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having consulted carefully, the government has noted the potential danger that introducing consequential improvements would, in fact, discourage people from undertaking home improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This measure ensures that it will remain straightforward for hard-working homeowners to undertake small-scale home improvements and conservatories.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January this year the Department for Communities and Local Government published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; on reforms to building regulations in England, aimed at providing significant savings to business, whilst ensuring buildings remain safe and sustainable. The consultation asked for views on whether to require ‘consequential improvements’ to the energy efficiency of a home when other building work such as the creation of extensions, large conservatories, loft and garage conversions was undertaken, or when boilers or a number of the home’s windows were replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most conservatories would not have been affected by such proposals ministers have carefully considered responses to the consultation, as well as research of the effects on homeowners and building professionals by the Energy Saving Trust and AECOM respectively. The Energy Saving Trust research indicated that over a third of households would be put off from doing home improvements if they had to undertake consequential improvements as well. The research also revealed concerns that there was greater potential for cowboy builders to mislead customers over what consequential improvements would be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the government’s growth agenda and the proposed lifting of planning rules to make it easier for people to carry out sensible extensions and improvements to their home Ministers have decided it would be inappropriate to place an additional cost on building owners. The Green Deal will continue to provide financial incentives to homeowners looking to improve their home’s energy efficiency, cut carbon emissions and reduce their long term energy bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minor-consequential-improvements"&gt;Written statement on minor consequential improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-l-proposals-for-consequential-improvements-in-existing-homes-report-of-focus-groups"&gt;Changes to Part L of the building regulations: proposals for consequential improvements in existing homes - report of focus groups&lt;/a&gt;, AECOM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.energysavingtrust.org.uk/Publications2/Corporate/Research-and-insights/Building-regulations-and-Green-Deal-research-report"&gt;Exploratory Research into Building Regulations in relation to the Green Deal&lt;/a&gt;, Energy Saving Trust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56460</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:01:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-l-proposals-for-consequential-improvements-in-existing-homes-report-of-focus-groups"/>
    <title>Building Regulations Part L: proposals for consequential improvements in existing homes - report of focus groups</title>
    <summary>This report examines the views of small businesses and building control officers on changes to consequential improvements in existing homes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government commissioned AECOM to research and examine the views of small businesses (gas safe engineers, competent persons, small builders and small architects) and building control officers on proposed changes to part L of the building regulations for consequential improvements in existing homes. This report details the findings from the 4 focus groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals are part of a package of changes to the building regulations published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; in January 2012, and this research was part of the consultation exercise. All the proposals described in this report are subject to consultation, and nothing in this document is a statement of government policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56280</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:03:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minor-consequential-improvements"/>
    <title>Minor consequential improvements</title>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles on changes to the building regulations on energy efficiency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, the Department for Communities and Local Government published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; on reforms to building regulations in England. The proposals contained a strong deregulatory element which seeks to deliver real and significant savings to business, whilst ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department will shortly publish details of some of the deregulatory reforms stemming from that consultation. However, I wanted to inform honourable members of the government’s conclusion on one aspect that attracted significant public and media attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation sought views on whether to require ‘consequential improvements’ to the energy efficiency of a dwelling when other defined building work was undertaken, such as (a) extensions or increases in habitable space (ie loft and integral garage conversions) and (b) the replacement of a boiler or a percentage of the home’s windows. Such proposals were coined as a ‘conservatory tax’, although it should be noted that most conservatories would not have been affected by such proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers have carefully considered the responses to the consultation. We have also taken into account quantitative research work by the Energy Saving Trust of householders and qualitative analysis by AECOM of building professionals, which I have today placed in the library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Energy Saving Trust research found that consequential improvements, even with Green Deal finance in place, would put off 38% of households from going ahead with building work on their property that they were otherwise planning (Energy Saving Trust, ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.energysavingtrust.org.uk/Publications2/Corporate/Research-and-insights/Building-regulations-and-Green-Deal-research-report"&gt;Exploratory Research into Building Regulations in relation to the Green Deal&lt;/a&gt;’, p.37).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AECOM focus groups found that the majority of the installers registered with Gas Safe Register or members of competent person schemes were very negative towards the idea of being responsible for informing homeowners of the consequential improvement requirements. They observed that given the current economic climate, increased costs would make it harder to win work - homeowners may be deterred from getting the work done or delay commissioning the work. There was concern that by leaving the responsibility to inform homeowners to the installer, it could increase dishonesty in the market. It would potentially present rogue traders with an opportunity either to not inform homeowners of the requirements (to keep costs down), or to inflate the requirements and ‘rip people off’ (AECOM, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-l-proposals-for-consequential-improvements-in-existing-homes-report-of-focus-groups"&gt;Changes to Part L of the building regulations: proposals for consequential improvements in existing homes - report of focus groups&lt;/a&gt;’, p.5). There were also concerns about non-compliance, with homeowners facing prosecution and £5,000 fines, leading to widespread problems with enforcement (p.44).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these concerns point to the danger that introducing consequential improvements would, in fact, discourage people from undertaking home improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having considered all the representations and evidence, including the public reaction, I can inform the House that we will not be going ahead with such regulatory proposals in any way at this point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding, there is significant scope to promote take up of the voluntary Green Deal, which allows householders - if they choose - to improve the energy efficiency of their home without any upfront cost. We intend to work with the industry and local authorities to help increase awareness of the Green Deal amongst householders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, it is my department’s stated policy (as outlined in my &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201213/cmhansrd/cm120906/wmstext/120906m0001.htm"&gt;statement of 6 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 29WS) to make it easier for householders to undertake small-scale home improvements and conservatories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cancellation of the council tax revaluation (as outlined in my &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm101011/wmstext/101011m0001.htm"&gt;statement of 11 October 2010&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 1WS) has also avoided the imposition of higher council taxes on home improvements. As explained in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201212/cmhansrd/cm120430/text/120430w0002.htm#1205012000001"&gt;answer of 30 April 2012&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 1105W, we have also discontinued the revaluation database and ceased the intrusive collection of data on the scenic views, gardens and patios of families’ homes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/48337</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:35:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:35:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient"/>
    <title>Providing effective building regulations so that new and altered buildings are safe, accessible and efficient</title>
    <summary>Ensuring that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date, safe and effective. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building regulations contain the rules for new and altered buildings to make them safe and accessible and limit waste and environmental damage. People carrying out building work must usually arrange for their work to be checked by an independent third party to make sure that their work meets the required standards. In some cases the installer can certify themselves that their work complies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building practices, technology and construction techniques are constantly evolving. We need to make sure that building regulations are fair, efficient, up to date and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government (DGLC) is &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/review-of-building-regulations" title="Review of Building Regulations"&gt;reviewing building regulations in England&lt;/a&gt; to make sure they continue to be up to date and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; also carries out many ongoing actions to provide effective building regulations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing guidance that builders must comply with called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/approved-documents" title="Approved Documents"&gt;Approved Documents&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overseeing and supporting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/building-control-system" title="Building control system"&gt;building control organisations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorising competent person self-certification schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;producing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-circulars"&gt;circulars&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/building-regulations-divisional-circular-letters" title="Building regulations: divisional circular letters"&gt;divisional circular letters&lt;/a&gt; to formally tell interested parties about changes to building regulations policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/building-regulations-research"&gt;publishing research&lt;/a&gt; to provide a scientific basis to underpin the regulations   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adjudicating in disputes between people carrying out building work and a building control body through processes called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-effective-building-regulations-so-that-new-and-altered-buildings-are-safe-accessible-and-efficient/supporting-pages/determinations-and-appeals" title="Determinations and appeals"&gt;determinations and appeals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the secretariat for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/building-regulations-advisory-committee"&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England (&lt;abbr title="Building Regulations Advisory Committee for England"&gt;BRAC&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; by March 2013, which advises the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government on the exercise of his or her power to make building regulations and on other related subjects in England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first set of national building standards were introduced with The Building Regulations 1965. These were a set of prescriptive standards that had to be followed.
The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1984/55" title="The Building Act - Legislation website"&gt;Building Act 1984&lt;/a&gt; brought fundamental changes to the building regulations regime. It introduced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;functional performance standards, set in terms of what was adequate, reasonable or appropriate, supported by statutory guidance in the Approved Documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;competition into the building control sector through the addition of private sector approved inspectors &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes were introduced to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the standards more flexible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the system more efficient and effective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, there have been further changes to the legislation and the supporting guidance. These have sought to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the overall quality of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve the effectiveness of the building regulations system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce any unnecessary burdens on those who use the system &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of July 2010 we ran an exercise to identify what changes are needed to ensure the building regulations continue to operate effectively in the future. We invited ordinary people, businesses and local authorities to submit their ideas about what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These views helped us decide the priority areas for further work and led to the development of a detailed package of proposals for changes to the building regulations. The proposals were contained in a consultation published on 31 January 2012 in 4 sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;section 1: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation overview and proposals on various technical aspects of the regulations&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 2: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;energy efficiency of buildings (Part L)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 3: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;electrical safety in homes (Part P)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;section 4: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;changes to the building control system&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, the Cabinet Office’s Red Tape Challenge has also looked at the potential to reduce the amount of regulation in this area. The next steps will be incorporated into our response to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="legislation"&gt;Legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="building-regulations-2010-and-building-approved-inspectors-etc-regulations-2010"&gt;Building Regulations 2010 and Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and all amendments to both, were revoked from 1 October 2010, and are no longer in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt; consolidated the Building Regulations 2000 and the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2000, and incorporated all of the amendments made since 2000. The regulations were also renumbered and reordered to make them easier to use and with a more logical structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/718/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012(SI 2012/718)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2012. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2215/contents/made"&gt;Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011(SI 2011/1515)&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 15 July 2011.  These should be read in conjunction with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2010/2214/contents/made"&gt;Building Regulations 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government has published the following circulars which help to explain the regulations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2011-circular-02-2011"&gt;Circular (02/2011)&lt;/a&gt; explains the amendments made by the Building (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-and-building-regulations-2010-circular-07-2010"&gt;Circular (07/2010)&lt;/a&gt; explains the 2010 regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <summary>Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles has announced a major milestone in the transfer of power to local communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/48343</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy in force for the East of England).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East of England regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East of England Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/39682</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <summary>Consultation about transferring some planning functions from the Homes and Communities Agency to Milton Keynes Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/39671</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T17:19:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/energy-performance-of-buildings-directive-article-8-equivalence-uk-biennial-reports"/>
    <title>Energy Performance of Buildings Directive article 8 equivalence - UK biennial reports</title>
    <summary>Equivalence reports produced by the Building Research Establishment.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive, published in January 2003, is designed to improve the energy efficiency of buildings across Europe. Article 8 of the Directive is specifically aimed at improving the performance of heating systems. The directive offers two alternatives for implementing article 8: option (a) which involves the implementation of an inspection regime; or option (b) which involves the provision of advice, but this option can also include ‘alternative solutions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has chosen to adopt option (b) and has prepared biennial Article 8 equivalence reports to demonstrate that this approach has an impact that is ‘broadly equivalent’ to that produced through the provisions of option (a).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reports were produced in January 2008 and November 2010 and we are publishing them in the interests of transparency and as part of our Freedom of Information commitment to publish the results of all commissioned research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17572</id>
    <published>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-02T14:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/zero-carbon-for-new-non-domestic-buildings"/>
    <title>Zero carbon for new non-domestic buildings</title>
    <summary>Consultation about working towards the government's ambition for all new non-domestic buildings to be zero carbon from 2019.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out proposals for working towards the government’s ambition that all new non-domestic buildings should be zero carbon from 2019, with the public sector leading the way from 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/17674</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T15:15:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T15:15:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development"/>
    <title>Giving communities more power in planning local development</title>
    <summary>Giving local people and councils more say about development through neighbourhood planning, Local Plans and the community infrastructure levy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want people to be able to influence decisions about new and modified buildings and facilities in their area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have the right to get involved in development decisions that affect them but in practice they have often found it difficult to have a meaningful say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give people more control over the development of their local area, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving communities the power to set the priorities for local development through &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning" title="Neighbourhood planning"&gt;neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requiring local planning authorities to draw up clear, up-to-date &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/local-plans" title="Local Plans"&gt;Local Plans&lt;/a&gt; that conforms with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework" title="National Planning Policy Framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;, meets local development needs and reflects local people’s views of how they wish their area to develop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils the power to raise money to support local infrastructure through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy"&gt;community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils new powers to stop unwanted development on gardens (so-called ‘garden grabbing’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a commitment in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf" title="Coalition agreement"&gt;coalition agreement (PDF 475KB)&lt;/a&gt; to give people more power over development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 introduced new powers for people to make neighbourhood plans and neighbourhood planning orders, with reduced interference from central government. These new powers are in addition to existing opportunities for community involvement, which are already part of the planning system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/neighbourhood-planning-regulations--2" title="Neighbourhood planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed regulations for neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; between October 2011 and January 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy" title="Community infrastructure levy consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the community infrastructure levy&lt;/a&gt; between October and December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also consulted on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-planning-regulations" title="Local planning regulations consultation"&gt;proposed changes to the regulations which govern the process by which local councils prepare their development plans&lt;/a&gt; between July and October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neighbourhood planning provisions are contained in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted" title="Localism Act 2011"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/637/contents/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (General) Regulations 2012"&gt;Neighbourhood planning legislation&lt;/a&gt; came into effect in April 2012. Further legislation covering the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2031/made" title="The Neighbourhood Planning (Referendums) Regulations 2012"&gt;referendum stage of neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 2 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/987/contents/made" title="Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 6 April 2011.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/2918/contents/made" title="The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011"&gt;The Local Authorities (Contracting Out of Community Infrastructure Levy Functions) Order 2011&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 7 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2975/contents/made"&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 29 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
