<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/planning-and-building</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/planning-and-building.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Planning and building"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59998</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:31:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-building-control-system-introduction-of-risk-based-service-plans-for-local-authorities-and-removal-of-the-warranty-link-rule"/>
    <title>Changes to the building control system: introduction of risk-based service plans for local authorities and removal of the Warranty Link Rule</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out the proposed changes to the building control system including introduction of risk-based service plans for local authorities and removal of the Warranty Link Rule. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This updates the consultation impact assessment version which was a supporting document for section 4 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system" title="Building regulations: the building control system"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60040</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:34:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improving-the-energy-efficiency-of-our-buildings"/>
    <title>Recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Energy Performance of Buildings Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings. The requirements of the Directive were implemented on a phased basis by the Energy Performance of Buildings (Certificates and Inspections) (England and Wales) Regulations 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key requirements were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be produced on the sale, rent or construction of a building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;display energy certificate to be produced and displayed in large public buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;air conditioning equipment above a certain size to be inspected regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes have been made to the regulations, to transpose the requirements of a recast of the Energy Performance of Buildings Directive in England and Wales. The main requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013 and are summarised below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;property advertisements to include details of energy performance certificate rating where available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no longer a requirement to attach front page of the energy performance certificate to written material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extension of current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m².  Unlike buildings larger than 1,000m²,  display energy certificates for smaller public buildings will be valid for 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy performance certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² where one has been previously issued&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidance documents have been revised to reflect the changes and can be viewed via the links above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new regulations consolidate all existing regulations which have been revoked. They are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/" title="legislation.gov.uk"&gt;legislation.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59982</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:30:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-act-1984-building-amendment-regulations-2012-circular-02-2012"/>
    <title>The Building Act 1984, Building (Amendment) Regulations 2012: Circular 02/2012</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this Circular is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw attention to these amendments and explain the changes they make to the Building Regulations 2010, the Building (Approved Inspectors etc.) Regulations 2010, the Building (Local Authority Charges) Regulations 2010 and various Local Acts listed in Annex D to this Circular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explain the transitional provisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;announce the approval and publication of new Approved Documents K, P and Regulation 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;announce the amendments to other Approved Documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;announce the authorisation of new and extended competent person schemes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Circular does not give advice on the technical requirements of Part K, Part P or Regulation 7 as these are matters covered by Approved Documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a priced publication available from TSO (The Stationery Office), PO Box 29, Norwich NR3 1GN. Order through the Parliamentary Hotline (Lo-call): 08457 023 474, fax: 0870 600 5533, textphone 0870 240 3701, email: &lt;a href="mailto:book.orders@tso.co.uk" title="mailto:book.orders@tso.co.uk"&gt;book.orders@tso.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tsoshop.co.uk/" title="TSO"&gt;www.tsoshop.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; to buy online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60107</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T10:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/evaluating-access-statement-requirements-in-part-m-of-the-building-regulations-and-minor-technical-amendments-to-part-m-of-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Evaluating access statement requirements in Part M of the building regulations and minor technical amendments to Part M of the building regulations</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out proposed changes to the way in which applicants demonstrate compliance with Part M (Access to and use of buildings) of the Building Regulations and provides an analysis of associated costs and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes support a risk based approach to demonstrating compliance by moving away from reliance on written access statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment updates the consultation impact assessment which was a supporting document for Section 1 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7" title="Building regulations: access statements, security, changing places toilets and regulation 7"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60035</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:33:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/consolidation-and-simplification-of-parts-m-k-and-n-of-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Consolidation and simplification of Parts M, K and N of the building regulations   </title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out proposed changes to Parts K (protection from collision falling and impact), Part M (access to and use of buildings) and Part N (glazing) of the building regulations and provides analysis of the associated costs and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals are not intended to make changes to technical requirements but will simplify compliance and reduce confusion and complexity for industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment updates the consultation impact assessment which was a supporting document for Section 1 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60037</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:33:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-p-electrical-safety-in-dwellings"/>
    <title>Building regulations Part P: electrical safety in dwellings</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out the proposed changes to Part P of the building regulations and provides an analysis of the associated costs and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals aim to reduce the bureaucracy and cost burdens that Part P imposes on installers, building control bodies and consumers, without undermining the improvements to electrical safety, installer competence and the quality of electrical installation work arising from the introduction of Part P in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment updates the consultation impact assessment which was a supporting document for Section 3 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60042</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:31:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/simplifying-the-provisions-of-part-b2-of-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Simplifying the provisions of Part B2 of the building regulations</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out the proposed changes to the provisions of requirement B2 of the building regulations relating to internal fire spread (linings).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes are intended to reduce the burden of these provisions on thermoplastic lighting diffusers and decorative wallcoverings whilst maintaining adequate levels of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment updates the consultation impact assessment which was a supporting document for Section 1 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60048</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:30:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-building-approved-inspectors-and-charges-amendment-regulations-2012-authorisation-of-new-extended-competent-person-schemes"/>
    <title>The Building, Approved Inspectors and Charges (Amendment) Regulations 2012: authorisation of new extended competent person schemes</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This final impact assessment sets out the costs to authorise one new competent person scheme operator for an existing type of work, and the extension of scope for 7 existing competent person scheme operators to cover both existing types of work and 3 new types of work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment updates the consultation impact assessment which was a supporting document for Section 4 of the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-the-building-control-system"&gt;Building Regulations consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60078</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:35:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/further-economic-and-analytical-support-for-proposals-to-amend-the-building-regulations-in-2013"/>
    <title>Further economic and analytical support for proposals to amend the building regulations in 2013</title>
    <summary>This report provides support to the evaluation work being carried out by the department on changes to the building regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government commissioned EC Harris to provide economic and analytical information to support evaluation work being carried out by the department on changes to the building regulations due to come into force in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research project was to provide information to help inform impact assessments of potential changes to the building regulations in 2013. It also investigated the impact of other changes to the building regulations that are not currently being taken forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17814</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:17:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/statutory-consultee-performance-and-award-of-costs"/>
    <title>Statutory consultee performance and award of costs</title>
    <summary>Proposals to amend guidance on awards in appeals and other planning proceedings.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes to amend guidance in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/costs-awards-in-appeals-and-other-planning-proceedings-circular-03-2009"&gt;Circular 03/09: Costs Awards in Appeals and Other Planning Proceedings&lt;/a&gt; in relation to statutory consultees and their advice at appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also announced clarifications to the guidance in relation to local councils and their development plan, and in relation to ensuring evidence submitted at appeal is manifestly accurate and truthful. The government is also requiring the 5 main statutory bodies to report on, and be accountable for their performance on dealing with planning applications as part of their individual Improvement Plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of responses was published on 18 December 2012. The report above summarises the key issues raised and provides a revised addendum to circular 03/09.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
