<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Public safety and emergencies"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55268</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65m contract to refit Royal Navy's largest warship secures hundreds of UK jobs</title>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65M upgrade, the MOD announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on the helicopter carrier will secure more than 600 UK jobs. The warship was moored on the Thames during the Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;Devonport Royal Dockyard&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to her radar, gun, command system and living quarters. Around 1,200 metres of new pipe work will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter number 10 dock at Devonport Royal Naval Dockyard to begin her refit 
[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible, and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympic duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache attack helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12844</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-operational-readiness-to-provide-military-support-for-activities-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>Maintaining operational readiness to provide military support for activities in the UK</title>
    <summary>Civil authorities have resources to cope with a wide range of emergencies but if they lack capability or are overwhelmed by the scale of events they can ask the Ministry of Defence for assistance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is constantly refining its ability to provide an effective response to all types of emergencies and major crises at national, regional and local level. This means having a pre-planned, coordinated response from the emergency services, civil authorities and where appropriate, the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is an emergency or crisis situation in the UK, local emergency services provide the first response. Government departments or civil authorities can also call on the Ministry of Defence for military help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces support is officially known as Military Aid to the Civil Authorities (MACA). The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/36/contents"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; states that military support is available for major incidents when the capability or capacity of civilian authorities has been overwhelmed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no standing military forces for these tasks so support isn’t guaranteed and when it is provided the civil authorities normally have to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces can be brought in to deal with a range of situations including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural disasters - helping people in severe weather situations, such as flooding, where there is a need to protect human life, property and alleviate distress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network failure or disruption - including animal disease epidemics and public service-related industrial disputes that affect our safety or security, or disrupt transport or communications links&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;criminal or terrorist activity - where there is a need, providing specialist expertise in specific circumstances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bomb disposal - known officially as ‘explosive ordnance disposal’, this can be related to terrorism, or involve unearthing a bomb from World War 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue - helping people in danger, searching for sunken vessels or aircraft, carrying out underwater or mountain rescue tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK waters - protecting our territorial waters, ports, ships and energy installations from terrorist attack, protecting fisheries, preventing drug or people smuggling and dealing with pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK airspace - detecting and deterring aircraft approaching UK sovereign airspace and protecting UK and NATO monitored airspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of recent emergencies and crises that needed help from the armed forces include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing security for the 2012 Olympics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue operations during widespread flooding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping UK travellers stranded by the Icelandic ash cloud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;managing the disposal of infected cattle during the ‘mad cow’ disease outbreak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detailed information for civil authorities on handling crises is contained in the guidance &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-response-and-recovery"&gt;Emergency Response and Recovery&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-preparedness"&gt;Emergency Preparedness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/securing-britain-age-uncertainty-strategic-defence-and-security-review"&gt;Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR): Securing Britain in an age of uncertainty 2010&lt;/a&gt; sets out how the defence establishment will contribute effectively to civil crises and emergencies in the UK, balancing against other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-strategy-for-deploying-the-armed-forces-in-the-uk"&gt;The strategy for deploying the Armed Forces in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All defence operations including those in the UK must be authorised by the Defence Council. The Secretary of State for Defence is the government minister responsible for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and there is a single chain of command that connects to service personnel on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a crisis the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Deputy Chief of the Defence Staff (Military Strategy and Operations) and the Director General Security Policy give guidance to ministers and other government departments. In this way, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; acts as both a military HQ and a department of state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Contingencies Act 2004 (&lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) defines how organisations, particularly local responders, prepare for emergencies. In the event of an emergency in which the supply and distribution of the essentials of life to the community are extensively threatened, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt; can be used to invoke emergency powers on a local, regional or national basis. The full &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/civil-contingencies-act"&gt;text of the Act&lt;/a&gt; is available from the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to deploy service personnel would be authorised by the Defence Council and they may be given the power to requisition equipment and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 2 of the the Emergency Powers Act 1964, the Defence Council may authorise the temporary deployment of service personnel on urgent work of national importance. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1964/38/contents"&gt;Read the full text of the Act&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39721</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <summary>Royal Marines and Albanian forces recently joined together for an assault on an abandoned Soviet submarine base as part of Exercise Albanian Lion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17621</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T10:24:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-28-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 28/2012</title>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consultation on proposed increases to employee pension contribution rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;departmental response to the consultation on amendments to the new Firefighters’ Pension Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update on the funding arrangements for localising support for council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government’s policy statement on business rates retention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of operational guidance and generic risk assessments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescues from lifts and escalators to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17112</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-5-7-incidents-involving-explosives"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 5.7: incidents involving explosives</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about incidents involving explosives to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 5.7 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to incidents involving ‘commercial’ explosives, while in manufacture, storage or transportation. It does not cover improvised explosive devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in November 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16920</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T12:36:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-reforms"/>
    <title>Firefighters’ pension scheme reforms</title>
    <summary>Details of the firefighters' pension scheme from 2015.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides details of the firefighters’ pension scheme from 2015. It relates to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-heads-of-agreement"&gt;heads
of agreement&lt;/a&gt; on the core parameters for reforms to the firefighters’ pension scheme that was published by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 9 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16737</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T16:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hazardous-materials-operational-guidance-for-the-fire-and-rescue-service"/>
    <title>Hazardous materials: operational guidance for the fire and rescue service</title>
    <summary>Best practice guidance to help fire and rescue authorities to resolve incidents involving hazardous materials safely and efficiently.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides comprehensive yet flexible guidance that can be adapted to the nature, scale and requirements of the incident. It consolidates the content of over 500 items of previously published subject related documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16085</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:54:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/asian-fire-service-association-afsa-conference"/>
    <title>Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference</title>
    <summary>Speech by Brandon Lewis to the Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be invited to speak here today and to see so many others here to support you. I understand that this is the fifth AFSA national conference, and my predecessor Bob Neill has spoken at the last 2. I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Bob, who has a deep understanding of the issues you face, as well as a great knowledge of the sector. I know that Bob, when he was Fire Minister, greatly valued the close and positive relationship he had with AFSA. I very much hope to be able to continue that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-afsa"&gt;The importance of AFSA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of groups such as AFSA cannot be underestimated. You provide a forum for people to come together to discuss key concerns, to support each other’s development, and provide an opportunity for challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of challenge, AFSA continues to perform a vital role in terms of ensuring that equality, diversity and fairness are mainstreamed in the Fire and Rescue Service. Events such as this provide excellent opportunities for the exchange of ideas, and for lively debate. I know that a regional AFSA group has been set up here in the West Midlands, supporting professional development and progression, sharing learning experiences, building a solid network of mutual support for employees, and supporting charities and fundraising. All of this shows the excellent work that the association is doing both at the national and local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="promoting-equality-and-diversity"&gt;Promoting equality and diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that Sir Graham Meldrum, when he was Chief Fire Officer in the West Midlands and again as Chief Inspector of Her Majesty’s Fire Service Inspectorate did a great amount of work to promote equality and diversity in the service, and this excellent work has been carried on by Vij as Chief Fire Officer of the West Midlands, and in his presidency of the Chief Fire Officers Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to say, on a personal note, that I am deeply committed to advancing equality of opportunity to one and all, not only in the fire and rescue service, but also in the communities they live in and serve. I am also of the firm conviction that this is best driven locally. And I say this because I want each fire and rescue authority to be responsible for reaching out to minority groups, and ensuring that they recognise that the service is for them - not as an add on - but for them along with everyone else in the community. I want fire and rescue services to go out into their communities, find the right people, engage with them and draw them into the heart of the fire and rescue service family. I want the entire community to be so integrated into the fire and rescue service that we no longer have to think in terms of equality and diversity - it will just happen automatically. I know that this is at the core of what AFSA is working for, and you have my full support in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt, a lot is already happening, and I would like to highlight some of the work going on here in the West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service. They have Welcome to the West Midlands, an education programme for new migrants to promote safety, well being, community understanding and citizenship. This has been developed in consultation with migrants to meet the information gap which can occur when someone arrives in this country. The West Midlands also has active employee engagement through the local AFSA group, working with them to target under represented operational and support staff to develop essential skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my short time as Fire Minister I have been very impressed by the wide range of local initiatives such as these, which not only reach out to the under represented, but also to the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, the fire service is leading a community project with the Asian Development Association of Bury. This project, which provided employment opportunities for local people, has already seen the production of a fire safety video that can be heard in eight of Manchester’s most commonly used languages. It will be the main communication tool used in community education sessions, facilitated by fire and rescue service volunteers recruited by the association. There will also be a series of workshops for the &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; business community designed to raise awareness of how the fire and rescue service can help them meet their responsibilities under the Fire Safety Order. This project will be rolled out across all of Manchester’s ten metropolitan boroughs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage young people from a community they have previously found hard to reach, and to respect religious beliefs, they have established a cadet scheme in Hyde for young women from the Bangladeshi community, and they are hoping to use this as a model to engage many ethnic communities in similar activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is being driven forward at the local level - not by central target or quotas, but by responding to the demands of their local communities. And to be able to respond to these, each fire and rescue service needs to make full use of the human resources at their disposal - and to do this equality and diversity has to be at the core of any organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to delivering the best service to the local community is to have a diverse, representative workforce, equipped to understand and meet the needs of those it serves and capable of delivering a first class service to everyone. This will also support the service’s aim to create a better understanding of its preventative role and of the support and advice it is able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire service must ensure that every employee is valued; that there truly is equality of opportunity for all, and that the working culture is such that unfair discrimination, unacceptable behaviour, bullying and harassment are not tolerated. I strongly believe that the fire and rescue service has gone a long way to achieve this goal and together with partners like AFSA they can continue to work to create an even more open and inclusive service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-kills"&gt;Fire Kills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also like to take this opportunity to thank AFSA for your continued support of the Fire Kills campaign. The Fire Kills campaign has had a focus on &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; groups since 2005 - and for good reason. Research has shown that certain &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; communities are at a potentially greater risk from fire. Smoke alarm ownership amongst Asian communities is ten per cent lower than the national average.  Recent analysis of accidental dwelling fire victim profiles has suggested that Asian communities are potentially more vulnerable than African communities. This has led to our 2012 campaign focussing solely on the Bangladeshi and Pakistani communities. With smoke alarm ownership levels lower in these communities the primary message will be on the importance of working smoke alarms. Two bursts of advertising will run - one which began this week, and another in March 2013. The new campaign will focus on blessings. As you know blessing of wellbeing, health and a long life are delivered on important occasions in these communities. The new campaign will encourage people to make their blessings count - ‘when you give a blessing, make it count: test your smoke alarm’. There will be radio advertising to demonstrate the fire consequences of not having a working smoke alarm, linking it back to a blessing that was given. I have no doubt that this campaign, targeted primarily at first generation Pakistani and Bangladeshi communities, will be a powerful tool for you and all those in fire and rescue services seeking to reduce deaths and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-position"&gt;Economic position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of this conference is ‘advancing equality during austerity’. I think that it is important to note that there are signs of improvement in the economy. Jobs are being created, manufacturing and exports have grown as a share of our economy, our trade with vibrant, emerging economies such as China and Brazil is improving, and the world is once again investing in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we face many challenges. The debts built up over many years will take time to work our way through, not helped by a decline in our competitiveness which was effectively masked by unsustainable borrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to cut the national deficit, fire and rescue, as a frontline emergency service, has been given funding protection with reductions back-loaded to give more time for sensible savings to be made, and reductions applied to fire and rescue authorities have been less than those applied to local authorities in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been heartened to hear how many fire and rescue authorities have risen to the challenges that the spending review has posed. However, I know some of you have concerns that fire and rescue services may disproportionately reduce funding on equality and diversity activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this is not the case. But if you see this happening, then you must speak up. It is vital that fire and rescue services do not make decisions that will impact on their ability to deliver on their statutory duties as required under the Equality Act 2010, and transparency and accountability are at the heart of our approach towards local government generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing I would like to thank you once again for giving me this opportunity to speak to you today. I do hope that your organisation goes from strength to strength, and that you remain and important and influential voice in the British fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to extend my congratulations to all the award winners who will be honoured at this evening’s event, well done, keep up the good work and have a great night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35161</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T09:28:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-fleet-of-rfa-tankers-named"/>
    <title>New fleet of RFA tankers named</title>
    <summary>Four new Royal Fleet Auxiliary (RFA) tankers, which will be bought as part of the Military Afloat Reach and Sustainability (MARS) programme, will be called the Tide Class.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 37,000-tonne ships will come into service from 2016 to replace the RFA’s single-hulled tankers, and will maintain the Royal Navy’s dedicated bulk fuel replenishment at sea capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 200-metre long tankers will also be able to carry helicopters and will support Royal Navy warships deployed around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the RFA, Commodore Bill Walworth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that the MARS fleet tankers will be called the Tide Class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The original Tides were the first purpose-built fleet tankers to support aircraft carriers and were highly successful and popular ships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new Tides promise to be better still. A large number of people have worked hard to get us to this point, with the ships on contract and the first to be delivered into service in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tidespring, Tiderace, Tidesurge and Tideforce, which is a new name, will be superb ships that will reflect the successful past and a confident future for the RFA service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ships will be built by Daewoo Shipbuilding and Marine Engineering to a design provided by UK company BMT Defence Services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The new Tide Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary tankers will come into service from 2016 " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1659/New_fleet_of_RFA_tankers_named2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The new Tide Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary tankers will come into service from 2016 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, UK companies will benefit from up to £150m of associated spending on key equipment, systems, design and support services, and on the customisation and trials package which will take place in the UK once the ships have been built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original Tide Class fleet tankers served in the RFA from 1954 until 1991, operating worldwide in support of numerous operations and exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developed using the lessons of the Pacific Campaign in the Second World War, these versatile ships were the first purpose-designed replenishment tankers for the RFA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying bulk fuels, oil and fresh water they replenished aircraft carriers and warships, both British and Allied, enabling task groups to remain at sea for extended periods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tidespring - the original Tidespring was awarded a battle honour in 1982&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tiderace - after service in the Suez Crisis, the Tiderace was renamed the Tideflow to avoid confusion with another ship name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tidesurge - originally launched as RFA Tiderange in 1954, she spent many of her early years east of Suez and served until 1976&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tideforce - a new name in the RFA service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
