<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Public safety and emergencies"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17112</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-5-7-incidents-involving-explosives"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 5.7: incidents involving explosives</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about incidents involving explosives to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 5.7 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to incidents involving ‘commercial’ explosives, while in manufacture, storage or transportation. It does not cover improvised explosive devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in November 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescues from lifts and escalators to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16920</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T12:36:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-reforms"/>
    <title>Firefighters’ pension scheme reforms</title>
    <summary>Details of the firefighters' pension scheme from 2015.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides details of the firefighters’ pension scheme from 2015. It relates to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-heads-of-agreement"&gt;heads
of agreement&lt;/a&gt; on the core parameters for reforms to the firefighters’ pension scheme that was published by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 9 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16737</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T16:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hazardous-materials-operational-guidance-for-the-fire-and-rescue-service"/>
    <title>Hazardous materials: operational guidance for the fire and rescue service</title>
    <summary>Best practice guidance to help fire and rescue authorities to resolve incidents involving hazardous materials safely and efficiently.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides comprehensive yet flexible guidance that can be adapted to the nature, scale and requirements of the incident. It consolidates the content of over 500 items of previously published subject related documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16085</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:54:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/asian-fire-service-association-afsa-conference"/>
    <title>Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference</title>
    <summary>Speech by Brandon Lewis to the Asian Fire Service Association (AFSA) Conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be invited to speak here today and to see so many others here to support you. I understand that this is the fifth AFSA national conference, and my predecessor Bob Neill has spoken at the last 2. I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Bob, who has a deep understanding of the issues you face, as well as a great knowledge of the sector. I know that Bob, when he was Fire Minister, greatly valued the close and positive relationship he had with AFSA. I very much hope to be able to continue that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-afsa"&gt;The importance of AFSA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of groups such as AFSA cannot be underestimated. You provide a forum for people to come together to discuss key concerns, to support each other’s development, and provide an opportunity for challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of challenge, AFSA continues to perform a vital role in terms of ensuring that equality, diversity and fairness are mainstreamed in the Fire and Rescue Service. Events such as this provide excellent opportunities for the exchange of ideas, and for lively debate. I know that a regional AFSA group has been set up here in the West Midlands, supporting professional development and progression, sharing learning experiences, building a solid network of mutual support for employees, and supporting charities and fundraising. All of this shows the excellent work that the association is doing both at the national and local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="promoting-equality-and-diversity"&gt;Promoting equality and diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that Sir Graham Meldrum, when he was Chief Fire Officer in the West Midlands and again as Chief Inspector of Her Majesty’s Fire Service Inspectorate did a great amount of work to promote equality and diversity in the service, and this excellent work has been carried on by Vij as Chief Fire Officer of the West Midlands, and in his presidency of the Chief Fire Officers Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to say, on a personal note, that I am deeply committed to advancing equality of opportunity to one and all, not only in the fire and rescue service, but also in the communities they live in and serve. I am also of the firm conviction that this is best driven locally. And I say this because I want each fire and rescue authority to be responsible for reaching out to minority groups, and ensuring that they recognise that the service is for them - not as an add on - but for them along with everyone else in the community. I want fire and rescue services to go out into their communities, find the right people, engage with them and draw them into the heart of the fire and rescue service family. I want the entire community to be so integrated into the fire and rescue service that we no longer have to think in terms of equality and diversity - it will just happen automatically. I know that this is at the core of what AFSA is working for, and you have my full support in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt, a lot is already happening, and I would like to highlight some of the work going on here in the West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service. They have Welcome to the West Midlands, an education programme for new migrants to promote safety, well being, community understanding and citizenship. This has been developed in consultation with migrants to meet the information gap which can occur when someone arrives in this country. The West Midlands also has active employee engagement through the local AFSA group, working with them to target under represented operational and support staff to develop essential skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my short time as Fire Minister I have been very impressed by the wide range of local initiatives such as these, which not only reach out to the under represented, but also to the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, the fire service is leading a community project with the Asian Development Association of Bury. This project, which provided employment opportunities for local people, has already seen the production of a fire safety video that can be heard in eight of Manchester’s most commonly used languages. It will be the main communication tool used in community education sessions, facilitated by fire and rescue service volunteers recruited by the association. There will also be a series of workshops for the &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; business community designed to raise awareness of how the fire and rescue service can help them meet their responsibilities under the Fire Safety Order. This project will be rolled out across all of Manchester’s ten metropolitan boroughs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage young people from a community they have previously found hard to reach, and to respect religious beliefs, they have established a cadet scheme in Hyde for young women from the Bangladeshi community, and they are hoping to use this as a model to engage many ethnic communities in similar activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is being driven forward at the local level - not by central target or quotas, but by responding to the demands of their local communities. And to be able to respond to these, each fire and rescue service needs to make full use of the human resources at their disposal - and to do this equality and diversity has to be at the core of any organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to delivering the best service to the local community is to have a diverse, representative workforce, equipped to understand and meet the needs of those it serves and capable of delivering a first class service to everyone. This will also support the service’s aim to create a better understanding of its preventative role and of the support and advice it is able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire service must ensure that every employee is valued; that there truly is equality of opportunity for all, and that the working culture is such that unfair discrimination, unacceptable behaviour, bullying and harassment are not tolerated. I strongly believe that the fire and rescue service has gone a long way to achieve this goal and together with partners like AFSA they can continue to work to create an even more open and inclusive service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fire-kills"&gt;Fire Kills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also like to take this opportunity to thank AFSA for your continued support of the Fire Kills campaign. The Fire Kills campaign has had a focus on &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; groups since 2005 - and for good reason. Research has shown that certain &lt;abbr title="Black and minority ethnic"&gt;BME&lt;/abbr&gt; communities are at a potentially greater risk from fire. Smoke alarm ownership amongst Asian communities is ten per cent lower than the national average.  Recent analysis of accidental dwelling fire victim profiles has suggested that Asian communities are potentially more vulnerable than African communities. This has led to our 2012 campaign focussing solely on the Bangladeshi and Pakistani communities. With smoke alarm ownership levels lower in these communities the primary message will be on the importance of working smoke alarms. Two bursts of advertising will run - one which began this week, and another in March 2013. The new campaign will focus on blessings. As you know blessing of wellbeing, health and a long life are delivered on important occasions in these communities. The new campaign will encourage people to make their blessings count - ‘when you give a blessing, make it count: test your smoke alarm’. There will be radio advertising to demonstrate the fire consequences of not having a working smoke alarm, linking it back to a blessing that was given. I have no doubt that this campaign, targeted primarily at first generation Pakistani and Bangladeshi communities, will be a powerful tool for you and all those in fire and rescue services seeking to reduce deaths and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-position"&gt;Economic position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of this conference is ‘advancing equality during austerity’. I think that it is important to note that there are signs of improvement in the economy. Jobs are being created, manufacturing and exports have grown as a share of our economy, our trade with vibrant, emerging economies such as China and Brazil is improving, and the world is once again investing in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we face many challenges. The debts built up over many years will take time to work our way through, not helped by a decline in our competitiveness which was effectively masked by unsustainable borrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to cut the national deficit, fire and rescue, as a frontline emergency service, has been given funding protection with reductions back-loaded to give more time for sensible savings to be made, and reductions applied to fire and rescue authorities have been less than those applied to local authorities in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been heartened to hear how many fire and rescue authorities have risen to the challenges that the spending review has posed. However, I know some of you have concerns that fire and rescue services may disproportionately reduce funding on equality and diversity activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this is not the case. But if you see this happening, then you must speak up. It is vital that fire and rescue services do not make decisions that will impact on their ability to deliver on their statutory duties as required under the Equality Act 2010, and transparency and accountability are at the heart of our approach towards local government generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In closing I would like to thank you once again for giving me this opportunity to speak to you today. I do hope that your organisation goes from strength to strength, and that you remain and important and influential voice in the British fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to extend my congratulations to all the award winners who will be honoured at this evening’s event, well done, keep up the good work and have a great night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/14119</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:15:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:15:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-with-local-partners-to-plan-for-and-respond-to-emergencies"/>
    <title>Working with local partners to plan for, and respond to, emergencies</title>
    <summary>Helping communities plan for, respond to, and recover from local emergencies such as floods or civil disorder.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important that local communities can be resilient in the event of major emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work with local and national bodies to ensure they work and communicate together effectively to respond to and recover from emergencies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="working-with-local-resilience-forums"&gt;Working with local resilience forums&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s aim is to reduce the risk from emergencies so that people can go about their business freely and with confidence, and the Cabinet Office co-ordinates the central government response. The Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) is responsible for the government’s work with local councils and other local services in England to plan for major emergencies. &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; works closely with other central government departments and local resilience forums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A local resilience forum is a formal group made up of representatives from local public services including the police, fire and ambulance services, local councils, the NHS, the Environment Agency and other organisations that have a duty or an interest in planning for major emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a national network of advisers who work closely with all 38 local resilience forums throughout England to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;help them plan for, respond to and recover from a wide range of emergencies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure that organisations effectively fulfil their roles and responsibilities set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/civil-contingencies-act" title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="working-with-local-strategic-co-ordinating-groups-when-emergencies-happen"&gt;Working with local strategic co-ordinating groups when emergencies happen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some emergencies need emergency responders and local agencies to work together and in these cases a strategic co-ordinating group, chaired in most cases by a senior police officer, will be set up to oversee and co-ordinate the local response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategic co-ordinating groups can ask for the help of a government representative to ensure that the government has a full understanding of the impact of the emergency and can help with any extra support or action that may help local organisations to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A response co-ordinating group may be convened where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;local organisations have been, or may be, overwhelmed and support from other places is needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an emergency affects a number of areas so it would be useful to bring together representatives from other strategic co-ordinating groups and/or organisations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="providing-strategic-support"&gt;Providing strategic support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government departments can provide strategic support for emergencies affecting their responsibilities. For any given emergency, a ‘lead government department’ usually takes overall responsibility for: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assessing the situation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring ministers are kept up to date &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing co-ordinated policy and other support as necessary to local responders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Resilience advisers work with the government departments that are responsible for dealing with specific emergencies. For example, as part of the Department for Transport and Department of Health winter preparations, resilience advisers highlight winter weather risks with local resilience forums and promote local resilience to severe weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="financial-support-for-responding-to-emergencies"&gt;Financial support for responding to emergencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities can apply for financial help from government through the Bellwin Scheme for their immediate costs of dealing with an emergency in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme is usually used as a response to incidents where bad weather caused threats to life and property beyond all previous local experience. Although the law does not rule out other types of incident, &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; expects that the scheme will continue to apply mainly to bad weather incidents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how the scheme works are available in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bellwin-scheme-2012-to-2013-guidance" title="Bellwin Scheme guidance notes and application form"&gt;Bellwin Scheme 2012-13: guidance notes and application form.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-communities-recover-from-emergencies"&gt;Helping communities recover from emergencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a small number of emergencies, an event is of such a scale that the recovery process may benefit from a degree of government co-ordination and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the government helped businesses and communities affected by the public disorder that happened in August 2011 by co-ordinating a range of support from across government for local businesses and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-risk-register"&gt;National Risk Register&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see an official government assessment of risks to the UK, both from natural hazards like flooding and different types of terrorism on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/national-risk-register" title="National Risk Register"&gt;National Risk Register.&lt;/a&gt; The government has also produced &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-recovery-guidance" title="National recovery guidance"&gt;national recovery guidance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2010, the government published its national security strategy ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/national-security-strategy-strong-britain-age-uncertainty" title="National security strategy"&gt;A strong Britain in an age of uncertainty.’&lt;/a&gt; This describes how we need the structures in place to allow us to react quickly and effectively to new and evolving threats to our security. Government departments contribute to tasks identified in the National Security Strategy, with overall co-ordination provided by the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Risk Register forms part of the National Security Strategy. In January 2012 the National Risk Register was updated to inform the public about the government’s current assessment of the likelihood and potential impact of a range of different civil emergency risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Risk Register divides risks into 3 main categories: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;major accidents &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;malicious attacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It evaluates a number of risks under each of these headings, rated by relative impact and relative likelihood, and discusses the measures currently in place to deal with each of these and what individuals and organisations can do to mitigate the effects of civil disruption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/16096</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T17:14:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T17:14:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires"/>
    <title>Supporting fire and rescue authorities to reduce the number and impact of fires</title>
    <summary>We work with all 46 fire authorities to make sure standards are consistent nationally, giving them freedom to decide on local services </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have a duty in law to promote fire safety and respond to fires and a range of other emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important that fire and rescue authorities have the right resources to do their job effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work with them to ensure that standards of service are consistent across the country, while also giving them the freedom to decide how best to provide services locally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provide funding to the fire authorities through the revenue support grant – an annual grant from central government for fire authorities to meet their ongoing expenses. Fire and rescue authorities, working with other organisations in their area, use this funding to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce deaths and injuries from fire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;help people to prevent fires, especially those who are most vulnerable because of old age or disability &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;respond effectively to major national emergencies like severe weather, flooding and terrorist incidents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We set the overall structure of 46 fire authorities in England, and are responsible for the laws they have to work within.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We publish a national framework, which is agreed by Parliament, to explain what we expect fire and rescue authorities to achieve with the government funding they receive. The most recent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-national-framework-for-england" title="fire and rescue national framework"&gt;Fire and rescue national framework&lt;/a&gt; was published in July 2012. The framework includes information about what fire and rescue authorities must do to prepare for and respond to national emergencies. However, it does not instruct fire and rescue authorities about local operational matters. We think fire and rescue authorities should work with people, businesses and other organisations to decide how to work effectively in their area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fire-prevention"&gt;Fire prevention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have helped to reduce deaths and injuries and the overall incidence of fire by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;running the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/firekills"&gt;Fire Kills&lt;/a&gt; campaign – the national campaign designed to educate people about fire safety to help them prevent fires &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commissioning research to identify particular groups likely to be at increased risk from fire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with the European Commission to develop a new safety standard for cigarettes so that only those that self-extinguish when not being smoked actively are available for sale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="fire-resilience-programme"&gt;Fire resilience programme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire resilience programme. We have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;provided digital radios for the fire and rescue service for England, Scotland and Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provided specialist equipment and training for fire and rescue services to respond effectively to major emergencies and accidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;established a new Fire and Rescue Strategic Resilience Board to provide a way for fire authorities and other organisations to plan for disasters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="fire-service-college"&gt;Fire Service College&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/supporting-pages/sale-of-the-fire-service-college" title="Sale of the Fire Service College"&gt;Fire Service College&lt;/a&gt; the flexibility to achieve commercial success, we have agreed to sell it to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="improving-control-rooms"&gt;Improving control rooms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been working with fire and rescue authorities to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-fire-and-rescue-authorities-to-reduce-the-number-and-impact-of-fires/supporting-pages/improving-control-rooms" title="Improving control rooms"&gt;improve control rooms.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths in the home have halved since the 1980s. Since 2007 the number of accidental fire deaths in the home has stabilised at around 210 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, fire and rescue authorities face new challenges. They need to be able to deal with the continuing threat of terrorism, the impact of climate change, and the impacts of an ageing population, against the need to cut the national deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is against this background that we launched the revised national framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous national framework (2008 to 2011) covered a broad range of activities and responsibilities for fire and rescue authorities including planning for and responding to national emergencies, and fire prevention, protection and response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the response to the fire and rescue sector’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-futures-report-government-response--2" title="Government response to the Fire Futures report"&gt;Fire Futures Reports,&lt;/a&gt; the government committed to work with fire and rescue authorities to develop and consult on a revised national framework. Our aim was to reset the relationship between central government and fire and rescue authorities to give the authorities more local control over how they operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran a public consultation on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/fire-and-rescue-national-framework-for-england--2" title="Consultation on the fire and rescue national framework"&gt;new national framework.&lt;/a&gt; This led to the development of the revised framework, which was laid before Parliament in July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-weve-consulted"&gt;Who we’ve consulted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-future-of-fire-and-rescue-control-services-in-england" title="The future of fire and rescue control rooms"&gt;consultation on the future of fire and rescue control rooms&lt;/a&gt; in January 2011. The overwhelming response to the consultation was that fire authorities wanted more freedom to decide how to provide services to meet the needs of people in their area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/fire-and-rescue-national-framework-for-england--2" title="Consultation on the fire and rescue national framework"&gt;consultation on the new national framework&lt;/a&gt; ran from December 2011 to March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/21/contents" title="Fire and Rescue Services Act"&gt;Fire and Rescue Services Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2007/735/contents/made" title="Fire and Rescue Services (Emergencies) (England) Order 2007"&gt;Fire and Rescue Service (Emergencies)(England) Order 2007&lt;/a&gt; give fire and rescue authorities mandatory functions in relation to fire and road traffic accidents and in connection with certain types of emergencies (chemical, biological, radiological or nuclear and urban search and rescue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities are also ‘category 1 responders’ under the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/36/contents" title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt;. This means they are subject to the full set of civil protection duties, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assessing the risk of emergencies happening (ranging from widespread flooding to terrorist attacks) and using this to inform contingency planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that emergency plans and business continuity management arrangements are in place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="regulatory-reform-fire-safety-order-2005"&gt;Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/1541/contents/made" title="Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005"&gt;Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005&lt;/a&gt; replaced over 70 pieces of fire safety law. It’s designed to prevent fires in non-domestic premises and protect employees and the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve produced &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/making-premises-safe-from-fire-short-guide--2" title="Making premises safe from fire: a short guide"&gt;guidance on making your premises safe from fire&lt;/a&gt; for those seeking advice on how to comply with the provisions of the order - usually employers or owners/occupiers of commercial buildings and those to which the public have access. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also manage the statutory determination of disputes process available under Article 36 of the order. This means that if someone responsible for fire safety in a non-domestic premises disagrees with a fire inspection recommendation of how fire precautions should be technically put in place in the building, the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government can decide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-were-working-with"&gt;Who we’re working with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 46 fire and rescue authorities in England of various size and structure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities are responsible for providing local fire and rescue services. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promoting fire safety and enforcing fire safety regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fire-fighting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;national resilience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;special services, like rescuing people from road traffic accidents &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also work with a number of organisations to develop fire and rescue policy, including the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cfoa.org.uk/" title="Chief Fire Officers' Association"&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association,&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fbu.org.uk" title="Fire Brigades Union"&gt;Fire Brigades Union,&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://therfu.org" title="Retained Firefighters Union"&gt;Retained Firefighters Union&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.firesectorfederation.co.uk" title="Fire Sector Federation"&gt;Fire Sector Federation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14742</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fire-minister-backs-call-for-action-on-false-alarms"/>
    <title>Fire Minister backs call for action on false alarms</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis has called for more to be done to combat the 250,000 false fire alarms across the country each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a speech to the Fire Sector Summit at Wembley on Wednesday, he pointed to new figures showing that, in London alone, a fire engine is called once every 12 minutes to a false alarm, at a cost of £34 million every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, throughout the country, there were nearly a quarter of a million false alarms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to an audience of fire professionals the Minister argued that many of these could be prevented through the use of new technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that technology can address this issue. To that end, I have asked the industry to see what can be done to drive down false alarms through improved equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Sector Federation has set up a group that is already looking at the use of more sophisticated technology such as multi-sensor fire detectors which can detect more than one factor such as smoke and heat. These are much more accurate at identifying whether there is a real fire or whether it is an environmental factor such as dust or steam that is triggering an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, improved procedures can hugely cut the number of false alarms. A well known food processing company reduced its false alarms from nearly 50 a year to less than one by training fire marshals to investigate the cause of an alarm before the fire and rescue authority was called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Mr Lewis went on to say that by working together the sector could find financial savings as well as save lives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At a time when every penny counts, this is an obvious area in which to make large savings. Dealing with the number of false alarms has got to be a priority and I would encourage the industry and fire and rescue authorities to work together to develop a common approach to cutting back on something that not only wastes money, but potentially could cost lives, and I look forward to hearing their findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16581</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:10:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/fire-sector-summit-2012"/>
    <title>Fire sector summit 2012</title>
    <summary>Fire Minister Brandon Lewis addresses the 2012 fire sector summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to say how delighted I am to be invited to speak to this summit - an event that grows in importance every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly pleased that the summit brings together all parts of the fire industry - not only those who deliver the fire and rescue service at the sharp end, but all those who, often behind the scenes, do so much to ensure the buildings we live in and the products we use on a daily basis, are safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-success-story"&gt;A success story&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in terms of fires you should all congratulate yourselves on a considerable success story. In England, fire fatalities and non-fatal casualties fell by 34% and 54% respectively between 2001 to 2002 and 2011 to 2012, and the average area of fire damage fell by 20% in dwellings and around 10% in other buildings during the same period. Last year, total fires fell by 6% to 227,000. I very much hope that these trends continue way into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of government’s commitment to maintaining a high profile focus on prevention activity, the Fire Kills campaign is currently running its hugely successful national advertising campaign. As with last year, we are encouraging everyone to test their smoke alarms when they change their clocks this weekend as you are four times more likely to die in a fire if you do not have a working smoke alarm. I would ask that in order to extend the reach and breadth of the campaign, you use your own websites to disseminate this important message. By working together we have the opportunity to really drive home the importance of fire safe behaviour and maintain the downward trend on fire deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interaction between the fire industry and fire and rescue is a complex one - and for that reason I am delighted that the Fire Sector Federation is playing an increasingly important role in pulling all parts of the fire industry together, into a forum where ideas and knowledge can be exchanged. And I would particularly like to thank Brian Robinson, the Chairman of the Federation, for his hard work and perseverance in bringing the Federation to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-importance-of-co-operation"&gt;The importance of co-operation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth is a top priority for this government. Supporting business growth for both new and existing companies is fundamental to our approach. And encouraging the creation of new businesses and sectors is crucial to this country’s future. These new businesses will help to create the necessary wealth and growth, and much needed jobs. But we need also to ensure that both new and existing businesses are strong and resilient, including safeguarding and protecting them from the devastating effects of a fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you here today will know a fire can result in a business loss both in terms of its employees, its contribution to the local economy, and ability to recover and trade again in the aftermath of an incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I urge the fire sector to go out and proactively engage with representative bodies for industry and commerce and make the case for effective and proportionate fire protection - passive and active interventions - in all areas of business in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="false-alarms"&gt;False alarms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry also has a vitally important role to play in ensuring that we make the best use of innovative technology. You will know better than me the scope for technology to improve resilience to fire - but one area where more can be done is in limiting the number of false alarms. Last year there were 249,000 fire false alarms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Fire Brigade says that despite a reduction of 23% in false alarms in the last 5 years, a fire engine is still called to a false alarm every 12 minutes in the capital, costing an estimated 34 million every year. More importantly, these unnecessary calls impact on the Brigade’s ability to attend real incidents, deliver training and carry out vital community safety work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that technology can address this issue. To that end I have asked Brian Robinson to see what the industry itself can do to drive down false alarms through improved technology. Brian has asked a Fire Sector Federation working group under Martin Harvey to look into this issue - and I very much look forward to hearing their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="workforce-development"&gt;Workforce development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area where I see significant improvement is in relation to workforce development in fire and rescue services. Here collaborative working between the Sector Skills Council - Skills for Fire and Rescue, and the Chief Fire Officers Association amongst others - is starting to produce tangible results, especially in the risk critical areas of intervention activity. Such work helps underpin integrated risk management plans, interoperability, national resilience and common working. Much energy is being devoted to this work. I would like to thank Max Hood, the chair of the National Occupational Committee for his efforts in leading this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="public-procurement"&gt;Public procurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of you have an interest in public procurement and accessing new markets. This is an area where government is keen to help. As you may know, the government has put in place the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/contracts-finder" title="Contracts Finder"&gt;Contracts Finder&lt;/a&gt; website, aimed at making it easier for suppliers to find and apply for public sector contracts. It is the main source of government opportunities worth more than £10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department has already approached certain fire and rescue authorities to help populate pipelines and is very grateful for the assistance given to date. We are now asking all fire and rescue authorities for help to get as much information on future procurements in the pipeline - this should not be difficult as fire and rescue authorities should already be publishing this information existing contracts and tenders under the local government transparency code. The information on future procurements will help strengthen the UK supply chain by identifying current gaps between supply and demand and giving industry the confidence to invest for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also committed to devolving power away from Whitehall so that fire and rescue authorities can decide how they can deliver services in a way that best meets their communities’ needs. I hope that the fire sector can join together to develop new ways of working and further innovation that can stimulate growth for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="youth-employment"&gt;Youth employment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to speak a little about youth employment. In response to the challenge of youth unemployment, year the Deputy Prime Minister has launched a £1 billion Youth Contract to help unemployed people get a job. The Youth Contract will provide a number of new opportunities for young people, including apprenticeships and work experience placements. Many of you will be aware of the The Prince’s Trust Fire Industry Scheme, and some have supported it. I wish to thank you for that, and encourage others to get involved if they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a number of fire and rescue authorities have started training apprentices. I was particularly impressed to hear that in Greater Manchester Fire and Rescue Service 12 young people have started a community safety apprenticeship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apprentices are young people who have already had some contact with Greater Manchester Fire and Rescue Service, for example through the Prince’s Trust courses, cadets and Fire Fly following a targeted recruitment campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support them through the application process, they put on a 10-day pre-recruitment course - run by Salford City College - to give candidates an understanding of working with people in the communities they would serve, as well as meeting a community safety adviser who is already in the job, so they know exactly what the role entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to commend Greater Manchester for this valuable initiative, and wish the new entrants every possible success in their apprenticeship, and future careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="retained-duty-system-firefighters"&gt;Retained duty system firefighters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, the one area where industry and the fire and rescue service co-operate on a daily, if not hourly, basis is in the retained duty system. There is no doubt that the retained duty system is the backbone of the fire and rescue response in large swathes of the United Kingdom. We must, as leaders in the fire sector, wherever possible, bring to people’s attention the valuable work done by retained duty firefighters, and encourage employers and members of the public to offer their services to this essential service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14728</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/charred-clocks-bring-an-emotional-reminder-that-it-s-time-to-test"/>
    <title>Charred clocks bring an emotional reminder that it’s Time to Test</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire Kills - When you change your clock test your smoke alarm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting campaign offers a timely reminder that changing our clocks isn’t the only important task to carry out over the weekend of 27/28 October - the clear Fire Kills message is that it’s time to take life-saving action and test our smoke alarms too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2237695.jpg" alt="Fire Kills poster showing a child"&gt;“Do you swear on your child’s life to test your smoke alarm this weekend?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple task of making sure our smoke alarms work is something that many often forget. But people are more than four times as likely to die in a fire if they do not have a working smoke alarm, so the Fire Kills campaign is using the twice-yearly clock change chore to remind people that it’s time to test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images of charred timepieces that bring to mind a child’s bedside table, a grandparents’ mantelpiece, and a quiet night in front of the TV, pull on the heartstrings to remind householders of the lives at stake if their smoke alarm isn’t working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011-12, there were 30,709 accidental fires in the home, resulting in 187 fatalities and more than 6,000 injuries. The number of fatalities was 12 per cent lower than in 2010-11 and Fire Kills aims to keep these figures going down because behind every death is a tragic story of loss for family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of those people who died in dwelling fires last year were aged 65 and over. This year the campaign is urging carers, family and close neighbours to offer to test older people’s smoke alarms for them as they are often out of easy reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a working smoke alarm can buy people valuable time to get out, stay out and call 999, only half of all householders who own a smoke alarm say that they test it is working on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign aims to make testing our smoke alarms part of every household’s routine when changing our clocks, potentially saving many lives in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The smoke alarm is a proven saviour, and while the great majority of homes now own one, that’s simply not enough - it must be working to save your life.
&amp;gt; “Keeping ourselves and our loved ones safe from the worst should never be left to chance. That’s why this campaign reminds us of exactly what’s at stake if the worst should happen.
&amp;gt; “The clock change offers the perfect prompt to carry out the simple task of testing your alarms and offering to test for other people - especially older friends and relatives who may find it difficult to do it for themselves.
&amp;gt; “Last year, nearly one in seven adults tested their alarms over the clock change weekends and we want many more to test this year. A simple task, taking just a few seconds, can mean the difference between life and death, so add it to your ‘to do’ list now. Our message is clear - it’s time to test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You’re more than four times as likely to die in a fire without a working smoke alarm. But despite this, only half of the people who own an alarm say they take the time to test that it’s working.
&amp;gt; “Almost half the people who die in accidental fires in their home are aged over 65. Let’s reduce this shocking statistic by offering to help older family members or other elderly people we care for and test their alarm for them.
&amp;gt; “A smoke alarm can give you the vital time you need to get out, stay out and call 999 in a house fire. As you put your clocks back on the weekend of 27/28 October take an extra moment to make sure your alarm is working properly - it could save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen out for the radio adverts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://web-cdn.coull.biz/communities/MP3Player/MP3Player.swf" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and look out for the press adverts supporting the ‘When you change your clocks, test your smoke alarms’ campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/8079926115/sizes/l/"&gt;Do you swear on your child’s life to test your smoke alarm this weekend?&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/8079926013/sizes/l/"&gt;It would have taken only seconds to test their smoke alarm&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/8079925829/sizes/l/"&gt;If he could turn back time and test his smoke alarm&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also an online video showing a mantelpiece clock melting in the heat of a house fire - bringing home just how fast a fire can hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3aw1JmjIA-I?rel=0" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more on the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.facebook.com/firekills"&gt;Fire Kills Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help keep yourself and your loved ones safe in the home by following these simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A working smoke alarm can buy you valuable time to get out, stay out and call 999. Make sure you fit one on every level of your home and test them regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make testing your smoke alarm part of your household routine. Test the alarm by pressing the button regularly; change your battery once a year or invest in a 10-year alarm; and clean the alarm casing twice a year to ensure dust doesn’t block the sensor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever happens, never remove the battery in your smoke alarm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure that everyone in your home knows what to do in a fire and practise your escape route.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more information visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.facebook.com/firekills"&gt;Fire Kills Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want an extra nudge to test your smoke alarm regularly, try setting an automatic reminder. Safelincs, in partnership with the Fire Kills campaign, has created a free service that reminds you, by email or text, when it’s time to test your smoke alarm, change the battery or renew the unit. The service is completely free and can be cancelled at any time. For more information visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.safelincs.co.uk/reminders/"&gt;Safelincs website&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;British Summer Time (BST) ends on the last Sunday in October. The clocks go back at 2.00 am BST on 28 October to 1.00 am Greenwich Mean Time (GMT).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fire statistics can be found on the DCLG website at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/monitorq1q42012"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/monitorq1q42012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research conducted by Ipsos API on the 2011/12 Fire Kills campaign showed that 14 per cent of respondents (total 1690) tested their smoke alarms over the March clock change weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
