<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Public safety and emergencies"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56197</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/preferred-bidder-for-the-fire-service-college-confirmed"/>
    <title>Preferred bidder for the Fire Service College confirmed</title>
    <summary>Fire minister Brandon Lewis has announced Capita as the preferred bidder for the purchase of the Fire Service College.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire minister said he was happy that the proposed sale of the college to Capita would achieve value for money for the public purse and secure the future of the college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that we are making real progress in securing the future of such an important facility. It is vital for the development of the Fire Service College that we put it on a sound footing, giving the private sector a chance to provide innovation and investment that will guarantee the future of a world-class asset.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure best value for money for taxpayers and enable the college to continue in its role, a number of conditions will be imposed on the proposed sale. These include commitments that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the college be preserved as a national training centre for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will continue to offer wider national resilience and emergency services training and exercises&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;government permission will be required if Capita wish to sell the incident ground&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councillor Kay Hammond, Chair of the Local Government Association’s fire services management committee, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is good news that government has listened to the views of the sector about the future of the Fire Service College and that it now looks set to get the outside investment it so badly needs. The Local Government Association and fire authorities will be keen to work with the future owners to help them transform the college into a first-class training facility fit for firefighters in the 21st century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association President, Vij Randeniya, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Chief Fire Officers’ Association welcomes the news that Capita has been selected. It has been a long and intensive process and we are glad that there is now clarity for the Fire Service College. We look forward to working closely with Capita to ensure that the very best provision is available for UK fire and rescue services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government now looks forward to holding constructive discussions with Capita to ensure that the transition from public to private sector is as smooth as possible and expects to complete the sale early in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Service College is a trading fund and executive agency of the department. Since becoming a trading fund in 1992, it has never been able to pay a dividend out of operating profits. The government’s response to Fire Futures on 12 April 2011 concluded that the college could achieve its full potential only if there was greater involvement from other sectors in its ownership, operation and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Options project considered 4 options for the future of the college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the status quo: the college remains as a trading fund of the department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a government owned contractor operated model: the assets remain under government ownership but management of the college is taken over by a private sector company under a long term contract, together with the staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disposal as a going concern: the college is sold to a private sector company who would continue to operate the college as a training centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closure: the college’s activities cease, staff are made redundant and the site is sold for an alternative use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the 4 options showed disposal as a going concern to be the best option, and the only one which both removes from government ongoing financial risks of ownership of the college and preserves a national training college for the fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers announced on 22 March 2012 that the Fire Service College would be sold as a going concern to a private sector company to continue operating as a training centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale process was launched on 10 April 2012 and the due diligence phase concluded in October with the receipt of final bids. Best and final offers were received in November. The aim is to complete the sale in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56085</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-10-2012-immediate"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 10/2012 immediate</title>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 is issued for the immediate attention of fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the announcement of the preferred bidder for the Fire Service College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55926</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T20:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/65m-contract-to-refit-royal-navys-largest-warship-secures-hundreds-of-uk-jobs"/>
    <title>£65 million contract to refit HMS Ocean</title>
    <summary>HMS Ocean, the Royal Navy's largest warship, will receive a £65 million upgrade, securing more than 600 UK jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The warship was moored on the Thames during the London 2012 Olympic Games and provided essential security support and a home for hundreds of military personnel responsible for venue security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her upgrade will be carried out at Devonport Royal Dockyard in Plymouth and will be the largest upkeep programme of its kind to be carried out at the docks in more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract has been awarded to UK maritime support specialists &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, securing 300 jobs in Devonport. More than 70 contractors are also set to be involved in the project, securing a further 300 jobs across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the refit, which is expected to last 15 months, upgrades and improvements will be made to the ship’s radar, gun, command system and living quarters. In addition, around 1,200 metres of new pipework will be laid and around 100,000 litres of paint will be applied to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Ocean" title="HMS Ocean"&gt;HMS Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Ocean plays a crucial role supporting operations as we saw during the Olympics and the Libya campaign and it is essential that we continue to invest in the upkeep of this formidable vessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Ocean" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4937/DR120330014g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dockyard workers watch HMS Ocean slowly enter Number 10 Dock at Devonport Royal Dockyard to begin her refit [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that this contract will not only ensure that HMS Ocean remains a significant, highly-flexible and capable warship for years to come, but will also secure hundreds of jobs within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew Mathews, Chief of Materiel (Fleet) for the MOD’s Defence Equipment and Support organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since entering service HMS Ocean has delivered comprehensive support to countless military operations as well as humanitarian and disaster relief missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extensive refit programme is essential in ensuring that this magnificent ship is able to continue in her role supporting and protecting the UK’s interests across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her Olympics duties, HMS Ocean played an integral role in the Libya campaign launching Apache helicopters from her deck to attack Libyan ground defences, the first time Apaches had been launched from a Royal Navy warship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/12844</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/maintaining-operational-readiness-to-provide-military-support-for-activities-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>Maintaining operational readiness to provide military support for activities in the UK</title>
    <summary>Civil authorities have resources to cope with a wide range of emergencies but if they lack capability or are overwhelmed by the scale of events they can ask the Ministry of Defence for assistance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is constantly refining its ability to provide an effective response to all types of emergencies and major crises at national, regional and local level. This means having a pre-planned, coordinated response from the emergency services, civil authorities and where appropriate, the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is an emergency or crisis situation in the UK, local emergency services provide the first response. Government departments or civil authorities can also call on the Ministry of Defence for military help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed Forces support is officially known as Military Aid to the Civil Authorities (MACA). The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/36/contents"&gt;Civil Contingencies Act 2004&lt;/a&gt; states that military support is available for major incidents when the capability or capacity of civilian authorities has been overwhelmed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no standing military forces for these tasks so support isn’t guaranteed and when it is provided the civil authorities normally have to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces can be brought in to deal with a range of situations including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural disasters - helping people in severe weather situations, such as flooding, where there is a need to protect human life, property and alleviate distress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network failure or disruption - including animal disease epidemics and public service-related industrial disputes that affect our safety or security, or disrupt transport or communications links&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;criminal or terrorist activity - where there is a need, providing specialist expertise in specific circumstances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bomb disposal - known officially as ‘explosive ordnance disposal’, this can be related to terrorism, or involve unearthing a bomb from World War 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue - helping people in danger, searching for sunken vessels or aircraft, carrying out underwater or mountain rescue tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK waters - protecting our territorial waters, ports, ships and energy installations from terrorist attack, protecting fisheries, preventing drug or people smuggling and dealing with pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK airspace - detecting and deterring aircraft approaching UK sovereign airspace and protecting UK and NATO monitored airspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of recent emergencies and crises that needed help from the armed forces include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing security for the 2012 Olympics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search and rescue operations during widespread flooding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping UK travellers stranded by the Icelandic ash cloud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;managing the disposal of infected cattle during the ‘mad cow’ disease outbreak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detailed information for civil authorities on handling crises is contained in the guidance &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-response-and-recovery"&gt;Emergency Response and Recovery&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/resource-library/emergency-preparedness"&gt;Emergency Preparedness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/securing-britain-age-uncertainty-strategic-defence-and-security-review"&gt;Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR): Securing Britain in an age of uncertainty 2010&lt;/a&gt; sets out how the defence establishment will contribute effectively to civil crises and emergencies in the UK, balancing against other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-strategy-for-deploying-the-armed-forces-in-the-uk"&gt;The strategy for deploying the Armed Forces in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All defence operations including those in the UK must be authorised by the Defence Council. The Secretary of State for Defence is the government minister responsible for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and there is a single chain of command that connects to service personnel on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a crisis the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Deputy Chief of the Defence Staff (Military Strategy and Operations) and the Director General Security Policy give guidance to ministers and other government departments. In this way, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; acts as both a military HQ and a department of state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bills-and-legislation"&gt;Bills and legislation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Contingencies Act 2004 (&lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) defines how organisations, particularly local responders, prepare for emergencies. In the event of an emergency in which the supply and distribution of the essentials of life to the community are extensively threatened, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Contingencies Act 2004"&gt;CCA&lt;/abbr&gt; can be used to invoke emergency powers on a local, regional or national basis. The full &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/civil-contingencies-act"&gt;text of the Act&lt;/a&gt; is available from the Cabinet Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to deploy service personnel would be authorised by the Defence Council and they may be given the power to requisition equipment and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 2 of the the Emergency Powers Act 1964, the Defence Council may authorise the temporary deployment of service personnel on urgent work of national importance. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1964/38/contents"&gt;Read the full text of the Act&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39721</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:16:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <summary>Royal Marines and Albanian forces recently joined together for an assault on an abandoned Soviet submarine base as part of Exercise Albanian Lion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17621</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T10:24:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-28-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 28/2012</title>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for December 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consultation on proposed increases to employee pension contribution rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;departmental response to the consultation on amendments to the new Firefighters’ Pension Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update on the funding arrangements for localising support for council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government’s policy statement on business rates retention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of operational guidance and generic risk assessments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17112</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-5-7-incidents-involving-explosives"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 5.7: incidents involving explosives</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about incidents involving explosives to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 5.7 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to incidents involving ‘commercial’ explosives, while in manufacture, storage or transportation. It does not cover improvised explosive devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in November 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescues from lifts and escalators to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16920</id>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-25T12:36:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-reforms"/>
    <title>Firefighters’ pension scheme reforms</title>
    <summary>Details of the firefighters' pension scheme from 2015.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides details of the firefighters’ pension scheme from 2015. It relates to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/firefighters-pension-scheme-heads-of-agreement"&gt;heads
of agreement&lt;/a&gt; on the core parameters for reforms to the firefighters’ pension scheme that was published by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 9 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16737</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T16:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hazardous-materials-operational-guidance-for-the-fire-and-rescue-service"/>
    <title>Hazardous materials: operational guidance for the fire and rescue service</title>
    <summary>Best practice guidance to help fire and rescue authorities to resolve incidents involving hazardous materials safely and efficiently.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides comprehensive yet flexible guidance that can be adapted to the nature, scale and requirements of the incident. It consolidates the content of over 500 items of previously published subject related documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
