<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/public-safety-and-emergencies.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Public safety and emergencies"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T10:44:03+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64195</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T10:44:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-29-2013"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 29/2013</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for January 2013 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;announcement of the operational efficiencies review led by Sir Ken Knight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fire capital bidding outcome for 2013 to 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;control centre buildings update&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of a new protective security strategy, framework and toolkit &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60241</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:25:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-awards-258-million-sea-king-helicopter-support-contract"/>
    <title>MOD awards £258 million Sea King helicopter support contract</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The MOD has agreed a £258 million contract to support Sea King helicopters, which will sustain 500 jobs across the UK.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; fleets of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-Mk5" title="Sea King Mk5"&gt;Sea Kings&lt;/a&gt; are best known for providing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/UK/Search-and-Rescue" title="Search and Rescue"&gt;Search and Rescue&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt;) services in the UK and Falkland Islands. They can also be used to carry troops and provide airborne surveillance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extension to the Sea King Integrated Operational Support (&lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt;) contract will ensure continued technical and maintenance support for the 90-strong helicopter fleet for the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD originally signed the &lt;abbr title="Sea King Integrated Operational Support"&gt;SKIOS&lt;/abbr&gt; arrangement with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.agustawestland.com/" title="AgustaWestland"&gt;AgustaWestland&lt;/a&gt; in 2005 and this is the final phase of the deal which is expected to sustain around 500 jobs at AgustaWestland’s UK headquarters at Yeovil, in the industry supply chain and at several &lt;abbr title="Search and Rescue"&gt;SAR&lt;/abbr&gt; bases across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5786/45153254g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Royal Navy Sea King Mk4 helicopter is pictured on an operation over Helmand Province, Afghanistan (stock image) [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This phase of the contract will provide support until Sea King is retired from service in 2016 and replaced by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin MK1"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Sea King helicopter fleet has been in service for over 40 years providing a vital capability in air/sea rescue and surveillance. This maintenance agreement, securing 500 jobs across the UK, demonstrates our commitment to keeping this aircraft in top condition until it is retired from service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Navy Captain Tony Gray, Defence Equipment and Support Sea King Team Leader, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing this contract ensures value for money for the taxpayer while maintaining the provision of search-and-rescue helicopters around the UK, 24-hours-a-day throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56832</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-protective-security-strategy-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue protective security strategy 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy is a refresh of the 2009 protective security strategy for fire and rescue authorities. It outlines 6 key deliverables to enhance protective security for fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57434</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/policy-on-protecting-personal-and-other-sensitive-information-in-fire-and-rescue-incident-and-casualty-data"/>
    <title>Policy on protecting personal and other sensitive information in fire and rescue incident and casualty data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This document summarises issues relating to data protection of fire and rescue incident records.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue services across Great Britain record details of all incidents attended and of casualties. A national database is populated from these and this contains details as described in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/incident-recording-system-for-fire-and-rescue-authorities"&gt;Incident recording system for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document summarises issues relating to data protection of fire and rescue incident records, and how these are managed in the context of the production of statistical outputs and access to record-level data sets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57532</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:49:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-joy-for-old-soldier-who-finally-got-his-medal"/>
    <title>Christmas joy for old soldier who finally got his medal</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A former soldier from Lancashire has received the only service medal he was ever entitled to… 42 years late</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Army veteran Joe McKenna, 72, who volunteers at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/" title="Duke of Lancaster's Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum"&gt;Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Preston, left the military in 1970 just months before his Northern Ireland service medal was minted and eventually decided to track down his medal after years of attending parades where he was the only veteran not wearing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Bob Dixon, from 2 Medical Regiment and a fellow volunteer at the museum, offered to help Joe claim his honour. Sergeant Major Dixon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had been helping some visitors at the museum with enquiries about their service medals and so I offered to help Joe too. I got all the paperwork together, went around to his house, and we filled in the documents before sending them off to the MOD Medal Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We got a reply within 2 months, the quickest I’ve ever known; I think the turnaround was so fast because he still lives at the same address that appeared on his service papers back in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe enlisted in the Loyal Regiment, a forebear to the North West’s current infantry regiment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/3477.aspx" title="The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;The Duke of Lancaster’s&lt;/a&gt;, almost exactly 51 years ago and served in Kenya, Swaziland, Cyprus and Malta as well as in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern Ireland service medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5711/Joe_smedal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Joe McKenna's Northern Ireland service medal [Picture: Sergeant Mark Garry, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After he left the Army as a Lance Corporal in 1970, Joe worked for more than 30 years as an &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; driver, married Josie, with whom he had his children Sandra and Peter, and is now a grandfather of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said until recently the distractions of day-to-day life meant he just never got around to claiming what was his: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was only when I was marching at the Armed Forces Day parade in Preston last summer when I thought ‘I’m getting on a bit now and I should really get my medal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think my son would like to have it when I’m gone; he and my daughter think that it is marvellous that it’s finally here. It’s the best Christmas present ever and it makes me very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe’s wife Josie added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It really was something special to see his face when he received the medal; it was as if all his Christmases had come at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe now plans to wear his medal at his regiment’s Kimberley Day service and parade in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56828</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:30:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-brize-norton-counting-down-to-christmas"/>
    <title>RAF Brize Norton counting down to Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As people tuck into Christmas dinner, it will be business as usual for RAF personnel deployed overseas or at RAF stations across the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we take a closer look at how &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;RAF Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt; in Oxfordshire prepares for the festive season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-boss"&gt;The boss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAF Brize Norton is the largest station in the RAF and has approximately 6,000 Service personnel and 1,400 MOD civil servants and contractors. It is the home of the Air Mobility Squadrons and the ‘gateway to operations’ as the main airport used for deploying UK troops worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The station never sleeps and supports operations around the world 24/7, 365-days-a-year. Station Commander Group Captain Steve Lushington and his family will be serving Christmas dinner to the junior ranks on the big day. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the festive season gets into full swing, for personnel at RAF Brize Norton work continues as normal. The support to operations is paramount; even during the festive period personnel are still required to be on duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pilots and engineers on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/216squadron.cfm" title="216 Squadron"&gt;216 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/99squadron.cfm" title="99 Squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; maintain their high readiness state, personnel continue to control from the tower, operations staff continue to plan missions and taskings, all supporting tri-Service personnel across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="squadron"&gt;99 Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Captain Steve Lushington" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5706/Brize1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Group Captain Steve Lushington, Station Commander at RAF Brize Norton [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/c17aglobemaster.cfm" title="C-17 Globemaster"&gt;C-17 Globemaster&lt;/a&gt; is a huge, heavy-lift transport aircraft operated by 99 Squadron. It can carry troops and all types of cargo around the world, including transporting &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/merlin.cfm" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/chinook.cfm" title="Chinook"&gt;Chinook&lt;/a&gt; helicopters direct to the front line in Afghanistan to provide support to ground troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stuart Lindsell is the Officer Commanding 99 Squadron and has volunteered to cover Christmas duties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The squadron is 300-plus-strong and moves an immense amount of personal mail and parcels from families and loved ones. It’s rewarding for us to know that we are helping to play a part in connecting Service families who are separated over the Christmas period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s very much ‘business as usual’ for 99 Squadron; we have crews covering aeromed standby, a crew based in the Middle East ready for normal tasking. The squadron engineers stand ready to generate an aircraft at short notice should an aeromed mission be called and they will also be manning the engineer control desks as normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best way to look at it is hopefully Christmas Day itself will be quiet, but Christmas Eve, Boxing Day and to that extent the New Year period are no different to any other time of year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festive season can bring wintry conditions and, a couple of years ago, when the UK was gripped by sub-zero temperatures and heavy snowfalls, in the thick of it were 99 Squadron who battled to get troops home for Christmas. Wing Commander Lindsell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Snow and ice are certainly not ideal flying conditions to say the least but as a station we are better off than we were when the wintry conditions of 2010 hit. We did manage to get everyone home but it was certainly a challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="snow-and-ice-operations"&gt;Snow and ice operations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Corporal John Oliver" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5707/Brize3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Corporal John Oliver from the Airfield Support Mechanical Transport section [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal John Oliver will also be on standby during Christmas and works at the Complete Equipment Schedule Store at Airfield Support Mechanical Transport that, amongst other things, makes sure vehicles are in working order. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve spent the last 2 months preparing and bringing online all the snow and ice prevention vehicles as they are not used during the summer months; we inflate their tyres, fill the vehicle up with whatever fluid it needs, test it and carry out daily inspections to make sure they are ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it was horrendous snow the main vehicle we would use is the airfield snow clearing vehicle or the compact jet sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicles are equipped to plough snow, break up compact ice and blow snow, broken ice or other debris to the side. Corporal Oliver continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is to make sure we have a serviceable fleet of vehicles to meet the minimum required to clear the airfield. It’s a priority to clear the runway and certain bays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Getting the airfield cleared is very important for the ‘airbridge’, especially for those personnel that want to get home in the last couple of days before Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="air-movements-squadron"&gt;Air Movements Squadron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5708/Brize4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wendy James, Corporal Mark Watson and Sergeant Shaun Anderson getting into the festive spirit at a check-in desk in the air terminal [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporal Emma Hopkinson works on the passenger check-in desk in the air terminal for the Air Movements Squadron. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s like a civilian airport. The difference is, if I went for a job in a civilian airport I would only just be either a check-in girl, departures, or elsewhere in the building, whereas here at Brize we have to multi-task and do everything - one minute I could be behind the check-in desk, then I could be on the check-through or departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We see the whole process through and make sure that nobody is left behind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked what it’s like checking in troops knowing they will be away for Christmas, Corporal Hopkinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My job is no different at Christmas, the process is still the same, it’s the personalities and how people are with you, and how you are with them - I try and be a bit more jolly! I’ve done Iraq, Afghanistan and Ascension Island at Christmas, so I know what it’s like being away at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Hopkinson will be on shift during the Christmas period but sets aside a day in the new year to have a ‘Christmas Day’ with her family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I remember one year my mum bought a second turkey and it stayed in the freezer until February! I go to college and have met a lot of people and they are surprised I’m working Christmas Eve and Christmas Day - they ask ‘are you open?’ and I say yes! it’s a 24/7 camp, and it’s the same for New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="christmas-presence"&gt;Christmas ‘presence’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5709/Brize5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as 'Kev the Rev', will be working over the New Year period [Picture: Paul Crouch, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like the station itself, the chapel is open 24/7, and for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/chaplains/" title="RAF Chaplains"&gt;RAF chaplains&lt;/a&gt; the run-up to Christmas is always busy. Reverend Squadron Leader Kevin Caplin-Jones, otherwise known as ‘Kev the Rev’, will be working over the New Year period, but last year was on duty over Christmas. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because our senior chaplain was away on ops, I joined other officers on station and helped serve Christmas lunch in the Junior Ranks Mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a great experience, my wife was with me and some personnel brought family along. There was that family feel, the military family; everyone was in very good spirits as the portions of potatoes were getting bigger and bigger!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We often think about the people who are deployed at home or overseas, but it’s harder for the families left behind. Service people will make the most of it, no matter what, and I’m sure they get an extra mince pie or an extra bit of turkey and will make the most of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s the families left behind and the kids that don’t have their mum or dad with them on Christmas Day that find it hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best gift at Christmas is ‘presence’. For those who have had loved ones away last year, they will know that having loved ones around is the best gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If not ‘presence’, instantaneous communication such as emails and Skype is great; however, people underestimate e-blueys and handwritten letters - they have that personal touch which means so much to people and always makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56779</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:14:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-portland-sets-sail-after-27-million-refit"/>
    <title>HMS Portland sets sail after £27 million refit</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Portland is on her way to Plymouth after a £27 million 50-week refit at Rosyth dockyard in Fife, Scotland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With more than 260,000 man-hours invested in the almost year-long project, the 133-metre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Portland" title="HMS Portland"&gt;HMS Portland&lt;/a&gt; has returned to sea bristling with the latest high-tech equipment, maintaining its role at the cutting-edge of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 19 major system and capability upgrades have been undertaken on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates" title="Type 23 frigates"&gt;Type 23 frigate&lt;/a&gt;, including the installation of new anti-submarine warfare sonar, full upgrade of the ship’s computer systems, an overhaul of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Weapons-Systems/Seawolf" title="Seawolf"&gt;Seawolf&lt;/a&gt; missile system, replacement of guns, refurbishment of the galley and upgrades of accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship sailed underneath the famous Forth Bridges having had a total exterior makeover too, with 15,000 litres of paint having been applied to her hull and superstructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Sarah West, Commanding Officer of HMS Portland, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very much looking forward to getting this fantastic ship back to sea to put her through her paces. In tandem with the MOD and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.babcockinternational.com/" title="Babcock"&gt;Babcock&lt;/a&gt;, the crew has spent many long months working hard to return HMS Portland to fighting form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Portland " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5675/NE120458002g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Portland sails from Rosyth following her refit [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ian Arthur, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ship is equipped for the many future challenges which greet the modern fleet and we are ready to be with her every step of the way. It is an exciting moment returning a warship to sea after refit - we know that HMS Portland is in great shape for regaining full operational readiness early next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has benefited from close partnership between Babcock, the MOD, ship personnel and the team under the Surface Ship Support Alliance, resulting in the refit programme being delivered on time and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babcock project manager Russell Glancy said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have successfully met the challenges of this project, and applied our experience from previous Type 23 refits, along with strong partnering, to ensure delivery of this upgrade and maintenance programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Portland will undertake a further 3 months of sea trials and training before returning to the fleet as a fully operational ship, prepared at any time to take on duties worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3,500-tonne Type 23 frigates, of which there are 13 in the fleet, are flexible and adaptable ships which protect the UK’s interests both in home waters and further afield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical deployments will include anything from the fleet ready escort, which is the UK’s high readiness ship, to counter-narcotics, piracy and terrorism patrols and the ship can provide humanitarian intervention and security when required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56473</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:31:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19th-regiment-royal-artillery-becomes-the-scottish-gunners"/>
    <title>19th Regiment Royal Artillery becomes The Scottish Gunners</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>19th Regiment Royal Artillery (The Highland Gunners) has marked its change of name to The Scottish Gunners with a parade.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24667.aspx" title="The Highland Gunners"&gt;19th Regiment Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has become The Scottish Gunners as a result of 40th Regiment Royal Artillery (The Lowland Gunners) being put into suspended animation as part of the Army 2020 restructuring process. In addition, 38 (Seringapatam) Battery has been subordinated to &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the only Scottish Artillery Regiment remaining, &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt; becomes The Scottish Gunners in order to continue the proud heritage of both the Highland and Lowland Gunners and retain its links with Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parade, which took place at Bhurtpore Barracks, Tidworth Camp, Wiltshire, on Wednesday 12 December, was attended by the Honorary Regimental Colonel Brigadier Will Bramble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Dawes, Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think today is significant and I think everyone has really enjoyed what we marked today. It is important for the regiment and their understanding of where it fits into our precious fabric and I think it is important for what we represent to Scotland as well and not just the Highlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Gunner Richard Caffrey " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5561/LAND-2012-218_19_Regt_Name_Change_079g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gunner Richard Caffrey was presented with a new pipe banner for his pipes [Picture: Corporal Richard Cave RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We put a lot of effort into staying connected with the areas which are most important to us and they are a long way away from Wiltshire. The soldiers get up to Scotland on a fairly regular basis and we make room in our programme to enable that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But in terms of identity and being remembered and staying in the conscience of the civic dignitaries and the cities that are important to us, you have got to put the effort in to get something out and we have really tried to do that this year despite being away on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think the homecoming parades in Dundee and Inverness were very fitting and a great tribute to everything the lads and lassies have put into Afghanistan on behalf of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the soldiers taking a central role in proceedings was Gunner Richard Caffrey, who was the event’s piper and was presented with a new pipe banner for his pipes. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a brilliant experience being out in front and recognised by the field regiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lance Bombardier Markie " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5562/LAND-2012-218_19_Regt_Name_Change_006g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lance Bombardier Markie taking part in the parade at Bhurtpore Barracks to mark the change of name of 19th Regiment Royal Artillery [Picture: Corporal Richard Cave RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have been playing for 11 years now and as a civilian I competed, and when I joined the Army I wanted to know what it would be like playing in a field pipe band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards a stone with a plaque made from brass cartridges fired on Operation HERRICK 16 was unveiled at the base of the flag poles on the parade square at &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Dawes explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have captured on the brass plate all of the tours and all the various sub-units involved and I myself have done several of those tours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a great opportunity to get Brigadier Bramble to unveil this for us, because he of course was the commanding officer on one of those previous tours as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt; returned to its base in Wiltshire in October after a demanding but successful deployment as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29026.aspx" title="12th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;12th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; in Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regiment was employed between March and October this year across Helmand province, supporting 5 battlegroups in its Joint Fires role and operating both on foot and from protected mobility vehicles such as the Jackal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit’s main piece of equipment was the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/equipment/artillery-air-defence/1511.aspx" title="L118 Light Gun"&gt;L118 Light Gun&lt;/a&gt;. During its tour the regiment played a significant role in the mentoring and monitoring of the Afghan National Police and Army and made significant progress in helping to achieve security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Dawes commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think this has been a really important year and really important chapter in our history. I am really proud of everything they have done on tour. We knew it would be a tough tour and we trained very carefully, very intelligently and very hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It came with an impact on our families and our own support networks but they have come through, they have supported everything we have done, and I am proud to say we all came back and are now getting back into family life and need a well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56532</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-fire-chief-to-lead-efficiency-review-of-fire-and-rescue"/>
    <title>Government fire chief to lead efficiency review of fire and rescue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An expert led review into the operational efficiency of the services delivered by fire and rescue authorities in England was announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the public sector deficit, the government has protected fire and rescue authority funding. Some reduction was unavoidable but it was back-loaded so sensible savings could be made without impacting the service the public gets. Overall, fire and rescue authority spending power reductions - which takes into account grants from central government and council tax, was limited to 2.2% in 2011-12 and 0.5% in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is to be conducted by former firefighter and out-going government Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, in the new year. The review will seek to identify ways fire and rescue authorities can pinpoint savings and improvements without reducing the quality life-saving services that the country’s fire firefighters are known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many authorities have begun making efficiencies, but there is more that can be done to be more transparent about spending or introduce joint working with other emergency services liked shared senior management structures, improved procurement practices and better use of estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths and incidents are at an all time low. Over the last decade attendance at incidences has fallen by 39% and attendance at fires by 48%. The review will help today’s fire service reflect that change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conducting the review, Sir Ken Knight will talk to key partners to help develop his findings including the Local Government Association, Fire Sector Federation, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association and the Fire Brigades Union, as well as individual authorities and other emergency services. The report is expected to be completed in the spring of 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We all recognise our firefighters perform an incredibly important public service. That is why spending for fire and rescue authorities, like other blue light services, has been protected. But we cannot escape the reality that every bit of the public sector has to help reduce the deficit we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Public safety is always our first concern and this review will make sure no stone has been left unturned in the quest for the most efficient and effective front-line fire service there can be. I know Sir Ken is passionate about the quality of fire and rescue services and he will bring an enormous amount of experience and knowledge to the task.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With over 40 years in the fire service, I know firefighters care deeply about public safety and want to provide the best possible service, but we need to make sure that service is as effective and efficient as possible. Many authorities have made great strides already, but there is much more that can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This review is a real opportunity to get to grips with what is happening on the ground, to highlight best practice and make sure that every option for efficient working is being explored. I will be talking to firefighters, fire authorities and union reps about how we can get there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review the ways in which fire and rescue authorities may deliver further efficiencies and operational improvements without reducing the quality of front-line services to the public. The review will examine options for savings both within and beyond the current Spending Review period, including through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefighter training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flexible staffing and crewing arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of retained firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaboration with emergency services and other organisations on service delivery and estates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing of senior staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;locally led mergers and operational collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new fire-fighting technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventative approaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with local businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conducting this review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir Ken Knight will talk to key organisations in the fire sector, including the Local Government Association, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association, the Fire Brigades Union, the Fire Sector Federation, individual fire and rescue authorities and others who Sir Ken deems relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Ken will undertake up to 10 visits to a representative range of fire and rescue authorities, including those covering urban and rural areas, and those constituted as metropolitan, county and combined authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department will provide Sir Ken with analytical support, in particular in looking at examples of efficiencies from outside of the fire sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will take into account the findings of previous reviews and reports and their recommendations, including the 2002 ‘Independent Review of the Fire Service’ (the Bain Report), the Audit Commission’s 2008 ‘Community Safety National Report’, ‘Rising to the Challenge’, the 2010 Fire Futures review, and the 2011/2012 ‘Independent Review of Police Officer’ and ‘Staff Remuneration and Conditions’ (the Winsor Reports).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="timeline"&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Announce review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December 2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct field work and analysis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January to March 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Write and present report to DCLG ministers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spring 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact-details-for-responses"&gt;Contact details for responses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sir-ken-knight-biography"&gt;Sir Ken Knight biography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight has been the UK Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser for England since October 2007, advising ministers and senior officials on policy matters including the structure, organisation and performance of fire and rescue services and crucially, providing advice during major and catastrophic emergencies. He is also responsible for the enforcement Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005 in Crown premises in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56197</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:26:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/preferred-bidder-for-the-fire-service-college-confirmed"/>
    <title>Preferred bidder for the Fire Service College confirmed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Fire minister Brandon Lewis has announced Capita as the preferred bidder for the purchase of the Fire Service College.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire minister said he was happy that the proposed sale of the college to Capita would achieve value for money for the public purse and secure the future of the college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that we are making real progress in securing the future of such an important facility. It is vital for the development of the Fire Service College that we put it on a sound footing, giving the private sector a chance to provide innovation and investment that will guarantee the future of a world-class asset.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure best value for money for taxpayers and enable the college to continue in its role, a number of conditions will be imposed on the proposed sale. These include commitments that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the college be preserved as a national training centre for fire and rescue authorities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will continue to offer wider national resilience and emergency services training and exercises&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;government permission will be required if Capita wish to sell the incident ground&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councillor Kay Hammond, Chair of the Local Government Association’s fire services management committee, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is good news that government has listened to the views of the sector about the future of the Fire Service College and that it now looks set to get the outside investment it so badly needs. The Local Government Association and fire authorities will be keen to work with the future owners to help them transform the college into a first-class training facility fit for firefighters in the 21st century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Fire Officers’ Association President, Vij Randeniya, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Chief Fire Officers’ Association welcomes the news that Capita has been selected. It has been a long and intensive process and we are glad that there is now clarity for the Fire Service College. We look forward to working closely with Capita to ensure that the very best provision is available for UK fire and rescue services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government now looks forward to holding constructive discussions with Capita to ensure that the transition from public to private sector is as smooth as possible and expects to complete the sale early in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fire Service College is a trading fund and executive agency of the department. Since becoming a trading fund in 1992, it has never been able to pay a dividend out of operating profits. The government’s response to Fire Futures on 12 April 2011 concluded that the college could achieve its full potential only if there was greater involvement from other sectors in its ownership, operation and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Options project considered 4 options for the future of the college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the status quo: the college remains as a trading fund of the department &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a government owned contractor operated model: the assets remain under government ownership but management of the college is taken over by a private sector company under a long term contract, together with the staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disposal as a going concern: the college is sold to a private sector company who would continue to operate the college as a training centre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closure: the college’s activities cease, staff are made redundant and the site is sold for an alternative use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the 4 options showed disposal as a going concern to be the best option, and the only one which both removes from government ongoing financial risks of ownership of the college and preserves a national training college for the fire and rescue service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers announced on 22 March 2012 that the Fire Service College would be sold as a going concern to a private sector company to continue operating as a training centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale process was launched on 10 April 2012 and the due diligence phase concluded in October with the receipt of final bids. Best and final offers were received in November. The aim is to complete the sale in early 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
