<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/regulation-reform</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/regulation-reform"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/regulation-reform.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Regulation reform"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/61088</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T13:47:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"/>
    <title>Red Tape Challenge: Retail and Manufacturing Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>The purpose of this consultation was to seek views on the amendment and removal of statutory instruments which were identified under the Retail and Manufacturing Red Tape Challenge spotlight process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s response to the consultation was published on the 16th July. This confirms the proposals we intend to take forward which include the revocation of the following measures on the 1st October 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bunk Beds (Entrapment Hazards) (Safety) Regulations 1987 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children’s Clothing (Hood Cords) Regulations 1976 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imitation Dummies (Safety) Regulations 1993 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wheeled Child Conveyances (Safety) Regulations 1997 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas cooking Appliances (Safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating Appliances (Fireguards) (Safety) Regulations 1991 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas Catalytic Heaters (safety) Regulations 1984 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All-Terrain Motor Vehicle (safety) Regulations 1989 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking Utensils (Safety) Regulations 1972 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indication of Prices (Beds) Order 1978 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Child Resistant Packaging and Tactile Danger Warning (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1992 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands for Carry-cots (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 1996 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magnetic Toys (Safety) (Revocation) Regulations 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second Government response was published on the 30th November. This confirms the amendment and revocation of the following regulations on the 6 April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/59915</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T10:57:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:57:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"/>
    <title>Reducing the impact of regulation on business</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Cutting red tape, improving existing regulations and avoiding unnecessary new regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regulations are ineffective and unnecessary. Complying with them costs businesses time and money, and can restrict growth. Red tape can also make running charities and community groups more difficult than it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to ensure all regulations are fair and effective. We want to strike the right balance between protecting people’s rights, health and safety and freeing them from unnecessary bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure regulations in the UK are fair and effective, we are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;controlling the number of new regulations by &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;operating a ‘one in, two out’ rule for business regulation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/assessing-the-impact-of-new-regulation"&gt;assessing the impact of each regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reviewing-the-effectiveness-of-government-regulations"&gt;reviewing the effectiveness of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-regulation-for-small-businesses"&gt;reducing regulation for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/improving-enforcement-of-government-regulations"&gt;improving enforcement of government regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/using-alternatives-to-regulation-education-campaigns-economic-instruments"&gt;using alternatives to regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/reducing-the-cost-of-eu-regulation-on-uk-business"&gt;reducing the cost of EU regulation on UK business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We publish &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publication_filter_option=guidance&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=department-for-business-innovation-skills"&gt;guidance for all government policymakers&lt;/a&gt; to help design better regulations or find other options instead of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, regulations - and the inspections and bureaucracy that go with them - have piled up. Businesses say the amount of new regulation is one of their biggest problems, preventing them from growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/sites/default/files/resources/coalition_programme_for_government.pdf"&gt;coalition agreement&lt;/a&gt;, published in 2010, we said that we would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut red tape for businesses and individuals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not rely on rules and regulations by themselves to get things done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-were-consulting-with"&gt;Who we’re consulting with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re running a series of reviews called ‘Focus on enforcement’ to get businesses’ views on how we could improve the way we enforce regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/"&gt;Have your say on how we enforce regulations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also running the Red Tape Challenge, asking businesses and the public which regulations they think could be removed or improved. See what businesses are saying: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Tell us which regulations you think should be removed or improved.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56972</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T12:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:03:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-figures-show-government-is-winning-war-on-red-tape"/>
    <title>New figures show government is winning war on red tape</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Business Minister pledges tougher action to eliminate burdens on enterprise.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business will benefit from nearly £1 billion in reduced red tape costs thanks to government action, independent figures revealed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Statement of New Regulation reports that the overall closing balance for ‘One-in, One-out’, the government rule that dictates that every new cost on business must be balanced by an equivalent saving, is predicted to be around £836 million since January 2011. These figures are independently verified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the statement shows that the government expects to reduce the regulatory burden by around a further £83 million between January 2013 - when ‘One-in, One-Out’ is replaced by ‘One-in, Two-out’ - and June 2013.  Expected measures include reforms to environmental regulation, employment law and consumer law.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said that Whitehall is increasingly putting the needs of businesses centre stage, but vowed to go further and faster to roll back barriers to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every department is predicting either a zero balance or being in credit at the start of One-in, Two-out, showing that the de-regulatory agenda is having an impact right across Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the overwhelming majority of government measures affecting business are deregulatory, with only ten new items imposing new costs on business compared with 89 that will save money or will impose a zero net cost. The costs from the ‘ins’ (£6 million) are also dwarfed by the savings from the ‘outs’ (£89 million), giving a predicted net saving to business of £83 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent deregulatory measures include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;changes to modernise and simplify the registration of company charges, saving £21.9 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a series of changes to building regulations to reduce cost and complexity for industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less heavy-handed Health and Safety regulations for low-risk businesses including shop and offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improvements to speed up processes covering adoption and foster-carer eligibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government has a very simple objective: to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business.  This requires a fundamental culture change in Whitehall, so that new regulation is only imposed as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve made a promising start, but firms still struggle with excessive red tape.  We’ll now push departments to go further to bear down on costs imposed on business, and we’ll fight harder to get EU bureaucracy off the back of our entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time this Statement sets out EU measures that will be introduced during the reporting period, giving businesses time to prepare for these changes.   Fifty-seven EU measures are expected to be implemented into UK legislation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every six months the government publishes a Statement of New Regulation listing of all the regulations it plans to introduce and remove in the next six months, and showing the net direct costs to business. The Fifth Statement of New Regulation is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business/supporting-pages/operating-a-one-in-two-out-rule-for-business-regulation"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘One-in, One-out’ rule was introduced on 1 September 2010 and applies to regulations introduced from January 2011.  The rule prevents any government department introducing new regulation that will impose a direct net cost on business and voluntary organisations - unless the department can find savings by removing or modifying another regulation of an equivalent cost. ‘One-in, Two-out’ will also operate in this way, but the removal or modification must be of twice the equivalent cost. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like ‘One-in, One-out’ , ‘One-in, Two-Out’ will not apply to EU legislation unless it has been converted into UK law in a way that goes beyond minimum EU requirements, putting UK businesses at a disadvantage.  A number of other areas are exempt from the rule, including tax administration and civil emergencies regulation. More detail is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-the-impact-of-regulation-on-business"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When developing a new regulatory or deregulatory proposal, each Government department must carry out an impact assessment. This includes estimating the likely cost to business. To ensure estimates are credible, the impact assessment is considered by an independent body, the Regulatory Policy Committee (RPC). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red Tape Challenge is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the Government inherited, with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The government announced on 10 September 2012 that at least 3,000 of the regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. A second phase of the Red Tape Challenge will start in spring 2013.  More information on the Red Tape Challenge is avaiable &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alongside the drive to remove superfluous regulation, government is working to ensure that necessary regulations on business are enforced more efficiently. Focus on Enforcement reviews are being carried out across a number of sectors where aspects of the enforcement regime may be imposing unnecessary burdens on business, making inefficient use of public sector resources or hampering economic growth.  At Autumn Statement, the government also announced a number of measures to tackle systemic issues, including the lack of consistent fees and charges and appeals mechanisms. The Focus on Enforcement website is available &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/iscuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56364</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T12:02:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dclg-statement-of-new-regulation-1-january-to-30-june-2013"/>
    <title>DCLG statement of new regulation - 1 January to 30 June 2013</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Overview of regulations that are scheduled to be implemented or removed between 1 January and 30 June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The headline figures show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we are introducing 24 measures in this period, 20 of which are deregulatory measures that will reduce the burden on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;none of these measures will increase the regulatory burden on businesses, as they are all either deregulatory measures that will bring savings to business, or regulatory measures that have no cost to business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Regulatory Policy Committee have evaluated 5 of our measures and estimated that they will reduce the burden on business by £45.36 million per year. We expect this figure to rise considerably as our other measures are validated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60126</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:15:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-regulations-covering-january-to-june-2013"/>
    <title>BIS fifth statement of new regulation: regulations covering January to June 2013</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Informs businesses and interested stakeholders of Department for Business domestic regulations that come into force between January and June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lists Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) measures in scope of ‘One in, two out’ regulations to come into force from January to June 2013, to show how &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; is removing burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60128</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-sonr"/>
    <title>Fifth statement of new regulation (SONR)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An overview of regulations planned to be implemented or removed by government departments between 1 January and 30 June 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides a forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘One-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect. The headline figures show that the sum total of government deregulation by July 2013 is expected to reduce the annual cost to business by around £919 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56434</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:00:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-tackles-red-tape-head-on-with-package-of-measures"/>
    <title>Government tackles red tape head on with package of measures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review of the way that appeals are handled by regulators launched today is the first stage of a new wave of bureaucracy busting measures announced by the government, Business Minister Michael Fallon confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and other interested parties will have a chance to take part in a review of the effectiveness of appeals mechanisms operated by national and local regulators. The Focus on Enforcement Appeals Review will give those affected the opportunity to talk about their experiences of formal and informal appeals processes, and suggest how they could be made to work more effectively, providing a swifter route to resolution and better industry understanding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will also gather examples of approaches that have successfully helped businesses understand regulators’ decisions and meet their obligations more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have started a bonfire of excessive red tape, but I know that it is just as important that we look at the way that regulations are enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is room for far more effective enforcement which reduces the burden on business which stick to the rules.  Despite best efforts, sometimes things can go wrong – that has become clear from previous Focus on Enforcement Reviews. So I want to hear views on how we can improve the way appeals currently work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greater clarity and trust between regulators and businesses will lead to better enforcement of the law and higher standards across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest review follows a package of new measures announced at the Autumn Statement to tackle systemic problems with the way regulations are enforced and cut the unnecessary red tape and burdens that companies have to deal with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a consultation on placing a legislative duty on non-economic regulators to have regard to growth and take into account the economic impacts of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new accounting system for regulators, so that in future regulators will have to publish impact assessments for prior consultation, scrutiny and challenge by industry, of the impacts of all changes in their activities that have a significant (positive and negative) financial impact on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consultation on an amended Regulators’ Compliance Code to ensure regulators are internally and geographically consistent, give consideration to earned recognition, and offer minimum service standards to those they regulate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;government action to ensure regulators are transparent about the fees they charge and bear down on their costs and improve their efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also today, as part of the package the government announced plans to cut bureaucracy by widening the range of regulations included in the Primary Authority scheme. The plans would see the scheme covering age-related sales of gambling, the Housing Health and Safety Rating system for assessing potential hazards in dwellings, sun-bed tanning and Welsh regulations for single-use carrier bag charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Michael Fallon added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships are reducing regulatory burdens for companies and allowing them to grow. It’s now time to extend the scope of the scheme to streamline the way regulators work with businesses, improve protections to the public and help local authorities to target their resources against rogue traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major business groups such as the CBI, British Retail Consortium and FSB are strongly in favour of Primary Authority and of its extension. The Trading Standards Institute and Chartered Institute of Environmental Health are also in favour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence arising from sector-specific Focus on Enforcement reviews has already indicated that businesses have concerns about how current appeals systems operate. These include confusing or multiple appeals mechanisms lack of transparency and in some cases resolution taking excessively long periods of time.   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The forthcoming review will invite evidence from all sectors of the economy and any regulatory regime. Appeals mechanisms for economic regulators are not included in the scope of this review. Interested parties can participate in the review of appeals at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/focusonenforcement/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year at Budget, the government announced a new approach to cutting red tape, looking at how rules are enforced, rather than the rules themselves. A series of Focus on Enforcement Reviews have shown that in addition to sector-specific issues, there are also systemic enforcement issues limiting industry that affect most if not all sectors. So, rather than tackling systemic issues case by case, the Government’s Autumn Statement package  aims to change the system, creating greater clarity and fairness for businesses while ensuring regulators focus their resources where they are needed most. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Primary Authority Scheme is run by the Better Regulation Delivery Office, an independent unit within the Business Innovation and Skills Department (BIS). See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are currently 602 businesses and 93 local authorities involved in Primary Authority partnerships, covering over 58,000 premises and over 1.57 million employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the scope of the scheme, or the list of regulations which can be covered by partnerships, can be achieved by secondary legislation. The consultation announced today runs until 24 January 2013 to allow feedback from stakeholders before secondary legislation is introduced into Parliament.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Housing Health and Safety Rating System (HHSRS) is a risk-based evaluation tool to help local authorities identify and protect against potential risks and hazards to health and safety from any deficiencies identified in dwellings. It was introduced under the Housing Act 2004 and applies to residential properties in England and Wales.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer, George Osborne, has delivered his 2012 Autumn Statement to Parliament.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56356</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:33:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation-second-government-response"/>
    <title>Red tape challenge retail and manufacturing consultation: second government response</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Second government response to the retail and manufacturing consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second government response to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/red-tape-challenge-retail-and-manufacturing-consultation--2"&gt;red tape challenge retail and manufacturing consultation&lt;/a&gt; covering the government’s amendment of the Pyrotechnic Articles and revocation of the Pencils and Graphic Instruments Regulations. Also summarises public responses to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56620</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/10-point-plan-for-eu-smart-regulation"/>
    <title>10 point plan for EU smart regulation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Business, along with Ministers from 12 other Member States, jointly signed a ‘10 point plan for EU smart regulation’. Sent to Commission President Barroso on 19 November 2012, in advance of the Commission’s forthcoming Smart Regulation Communication in December 2012. It calls on the Commission to advance the agenda on smart regulation, and to cut red tape at the EU level by reducing the overall EU regulatory burden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
