<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/science-and-innovation</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/science-and-innovation"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/science-and-innovation.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Science and innovation"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <summary>New Innovation Vouchers for businesses who want to use public open data to develop new ideas, improve processes and target new markets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56759</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:45:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:45:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-innovation-workshop"/>
    <title>Support for Innovation Workshop</title>
    <summary>Support for Innovation Workshop, 30th January 2013, 9.30am to 3.30pm, Business &amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library, NE1 8AX</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library, NE1 8AX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30th January 2013, 9.30am to 3.30pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying competitive and growing a business in today’s challenging trading conditions is tough.  However, a range of Government support and funding is available to help your business innovate and grow. Find out more at this free practical workshop for small and medium sized businesses with the appetite and potential to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus will be on the importance of innovation to future success and how government schemes can help you develop, protect and commercialise new ideas. Subjects include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-innovation"&gt;Importance of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Addison, innovation specialist and pioneer of Procter &amp;amp; Gamble’s open innovation programme, will describe how innovation is vital for growth. In particular, P&amp;amp;G’s approach to open innovation could be reused in your business for sourcing and commercialising new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="support-for-innovation"&gt;Support for Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering grants and other support for R&amp;amp;D through the Technology Strategy Board and the R&amp;amp;D Tax Credit scheme run by HMRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-your-innovation"&gt;Protecting Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering support from the Intellectual Property Office to protect your IP and how schemes like Patent Box can make it much more cost effective to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commercialising-your-innovation"&gt;Commercialising Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including support from the Design Council to enhance product value through design and how Growth Accelerator can support your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Register for the free workshop at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk"&gt;www.business-events.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is being held at the Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library. The Centre is designed to support entrepreneurs, inventors and small businesses from that first spark of inspiration to successfully launching and developing a business. It is the first regional centre based on the British Library’s model and have been running since September 2011. Since the launch, over 2,000 entrepreneurs have used the Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre is a partnership between the British Library, Newcastle City Council, Newcastle Science City and Northumbria University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56674</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/science-and-innovation-network-annual-report-2011-12"/>
    <title>Science and Innovation Network: Annual Report 2011 - 12</title>
    <summary>The Science and Innovation Network supports UK economic and social goals through international collaboration in science research and innovation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report shows the scope of the work carried out by the Science and Innovation Network, a joint &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;-&lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; network operating in around 28 countries and territories around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt; officers are scientifically literate staff in &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; posts who work to benefit the UK through influencing the science and innovation policies of governments, businesses and academia, informing UK policy, and promoting ‘best with best’ collaboration between the UK and other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report, launched by &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; Permanent Secretary, Martin Donnelly, and &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; Chief Scientific Advisor, David Clary, at the &lt;abbr title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; on 12 December 2012, gives an overview of the &lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt; and highlights some of its achievements over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Science and Innovation Network"&gt;SIN&lt;/abbr&gt;’s 90+ staff are managed by a team based in &lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;’s International Knowledge and Innovation Unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56702</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/engaging-the-public-in-science-and-engineering--3"/>
    <title>Engaging the public in science and engineering</title>
    <summary>High levels of skills in science, technology, engineering and maths are essential for the UK’s prosperity</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science and research are major contributors to the prosperity of the UK. For our prosperity to continue, the government believes we need high levels of skills in science, technology, engineering and maths (&lt;abbr title="science, technology, engineering and maths"&gt;STEM&lt;/abbr&gt;), and citizens that value them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To engage the public in science and engineering we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hold the British Science Festival and the National Science and Engineering Week, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/engaging-the-public-in-science-and-engineering--3/supporting-pages/raising-public-awareness-of-science-engineering-and-technology"&gt;events that promote science and raise the public’s awareness of science issues&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/engaging-the-public-in-science-and-engineering--3/supporting-pages/funding-national-academies"&gt;fund the work of 3 independent national academies&lt;/a&gt;: the Royal Society, the British Academy and the Royal Academy of Engineering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/engaging-the-public-in-science-and-engineering--3/supporting-pages/making-informed-science-policy-decisions"&gt;make science and engineering policy decisions that are informed by monitoring public opinion&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promote science in schools and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/engaging-the-public-in-science-and-engineering--3/supporting-pages/inspiring-students-to-study-science-technology-engineering-and-mathematics"&gt;fund programmes and events that inspire students to study &lt;abbr title="science, technology, engineering and maths"&gt;STEM&lt;/abbr&gt; subjects&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008 the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) funded &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-vision-for-science-and-society--2"&gt;A Vision for Science and Society - A consultation on Developing a New Strategy for the UK&lt;/a&gt; to find out how we should develop science skills, improve science communication and build public confidence in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation identified five areas for us to improve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;science for all - changing public attitudes on science&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;science and the media - training the scientific community to work with the media     &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;science and learning - inspiring young people to take an interest in and study &lt;abbr title="science, technology, engineering and maths"&gt;STEM&lt;/abbr&gt; subjects     &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;science and careers - improving career advice for people wanting to work in science&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;science and trust - increasing public trust in how science is done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on this consultation we have drafted a set of criteria on what we should fund, which has been open to the public for comment. The next step is to develop a new set of science and society activities ready for the next financial year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/55784</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:00:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth"/>
    <title>Investing in research, development and innovation</title>
    <summary>We want to use our talent to make the UK the best place in the world to run an innovative business or service</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK excels in research, development and innovation, and innovative companies are an important contributor to economic growth. We want to use our talent to make the UK the best place in the world to run an innovative business or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trying to be smarter and more strategic in how we &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/supporting-pages/using-government-purchasing-power-to-stimulate-innovation"&gt;procure goods, works and services to encourage innovation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping researchers, developers, innovators and businesses &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/supporting-pages/bringing-together-knowledge-skills-technical-resources-and-capital"&gt;bring together specific knowledge, skills, technical resources and financial capital&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;getting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/supporting-pages/business-and-academia-working-together"&gt;business to work more closely with universities and research institutions&lt;/a&gt; to create more opportunities to commercialise their research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/supporting-pages/making-taxpayer-funded-research-accessible"&gt;taxpayer-funded research accessible and free of charge to use&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-investment-in-research-development-and-innovation-for-growth/supporting-pages/growthaccelerator-and-the-uk-innovation-investment-fund"&gt;helping England’s 26,000 most promising mid-sized businesses achieve growth - a 70% increase in turnover or employment, and funding business through the UK Innovation Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We published the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/innovation/docs/i/11-1387-innovation-and-research-strategy-for-growth.pdf"&gt;Innovation and research strategy for growth&lt;/a&gt; on 8 December 2011. The main aim of the strategy is to support business research and development in areas where the UK excels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56637</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T13:40:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/strength-opportunity-2012-the-landscape-of-the-medical-biotechnology-industrial-biotechnology-and-pharmaceutical-sectors-in-the-uk-annual-update-december-2012--2"/>
    <title>Strength &amp; opportunity 2012: the landscape of the medical biotechnology, industrial biotechnology and pharmaceutical sectors in the UK. Annual update - December 2012</title>
    <summary>Fourth annual report analysing the updated 2012 dataset from the bioscience and health technology database.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fourth annual report analysing the updated 2012 dataset from the bioscience and health technology database. The data relates to companies that are active in the UK in three of the life sciences sectors: medical technology, medical biotechnology and industrial biotechnology. Enables comparisons against last year’s information to see how these sectors are changing. Overview of this highly innovative industry with over 4,500 companies, employing over 167,000 people and generating a turnover of over £50 billion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56987</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/annual-innovation-report-2012-innovation-research-and-growth"/>
    <title>Annual innovation report 2012: innovation, research and growth</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fourth annual innovation report that gives the latest available evidence on UK innovation performance and the contribution of business, government, higher education and research organisations to UK innovation activities. Presents key measures of innovation and research performance, and provides a benchmark to track performance measures for the Innovation and research strategy for growth (URN 11/1387). Also records the practical progress made implementing the strategy. Underlying data for this publication is available in a machine processable format on the Transparency/Report Data webpage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48270</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uk-innovation-survey-2011-statistical-annex-revised"/>
    <title>UK innovation survey 2011: statistical annex [revised]</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statistical annex for data from the 2011 UK innovation survey (12/P107). It includes an overview of the methodology, details of response rates and weighting, and reference tables with the survey results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56302</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-a-synthetic-biology-roadmap-for-the-uk-letter-from-david-willetts-mp-to-dr-lionel-clarke"/>
    <title>Response to 'A synthetic biology roadmap for the UK': letter from David Willetts MP to Dr Lionel Clarke</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government’s response to the UK Synthetic Biology Roadmap Coordination Group’s recommendations for the future development of synthetic biology in the UK. Synthetic biology aims to design, engineer or replicate biological systems, for example biosynthetic insulin. This letter explains how the government is working to stimulate innovation, responsible commercial exploitation, economic growth and quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47148</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/vince-cable-promotes-uk-advanced-manufacturing"/>
    <title>Vince Cable promotes UK advanced manufacturing</title>
    <summary>On 5 November Vince Cable officially opened MIRA Technology Park's new control centre. He also visited Toyota in Burnaston to celebrate the first new Auris model to roll off the production line.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;8 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="mira-technology-park"&gt;MIRA Technology Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIRA Technology Park (MTP) was granted &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;Enterprise Zone&lt;/a&gt; status by the government in August 2011. This has enabled MIRA to become Europe’s most advance independent transport technology facility. It is the first milestone in MIRA’s aim to become Europe’s most advance independent transport technology facility. Vince Cable opened the Technology Park’s new £6 million Control Centre, with the help of a MIRA unmanned vehicle to cut the ribbon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIRA provides state-of-the-art secure research facilities where high-tech companies can develop products that will make the world’s vehicles cleaner, smarter and safer. With companies like Bosch, Ashok Leyland, Triumph Motorcycles, Norgren and Lockheed Martin, the MTP cluster will help the UK to benefit from advanced automotive manufacturing, through deep rooted research and development.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was created the Technology Park has created 188 jobs, and a further 145 will be created in 2013. These are steps towards the goal of creating 2,000 jobs at MIRA over the next 10 years, and will contribute to the growth of advanced manufacturing in the Midlands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-for-low-carbon-automotive-research-and-development-challenge"&gt;Funding for low carbon automotive research and development challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary also announced £16.5m of funding for the next low carbon automotive research and development challenge from the Technology Strategy Board (TSB), the Office of Low Emission Vehicles (OLEV) and the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC). This will support R&amp;amp;D into four key areas: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internal combustion engines &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy storage and management &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lightweight vehicle and powertrain structures, and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electric machines and power electronics. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="toyota"&gt;Toyota&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the day at Toyota in Burnaston, Vince Cable witnessed the launch of production of the new Auris model - this time in all its hybrid, petrol and diesel guises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary acknowledged Toyota’s critical part in the success story of the UK automotive manufacturing industry. Toyota has &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;made the technology to reduce carbon dioxide from cars a mainstream proposition, as the first company to manufacture a volume hybrid vehicle in Europe &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;boosted UK automotive manufacturing by investing in Burnaston, including £185 million in Auris for its European markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable met Toyota workers who were initially recruited as temporary contractors and were then offered production apprenticeships. Toyota now offers all new production workers a Level 2 apprenticeship. A high percentage have taken up this apprenticeship offer, with some going on to become direct Toyota employees. This supports the government’s aim to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/holt-review-new-measures-to-improve-apprenticeships-for-smes"&gt;promote apprenticeships and make them more widely available&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regional-growth-funding-for-derby"&gt;Regional Growth Funding for Derby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable also confirmed that Derby City Council will receive £40 million for its programme bid under Round 2 of the Regional Growth Fund (RGF), supporting growth and sustainable employment in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Programme will provide funds to support local business investment. This is expected to create around 3,000 new private sector jobs in the area in 2020, and develop local transport infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://enterprisezones.communities.gov.uk/"&gt;Enterprise Zones&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-sectors/docs/g/12-1010-growing-uk-automotive-supply-chain-2012-update.pdf"&gt;Growing the automotive supply chain: the road forward - 2012 update (PDF, 257 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/holt-review-new-measures-to-improve-apprenticeships-for-smes"&gt;Support for small businesses in taking on apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Employers/The-Benefits.aspx"&gt;Business benefits of apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
