<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/trade-and-investment</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/trade-and-investment"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/trade-and-investment.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Trade and investment"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60204</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria"/>
    <title>UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria  </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt: The UK will continue to support work of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria to ensure accountability. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the publication of a new UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today the UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria published its latest report on the human rights situation in Syria. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. The Commission concludes that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commission has received credible accounts of Government soldiers executing captives. Incidents of direct targeting of civilians by aerial bombardment, including “barrel bombs,” rocket attacks and machine gun fire have risen significantly over recent months. There is testimony of systematic patterns of torture in detention centres, including of children. This report is a stark reminder of the horrific situation in Syria. I call upon all sides to put an end to the violence and pursue a process of genuine political transition which reflects the will of the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work undertaken by the UN Commission of inquiry, in difficult circumstances, is vital to ensure that human rights violations and abuses committed by all parties are documented. We will continue to do all we can to support their work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Countries/SY/ColSyriaDecember2012.pdf" title="UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Countries/MENARegion/Pages/SYIndex.aspx" title="UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60181</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-court-of-human-rights-decision-on-chagossian-case"/>
    <title>European Court of Human Rights’ decision on Chagossian Case</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary has commented on the European Court of Human Rights’ decision on the Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom case. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case concerns complaints made by the Chagos Islanders arising from the evacuation of the British Indian Ocean Territory between 1967 and 1973.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the end of this legal process, which has taken many years. We have made clear our regret for the wrongs done to the Chagossian people over forty years ago. Nevertheless, it was right for the Government to defend itself against this action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that this litigation is concluded, the Government will take stock of our policy towards the resettlement of the British Indian Ocean Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;), as we have always said we would. There are fundamental difficulties with resettlement in &lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;, but we will be as positive as possible in our engagement with Chagossian groups and all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Human Rights decision on application 35622/04: Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.echr.coe.int/ECHR/Homepage_EN" title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60742</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:30:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-partnership-to-support-defence-industry"/>
    <title>New partnership to support defence industry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior defence industry leader Steve Wadey is today named as the co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership (DGP) – a new partnership between industry and Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon, who will also be co-chair of the DGP, announced Mr Wadey’s appointment as he underlined the importance of the defence industry to the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Wadey is UK Managing Director of missile systems company MBDA, a multi-national group with over 10,000 employees in the United Kingdom, France, Italy, Germany, Spain and the United States. He is also Executive Group Director Technical for the MBDA Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence industry is a significant contributor to the UK’s economy, contributing more than £22 billion of annual revenues of which £5.4 billion is from exports. It directly employs more than 107,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government, working closely with industry, is determined to support the sector. Government already plays a leading role in promoting defence exports and encouraging defence SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  DGP will continue this work – but will also look at how links between civil and military technologies can be better exploited. In addition, it will look at the skills required for the sector and how there can be more flexibility in the workforce between the defence sector and advanced manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK’s defence sector is world class – employing the latest technology and advanced engineering to products relied upon by armed forces around the world. In doing so, it provides many thousands of highly skilled jobs in the UK and is an important part of the nation’s industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Along with other parts of the economy, the sector is facing tough times. This new partnership between Government and industry will help address the barriers to growth for the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology Philip Dunne said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MOD has active engagement with the defence industry which faces testing times as defence budgets come under pressure across the world. It is important for Government and business to understand each other and work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Defence Growth Partnership will help us to confront these challenges and build on existing relationships and industry successes to date – helping the UK defence industry maintain its position as the world’s second largest exporter of new Defence products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wadey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to accept the position of co-chair of the Defence Growth Partnership alongside Michael Fallon. The defence industry plays a vital and strategic role in the UK’s industrial, technological and manufacturing base, as well as being a major driver of exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to investing in the skills and industrial capability needed for future prosperity.  Working in partnership with the Government, the defence industry will play its role in driving growth in the UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Chisnall, Deputy Chief Executive, ADS, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of a Defence Growth Partnership, building on the growing success of the Aerospace Growth Partnership, is strongly welcomed and supported by ADS and our many hundreds of member companies large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Defence sector is of profound importance to national security, equipping and supporting our Armed Forces and key Allies. It is also a major economic force, contributing over £22 billion of annual revenues to the UK, of which £5.4 billion are from exports, and maintaining directly over 107,000 highly skilled jobs across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister expressed his view at the Farnborough International Airshow in July that the AGP is seen as a model engagement process between Government and industry and we look forward to a similar constructive partnership as we jointly develop a growth plan for UK defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DGP builds on the successful Aerospace Growth Partnership model which is a new approach to Government-industry relations in the growing and high potential aerospace sector. A vision document for the aerospace sector was launched by Business Secretary Vince Cable at the Farnborough International Airshow in July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Prime Minister announced the intention to form the DGP at the Farnborough International Airshow this year. Business Secretary Vince Cable is the lead Cabinet Minister for the DGP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steve Wadey was appointed UK Managing Director of MBDA at the start of 2003, responsible for delivery of the UK Business. Steve is also Executive Group Director Technical with responsibility for the technical capability, industrial policy, company investment and advanced systems and products across the MBDA Group.
In addition to his role within MBDA, Steve has been the National Defence Industries Council Research and Development Group (NDIC RDG) Co-Chairman since 2006 and in 2010 was appointed as the Industry Representative to UK MoD Research &amp;amp; Development Board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on membership of the DGP and its exact remit will follow in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Monmouth and her Royal Marines have been working with the US Navy to demonstrate how they can help keep the sea lanes open in the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/56575</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T09:02:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T09:02:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the single market more effective</title>
    <category>Policy</category>
    <summary>Plans to make the single market more competitive, easier to do business in and create new jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the EU expanded to include more states, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate acheived by other EU states. However, the European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at a rate as low as just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the EU and other dynamic markets, such as South Korea, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the EU as a whole. To achieve higher growth and increased employment, all member states and the EU institutions will need to take action. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which encourages all member states to reinforce financial stability, create jobs and improve competitiveness, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong single market creates jobs and benefits all member states. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234 billion, went to the EU. The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other EU prime ministers, urged the EU to improve the single market, concentrating on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update EU single market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting EU consumers in cyberspace. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;.  Member States must implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013. E-invoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-invoicing within the EU could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;EU-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; which came into force on 1 July 2011 is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for EU exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act (2011)&lt;/a&gt; sets out twelve ways to boost growth and improve confidence in European business. In October 2012 the European Commission proposed a second set of actions, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smact/docs/single-market-act2_en.pdf"&gt;Single Market Act II&lt;/a&gt;, to further develop the single market’s economic opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52011DC0206:EN:NOT"&gt;The Single Market Act II (2012)&lt;/a&gt; describes the EU’s goals of improving the digital economy, including e-commerce and electronic invoicing, and creating more efficient transport and energy networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/europe/docs/u/11-760-uk-response-single-market-act"&gt;response to The Single Market Act&lt;/a&gt; in February 2011 looks at how the UK will work with other member states on reforms that will create the most jobs and economic growth at the lowest cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;) published a study, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/e/11-517-economic-consequences-of-completing-single-market"&gt;The economic consequences for the UK and the EU of completing the single market&lt;/a&gt;, in February 2011. This paper considers the benefits of the single market and the negative effects of the UK opting out of future European trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Business, Innovation &amp;amp; Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt; published a study in 2011, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/feeds/~/media/568CC723188C40DFBB02E868353B40B9.ashx"&gt;The UK and the single market: trade and investment analytical papers topic 4 of 18&lt;/a&gt;, that examines the importance of the EU for British exporters and investors. The analysis found that businesses have benefited from the opportunities provided by the single market. Such benefits include: better connected and cheaper networks; mutual recognition of standards; and easier access to cheap and competitive inputs for British manufacturers. In addition greater competition within the single market has fostered innovation. For consumers, the single market has created more choice and lowered prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
