<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:03+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/59922</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:03+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/passengers-come-first-in-new-civil-aviation-act"/>
    <title>Passengers come first in new Civil Aviation Act </title>
    <summary>The Civil Aviation Act has become law today and paves the way for airports to offer better facilities and information for passengers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers have today been placed firmly at the heart of UK airport regulation as a new Civil Aviation Act becomes law. The Act paves the way for the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) to motivate airports to deliver better facilities, provide more information for passengers and give greater incentives for airports to prepare for disruptive events such as severe weather. The Act also makes provisions for future reforms to the Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing (&lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme, which offers financial protection for holiday makers in the event of their tour operator going bust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Act sees a number of key changes to the powers and responsibilities of the aviation regulator, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; a single overriding duty, for its airport economic functions, to further the interests of passengers and owners of cargo in the provision of airport operation services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a flexible licensing regime for regulated airports, enabling the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; to include licence conditions that require airports to respond more effectively when things go wrong (e.g. severe weather)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;, where appropriate, to replace fixed price caps on airports with lighter touch forms of regulation and removing unnecessary central government involvement from airport regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; more effective enforcement powers, allowing it to impose sanctions of up to 10% of an airport operator’s annual turnover and daily amounts of 0.1% of turnover for breaching licence conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; with a new role in promoting better public information about airline and airport performance levels, enabling passengers to make informed decisions when making travel arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; with a new role to promote better public information about the environmental effects of aviation and measures taken to mitigate adverse effects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conferring certain aviation security functions currently carried out by the Department for Transport, on to the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Responsibility for aviation security policy, and giving aviation security directions to industry, will remain with the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Act also enables Ministers to make future changes to the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; holiday protection scheme, including the ability to bring holidays sold by airlines into the scope of the scheme. Earlier this year, the government introduced secondary legislation to update the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; holiday protection scheme, making it more relevant to today’s market. The new powers in the Act will enable the protection available to consumers to be further strengthened. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is an important milestone in our drive to put the passenger experience unequivocally at the heart of how our airports are run.  Aviation is vital for providing the UK with the connections we need to do business, travel for leisure and visit our friends and families around the world.  I am grateful for the cross-party support this Act has received during its passage through Parliament – ensuring passengers and those sending cargo can enjoy the benefits of this new regime as swiftly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the Act has received Royal Assent, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will work to bring the new airport economic regulatory framework fully into force in April 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act introduces, and enables, reform in 4 main areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the framework for economic regulation of airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the legislative framework of the Civil Aviation Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing scheme (&lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conferring certain aviation security functions currently carried out by the Department for Transport, on to the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; - responsibility for aviation security policy remains with the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the new regulatory regime for airports, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; is empowered to carry out a market power test, as set out in the Act, to determine whether an airport operator should or should not be subject to economic regulation. This replaces the designation of airports for price control regulation by the Secretary of State. Heathrow, Gatwick and Stansted airports are currently designated and their current price controls, set under the Airports Act 1986, will continue to run until 31 March 2014. Over the next 18 months, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will determine how to apply the new regime set out in the Act to the airports that are subject to economic regulation after this date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the existing regime, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; has 4 duties for the purposes of economic regulation, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to further the reasonable interests of users of airports within the UK. Users comprises airlines, passengers and other user of air transport services at the airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote the efficient, economic and profitable operation of such airports &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment in new facilities at airports in time to satisfy anticipated demands by the users of such airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to impose the minimum restrictions that are consistent with the performance by the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; of its functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also required to take account of international obligations notified to it by the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures set out today will replace these with a single primary duty and a number of further duties to which the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; must have regard in carrying out the primary duty for the purposes of airport economic regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="primary-duty"&gt;Primary duty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to further the interests of passengers and owners of cargo (both present and future), in the provision of airport operation services and to do so, wherever appropriate, by promoting competition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="further-duties"&gt;Further duties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to ensure that licence holders are able to finance their provision of airport operation services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to secure that all reasonable demands for airport operation services are met&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote economy and efficiency on the part of licence holders in their provision of airport operation services at regulated airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to secure that licence holders are able to take reasonable measures to reduce, control or mitigate adverse environmental effects of the airport to which the licence relates and aircraft using that airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to guidance issued by the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to any international obligation of the UK notified to it by the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to the principles of better regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will have a duty not to impose or maintain unnecessary burdens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expanded regulation-making powers in the Act would allow more holidays to be included in the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme and would provide even greater clarity for consumers whilst ensuring a level regulatory playing field for businesses selling flight-inclusive holidays. The government’s intention is that such a step would only be taken following full consultation with stakeholders including an impact assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57512</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/operators-urged-to-tackle-crowding-on-busiest-services"/>
    <title>Operators urged to tackle crowding on busiest services</title>
    <summary>Train operators are urged to tackle overcrowding on their services after a list reveals the top 10 most congested trains.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker has urged train operators to continue work to tackle congestion on their services following the publication today of the top 10 most crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London is served by some of the busiest trains in the country according to the list of crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Climbing on a crowded train where there is little space can often be an unpleasant experience and I sympathise with passengers who have to travel on these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The operators on the list are aware of the crowding problems on these particular services. I will be monitoring these services closely, and others which have not made the top 10 list, and urging train companies to reduce crowding on the busiest services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail has experienced unprecedented growth in recent years. That is why we are investing in more carriages, longer trains and better services and funding major projects like HS2, Crossrail and Thameslink, all of which will significantly boost capacity on our rail network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an important tool to give increased transparency to passengers and help the industry act to improve journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list, compiled from data collected in Autumn 2011, shows that the following services were the busiest in England and Wales (in descending order): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington – load factor 180%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:32am service from Woking to London Waterloo – load factor 164%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:13pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 162%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4:48pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 160%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington – load factor 158%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon – load factor 157%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough – load factor 155%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:17pm service from London Liverpool Street to Shenfield – load factor 154%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:14am service from Alton to London Waterloo – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5:46pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport (DfT) collects rail passenger counts from train operating companies to monitor train crowding levels. All franchises let by DfT require the train operator to address crowding and to plan their timetables in such a way as to ensure, as far as possible, that crowding is not unduly concentrated on any particular route or individual service. The table included in this paper shows the 10 most overcrowded peak services in the autumn 2011 passenger counts data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘top 10’ list is determined based on ‘load factor’, which is the number of standard class passengers on a service expressed as a percentage of the standard class passenger capacity for that service. For example, a train which has the same passenger load as the passenger capacity would have a load factor of 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Great Western has recently strengthened the 7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington by adding an additional carriage, so that the number of standard class seats has increased to 340.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From December 2012 London Midland is providing three Class 350/2 ‘high density’ units for the 6:13pm service from London to Birmingham New Street to maximise the number of seats. In the long term, London Midland has 10 new 4 car trains on order that will allow them to operate additional trains on this route from 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From September 2012, the 6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington has started from Oxford not Banbury, leaving Oxford at 7:00am. It is now operated by a different type of rolling stock which provides a higher standard class seating capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More recent counts on the 7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon suggest much lower loadings on this service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the long term, from the May 2014 timetable period, it is planned to introduce a fifth train per hour between Manchester and Leeds which should relieve capacity on the 6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 10 list can be accessed on the &lt;a href="/government/publications/top-10-overcrowded-train-services-england-and-wales"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60046</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:10:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-aviation-act-frequently-asked-questions"/>
    <title>Civil Aviation Act: frequently asked questions</title>
    <summary>Questions and answers about the Civil Aviation Act.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The document features frequently asked questions about the Civil Aviation Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act paves the way for the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) to motivate airports to deliver better facilities, provide more information for passengers and give greater incentives for airports to prepare for disruptive events such as severe weather. The Act also makes provisions for future reforms to the Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing (ATOL) scheme, which offers financial protection for holiday makers in the event of their tour operator going bust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48870</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/top-10-overcrowded-train-services-england-and-wales"/>
    <title>Top 10 overcrowded train services: England and Wales</title>
    <summary>A list of the 10 most overcrowded peak train services recorded in passenger count data collected by train operators.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper shows the 10 most overcrowded peak train services recorded in passenger count data collected by train operators in autumn 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) collects rail passenger counts from train operating companies to monitor train crowding levels. All franchises let by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; require the train operator to address crowding and to plan their timetables in such a way as to ensure, as far as possible, that crowding is not unduly concentrated on any particular route or individual service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59988</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:21:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-06-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 06/2012</title>
    <summary>Despatch is the ezine for road safety professionals from the Driving Standards Agency (DSA). You can download issue 06/2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving motoring services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new online service being rolled out to approved driving instructors (&lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADIs&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;booking tests from mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to improve &lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADI&lt;/abbr&gt; check tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better rehabilitation for drink drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; launching an &lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADI&lt;/abbr&gt; theory test DVD-ROM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57030</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-local-roads"/>
    <title>Cash boost for local roads</title>
    <summary>Extra £215 million to local authorities for road maintenance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils can plan how to spend their share of a £215 million fund for local road maintenance after funding allocations were published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £215 million is part of a £333 million fund announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend the life of roads in England.  This funding is in addition to the £3 billion the government is already providing for councils in England between 2011 and 2015 for highways maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This maintenance funding could be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges or repairing damage to highway infrastructure caused by severe weather events, such as the recent flooding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extra money will support economic growth and development by helping local authorities to get the best out of their local road networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding can be spent on measures to bring smoother, safer and more reliable journeys to the travelling public whether they are commuting to work or taking the children to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help local residents see where this money has been spent it will be a condition of the funding that local authorities commit to publishing a short statement on their websites at the end of each financial year setting out what and where this additional funding has been spent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities are also encouraged to look at the information published by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep"&gt;Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme&lt;/a&gt; which is leading the way by bringing together the public and private sectors to develop good practice and reduce costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne announced in the Autumn Statement on 5 December additional funding of £333 million for highways maintenance for both the motorway and trunk road and local road network. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£215 million additional capital funding will be provided to local highway authorities, including London, to help renew and repair the network in England. £140 million will come in 2013 to 2014, with the remaining £75 million following in 2014 to 2015. The funds will be distributed on the basis of the department’s existing highways maintenance capital funding formula. A &lt;a href="/government/publications/local-transport-capital-block-funding"&gt;full list of the allocations by region and local authority&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be eligible for this additional funding and to promote greater transparency and accountability, the department will require local highway authorities to publish a brief note on their website by the end of each financial year (end of April 2014 and end of April 2015) on where (in terms of location) and how this additional funding was spent on highways maintenance. This is so local communities are able to see how this extra funding has been spent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme (HMEP) is a sector-led programme designed to maximise returns from highways investment and deliver efficient and effective services.  HMEP provides practical guidance on highway maintenance efficiencies for local authorities, supplier organisations and representative bodies in the form of toolkits, case studies and good practice.  The most recent of these, launched on 29 November, are the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/standard-spec.php"&gt;standard specification&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/asset-management.php"&gt;asset management toolkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <summary>A new EU regulation is set to give passengers travelling by water improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/57054</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:07:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-highways-and-rail-schemes-amendments-to-planning-act-2008-definitions"/>
    <title>Nationally significant highways and rail schemes: amendments to Planning Act 2008 definitions</title>
    <summary>Consulting on making changes to definitions of nationally significant projects with a view to reducing costs and meeting deadlines quicker.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is on proposals to amend the definitions of ‘nationally significant’ rail and highways projects set out in the Planning Act 2008. The aim of this is to speed up the completion of projects and reduce the costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57524</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T16:28:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"/>
    <title>Port marine safety code</title>
    <summary>Safety code for harbour authorities with statutory powers and duties in the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The port marine safety code establishes a national standard for every aspect of port marine safety and aims to enhance safety for those who use or work in ports, their ships, passengers and the environment. The code applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56774</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-ec-392-2009"/>
    <title>Consultation on the implementation of EU Regulation (EC) 392/2009</title>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on the UK's draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the UK’s draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation gives effect, within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention to create parity for the passenger shipping industry and help ensure that UK citizens have access to the same levels of compensation when travelling between two different &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states. Furthermore, it increases the limits of liabilities for death or personal injuries to passengers being carried by sea; requires carriers to have compulsory insurance, and provides claimants with the right of taking direct action against the insurers. The intended effect is to provide an enhanced framework of compensation in the event of death or personal injury to a passenger, or the loss or damage to luggage when travelling on a sea journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation also brings into scope certain domestic passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
