<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/64205</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"/>
    <title>Stopping up and diversion orders: reform of the application process for local highways</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the ‘Penfold review’, this consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway where this is required for the purpose of property development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose to permit applications for a stopping-up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission for the proposed development (whereas under the existing legislation the developer can only apply after securing planning permission), and options for devolving decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 9 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--2"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 16 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64032</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Explaining the Secretary of State's decision about the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This letter gives details about the Secretary of State’s decision on the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It explains that the Secretary of State has decided to confirm the order subject to a specified modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector’s report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64307</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:03:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"/>
    <title>Implementation of the Penfold Review</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Proposals to simplify the process of stopping up or diverting a highway will be announced in a consultation response today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a government response to the consultation that closed on 24 August detailing proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up or diversion of a highway, where this is required for the purposes of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main options presented in the consultation were to permit applications for a stopping up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission and to devolve decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided not to devolve the stopping up and diversion order process to a local level. Consultation responses suggested that any devolution should be accompanied by a charging regime; additional costs and charges would be borne by both local authorities and those making applications, with no guarantee of a simpler or faster process. The government does not feel that placing additional burdens on local authorities and costs on developers is right at this time. And the government is aware that the speed of processing applications for stopping up or diversion orders has increased considerably in the last year. Additionally, we do not propose to reform or encourage a greater use of section 116 of the Highways Act 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government continues to support the first option, to allow stopping up and diversion applications to be made alongside planning applications. The government considers this will remove a significant barrier to growth, by speeding up the process and allowing a reduction of burdens on both applicants and local authorities, as both applications can be considered concurrently. Legislation currently in Parliament, as part of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, will give effect to this measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government response will be available in the libraries of both Houses and on the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"&gt;department’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64036</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector's report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report was written by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It contains recommendations to amend words in the order and then confirm it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk//government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64184</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-driving-tests-at-halfords"/>
    <title>Green light for driving tests at Halfords</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans to offer practical driving tests from branches of Halfords have been given the go ahead by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving tests will be available from the Halfords store in Wellingborough from Tuesday 5 February. Other branches of Halfords across the country are expected to start offering tests in coming months. All tests will be conducted by Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) examiners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move is part of an initiative to offer a more local service for driving test candidates. As well as using conventional test centres, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working with public and private sector partners to provide driving tests in areas that don’t have a local test centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very pleased to be working with Halfords to provide a more local service for driving test candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great example of working with private sector partners to provide an important local service that is convenient as well as being cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfords Commercial Director, Paul McClenaghan, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Halfords is already a local destination for motorists, who come to us for a diverse range of automotive products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re always seeking new ways in which to enhance our offer, so working with the Driving Standards Agency is a natural fit for the business and extends the help we are able to provide to motorists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is currently consulting on proposals to improve the way all motoring services are delivered. The &lt;a href="/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy" title="Motoring Services Strategy"&gt;Motoring Services Strategy&lt;/a&gt; consultation outlines long term proposals to put customers firmly at the heart of the way motoring services are delivered, so that they best serve the consumer while getting the best possible deal for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61518</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-guide-to-good-practice-on-port-marine-operations"/>
    <title>A guide to good practice on port marine operations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This supplement to the 'Port marine safety code' contains detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is a supplement to the ‘Port marine safety code’. It contains more detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. It is designed to provide general guidance and examples of how a harbour authority can meet its commitments in terms of compliance with the code. The guidance applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide should not be viewed as the only means of complying with the code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"&gt;Port marine safety code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64055</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-lighthouse-fund-report-and-accounts-2012"/>
    <title>General Lighthouse Fund: report and accounts 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report and accounts for the General Lighthouse Fund (year ended 31 March 2012)</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report and accounts of the General Lighthouse Fund (GLF) are prepared pursuant to Section 211(5) of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995. These accounts have been prepared in accordance with the 2011/12 Government Financial Reporting Manual (&lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt;) issued by HM Treasury. The accounting policies contained in the &lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt; follow International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) to the extent that it is meaningful and appropriate to the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64086</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T10:28:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-7-january-2013"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 7 January 2013</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Stephen Hammond MP provides an overview of the last EU Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the last Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council agreed a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. Following widespread criticism of the commission’s proposal at the October Transport Council, the UK has been an active and leading negotiator at the working group meetings chaired by the presidency. The presidency subsequently presented a compromise text that reflected the reality of member states’ road safety testing practices. We supported the change of the legal form of the proposal from a (directly applicable) regulation to a directive (which gives member states some flexibility in transposition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcomed the many improvements in the presidency’s text which had substantially reduced the cost implications to a manageable level, and indicated that the UK could accept the presidency’s text.  I made clear that as negotiations begin with the European Parliament, we would seek to provide members of the European Parliament with as much information as possible to explain why the changes to the original proposal were both justified, and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presidency provided progress reports on 2 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council establishing the Connecting Europe Facility. This regulation will provide the legal basis for funding of trans-European transport, energy and telecoms networks for 2014 to 2020. The text will not be finalised until the budget figures for 2014 to 2020 have been agreed in discussions on the Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The council’s position on this regulation, which will provide the legal basis for taking forward the Galileo satellite navigation programme from 2014, was agreed earlier in the year. However, technical discussions with the European Parliament since then have not led to much progress. The dossier will be passed to the Irish Presidency to conclude negotiations with the European Parliament once the budget for Galileo under the &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; has been confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The commission welcomed the conclusions, highlighting in particular the worsening aviation relationship with Russia, especially Russia’s ongoing refusal to implement its commitments on Siberian overflight charges. The commissioner called for collective action at EU level and said he would be producing a roadmap in the new year with a view to pursuing an EU/Russia comprehensive agreement in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council also adopted a proposal for a decision on the comprehensive aviation agreement between the EU and its member states and Israel. The original plan had been for the agreement to be signed in the margins of the council, but due to internal political reasons, Israel was not able to sign at this time. The commission hoped that Israel would be in a position to sign this agreement shortly after national elections in the Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high level cooperation agreement with Eurocontrol (European Organisation for the Safety of Air Navigation) was signed in the margins of the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the commission provided an update on recent discussions at the International Civil Aviation Organisation to agree a global approach to tackling emissions from aviation. The commission clarified that it was proposing a temporary derogation on enforcement of the Aviation Emissions Trading System (ETS) relating to international flights and hoped the European Parliament and the council would approve this through a decision in the first quarter of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under any other business, France tabled a room document which called for a discussion to be held in the International Maritime Organization on the 2015 deadline for implementing the new requirements on the sulphur content of marine fuels. A number of member states intervened and stressed that they would be keen to discuss practical issues, such as the cost of low sulphur fuels to businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cleaner Power for Transport Package which was due to be discussed as an &lt;abbr title="any other business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt; item was taken off the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Brown &lt;abbr title="Member of the Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSP&lt;/abbr&gt;, Scottish Minister for Transport and Veterans also attended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
