<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60990</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-pinch-point-fund-application-pack"/>
    <title>Local Pinch Point Fund application pack</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These documents make up the application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund. As part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2011_index.htm"&gt;2012 Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt; the government announced the creation of a Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network which are impeding growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application pack consists of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;guidance about how to apply for this funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application form &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme impact pro forma for small project bids &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61037</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T08:52:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"/>
    <title>TAL 1/13: Reducing sign clutter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Advice on the removal of unnecessary traffic signs to highway authorities in Great Britain.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="traffic-advisory-leaflet-tal-113"&gt;Traffic advisory leaflet (&lt;abbr title="Traffic advisory leaflet"&gt;TAL&lt;/abbr&gt;) 1/13&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over-provision of traffic signs can have a detrimental impact on the environment and can dilute more important messages if resulting in information overload for drivers. This leaflet, gives practical advice on reducing sign clutter. It emphasises that designers should use their engineering judgement and local knowledge to complement guidance to ensure signing solutions are effective. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61023</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:08:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/proportion-of-trains-running-on-time"/>
    <title>Proportion of trains running on time</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-input-indicator"&gt;DfT Business Plan input indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-dft-franchised-train-operators-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: DfT franchised train operators (Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-train-operator"&gt;Information broken down by: Train operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85.3 per cent of trains arrived on time between 11 November 2012 and 8 December 2012 in Great Britain, a decrease from 88.4 per cent for the same period last year (GB total). The GB average headline figure incorporates Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) averages for operators franchised by devolved administrations (Arriva Trains Wales, First Scotrail, London Overground and Merseyrail), and non-franchised operators (Grand Central, Heathrow Express and Hull Trains), however, the following table covers only DfT franchised operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="public-performance-measure-ppm-for-dft-franchised-train-operating-companiessup1sup"&gt;Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) for DfT franchised Train Operating Companies&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Percentage of trains running on time 2011-12 P9 and 2012-13 P9 &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Latest rail period&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Latest rail period&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Train Operating Company&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011-12 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012-13 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011-12 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012-13 P9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;c2c&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;95.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;96.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97.3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chiltern Railways&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;94.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;94.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CrossCountry&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;74.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Coast&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;85.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Midlands Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Capital Connect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Great Western&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First TransPennine Express&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Greater Anglia&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;London Midland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;77.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northern Rail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southeastern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South West Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;83.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virgin Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;85.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;These are provisional statistics and are subject to revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;Period 9 2011/12 ran from 13 November 2011 to 10 December 2011. 
Period 9 2012/13 ran from 11 November 2012 to 8 December 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;Formerly National Express East Anglia. Greater Anglia took over the franchise on 5 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#02"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 11 November 2012 and 8 December 2012, 95.8 per cent of c2c services arrived on time, the highest figure for any DfT franchised train operator. CrossCountry had the lowest figure with 74.5 per cent of trains on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following restrictions brought in after the Hatfield crash in October 2000, &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; fell sharply across the country, and took nearly a decade to recover to previous levels. Since 2008/09 national &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; has generally been above 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Proportion of trains arriving on time’ Excel file contains a longer time series of &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; figures for each of the DfT franchised train operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) combines figures for punctuality and reliability into a single performance record. It covers all scheduled franchised passenger services, seven days a week and measures the arrival punctuality of individual trains against their planned timetable. These plans, technically called ‘plan of the day’, are usually the same as the published timetable with amendments reflecting pre-published engineering amendments; however, they may differ from their originally published timetable. The reliability figure records the percentage of services that are cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; represents the percentage of trains which are ‘on time’ compared to the total number of trains planned. A train is defined as on time if it arrives at its destination within five minutes of the scheduled destination arrival time for London and South East and regional operators; or within ten minutes for long-distance operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; can fluctuate widely period-by-period for many reasons, many of which are not within the control of the train operators. For example poor &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; performance can also be caused by other train operators or Network Rail. More information is available from the Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;) and on Network Rail’s and individual operators’ websites. &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; data can be expressed as either for the time period, or as a Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is an average for the most recent 13 four-week reporting periods. &lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt; figures smooth out short-term fluctuations and highlight the annual background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: 4 weekly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: 2 January 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information about this indicator can be found in the measurement template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; data are published on the Office of Rail Regulation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://dataportal.orr.gov.uk/"&gt;Data Portal.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: &lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60873</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-this-new-years-eve-try-a-mocktail"/>
    <title>Driving this New Year's Eve? Try a mocktail</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Department for Transport has produced a number of non-alcoholic cocktail recipes to help designated drivers celebrate in style.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is encouraging drivers to opt for non alcoholic ‘mocktails’ in a bid to cut down on drink driving this New Year’s Eve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has produced a number of recipes – from a Berry Breezer to a Piña Banana – to appeal to those who are designated drivers on nights out.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is also warning party-goers to plan their way home in advance so they can celebrate the New Year in style, not in the cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting television advert highlighting the consequences of drink driving has been shown throughout December as part of the Department for Transport’s THINK! drink drive campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our message is clear: have a great New Year’s Eve, don’t risk the consequences of drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you get behind the wheel after drinking you risk losing your licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2011, 280 people were killed in accidents where the driver was over the limit. Do not let 1 selfish and foolish decision ruin your or another family’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, drivers aged between 20 and 24 failed more breath tests than any other age group. This year’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign is aimed at young people who are shown to be consistently over-represented in drink drive casualty figures. THINK! advises planning your journey home well in advance and treating your designated driver to a non-alcoholic Christmas cocktail. The recipes are easy to make at home and provide a festive alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is currently consulting on a package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers. This includes removing drink drivers’ rights to demand a blood or urine test. This is because evidence shows it is used as a delaying tactic by drivers caught over the limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also supported Coke’s designated driver scheme, which offered buy 1 get 1 free soft drinks in pubs around the country throughout December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACPO lead for roads policing, Deputy Chief Constable Suzette Davenport, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millions of people will be heading out for New Year’s Eve celebrations and we would ask the public to play their part in remaining safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen hundreds of people die from drink driving this year and it has to stop. Innocent people are needlessly dying on our roads and people who make the decision to drive after taking alcohol or drugs are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are someone who drinks and drives, by making a decision to stop in 2013 could save someone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is provisionally estimated that 2011 saw 280 deaths, 1,290 serious injuries and 9,990 total casualties directly related to drink driving incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign budget totals £783,925&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for a high-resolution copy of the advert the THINK! ‘moment of doubt’ TV advert, contact the Department for Transport’s press office on 020 7944 6898&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK! campaign posters can be downloaded directly from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/drink-driving.html"&gt;campaign site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for more information about the Department for Transport’s consultation into the removal of a driver’s right to a blood test, visit &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"&gt;the GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;read table RAS51004 to see drink drivers by age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="non-alcoholic-christmas-cocktail-recipes"&gt;Non-alcoholic Christmas Cocktail Recipes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="berry-breezer"&gt;Berry Breezer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half a fresh lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the lime and sugar together, add the juices, shake and strain over ice. Top with tonic and garnish with a lime wedge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="elderflower-spritzer"&gt;Elderflower Spritzer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of elderflower cordial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 lemon wedges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;half a teaspoon of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soda water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mint to garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the sugar and lemon wedges together, add the elderflower cordial, shake, top with soda, stir and add more ice as required. Garnish with a lemon wedge and a sprig of mint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="winter-warmer"&gt;Winter Warmer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of apple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lemon and cloves for garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heat the apple and cranberry juice together for 1 minute in the microwave, stir in the honey and serve immediately in a heated mug or handled glass. Garnish with a clove-studded lemon wheel. For an extra twist replace the honey with spiced sugar syrup. To make this, mix some sugar gomme, vanilla pods, a cinnamon stick, a handful of cloves and some cardamom and allow to infuse for 3 days. Sieve
the sugar and mix with the heated apple and cranberry juices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="citrus-mock-tini"&gt;Citrus Mock-tini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 fresh kumquats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons of lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marmalade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 millilitres of clementine juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the kumquats with the marmalade, add the clementine juice, shake, pour over ice and top with tonic. Garnish with spent kumquat shells. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pia-banana"&gt;Piña Banana&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 banana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon of almond syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres single cream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dash of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blend all the ingredients together with some ice until frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60832</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T09:12:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/rail-passenger-count-and-loading-data-released-to-to-individuals-and-organisations"/>
    <title>Rail passenger count and loading data released to to individuals and organisations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Freedom of Information response concerning passenger count and loading data released by the government to individuals and organisations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Freedom of Information response concerns passenger count and loading data originally provided by train operating companies and then released by the Department for Transport to individuals and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60311</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/clear-up-initiative-saving-economy-millions-by-reopening-roads-quicker"/>
    <title>Clear-up initiative saving economy millions by reopening roads quicker</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An initiative to improve incident clear-up times is saving the economy tens of millions of pounds annually.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and the economy are seeing huge benefits from a government-led initiative to reopen motorways and roads quickly following major incidents, Roads Minister Stephen Hammond announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;’ (collision, lead, evaluate, act and reopen) initiative - launched by the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) last year to improve incident clear-up times – is helping to save the economy tens of millions of pounds annually, with even more savings to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key achievement has been the success of 38 &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;/police-funded 3D laser scanners which allow police forces to capture evidence quickly following collisions - helping to reopen major roads and motorways more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show an average time saving of 44 minutes per investigation – a 5 minute improvement on test estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other initiatives include the launch of a new hands-free smart phone app that notifies users of incidents and congestion, as well as the planned roll out of incident screens to shield collisions and prevent rubber necking. Time savings associated with screens alone can be up to several hundred thousand pounds per incident.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is confident these measures will help reduce the estimated £750 million cost to the economy that incidents cause on the strategic road network in England annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more frustrating than being stuck in a traffic jam for hours on end.  There is also the shocking cost of those lost hours for our economy. That is why we are improving the clear-up of incidents so we can get our motorways and major roads re-opened as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now witnessing even greater than expected time savings as a result of the roll out of laser scanning programme. This and other elements of the initiative, such as the use of incident screens, will help to keep traffic moving and save the economy tens of millions of pounds a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very encouraged by the cooperation shown by the Highways Agency, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Police and other emergency services, and fully expect these initiatives to result in further time and cost savings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief Constable Sean White, lead on collision investigations for the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This equipment allows police to manage critical events in a more efficient way and present the most accurate and detailed evidence to criminal, civil and coroners’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The time saved by using this technology is more economically friendly and reduces disruption on the roads, while allowing for thorough investigations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the success of this equipment, which has reduced delays for road users and proved extremely important in police investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Highways Agency signing a memorandum of understanding to facilitate data sharing about heavy goods vehicles. Studies have shown this type of vehicle is involved in a high proportion of the longest incidents. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working closely with operators to make sure problems are addressed   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the roll out by the Highways Agency of new towing equipment (load cells) to remove heavier vehicles obstructing live lanes and spill kits to clear spillages from motorway lanes. Time savings associated with the use of load cells have been estimated at several million pounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the production and distribution of a &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet to emergency responders outlining the roles and responsibilities of key organisations involved in managing incidents on the strategic road network. The Highways Agency has also produced a film reinforcing the booklet’s messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of emergency response guidance, training and learning to take on board &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of the 2007 Road Death Investigation Manual (RDIM) – the guiding doctrine of &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the 43 police forces of England and Wales to investigate and report on collisions that have resulted in a death. This is expected to be published in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report which sets out the next steps of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; is currently being finalised for publication next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laser-scanners"&gt;Laser scanners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laser Scanning Technology (LST) saves time by quickly making a 3D image of the whole incident scene, rather than investigators painstakingly surveying multiple sections of a scene. This digital image of the site can then be viewed on a computer screen remotely allowing investigators to take measurements of where vehicles are in relation to each other and examine other important evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009, the Highways Agency carried out an independent trial of 3D laser scanning technology using results from separate trials conducted by the Metropolitan Police Service and Humberside Police. The trials found that on average using laser scanners saved a total of 39 minutes on investigation time per incident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;38 laser scanners were funded by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Police for use by 27 police authorities at a cost of £4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest figures relate to information compiled from incidents over 4 months from forces using them on the strategic road network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clear"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2010 the Police, Highways Agency, Ambulance and Fire Services, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and related sponsoring departments came together to review evidence and knowledge about the handling of motorway incidents, and to make recommendations for improvement  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/review-of-investigation-and-closure-procedures-for-motorway-incidents-preliminary-report/review-of-investigation-closure-procedures-motorway-incidents.pdf"&gt;resultant report, published in May 2011 as the ‘Review of investigation and closure procedures for motorways incidents’ (PDF, 345KB)&lt;/a&gt;, made 10 recommendations and came together as the &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; initiative. The recommendations included further analytical work and some more immediate actions around, for example, supporting the wider roll out of laser scanning technology for the police to assist in speeding up incident investigation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congestion on the strategic road network is estimated to cost the economy £3 billion each year, 25% of which is caused by incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single incident that closes a 3 lane motorway for 4 hours can cost several million pounds in lost time, and there are some 80,000 incidents that impact at least one motorway lane each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; makes just 5% difference to the cost of congestion on the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Road Network"&gt;SRN&lt;/abbr&gt; it could save over £30 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="incident-screens"&gt;Incident screens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 105 sets of incident screens which will be made available for use by the Highways Agency next year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each set has 30 screens which are loaded onto purpose-built trailers and can screen up to 75 metres if used end-to-end (the individual screens are approximately 2.1 by two metres high)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They cost £2.3 million with each set costing £22,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="smart-phone-app"&gt;Smart phone app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	The Highways Agency app received 5,000 hits within the first 2 months of its launch. Further &lt;a rel="external" href="http://press.highways.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Hands-free-traffic-app-makes-Highways-Agency-data-available-to-road-users-ready-for-summer-67e24.aspx"&gt;information is available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spill-kits"&gt;Spill kits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Highways Agency"&gt;HA&lt;/abbr&gt; traffic officers will be equipped with spill kits to clear up small spillages such as fuel or other fluids which leak onto the carriageways from vehicles. The spill kits will absorb small spills and will allow the road to be safely re-opened while reducing damage to the carriageway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="load-cells"&gt;Load Cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load cells will be fitted to the tow straps used by traffic officers and will allow them to clear live lanes - moving heavier or damaged vehicles to the nearest place of safety.  The load cell acts as a strain gauge and will ensure that the safe towing load is not exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60283</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-for-transports-boost-to-train-builders"/>
    <title>Department for Transport's boost to train builders</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New train carriages procured by Southern Railway. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train builders have received a year-end boost as the government announces its backing for two new train orders, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of government support, Southern Railway has now procured 40 new carriages from Bombardier based in Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 40 carriages, the government is also supporting Southern’s tendering process for 116 new electric carriages with the option for a further 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our support for Southern will not only boost capacity but help secure British jobs. The deal for the 40 new carriages, helped along by my department, demonstrates the government’s ongoing commitment to invest in Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My officials are working with Southern to accelerate their procurement process for up to 256 carriages because our ambitious electrification plans requires additional rolling stock on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2011 Southern Railway, with government support, announced its plans to buy 130 carriages from Bombardier to run on services in south London, Surrey, Sussex and Kent. Southern expects these will be in service by December 2013. As part of this deal Southern had the option to buy the additional 40 carriages at a later stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July the government announced the biggest programme of rail modernisation since the Victorian era. At the heart of the scheme was the electrification of the Midland Main Line, from London to Sheffield, with additional spurs linking it to the Great Western Main Line and the Port of Southampton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Southern progresses with the procurement, these 116 new vehicles, and potentially 140 more, could initially be used on the Thameslink routes. Once the expected new Thameslink trains are operational these carriages will be moved to the newly electrified routes, which could include the Midland Main Line to Corby and North Transpennine Routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60319</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T14:46:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/cost-of-running-the-rail-network"/>
    <title>Cost of running the rail network</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>The costs of running the passenger rail network by DfT franchised train operating companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-input-indicator"&gt;DfT Business Plan input indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-dft-franchised-train-operators-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: DfT franchised train operators (Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-dft-franchised-train-operator"&gt;Information broken down by: DfT franchised train operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total cost of operating the rail network for train operators franchised by the Department for Transport (DfT) in 2010/11 was £9.3 billion. This consisted of £6.3 billion of train operator operating costs, and £3.0 billion of Network Grant paid to Network Rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The costs of running the passenger rail network by DfT franchised train operating companies are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#09"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cost by franchise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Operator&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total Operating Cost (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Allocated Network Grant (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;c2c&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;98.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;42.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chiltern Railways&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;125.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;200.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CrossCountry&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;407.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;291.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;698.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Coast&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;454.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;191.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;645.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Midlands Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;292.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;183.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;476.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Capital Connect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;334.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;117.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;452.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Great Western&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;629.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;317.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;946.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First TransPennine Express&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;220.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;116.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;336.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;London Midland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;322.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;137.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;459.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;National Express East Anglia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;420.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;211.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;631.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northern Rail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;522.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;359.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;882.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southeastern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;694.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;244.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;938.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;549.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;191.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;740.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South West Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;559.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;259.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;818.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virgin Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;639.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;297.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;937.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total DfT franchised operators&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6,269.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3,036.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9,305.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source: Train operating companies, DfT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The operating costs relate to the financial year 2010/11.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="change-in-methodology-in-sourcing-cost-of-running-the-rail-network-figures"&gt;Change in Methodology in sourcing Cost of Running the Rail Network figures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication last year used data from operators’ statutory accounts.  This year the data are based on management accounts; this ensures that the time period to which the data applies is consistent across operators, and allows comparisons to be made over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="operating-costs"&gt;Operating costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) These data are based on the ORR study “Costs and Revenues of Franchised Passenger Train Operators in the UK”, which in turn sourced data from the operators’ management accounts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any figures relating to premia or associated payments to the Department for Transport or Passenger Transport Executives are excluded. Within this total are payments made by operators to Network Rail for access to the rail network which contribute towards infrastructure costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Operators may not treat all aspects of operating costs in the same way in their accounts, and so care should be taken when using these figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="network-grant"&gt;Network Grant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(c) This is calculated by taking the total Network Grant paid to Network Rail by DfT in 2010-11, and allocating it to each franchise based on their share of Fixed Track Access Charges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Allocated Network Grant’ column, allocates, to each operator, the grant paid by the Department for Transport to Network Rail in 2010-11. The grant effectively pays the infrastructure costs incurred by Network Rail that are not covered by operators. In the table above, each operator is allocated a share of the grant in proportion to their Fixed Track Access Charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train operating companies’ costs are taken from ORR publication &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk/upload/pdf/toc-benchmarking-report-2012.pdf"&gt;Costs and Revenues of Franchised Passenger Train Operators in the UK&lt;/a&gt;
Further information about this indicator can be found in the measurement template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: annually&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: Spring 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: &lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
