<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16957</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-weston-transport-improvements"/>
    <title>Green light for Weston transport improvements</title>
    <summary>Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare has been given final approval today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will support economic growth in Weston-super-Mare and reduce congestion in the town centre. The work will also improve links between local roads and the M5 motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to increase capacity of the M5 Junction 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new link road for buses to access Worle railway station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bus priority measures at junctions and bus only sections to improve bus access to the south of Worle Station, linking it with regeneration areas at Weston Airfield and Locking Parklands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new 320 space car park with a bus interchange, drop-off and cycle facilities together with improvements to the north-side car park at Worle Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased capacity between the town centre and the regeneration areas through road widening and new routes for pedestrians and cyclists as well as bus priority measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great scheme that will support employment, reduce congestion and make it easier for people using public transport in and around Weston-super-Mare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £10.4 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country and the region needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Weston package scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work is currently planned to start in March 2013 with the package scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Weston package scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The package of measures, promoted by North Somerset Council, is scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16877</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:47:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/greater-anglia-franchise-specific-agreement"/>
    <title>Greater Anglia franchise specific agreement</title>
    <summary>Franchise agreements for Greater Anglia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that the Public Register of Franchise Agreements is updated on a quarterly basis and that the data held on the website may not be necessarily be the most current information held by the department. If you cannot find the information that you need, please contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications?tag=public-register-of-franchise-agreements"&gt;Public Register of Franchise Agreements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16857</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T09:27:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link inspector's report</title>
    <summary>Report by the inspector who held inquiries following the publication of Cornwall Council's side roads order and compulsory purchase order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This inspector’s report was written by the inspector who held inquiries following the publication of Cornwall Council’s side roads order and compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-decision-letter/" title="decision letter"&gt;Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link decision letter, 22 November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16855</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T09:27:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link decision letter</title>
    <summary>Features the Secretary of State's decision on Cornwall Council's side roads order and compulsory purchase order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This decision letter features the Secretary of State’s decision on Cornwall Council’s side roads order and compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-inspectors-report" title="inspectors report"&gt;Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link inspector’s report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16873</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T14:50:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:50:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/crucial-road-improvements-to-be-delivered-twice-as-fast"/>
    <title>Crucial road improvements to be delivered twice as fast</title>
    <summary>Accelerated improvements to various motorways will see more benefits for drivers and hauliers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and hauliers will benefit from increased capacity on England’s motorways by spring 2015 thanks to the acceleration of three upgrades, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be delivered in this spending review period rather than the next, as the government introduces major improvements to the way road schemes are planned and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new way of working should in future see lanes added to motorways in up to half the time it normally takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three schemes being accelerated are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vital improvements to A160/A180 route to the Port of Immingham will also start construction sooner than originally planned in the summer of 2015 and completed autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half by dismantling procedures that have slowed us down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Together these schemes will increase capacity for millions of road users by 72 miles. My ambition is that in future all major road schemes will be accelerated, tackling congestion more quickly and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a keynote speech to the &lt;abbr title="Confederation of British Industry"&gt;CBI&lt;/abbr&gt; yesterday, the PM announced that “it’s our ambition to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Highways Agency has looked hard at how to speed up the decision making process and the time it takes to have roads ready for use by motorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1km of managed motorway (using the hard shoulder as extra lanes and variable speed limits) can be built every two weeks, instead of every four. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected more complex, traditional capacity improvements on non motorway routes, such as the A160/A180 Immingham improvements, will be delivered up to 25% quicker/a quarter more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to faster delivery means this government will bring forward £75 million of investment forward into this spending review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There are four schemes in the programme where this new approach to road upgrades will be piloted, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A160/A180 Immingham dualling scheme - improving access to the Port of Immingham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 rather than during 2016. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £159 million (minimum) to £223 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is located on 13.4 miles of the M3 Motorway between Junction 12 of the M25 (M3 J2) to the A327 (M3 J4a) in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide more reliable journeys from London and Heathrow to Solent Ports – important for both leisure and business commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn is expected to start 2013/14 instead of 2014/15 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £140 million (minimum) to £201 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is located on a 9.6-mile stretch of the M6 between junctions 10a and 13, to the north west of Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support the economic development in and around the M6 by increasing business efficiency and improving reliability for business travellers, freight and logistics operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will add extra capacity on the M1 near Sheffield, between junctions 28 and J31 (18.9 miles), which is the primary strategic link between Nottingham and Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity improvement will support the economic development in the 7th and 8th largest urban areas in the United Kingdom by increasing business efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Immingham A160 and A180 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme is expected to start in summer 2015 instead of during 2016 and complete by autumn 2016 instead of during 2018 - this is subject to the successful completion of statutory processes, and the construction budget being agreed (for the next spending review period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an original five-and-a-half year programme, our ambition is to cut 18 months off the completion date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £89 million (minimum) to £132 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to improve the A160/A180 by upgrading it to a dual carriageway and improve access to the Port of Immingham. The A160 is approximately three miles long and has sections of both single carriageway and dual carriageway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the A160 carries around 13,000 vehicles per day, including approximately 5,700 heavy goods vehicles (44%) with road users experiencing severe congestion at times, particularly along the single carriageway sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Road schemes can be delivered more quickly by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undertaking concurrent planning, design and construction preparation activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking more work off-site and bringing to site as pre-fabricated/pre-assembled units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving toward a 24 hour operation with more people on site working on multiple phases at once &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16840</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T10:48:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/list-of-certifications-granted-for-approved-devices"/>
    <title>List of certifications granted for 'approved devices'</title>
    <summary>CCTV and evidence-recording equipment must be certified under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List of certifications granted by the Secretary of State for Transport for ‘approved devices’, CCTV and associated evidence-recording equipment, under the Transport Act 2000 and the Traffic Management Act 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="see-also"&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tma-part-6-certification-of-approved-devices"&gt;Civil traffic enforcement: certification of approved devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16871</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-23T14:44:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-for-local-transport-bodies"/>
    <title>Guidance for Local Transport Bodies</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has announced its firm intention to devolve funding for local major transport schemes to Local Transport Bodies from 2015. The guidance sets out the necessary arrangement Local Transport Bodies will need to have in place to ensure value for money and sound decision making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17003</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:27:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"/>
    <title>Tough new measures to tackle drink drivers</title>
    <summary>A consultation on tough measures to crack down on drink drivers has been unveiled.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers has been unveiled today by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included in the proposals are plans to remove the statutory right to a replacement blood or urine test where a breath test reading is above and close to the legal limit, closing the loophole which allows those testing positive in breath to sober up while they wait for a blood or urine sample to be taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also intends to legislate to allow police the option not to perform a preliminary breath test where roadside evidential breath tests are carried out following the rollout of roadside evidential breath testing devices and give registered health care professionals greater roles in testing drink drivers - both of which options would speed up the enforcement process and deal with more drink drivers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have made great progress in tackling drink drivers and the 2011 fatality figure for drink and drive accidents is the second lowest ever recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, last year 280 people died ruining the lives of families up and down the country so more needs to be done to eradicate this menace. That is why we are taking forward a package of measures to streamline enforcement against drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to make the jobs of those who deal with drink drivers easier and less bureaucratic so that bringing offenders to justice is not left to chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, drivers who record less than 50 microgrammes of alcohol per 100 millilitres of breath have the right to demand a blood or urine test - despite being over the legal limit of 35 microgrammes per 100 millilitres. This is known as the statutory option. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This option dates back to the original introduction of breathalyser technology when there were concerns over reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his review of drink and drug driving Sir Peter North recommended the removal of the right to demand a blood or urine test as evidence showed people were using it as a delaying tactic. The government also believes that improvements in the accuracy of technology means that this option is no longer necessary.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/consultations/enforcement-procedures-against-drink-drivers-and-other-offenders"&gt;consultation also seeks views&lt;/a&gt; on removing the requirement for a preliminary breath test where roadside evidential breath testing is used. At the moment, when a suspected drink driver is pulled over by police, they undergo a preliminary breath test and are then taken to a police station for a further evidential test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results from the evidential test taken at police stations are the only ones used as evidence. Under the new plans, following the introduction of mobile evidential testing devices the police could perform the eventual test at the roadside so the preliminary test would not be required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also want to see a wider range of registered healthcare professionals given the power to take evidential blood samples in hospitals and to assess whether a driver may have a condition due to a drug. This will enable tests to be carried out more swiftly, easing the pressure on doctors who are currently the only professionals with the authority to carry out the tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other proposals within the plans include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commissioning further research into the current process used to decide whether a driver banned due to drink driving can regain their licence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;further exploration of how greater use can be made of vehicle forfeiture powers to get the most dangerous and irresponsible motorists off the road, including drink drivers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation encompasses the legislative changes the government proposed in its response of March 2011 to the reports by Sir Peter North and the Transport Select Committee on drink and drug driving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation period runs until 2 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile breath testing devices are still subject to type approval by the Centre for Applied Science and Technology and have not yet been deployed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100921035225/http://northreview.independent.gov.uk/docs/NorthReview-Report.pdf"&gt;Report of the review of drink and drug driving law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmtran/460/46002.htm"&gt;Report of the Transport Select Committee: Drink and Drug Driving Law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm80/8050/8050.pdf"&gt;Government’s response to the reports by Sir Peter North CBE QC and the Transport Select Committee on drink and drug driving: command paper 8050&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16697</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T10:14:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:14:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/enforcement-procedures-against-drink-drivers-and-other-offenders"/>
    <title>Enforcement procedures against drink drivers and other offenders</title>
    <summary>Seeking views about changes to various drink driving procedures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation encompasses the legislative changes the government proposed in its response of March 2011 to the reports by Sir Peter North and the Transport Select Committee on drink and drug driving (“the Government’s response”). The changes covered in this consultation do not, however, include creating a new offence related to driving with a specified impairing drug in the body, which is also being progressed by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed legislative changes relate to Great Britain (and not to Northern Ireland) and will be implemented subject to the outcome of this consultation and the securing of legislative time. The proposals are consistent with the devolution of the drink drive limit in Scotland, through the Scotland Act 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views about proceeding with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the withdrawal of the ‘statutory option’;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes as to when preliminary breath tests are needed;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes to the testing procedures in hospital;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes to who can assess whether someone is under the influence of drugs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;amendments to the regimes for aviation, rail and shipping which mirror the road regime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16693</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T10:24:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/consultation-on-changes-to-enforcement-procedures-for-drink-driving-offences"/>
    <title>Consultation on changes to enforcement procedures for drink driving offences</title>
    <summary>Written statement by Stephen Hammond, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has today &lt;a href="/government/consultations/enforcement-procedures-against-drink-drivers-and-other-offenders"&gt;launched a consultation on some enforcement issues relating to the current legislation on drink and drug driving&lt;/a&gt;.  This consultation encompasses the legislative changes the government proposed in its response of March 2011 to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100921035225/http://northreview.independent.gov.uk/docs/NorthReview-Report.pdf"&gt;reports by Sir Peter North&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmselect/cmtran/460/46002.htm"&gt;Transport Select Committee&lt;/a&gt; on drink and drug driving (“&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm80/8050/8050.pdf"&gt;the Government’s response&lt;/a&gt;” ).  The changes covered in this consultation should not be confused with the legislation related to driving with a specified impairing drug in the body, which is currently passing through Parliament in the Crime and Courts Bill.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation on enforcement of drink driving will cover four potential legislative changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) withdrawal of the right people have to replace their breath alcohol specimens with either a specimen of blood or specimens of urine in cases where the lower of the two breath readings provided does not exceed 50 microgrammes (mcg) of alcohol per 100 millilitres (ml) of  breath (known commonly as the ‘statutory option’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) removing the requirement for preliminary testing where evidential testing is undertaken away from a police station.  This would mean that a preliminary breath test would not to have to be taken in addition to two evidential breath tests, when mobile evidential breath testing devices are used away from a police station.  While such devices are not yet available, it is expected that they may be type approved within the next 2 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) streamlining the procedure for testing drink drivers and drug impaired drivers in hospital so that a wider range of registered healthcare professionals are allowed to take evidential blood specimens.  This would make it consistent with other policing provisions.
4) the consultation asks for views on whether a health care professional other than a doctor should be able to assess whether a driver may be under the influence of a drug prior to evidential testing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislative changes proposed in this consultation would apply to the Road Traffic Act 1988.  Subject to the outcome of the consultation, we intend to legislate as soon as Parliamentary time allows on the matters covered in points 1-4 above.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-proposals-in-the-consultation"&gt;Other proposals in the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Road Traffic Act 1998 (and other parallel legislative provisions) apply similar measures to the drink drive offence to railways, shipping and aviation.  The consultation seeks views about whether any changes here should also apply to these other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation explores how further use can be made of vehicle forfeiture powers to get the most dangerous and irresponsible motorists off the road including those who drive while under the influence of alcohol. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document explores the scope for further research into the processes for reassessing whether a driver banned due to drink driving should regain their licence. The research would develop the evidence base for longer term solutions in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views about the way forward on three as yet un-commenced legislative provisions in the Road Safety Act 2006 relating to the training and punishment of certain road traffic offenders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with the revised guidance on consultations, we propose to shorten the consultation time for this to just over 5 weeks.  We are particularly interested in the views of the healthcare sector on points 3 and 4 and are planning to meet representative bodies for medical professionals in early December. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
