<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16141</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-views-multi-billion-pound-plans-for-the-north-west"/>
    <title>Minister views multi-billion pound plans for the north west</title>
    <summary>Major upgrades to rail links in the north west are progressing well.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major upgrade to rail links which will bring over £4 billion of economic benefits to the north west is progressing well, said Transport Minister Simon Burns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister visited Manchester and Liverpool today to see for himself work on the Northern Hub and plans for the electrification of rail lines – both projects could bring up to 30,000 jobs to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Hub will see a new rail link being built (the Ordsall Chord), stations extended and journey times improved while the electrification programme will enable faster, more reliable and greener trains to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport provides the crucial links that allow individuals and communities to prosper and that is why this investment is so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Commuters and businesses in the region will be big winners thanks to quicker and greener trains and more services across Manchester. But these improvements will also benefit the UK as a whole due the crucial role the north west plays in the country’s transport system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This investment demonstrates that the government is delivering on its commitment not only to improve the transport system but also to use it as an engine to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the minister toured Manchester Airport and Manchester Airport railway station where he viewed plans for a 4th railway platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new platform will increase capacity by enabling the station to accommodate longer and more trains. He also visited Piccadilly station which will have extra platforms as part of the Northern Hub project and toured Tuebrook Sidings, in Liverpool, which is 1 of 13 compounds which will be used to store materials during the second phase of the north west electrification scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Northern Hub is a series of proposed projects to boost economic growth through better train services across northern England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The individual projects were identified in a study published by Network Rail in February 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In July 2012 the government announced it was backing the full scheme. The full package of enhancements is set to be in place by 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s electrification programme will also see rail lines on the Great Western Main Line electrified all the way to the South Wales Valleys. The Midland Main Line between Bedford and Sheffield will also be electrified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A study by Network Rail estimates the investment will bring over £4 billion of wider economic benefits to the north west resulting in 30,000 new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16121</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:53:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:53:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-15-november-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 15 November 2012</title>
    <summary>Annual bus release and concessionary travel statistics for the last 2 years.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport on Thursday 15 November published the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/annual-bus-statistics-2011-12"&gt;Annual bus statistics 2011/12&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/concessionary-travel-statistics-england-2011-12-and-2012-13"&gt;Concessionary travel statistics 2011/12 and 2012/13&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16093</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/channel-tunnel-transposition-of-railway-safety-and-interoperability-directives"/>
    <title>Channel Tunnel: transposition of railway safety and interoperability directives</title>
    <summary>We are currently seeking views on whether to incorporate the provisions of 3 European directives into the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking views on whether to transpose the requirements of 3 European directives on railway safety and interoperability so that these provisions are in force for the Channel Tunnel. In recognition of the Tunnel’s cross-border nature these we would like to incorporate the provisions of these railway safety and interoperability directives by making amendments to the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16290</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T16:34:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-regulated-agents-and-in-flight-suppliers"/>
    <title>Department for Transport regulated agents and in-flight suppliers</title>
    <summary>A list of aviation related agencies that are regulated by the Department for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-number-for-all-enquiries"&gt;Contact number for all enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone: 0207 944 6430&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="communication-with-cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Communication with Cargo and In-Flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could all non-urgent communication with inspectors, wherever possible, please be sent to their email addresses (listed below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Cargo and in-flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christian Whitley, Team Leader Cargo and In-flight Supplies &lt;a href="mailto:Christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daz Salmon &lt;a href="mailto:daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gillian Stephens &lt;a href="mailto:gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Sidney &lt;a href="mailto:james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jerry Koster &lt;a href="mailto:jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin Gurney &lt;a href="mailto:martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maurice Stearn &lt;a href="mailto:maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carole Cousins &lt;a href="mailto:carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="validation-and-known-consignors-scheme"&gt;Validation and Known Consignors Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email all enquires to &lt;a href="mailto:current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="correspondence"&gt;Correspondence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport  
&lt;br&gt;Transport Security Compliance  
&lt;br&gt;3rd Floor, Fry Building  
&lt;br&gt;2 Marsham Street  
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1P 4DF
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16253</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T11:51:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/driver-certificate-of-professional-competence-cpc-statistics"/>
    <title>Driver Certificate of Professional Competence (CPC) statistics</title>
    <summary>Driver CPC statistics, including modules conducted, periodic training, driver qualification cards and centres and courses approved.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="about-these-statistics"&gt;About these statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These operational statistics about Driver Certificate of Professional (&lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt;) modules and training have not been designated as an official statistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics come from data held by the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;), and are compiled and published by staff in &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="information-you-cannot-find"&gt;Information you cannot find&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you cannot find the information you need, it may have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;published in &lt;a href="/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=driving-standards-agency&amp;amp;publication_type=foi-releases" title="Responses to FOI requests"&gt;response to an Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designated as an &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/driving-tests-and-instructors-statistics" title="Official driving test statistics"&gt;official statistic&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.dft.gov.uk/foi/form/" title="Send an FOI request"&gt;send an &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; request&lt;/a&gt; if you still cannot find the information you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="information-that-cannot-be-released"&gt;Information that cannot be released&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; cannot send you information if it is part of an official statistic that has not yet been published. This is because the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/2998/contents/made" title="Pre-release Access to Official Statistics Order 2008"&gt;Pre-release Access to Official Statistics Order 2008&lt;/a&gt; limits access to official statistics until they are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="downloads"&gt;Downloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These older statistics are available from the The National Archives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2011-12.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2011 to 2012)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2010-11.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2010 to 2011)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2009-10.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2009 to 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa_conducted_module_4_cpc_pass_rate_09-10.pdf"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; module 4 pass rate (2009 to 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2008-09.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2008 to 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa_conducted_module_4_cpc_pass_rate_08-09.pdf"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; module 4 pass rate (2008 to 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16063</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boxing-day-boost-for-bargain-hungry-passengers"/>
    <title>Boxing day boost for bargain-hungry passengers</title>
    <summary>Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra rail services – which will make it easier for shoppers to access retail hubs in central London, Stratford and Kent – are being provided thanks to an agreement between the Department for Transport, Southeastern, and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have devised a unique agreement to enable Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; to make it easier for their passengers to get to the sales following Christmas, which will provide more services at no cost to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Southeastern ran some very successful services on High Speed 1 during the Olympics and the train operator has shown there is sufficient demand for these services so we were happy to consider allowing them to adjust their timetables. This is an excellent example of the government, infrastructure owners and train operators working innovatively together to improve services for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern’s managing director, Charles Horton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to offer this trial Boxing Day service for our passengers thanks to the collaboration with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our high speed Javelin service will transport people from Ashford to St Pancras International in just 37 minutes, and 19 minutes from Ebbsfleet. We’re also pleased to offer free parking at these 2 stations for Boxing Day so everyone has a little bit extra to spend in the sales!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Ruse, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, the company that owns High Speed 1 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Demand for high speed rail travel is rising all the time and this welcome example of teamwork on the railways means we can offer high speed rail customers a service that will prove hugely popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The half hourly service will run between Ashford International, Ebbsfleet International, Stratford International and St Pancras International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd ran a special timetable through the Olympics and Paralympics with extra high speed services to carry spectators to and from Stratford International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timetables and ticket information can be viewed online at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/"&gt;nationalrail.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/15629</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:19:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/caa-board-members-reappointed"/>
    <title>CAA board members reappointed</title>
    <summary>Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin has reappointed 2 members of the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) board for second terms in office.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin has reappointed 2 members of the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) board for second terms in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Gray and Michael Medlicott joined the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; as non-executive Members in November 2009 and February 2010 respectively. David Gray has particular expertise in economic regulation including a period at Ofgem, where he was responsible for gas and electricity price control reviews. Michael Medlicott has many years’ experience in the transport and tourism sectors, including senior roles in the airline and airport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will serve for second terms of 3 years each at their existing salaries of £22,000 per annum for a time commitment of 1 day per week, with additional remuneration for chairing committees and participation in appeals hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A successful, safe and efficient aviation sector is vital to the UK’s success on the global stage. These reappointments recognise the contributions that both individuals have made to ensuring the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; remains an effective, reforming regulator in what has been a challenging period for the aviation sector. I wish them well as they continue in these important roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Authority is responsible for the regulation of civil aviation in the United Kingdom and is the government’s principal advisor on aviation matters. It has specific responsibility for aviation safety, consumer protection, airspace policy and the economic regulation of the industry. It is based mainly in London and Gatwick and has approximately 950 employees. The great majority of the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s funding comes from the charges it imposes on the industry, rather than the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both members were originally appointed following an open competition regulated by the Office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments. The appointments were made on merit and political activity plays no part in the selection process. They have both declared that they have undertaken no relevant political activity during the past 5 years and that they hold no other current public appointments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16224</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:50:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/peterborough-station-makeover-official-opening"/>
    <title>Peterborough Station makeover – official opening</title>
    <summary>Speech by the Rt Hon Simon Burns MP, Minister of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along. It’s a genuine pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my officials first asked me if I was interested in a makeover, I thought they meant for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for my self-esteem the officials in my private office eventually put me straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The makeover is right here at Peterborough Station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, looking around, I can see that every penny of that £3 million was well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-makeover-that-really-delivers"&gt;A makeover that really delivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a new station front, a bigger main concourse and a much brighter interior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a new information point, as well as a new customer waiting area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People using the station will feel safer and more secure thanks to improved &lt;abbr title="Closed Circuit Television"&gt;CCTV&lt;/abbr&gt; coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated ticket machines mean less hassle and more convenience for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, talking of convenience, even the toilets have been refurbished.
Looked at from any angle, this is a makeover that really delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say it doesn’t stop there. Because I understand there’s more to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be new lifts and footbridges, as well extra and longer platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all the work is due to be completed by the end of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bigger-picture"&gt;Bigger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, the passenger friendly changes we see here are part of a much bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’re actually engaged in a massive rail modernisation effort:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new services and extra carriages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more seats and faster journeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transforming conventional rail and backing rail high speed rail &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;From massive, multi-billion pound projects like Crossrail, to smaller multi-million pound projects like Peterborough, we’re renewing and rebuilding Britain’s railways and making them truly fit for the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="team-effort"&gt;Team effort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that it takes a real team effort to pull off something like this - from back office to building site, from accountants to architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as far as I’m concerned, it doesn’t matter if you were sat in front of a computer or you wore a hard hat, or whether you’re from Network Rail or part of East Coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were involved in modernising this station then you should feel very proud of yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I’d like to take this opportunity to applaud you for an absolutely fantastic job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common interests and a common purpose….coming together and working together to achieve this station improving, passenger friendly end result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a big thank-you for all of your hard graft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks--cutting-ribbonplaque-unveiling"&gt;Concluding remarks – cutting ribbon/plaque unveiling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience “I wish they’d gone on longer” is rarely a tribute paid to a public speaker, especially a politician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, without any further ado, it’s an honour and a privilege to declare this station open.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16218</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/nuneaton-north-chord-event"/>
    <title>Nuneaton North Chord event</title>
    <summary>Speech by the Rt Hon Simon Burns MP, Minister of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for asking me along today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely delighted to be here because what you’ve achieved with this new chord really matters. And let me tell you why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, today we earn our living in a global marketplace - one where what we sell in Boston or Shanghai is just as important as what we make in Bristol or Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that rail freight is more important than it’s ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving products and raw materials quickly and reliably - that’s how you power up the recovery and grow the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-sense-environmental-sense"&gt;Economic sense, environmental sense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although this new chord isn’t massive in scale like Crossrail or &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, it’s certainly a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment worth more than £25 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that will allow freight traffic to travel through Nuneaton station, without affecting passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that means better and faster links between the global gateway of Felixstowe and the Midlands, the north west and Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this new chord makes sound economic sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you consider the chord’s potential to cut carbon emissions and ease traffic congestion by attracting freight from road to rail, then it soon becomes obvious that it makes environmental sense too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions---right-investment-right-project-right-reasons"&gt;Conclusions - right investment, right project, right reasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add all that up and what you have is the right investment, in the right project, for the right reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I finish I just want to say a big thank you to everyone who made this possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have done a terrific job of work and, if I had a hat, I’d take it off to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on that note it is now my absolute pleasure to declare the Nuneaton North Chord officially open (minister unveils plaque).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16037</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:35:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-to-scrap-motor-insurance-certificates-launched"/>
    <title>Consultation to scrap motor insurance certificates launched</title>
    <summary>The government has announced a consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates and reduce motor insurance red tape.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drivers could benefit from less motor insurance red tape after a government consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates was launched today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8 week exercise will seek the views of the industry, motorists and other stakeholders on the benefits of moving towards a purely online system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under current law, insurance companies must issue a paper or electronic certificate when agreeing a policy. However, many organisations, including the police and vehicle rental companies, already rely on information stored on the Motor Insurer’s Database (MID) as evidence of valid insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More and more people are using technology to organise their everyday lives so it is only right we look at how we can make life easier for motorists and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are launching a consultation to scrap the legal requirement for insurance certificates to be issued and consolidate a system whereby all information is online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has the potential to make significant savings down the line which I hope will be passed on to policyholders. It will also make the lives of motorists and police easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to moving to an online system include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motorists will no longer be forced to retain certificates as details will be accessible online. This will remove the legal requirement whereby vehicle owners are required to return their certificates to insurance companies in order to cancel the policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;police and the commercial motor industry would be better able to check details at source, instead of relying on policyholder documents which can be forged. The Police already use a download of the MID to identify uninsured drivers on the road.
If the consultation is successful then the Department would look to repeal the current law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposal is part of the government’s Red Tape Challenge, which invited the public and stakeholders to give their views on which regulations should stay, be improved, or be scrapped altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"&gt;consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available on the DfT website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department proposes to amend s147 (1) of the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue motor insurance certificates (whether issued as a paper document or electronically)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Association of British Insurers (ABI) estimate the cost of producing each certificate is about £1 and around 34.2 million insurance documents are issued per annum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
