<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/topics/transport</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topics/transport.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Transport"</title>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-20T16:28:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16524</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T16:28:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T16:28:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-examiner-strike-on-30-november-candidates-urged-to-attend-tests"/>
    <title>Driving examiner strike on 30 November: candidates urged to attend tests</title>
    <summary>Driving test candidates with a test on Friday 30 November should still come for their test despite the threat of strike action by examiners.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving examiners who are members of the Public and Commercial Services (&lt;abbr title="Public and Commercial Services"&gt;PCS&lt;/abbr&gt;) union could take strike action on Friday 30 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Chief Executive Rosemary Thew said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not all examiners are members of the &lt;abbr title="Public and Commercial Services"&gt;PCS&lt;/abbr&gt; union. Even if they are, we can’t be sure that they’ll support the strike. So we’re asking you to come for your test so it can go ahead if possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re sorry for the inconvenience this will cause. We’ll do everything we can to minimise disruption for our customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You won’t have to contact &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; to rebook if you can’t take your test because of the strike action. You should hear from the agency with a new date within 5 to 10 working days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="out-of-pocket-expenses"&gt;Out-of-pocket expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can claim out-of-pocket expenses if your test is cancelled, but you must have turned up for your test to do this. You’ll have to rebook your own test and you won’t be able to claim expenses if you don’t turn up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/practical-driving-test-for-cars/cancelled-or-stopped-tests-and-bad-weather" title="Claiming out-of-pocket expenses"&gt;Find out how to claim out-of-pocket expenses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="customer-service-centre"&gt;Customer service centre&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s customer service centre for practical driving tests might also be affected by strike action on Friday 30 November. You’ll still be able to &lt;a href="/browse/driving/learning-to-drive" title="Book, change or cancel practical driving tests"&gt;book, change or cancel practical driving tests&lt;/a&gt; online on GOV.UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="theory-tests"&gt;Theory tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theory tests aren’t affected by the strike action and will be taking place as planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16506</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T14:38:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T14:38:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/crucial-road-improvements-to-be-delivered-twice-as-fast"/>
    <title>Crucial road improvements to be delivered twice as fast</title>
    <summary>Accelerated improvements to various motorways will see benefits for drivers and hauliers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and hauliers will benefit from increased capacity on England’s motorways by spring 2015 thanks to the acceleration of three upgrades, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be delivered in this spending review period rather than the next, as the government introduces major improvements to the way road schemes are planned and built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new way of working should in future see lanes added to motorways in up to half the time it normally takes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three schemes being accelerated are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vital improvements to A160/A180 route to the Port of Immingham will also start construction sooner than originally planned in the summer of 2015 and completed autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half by dismantling procedures that have slowed us down. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Together these schemes will increase capacity for millions of road users by 72 miles. My ambition is that in future all major road schemes will be accelerated, tackling congestion more quickly and boosting the economy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a keynote speech to the &lt;abbr title="Confederation of British Industry"&gt;CBI&lt;/abbr&gt; yesterday, the PM announced that “it’s our ambition to cut the time it takes to upgrade our roads in half”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport and the Highways Agency has looked hard at how to speed up the decision making process and the time it takes to have roads ready for use by motorists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1km of managed motorway (using the hard shoulder as extra lanes and variable speed limits) can be built every two weeks, instead of every four. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected more complex, traditional capacity improvements on non motorway routes, such as the A160/A180 Immingham improvements, will be delivered up to 25% quicker/a quarter more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commitment to faster delivery means this government will bring forward £75 million of investment forward into this spending review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There are four schemes in the programme where this new approach to road upgrades will be piloted, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A160/A180 Immingham dualling scheme - improving access to the Port of Immingham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;2) Surrey, M3 J2 to 4a managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 rather than during 2016. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £159 million (minimum) to £223 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is located on 13.4 miles of the M3 Motorway between Junction 12 of the M25 (M3 J2) to the A327 (M3 J4a) in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will provide more reliable journeys from London and Heathrow to Solent Ports – important for both leisure and business commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) West Midlands, M6 J10a to 13 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, which was added to the roads programme last autumn is expected to start 2013/14 instead of 2014/15 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £140 million (minimum) to £201 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is located on a 9.6-mile stretch of the M6 between junctions 10a and 13, to the north west of Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will support the economic development in and around the M6 by increasing business efficiency and improving reliability for business travellers, freight and logistics operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Derbyshire, M1 J28 to 31 managed motorway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme, is expected to start 2013/14 and be completed by spring 2015 instead of during the next financial year – 2015/16. The start of work is subject to the completion of necessary statutory processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will add extra capacity on the M1 near Sheffield, between junctions 28 and J31 (18.9 miles), which is the primary strategic link between Nottingham and Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra capacity will come through converting the hard shoulder to a traffic lane – with variable speed limits helping to reduce congestion and smooth traffic flows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capacity improvement will support the economic development in the 7th and 8th largest urban areas in the United Kingdom by increasing business efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Immingham A160 and A180 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on this scheme is expected to start in summer 2015 instead of during 2016 and complete by autumn 2016 instead of during 2018 - this is subject to the successful completion of statutory processes, and the construction budget being agreed (for the next spending review period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an original five-and-a-half year programme, our ambition is to cut 18 months off the completion date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest cost-range estimate for the project is £89 million (minimum) to £132 million (maximum). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proposing to improve the A160/A180 by upgrading it to a dual carriageway and improve access to the Port of Immingham. The A160 is approximately three miles long and has sections of both single carriageway and dual carriageway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the A160 carries around 13,000 vehicles per day, including approximately 5,700 heavy goods vehicles (44%) with road users experiencing severe congestion at times, particularly along the single carriageway sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Road schemes can be delivered more quickly by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undertaking concurrent planning, design and construction preparation activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking more work off-site and bringing to site as pre-fabricated/pre-assembled units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving toward a 24 hour operation with more people on site working on multiple faces at once &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16458</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-port-security-regulations-2009-at-certain-ports"/>
    <title>Implementation of Port Security Regulations 2009 at certain ports</title>
    <summary>This is a consultation on draft designation orders implementing Port Security Regulations 2009.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Directive 2005/65/EC is to enhance security coordination in the wider area at certain ports. The directive requires the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designation of a port security authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointment of a port security officer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a port security risk assessment to be conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a port security plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft designation orders which we are are consulting on here append plan(s) outlining the area which the port security authority will have responsibility over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16370</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T11:01:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/model-ship-security-plan-templates"/>
    <title>Model ship security plan templates</title>
    <summary>Model plans to help company and ship security officers compile a ship security plan.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These model ship plans will help company and ship security officers to compile a ship security plan (SSP) under the International Ship and Port Facility Security (ISPS) Code, for agreement and verification by the Department for Transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents are cruise ship and ro-ro (roll-on/roll-off) passenger ferry templates. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/mcga07-home/shipsandcargoes/mcga-shipsregsandguidance/mcga_dops_maritimesecurity_mainpage/dops_ms-guidance/mcga_dops_msb_ssp/dops_msb__model_ship_security_plan.htm"&gt;template for use with cargo ships&lt;/a&gt; is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/"&gt;Maritime and Coastguard website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16471</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:30:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/westbourne-hs2-alliance-dinner"/>
    <title>Westbourne HS2 Alliance dinner</title>
    <summary>Speech by the Rt Hon Simon Burns MP, Minister of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction James (James Bethall, Westbourne Comms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough the importance of the work the Alliance does to build up a coalition of support for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value your support for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; and we need other organisations to continue make the case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; in a positive manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your efforts are highly regarded and greatly appreciated, so it’s a genuine pleasure to be with you all this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-only-game-in-town"&gt;The only game in town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaac Singer, the Polish-American author and Noble Prize winner, once told a journalist: “We have to believe in free will. We’ve got no choice”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s pretty much how I feel about high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I’m convinced that a high speed rail network won’t simply transform the way we travel in Britain, it will also transform the way we live, work and do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And transform it for generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also one hundred per cent certain that opting out of a high speed future would be a disaster for Britain, a missed opportunity we’d regret for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for me, there’s only one choice that makes sense for our country’s success and our children’s future, and that’s &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really is the only game in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bigger-picture"&gt;Bigger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; debate, we can talk about the line of route, design and technology or even mitigation measures and compensation packages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of these things matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also vital that we never ever lose sight of the bigger picture - the long-term potential of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the brief time I have tonight, that’s what Id like to focus on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-potential"&gt;Economic potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s economic potential:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will mean faster journey times, more capacity and better connected cities and regions - which, in turn, means that British businesses will be able to use it to exploit new markets and win new customers both at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also create and support tens of thousands of jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; can help to power up the recovery and put people back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="social-potential"&gt;Social potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will help to close the decades’ long north-south divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will help to open up access to employment opportunities and essential services like education and health for millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in a very real sense, a high speed rail network is as much about delivering better life chances as it is about getting from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="environmental-potential"&gt;Environmental potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me then, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; makes economic and social sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can also see a persuasive environmental case for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because I really do believe that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will offer people and businesses a high speed, low carbon alternative to short-haul flying and long-distance motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="willing-to-accept-unwilling-to-postpone-determined-to-meet"&gt;Willing to accept, unwilling to postpone, determined to meet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I look at the bigger &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; picture I don’t just see an investment in a high &lt;abbr title="technology"&gt;tech&lt;/abbr&gt;, high capacity, high speed rail network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see an investment in a stronger economy, a fairer society and a cleaner and greener environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why it has my full on and flat commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know that building high speed rail will be a test of Britain’s energy and skills. And yes, I know this challenge is as big as they come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know this country - .its people and its companies, its spirit and resolve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I am absolutely convinced it’s a challenge that we in Britain are willing to accept, unwilling to postpone and determined to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, when I first started out in politics I was told that the Golden Rule of public speaking was exhaust neither the subject nor the audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, down the years I’ve discovered another rule - never keep an audience from their dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ahead of our dinner and discussion, it only remains for me to say thank you for listening and here’s to a night of good food and great conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16298</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T09:29:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-lighting"/>
    <title>Street lighting</title>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information response regarding the switching off of street lighting on sections of some roads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16141</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-views-multi-billion-pound-plans-for-the-north-west"/>
    <title>Minister views multi-billion pound plans for the north west</title>
    <summary>Major upgrades to rail links in the north west are progressing well.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major upgrade to rail links which will bring over £4 billion of economic benefits to the north west is progressing well, said Transport Minister Simon Burns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister visited Manchester and Liverpool today to see for himself work on the Northern Hub and plans for the electrification of rail lines – both projects could bring up to 30,000 jobs to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Hub will see a new rail link being built (the Ordsall Chord), stations extended and journey times improved while the electrification programme will enable faster, more reliable and greener trains to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport provides the crucial links that allow individuals and communities to prosper and that is why this investment is so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Commuters and businesses in the region will be big winners thanks to quicker and greener trains and more services across Manchester. But these improvements will also benefit the UK as a whole due the crucial role the north west plays in the country’s transport system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This investment demonstrates that the government is delivering on its commitment not only to improve the transport system but also to use it as an engine to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the minister toured Manchester Airport and Manchester Airport railway station where he viewed plans for a 4th railway platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new platform will increase capacity by enabling the station to accommodate longer and more trains. He also visited Piccadilly station which will have extra platforms as part of the Northern Hub project and toured Tuebrook Sidings, in Liverpool, which is 1 of 13 compounds which will be used to store materials during the second phase of the north west electrification scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Northern Hub is a series of proposed projects to boost economic growth through better train services across northern England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The individual projects were identified in a study published by Network Rail in February 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In July 2012 the government announced it was backing the full scheme. The full package of enhancements is set to be in place by 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s electrification programme will also see rail lines on the Great Western Main Line electrified all the way to the South Wales Valleys. The Midland Main Line between Bedford and Sheffield will also be electrified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A study by Network Rail estimates the investment will bring over £4 billion of wider economic benefits to the north west resulting in 30,000 new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16121</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:53:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:53:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-15-november-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 15 November 2012</title>
    <summary>Annual bus release and concessionary travel statistics for the last 2 years.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport on Thursday 15 November published the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/annual-bus-statistics-2011-12"&gt;Annual bus statistics 2011/12&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="/government/publications/concessionary-travel-statistics-england-2011-12-and-2012-13"&gt;Concessionary travel statistics 2011/12 and 2012/13&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16093</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/channel-tunnel-transposition-of-railway-safety-and-interoperability-directives"/>
    <title>Channel Tunnel: transposition of railway safety and interoperability directives</title>
    <summary>We are currently seeking views on whether to incorporate the provisions of 3 European directives into the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking views on whether to transpose the requirements of 3 European directives on railway safety and interoperability so that these provisions are in force for the Channel Tunnel. In recognition of the Tunnel’s cross-border nature these we would like to incorporate the provisions of these railway safety and interoperability directives by making amendments to the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16457</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T16:34:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-regulated-agents-and-in-flight-suppliers"/>
    <title>Department for Transport regulated agents and in-flight suppliers</title>
    <summary>A list of aviation related agencies that are regulated by the Department for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-number-for-all-enquiries"&gt;Contact number for all enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone: 0207 944 6430&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="communication-with-cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Communication with Cargo and In-Flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could all non-urgent communication with inspectors, wherever possible, please be sent to their email addresses (listed below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Cargo and in-flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christian Whitley, Team Leader Cargo and In-flight Supplies &lt;a href="mailto:Christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daz Salmon &lt;a href="mailto:daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gillian Stephens &lt;a href="mailto:gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Sidney &lt;a href="mailto:james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jerry Koster &lt;a href="mailto:jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin Gurney &lt;a href="mailto:martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maurice Stearn &lt;a href="mailto:maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carole Cousins &lt;a href="mailto:carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="validation-and-known-consignors-scheme"&gt;Validation and Known Consignors Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email all enquires to &lt;a href="mailto:current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="correspondence"&gt;Correspondence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport  
&lt;br&gt;Transport Security Compliance  
&lt;br&gt;3rd Floor, Fry Building  
&lt;br&gt;2 Marsham Street  
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1P 4DF
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
