<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/strengthening-uk-relationships-in-asia-latin-america-and-africa-to-support-uk-prosperity-and-security/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/strengthening-uk-relationships-in-asia-latin-america-and-africa-to-support-uk-prosperity-and-security/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/strengthening-uk-relationships-in-asia-latin-america-and-africa-to-support-uk-prosperity-and-security/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Strengthening UK relationships in Asia, Latin America and Africa to support UK prosperity and security"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP led a trade mission to Burma earlier this week.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/50172</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:14:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-philippines-partners-for-prosperity"/>
    <title>Britain and the Philippines: Partners for Prosperity</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has given a speech about the growing trade partnership between the UK and the Philippines. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here today, and especially pleased that we are in the company of Foreign Secretary del Rosario. I would like to thank the Makati Business Club, the Management Association of the Philippines and the British Chamber of Commerce for inviting me to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real thrill to be in the Philippines, on my first official visit to this beautiful country. It is almost 30 years since I was last here, in a personal capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a busy two days ahead and have just come from a very productive meeting with President Aquino, during which we discussed how Britain and the Philippines can work together to tackle today’s global challenges and support each other’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on the latter that I will focus today. I will talk first about the United Kingdom’s role in today’s changing world, before setting out why I think Britain and the Philippines can be powerful partners for prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom, like the Philippines, is an island nation – a characteristic which, unsurprisingly, has shaped how we view ourselves and the world around us. Britain is a relatively small place. We had enough but not bountiful natural resources. Combine that with a predisposition towards adventure and discovery, and it led us to build truly global networks and trade links. One thinks of names like Drake, Raleigh and Shackleton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No market was too far or too difficult; no peak too high. Indeed, the globalisation that people tend to view today as a very modern phenomenon has roots that go much deeper. The world in which the Victorians lived was far more integrated in some ways, with Britain sitting at the heart of a global economic system, including a de facto single currency – the Gold Standard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this brought us to South-East Asia. Our ties to countries like Malaysia and Singapore are perhaps best known and are still extremely strong. However, Britain’s links to the Philippines stretch back just as far. The first British Consul arrived as early as 1844. And I am reminded of one of your most famous national heroes, José Rizal, who lived in London’s Primrose Hill in the 1880s. Visitors today will find a blue plaque on the house in which he lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, and particularly in the last couple of decades, I have heard some say that Britain lost sight of the importance of South-East Asia; that our attention was diverted elsewhere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that relationships changed. But while it may have felt to some as if Britain had lost focus, we never went away. The commercial figures alone bear this out. UK trade and investment with South-East Asia today is still far higher than it is with China, despite the exceptional levels of growth and development that China has seen over the past 15 years. That said, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office has under the current Government significantly strengthened this focus, placing an even greater emphasis on our engagement with South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have rebalanced our foreign policy and diplomatic network. On a practical level, that means opening new missions, sending more diplomats to places like the Philippines. We are creating around 50 new jobs across the region. And I am sure many of you will have taken note of last month’s visit to Laos by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, to reopen the British Embassy there. The UK is now represented in all ten ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking this new approach because we see the emergence and re-emergence of economies across the world – not least the growth and development in Asia – as an opportunity. I believe there is much that we can achieve if we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is a key element of my Government’s efforts to deliver sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from an unbalanced growth model, reliant on government spending, to one based on expanding trade, encouraging inward investment, increasing the share of our economy that comes from exports, and manufacturing the goods that today’s consumers want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to meet our ambitious target to double exports to £1 trillion a year by 2020, we need to grow our exports by eight percent a year. Some of these will go to traditional markets like the European Union, but we are looking increasingly to fast-growing economies in places like South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Europe, the UK is leading the efforts to open up the EU market to trade with other nations. Growth may be slow in Europe – the forecasts suggest we can expect only 0.4 per cent next year – but it is still the biggest marketplace in the world, doing £11 trillion of business every year and encompassing 500 million consumers and 21 million companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our prosperity agenda forward won’t be easy – the global economic environment clearly remains a challenge. But it is a challenge I am confident Britain can respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we are doing within the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to embed commercial thinking should help. We are now training our diplomats in commercial as well as foreign affairs, and deploying new commercial staff across our diplomatic network. Our Ambassadors increasingly undertake secondments to companies before taking up their postings to gain firsthand commercial experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the often bleak commentary from elements of the media, the British economy has real strengths. Just think of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games held earlier this year. The Games followed hot on the heels of Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, and showcased to the world Britain’s diversity, openness, creativity and dynamism – politically, culturally and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is renowned for its excellence in financial services, the creative industries and, of course, in education. But as anyone who visited the British Business Embassy at Lancaster House in London during the Olympics would have noticed, we also remain one of the world’s most important manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s car industry, currently undergoing a renaissance, is one such example. We are home to seven global car manufacturers.  Ford, General Motors, Jaguar Land Rover and Mini you will know, but we also have big investments from Honda, Toyota and Nissan too, who produced over 480,000 vehicles in Britain last year. In total, more than one million vehicles and two million engines are produced in the UK each year, and over three-quarters of the vehicles we manufacture are exported. And enthusiasts of faster cars will know that eight Formula One teams have their headquarters in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the UK’s expertise across this and many other sectors makes us a highly compatible partner for the Philippines. I would point, for instance, to finance, where our ICT specialists are helping the Philippine Stock Exchange expand their optic fibre network across the ASEAN region; and to healthcare, where our extensive experience in Public-Private Partnerships is helping the Philippines in their plans to develop a centre of excellence in orthopaedic medicine, modelled on the Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our sectoral expertise is certainly not the only reason. What makes Britain a particularly attractive partner is, I think, the openness of our economy, our transparency and adherence to the rule of law and our firm belief in the rules-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of economic uncertainty, some are inevitably tempted to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. But protectionism is a short-term measure with long-term consequences, and in Britain we are taking the opposite approach. History has taught us that more trade, more competitiveness and making the UK open for business and open for investment are what will steer us towards sustainable economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines is heading down the same path, and I would highlight four areas that point towards this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is corruption, which remains a scourge on the global economy. It adds as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries. Those who are hardest hit are often the poorest and most vulnerable in society. That is why we are proud to have introduced the Bribery Act in the UK to address this all-too-common problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Aquino’s anti-corruption efforts and business-friendly policies such as the Integrity Initiative and the decision to join the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative are exactly the right thing to be doing – particularly now, during this period of global economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area is building the infrastructure needed to provide the foundations for long-term prosperity. Modern economies need roads, digital and cellular communications, public transport, schools and hospitals. Without them, we cannot deliver the skilled and trained workforce required to compete in the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third area is ensuring peace and stability. This is perhaps the most crucial platform for prosperity. I am proud that the UK played a small but important role in the framework agreement in Mindanao as a member of the international contact group.  And I would like to take this opportunity to repeat our deepest condolences for the terrible devastation caused there by Typhoon Pablo. Successful implementation of the framework agreement will unlock the economic potential of that area. We are also working closely with Secretary del Rosario and his team to bring about a peaceful resolution of the claims in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connected to international peace and stability is the fourth area: shunning protectionism and embracing free trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ future will not be shaped by growth in the archipelago alone. Whether it is through its overseas workers, the foreign investment that can create jobs, or its export markets abroad, it is clear that future prosperity here will be based on partnerships. This agenda is moving in the right direction.  But I think we can go further and faster. Agreeing a free trade agreement between the EU and the Philippines would be a valuable step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this policy prescription is good for your economy. But it is also vital for your broader development. International trade and investment is not just the best route to development; history tells us it is the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am speaking to you here today because I think – in fact I am certain – that the relationship between Britain and the Philippines can play an important part in promoting our mutual prosperity. We have much in common, and economies that rely on a strong and open global economy. We are democracies, with a strong attachment to human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today Secretary del Rosario marked this growth by signing a joint plan of action that will take our relationship to a new level. This is a genuinely exciting proposition. Our partnership will help to shape the business environment – working together on issues like anti-corruption, competitiveness, economic reform, a low-carbon economy and building awareness about the opportunities for trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade between our countries currently stands at around £1.1 billion. That is impressive, but is I think a fraction of what it can be, particularly when you consider just how fast your country is growing. In this year’s third quarter, growth in the Philippines reached 7.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joint action plan should help us to realise this potential. But we as governments can only do so much. Ultimately, it is businesses that will drive growth. We need your help to generate interest, build awareness and deliver projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore pleased that we have with us today some excellent examples of successful companies operating here –like Standard Chartered Bank, Marks and Spencer and Debenhams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On visas – not always an easy subject – I know that we have a fast, fair and efficient service here, and that we are opening new services to facilitate quick and easy travel for business via Saturday openings, a premium service and a new visa application centre in Cebu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sign that we are indeed open to business is the large number of Filipino overseas workers that are employed in the UK, who are making a valuable contribution to our economy but also sending back remittances to family in the Philippines. Their contribution cuts across many sectors, but is particularly evident in health and care work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that our new visa services will lead to many more visitors travelling between our countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help bring this about, I will sign a new air services agreement later today with Secretary Abaya, and meet Ramon Ang and Philippines Airlines, who hope to start direct flights to London soon. And, incidentally, their passengers will probably be arriving on new aircraft made partly in Britain, following the announcement by Philippines Airlines in August of a $7 billion order from Airbus for over 50 new aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to share our policy experience in infrastructure development, energy and Public-Private Partnerships so you can learn from our experiences, our successes and, occasionally, our mistakes. When President Aquino visited London in the summer, he went to St Pancras Station, a successful example of how well Public-Private Partnerships can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope what you have heard today is a clear indication of the UK’s role in today’s global economy, of what is happening here in the Philippines and, most importantly, a compelling vision for how Britain and the Philippines can be partners for prosperity, looking to the future with confidence and optimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit is just one of what I am confident will be many high-level visits in the coming months. I know that my colleague, the Foreign Secretary William Hague, is keen to visit in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the rest of my programme, and – with your agreement – I will not leave it another 30 years before I return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55493</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:03:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council </title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister David Lidington has updated parliament on the Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council in a Written Ministerial Statement.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I will attend the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, and I will attend the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council will be chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council will be chaired by the Cypriot Presidency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will discuss the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. Whilst I do not expect conclusions to be issued, we will aim to ensure that this meeting, the 30th such summit, delivers concrete results for the EU in its relationship with Russia. The discussion provides an opportunity for the UK to steer the EU’s objectives for the Summit and to ensure discussion focuses on concrete achievable outcomes, such as: resolution of the Siberian overflight charges; movement on market reform; positive developments in the energy relationship; underlining Member States’ concerns on human rights and democratic standards; and a more effective Partnership for Modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will review the situation in the countries of the Western Balkans, in advance of the discussion of EU enlargement at the GAC the following day. This will be an opportunity to consider the latest developments in the EU-facilitated dialogue between the Prime Ministers of Serbia and Kosovo: the UK welcomes the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this and is keen to see further improvement in the relations between the two sides. There may also be some discussion of the situation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, where the pace of reform has recently slowed and renewed progress is badly needed, as well as consideration of the situations in Macedonia and Albania. I do not expect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a discussion on Syria. Further to a UK drive to increase EU support to Syrian civil society, I anticipate that the EEAS will present its vision on how the EU can support civil society in coping with the consequences of the ongoing conflict and better prepare it for political transition. We also expect discussion on the relationship between EU Member States and the newly formed Syrian National Coalition. Having successfully amended the EU arms embargo (and sanctions package) by setting a three-month renewal period, we will make fresh arguments in support of amending the arms embargo ahead of the March 2013 deadline in a way that offers sufficient flexibility to increase practical support to the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers may also take stock of recent events in Libya, including how to support the priorities of the new Prime Minister, Ali Zidan, and his government which has now taken office. There will be an opportunity to discuss the provision and coordination of international assistance to the new Libyan authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council may discuss events in Egypt following President Mursi’s 22 November Constitutional Declaration. The situation on the ground is changing rapidly, but we will argue for the EU to respond appropriately to the latest developments and clearly underline support for continued progress towards democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussions on the Middle East Peace Process will focus on follow-up to the 29 November UN General Assembly Resolution, including the EU’s response to the Israeli decisions to build 3,000 new housing units in East Jerusalem and the West Bank, to unfreeze planning in the area known as E1 and to withhold tax revenue from the Palestinian Authority. EU Ministers will also discuss facilitating a rapid return to credible negotiations in order to secure a two-state solution. We will reiterate our condemnation of the Israeli decision, underlining the threat this poses to the two-state solution, and stress the need to continue work to build on the May FAC conclusions. We will also emphasise the need for the US, with the strong and active support of the EU, to do all it can in the coming weeks and months to take a decisive lead and push the peace process forward urgently. Additionally the UK will stress the need to build on the Gaza ceasefire and to address the underlying causes of the conflict including more open access to and from Gaza for trade as well as humanitarian assistance, and an end to the smuggling of weapons. The UK will support conclusions covering these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eu-us"&gt;EU-US&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This item has been re-scheduled from November’s FAC. Ministers will have the opportunity to discuss the EU’s priorities with the US following the US presidential elections on 6 November and the re-election of President Obama.  I expect the discussion to cover a spectrum of leading international issues, including the global economy and a possible EU-US free trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukraine and Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC)
We also expect Ministers to agree conclusions on Ukraine and the DRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a substantial agenda for the GAC in December. There is a legislative deliberation on the Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union; a presentation by the Commission on the Annual Growth Survey; Preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December; endorsement of the 18 month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece; and a discussion on Enlargement, covering all potential candidates and including the adoption of EU Common positions for the Accession Conference with Iceland. Due to the large agenda, I expect many of these items to be brief and I expect most of the discussion to focus on the preparation for the European Council on 13 and 14 December and on Enlargement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cypriot Presidency hopes to secure agreement on a selection method for additional judges at the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union: we have not yet received the final proposal for this.  I remain concerned at the current backlog at the General Court, which is damaging to the interests of British business.  My priorities in the discussion will be: to ensure that there is proportionate common law representation among any additional judges; that the costs of additional judges are covered within existing budgets; and that the selection method provides the Court with the stability it requires to function effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission will present key elements of the 2013 annual growth survey which can be found on the Commission’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual growth survey sets out the Commission’s views on the economic priorities for Europe for 2013, focusing on fiscal consolidation, promoting economic growth and employment. The survey, which represents the first stage of the 2013 European Semester, focuses on growth-friendly fiscal consolidation measures across the EU.  The European Semester is the EU-wide framework for coordinating structural reforms and growth-enhancing policies. We do not expect this item to be opened for substantive discussion but, in the event that it is, I will be supporting the focus on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agenda for the December European Council will cover: economic policy, including Economic and Monetary Union and Banking Union; defence; enlargement; and foreign policy. The last two items are covered by the separate sections of this Written Ministerial Statement on enlargement and on the Foreign Affairs Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the European Council meeting will focus on agreeing a legislative framework for Banking Union and an agenda for further Economic and Monetary integration in the Eurozone.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the December European Council the Prime Minister will seek to ensure the integrity of the Single Market at 27, including in the context of the Banking Union and the European Banking Authority. We will also press for further progress on growth and ensure that the timetable for further integration in the Eurozone progresses at the right pace and in the right way.  I will argue that these concerns should be addressed prior to the December European Council so that solutions to these issues can be put to leaders on 13 and 14 December.
The December European Council agenda item on defence will pave the way for further discussion in 2013.  I will argue for a focus on developing capabilities, enhancing operational effectiveness and strengthening the European defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GAC has been asked to endorse the 18-month programme of the Council. This sets out the combined programme for the Irish, Lithuanian and Greek Presidencies of the European Council covering the period January 2013 to June 2014. I expect the programme to be published shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ministers will seek to agree conclusions taking stock of progress on EU enlargement, and on the stabilisation and association process in the Western Balkans. The Commission released their Annual Enlargement Package on 10 October.  In this communication, the Commission recommended: (i) opening accession negotiations with Macedonia; and (ii) granting Albania candidate status subject to the completion of three specific measures and evidence of continued commitment in the fight against organised crime and corruption. We believe the communication to be a broadly fair and balanced assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek conclusions reconfirming the European Council’s support for EU enlargement and recognising that the accession process gives strong encouragement to political and economic reform and reinforces peace, democracy and stability. We agree with the Commission’s view that closer relations with the EU should be based on the principles of delivery on commitments, fair and rigorous conditionality, and good communication with the public. We agree that key challenges remain for most enlargement countries, including in the area of the rule of law. We also support a focus on freedom of expression and regional co-operation, particularly for the Western Balkans countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out the Government’s views on the Commission’s reports in my explanatory memorandum of 18 October. We will seek Council conclusions welcoming Croatia’s continued progress towards meeting all of its commitments in full before its expected accession on 1 July 2013, while reiterating the Commission’s call for Croatia to sharpen its focus to ensure this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will seek conclusions that provide a fair and balanced assessment of Turkey’s progress, which will inject much needed momentum into the process to allow accession negotiations to move forward in 2013. I will argue that Iceland should be commended on the progress made in accession negotiations this year, while recalling the need for Iceland to address existing obligations, such as those identified by the European Free Trade Association Surveillance Authority under the European Economic Area Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also expect the Council to welcome the opening of accession negotiations with Montenegro in June 2012, while calling for early progress in the area of the rule of law, in line with the new approach to accession negotiations endorsed by the Council in December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the FAC discussion of 10 December, the GAC will discuss the Commission’s enlargement package for the Western Balkans countries. We remain fully supportive of a future for all of the Western Balkans countries in the EU, once conditions are met. We want the European Council to commend good progress on reform in Macedonia through the High Level Accession Dialogue, and hope the European Council will be able to build on this by agreeing to the Commission’s fourth successive recommendation to open accession negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a further report from the Commission, the December European Council will not be in a position to grant candidate status to Albania; we will want it to call on Albania to make early progress on reform implementation and establish a track record on tackling organised crime and corruption to enable a decision in 2013. I will argue for Council conclusions that underline that Serbia still needs to make real progress to deliver a “visible and sustainable improvement” in its relations with Pristina before accession negotiations can be opened, while noting that this remains in reach if recent progress continues.  We want the Council to welcome the Commission’s assessment that a Stabilisation and Association Agreement with Kosovo is feasible and to signal that negotiations should begin as soon as possible.  We agree with the Commission’s assessment that Bosnia and Herzegovina’s progress on its EU agenda has stalled. We will want the Council to press the leaders of Bosnia and Herzegovina to make progress and deliver quickly on those issues they themselves have agreed to, for example, on the EU road map agreed in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/35445</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-in-latin-and-central-america"/>
    <title>Britain in Latin and Central America</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire talked about strengthening UK ties with Latin and Central America at the Diplomatic Academy (IEESFORD) in El Salvador</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my first visit to El Salvador. It is a pleasure to be here, and a privilege to address the IEESFORD diplomatic academy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would first like to repeat my message of last week and express my deepest condolences to the families and friends of those who lost their lives, or were injured, as a result of the earthquake in Guatemala. I know the tremors were felt here too.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake has been a tragic reminder of the very real threat this region faces day-to-day. The brave response of those on the ground, and the offer of support from countries across the region, has been an example to us all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, the British Foreign Secretary, William Hague, gave a speech at Canning House in London, on the United Kingdom’s relations with Latin America. His speech marked the opening of a new chapter in Britain’s approach to this region; that, and I quote, “the UK’s retreat from Latin America is over”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come here today to reaffirm this message, and to set out what this new chapter means for the United Kingdom and the countries of Central America.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historic partners   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has enjoyed a long and very special bond with Latin America.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Canning, the nineteenth-century Foreign Secretary and Prime Minister after whom Canning House was named, remains perhaps the most striking example. Under his leadership, Britain was among the very first countries to recognise newly independent Argentina, Colombia, Mexico, and, of course, Brazil, whose independence Canning himself helped to negotiate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Canning was certainly not the only Englishman to see the huge potential of Latin America. Weetman Pearson, one of the great Victorian entrepreneurs and an early proponent of globalisation, built railroads and harbours in Colombia, Mexico and Chile.  He also had ventures in oil and energy, illuminating Mexico and Chile with energy generated by the countries’ first hydroelectric plants.  Visitors to Veracruz can see a statue of Pearson, which was unveiled ten years ago to mark the centenary of its port.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearson’s endeavours reflected our strong trade links: by the time of the First World War, 50 percent of foreign investment in Latin America came from Britain, and 20 percent of its trade was with Britain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European and Central American economies had been closely linked since the Industrial Revolution. When we started importing jute from India, for example, the blue indigo dye used to colour textiles - particularly shirts - came from Central America, principally El Salvador. The term “blue collar workers”, which originated at that time, is still used in English to this day.&lt;br&gt;
By the late twentieth century, however, Britain had lost sight of the importance of Latin America. We had shut Embassies, withdrawn diplomats, found other trading partners.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s return to Latin America   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when this Government came into office, we inherited a relationship with Latin America that was well short of its potential. That was bad for Britain and, I think, bad for Latin America.&lt;br&gt;
It meant that we in Britain were not making the most of our relations with one of the world’s leading engines of economic growth. Latin America has a combined GDP greater than that of India and Russia together, with growth rates forecast at around four to five percent for the next five years. The region’s middle class is already bigger than China’s and India’s combined.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its countries are also playing an increasing role in international affairs. Guatemala currently has a seat on the UN Security Council, and will be joined from January by Argentina - who will take over from Colombia. Eight Latin American states are currently members of the UN Human Rights Council. Countries like Brazil are increasing their development co-operation in Africa.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from a Latin American perspective, it meant losing out on all that Britain has to offer - whether making the most of British expertise in energy, education or financial services, or taking full advantage of the UK’s position as a springboard to the EU’s Single Market of over five hundred million customers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So over the past two years, the Foreign Secretary has led Britain’s most ambitious effort to strengthen our ties with Latin America since the days of Canning.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the difficult economic situation we face, we have opened a new Consulate General in Recife in Brazil, and we are on track to re-open our Embassy in Paraguay next year. We have sent more diplomats to Brazil, Mexico, Columbia, Chile and Peru - by creating, for instance, a new network of Prosperity Officers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we recognise that there is no substitute for high-level engagement. So we are visiting more.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been over forty Ministerial visits to Latin America since this Government came into office - including those by the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister to Mexico, and the Prime Minister’s visit to Brazil in September, with the largest ever trade and education delegation.  I joined him on that trip - my first as a Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, Ministers from no fewer than ten Whitehall Departments have touched down in Latin American countries so far this year. We have also hosted several major inward visits, President Santos of Colombia and the incoming President of Mexico among them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have increased co-operation at the highest levels with Brazil, for example through our Host-to-Host programme on the Olympics, and with Mexico during their very successful Presidency of the G20.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America has been crucial to our refocus too. We have, for example, strengthened our Embassy in Panama, and we are increasing our resources for engaging with Honduras. The Foreign Secretary visited Panama last year, as did my predecessor, Jeremy Browne, who also went to Costa Rica. Panamanian President Martinelli has visited the UK twice in the past year, and Ministerial contact with Guatemala has also increased.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is perhaps most evident right here: I am in El Salvador first and foremost to re-open the British Embassy, which I will do this afternoon.  Since it was closed nine years ago, El Salvador has been the largest economy in the world without a British Embassy. That is something we had to put right.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that in the short time we have been back, much has already been achieved. We have worked more closely on climate change and prison reform, and on preventing violence against women, which I know is a priority for the government here, including the First Lady.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, our Ambassador launched the GREAT campaign to spread the message that Britain is open for business. Shortly afterwards, the Embassy marked Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee. And we held a series of events around the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games, with more to follow to help build a lasting legacy here. Incidentally, I should offer my congratulations to El Salvador on the design of your Olympic uniform, which quite rightly won plaudits around the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These activities are only a sign of what is to come. I say this because I believe that it is strongly in the interests of the UK to work more closely with Central America across the bilateral agenda. That means engaging more on security, as well as prosperity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the security challenge   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we should not exaggerate the security challenge that Central America continues to face, nor should we downplay it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belize, Guatemala, El Salvador and Honduras have some of the highest homicide rates in the world, linked mainly to the activities of criminal gangs. Central America, situated as it is between drug producers to the south and major consumers to the north, clearly faces significant challenges. We recognise this, which is why co-operation between security authorities and Britain’s Serious Organised Crime Agency remains a crucial part of our work in the region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central American governments are taking positive steps to tackle organised crime and the drugs trade, and we want to support your efforts - not just because it is in the interests of Central America, but because your security problems affect Britain too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons we have stepped up our involvement with SICA, the Central American Integration System - which is, I know, based just down the road from here. Last November we committed an extra £250,000 in funding for SICA projects, ranging from training police in Belize to supplying equipment for counter-narcotics work in Costa Rica and Honduras.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be meeting SICA representatives tomorrow and am delighted to announce today that Britain, currently a “Friend of SICA”, has applied to become an Extra-Regional Observer. This demonstrates how seriously we take your efforts to tackle violence, organised crime and insecurity. If our application is agreed, I hope our strengthened commitment will enable us to work more closely with SICA, its Friends and Observers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time that Central America is underpinning its own security, it is playing an increasingly important role outside its neighbourhood.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costa Rica and Guatemala are providing a strong voice on human rights internationally in their roles as members of the UN Human Rights Council.  Central American countries have been strong supporters of the growing international consensus on Syria. It is important that your voices are heard, not least because you have a wealth of experience you can share with the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to hear that El Salvador is considering increasing its international peacekeeping contribution, partly as a way of thanking the United Nations for the role it played in helping to draw up the Peace Accords to end the civil war in 1992. This is an important and welcome step. I know that El Salvador already participates in nine peacekeeping missions, from MINUSTAH in Haiti to UNIMIT in East Timor.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central American governments are taking a constructive approach on a range of international issues. Many of you have shown a real willingness to listen to others’ views, including on issues like the Falkland Islands. We are grateful to those countries that allowed the Islanders’ representatives to visit recently and set out their case for determining their own political status and being allowed to live in peace.  We very much hope that Argentina too will one day listen to their views.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting our mutual prosperity   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the security situation in the region continues to improve, it will reinforce the conditions for trade and investment to flourish. British exports to Latin America as a whole increased by fourteen percent last year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America is already an important market for trade, and the figures bear this out.  It has a combined GDP of over $167 billion, and its countries represent a market of close to forty-two million people.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Panama, which is growing at an impressive rate. Its GDP is projected to grow by 9.5 percent this year, and according to the Latin Business Index it ranks second in Latin America for ease of doing business. Consider Nicaragua, whose investment agency, ProNicaragua, was named by a World Bank study earlier this year as the top investment facilitator globally.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive stories like these are helping to attract foreign investment to the region. And the opportunities, I know, are significant - particularly in infrastructure, energy, green technology, education and retail.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore unsurprising that British companies are already operating successfully - including familiar British names such as Lloyds Insurance, BT, BUPA, Unilever, GlaxoSmithKline and JCB. The UK is already the world’s biggest investor in Panama.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, UK exports of goods to SICA countries totalled just £355 million last year. I think there is scope to increase this significantly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why within the last year we arranged a trade mission to Guatemala and El Salvador, and brought a Costa Rican business delegation to the UK.  It is why we are negotiating a new Double Taxation Agreement with Panama, which we hope to conclude by the end of the year; and why we have signed a bilateral Memorandum of Understanding with the Dominican Republic, which covers trade and investment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is why we are supporting Central American countries as they address the underlying barriers to prosperity such as corruption - by, for example, funding training in Belize to tackle money laundering.  And it is why we will continue a busy programme of high-level visits, including a landmark visit by the Lord Mayor of London to Panama next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And countries across the region can take steps to drive growth in our trade too. Ratifying the EU-Central America Association Agreement, signed in June, would have a particularly significant impact.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once implemented, its trade pillar will reduce or eliminate tariffs that Central American countries pay when exporting goods to the European Union.  This will be hugely beneficial, with gains on exports such as coffee, sugar and spices, as well as textiles and vehicle parts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, Central American signatories are expected to experience gains in national income of around $3 billion as a result of the Agreement’s trade pillar coming into force. It will also diversify your trade markets, create jobs and, ultimately, help to reduce poverty.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it will liberalise sixty-nine percent of Central America’s existing trade with the EU, saving EU exporters an estimated £68 million annually in customs duties. And by introducing new safeguards such as better protection of Intellectual Property and Geographical Indications, the Agreement will make Central America a more attractive destination for investment.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the very real benefits it will bring, I was pleased to hear that on 18 October Nicaragua became the first Central American country to ratify the Association Agreement.  I would strongly encourage others to follow.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canning Agenda launched by the Foreign Secretary is just two years old. It will take time for us to rebuild the sort of relationship between the United Kingdom and Latin America that Canning would be proud of.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I think the actions we have taken have put us on the right track. And we are starting to see the benefits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central America will remain a crucial part of our re-engagement. I hope that when Foreign Minister Martinez and I cut the ribbon at the new British Embassy this afternoon, it will underline Britain’s commitment to this exciting and dynamic region.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that as we tackle today’s global challenges; as we work closer together on trade, counter-narcotics, international crime, on climate change, human rights and the most pressing of international issues, we will go some way to supporting our mutual prosperity in the years to come.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there is a bright future ahead for Britain and Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35586</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-of-thailand-visit-to-the-uk"/>
    <title>Prime Minister of Thailand visit to the UK</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Prime Minister David Cameron and Prime Minister of Thailand Yingluck Shinawatra agree to establish a Strategic Dialogue for future bilateral cooperation</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;During 13-14 November 2012 Her Excellency Ms. Yingluck Shinawatra, Prime Minister of the Kingdom of Thailand, paid an official visit to the United Kingdom at the invitation of the Rt. Hon. David Cameron, Prime Minister of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thai Prime Minister was accompanied by key members of the Thai Cabinet, namely Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Finance, Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Foreign Affairs, Minister of Commerce, Minister of Industry, Minister of Transport, senior officials, and CEOs from prominent Thai enterprises.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 13th November the Thai Prime Minister had an audience with Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II. On 14th November the two Prime Ministers held bilateral discussions and exchanged views on various matters of mutual interest, bilaterally, regionally and globally. Both sides noted with satisfaction the increasing contacts and activities at all levels and in all dimensions of bilateral relations. They agreed to intensify efforts to elevate the already excellent state of their relations to an even higher plain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, both leaders have agreed to the establishment of a “Strategic Dialogue” as a high-level, consultative forum to set and monitor the future direction for their bilateral cooperation in all areas. This new mechanism will also serve as a concrete platform for both sides to exchange views on regional and multilateral issues and will be convened on a regular basis between high-ranking officials of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Thailand and the Foreign and Commonwealth Office of the United Kingdom, at a venue to be alternated between Thailand and the United Kingdom. To give a further boost to this new mechanism, the Thai Prime Minister expressed her kind offer for Thailand to play host to the first Dialogue at the time to be mutually agreed upon by both sides.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two Prime Ministers also welcomed increasing two-way trade and investment, highlighted by the long-established presence and active role of the British private sector in Thailand which has made a significant contribution to this growth, making the UK Thailand’s second largest trading partner and one of the top three foreign investors from the European Union. The UK side also welcomed growing interest from the Thai private sector to expand investments in the United Kingdom. Both leaders welcomed progress made on the Thai-EU Free Trade Agreement (FTA) and expressed their optimism that an early negotiation of an FTA will be beneficial for both sides. They also underlined their commitment to develop further partnerships both at the public and private levels in areas of mutual interest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both sides agreed to work together to share expertise and best practice in flood prevention, and to this end the UK offered to fund four senior Thai officials to attend a flood risk management course at Cranfield University.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both leaders also agreed to promote further people-to-people contacts between the two countries. To this end, the Thai Prime Minister stressed Thailand’s commitment to ensuring safety and hospitality for foreign tourists. To facilitate a greater volume of exchanges, the British Prime Minister has announced that from 1 December 2012 student applicants will be able to access the priority visa service, which is already available to Thai business people and general visitors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both leaders expressed appreciation towards expanding cooperation in the area of education, especially on-going projects between the Ministry of Education of Thailand and the British Council on the English Language Teaching Assistance Programme, and Provision of English Language Applications for tablet PCs provided for school children by the Thai Government. They are confident that such  collaborations will help prepare Thai workforce for ASEAN Community in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, both leaders welcomed the political and economic developments in Myanmar/Burma and underlined the need for the international community to further promote developments there.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both leaders recognised the importance of ASEAN to regional peace and stability and the dynamism and economic potential of ASEAN’s 600 million population, Thailand’s potential to serve as a gateway to the region, and the role of the UK-ASEAN Business Council in increasing the UK’s trade and investment links.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Thailand and the United Kingdom share similar values, the two leaders agreed to work more closely to tackle global challenges, such as transnational crimes, counter terrorism, maritime security, and climate change. Both sides reaffirmed their support for the ongoing reform of the United Nations and its principle organs with a view to making the United Nations more efficient and transparent. Thailand commended the United Kingdom for her role in the process to develop a successor framework to the MDGs and expressed her readiness to collaborate with the international community towards such goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister of Thailand conveyed her deep gratitude to the Government of the United Kingdom and its people for the excellent hospitality extended to her and the Thai delegation. She extended an invitation to the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom to visit Thailand in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35567</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-india-and-uk-partnership"/>
    <title>The India and UK partnership</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary has made a statement about building a stronger partnership with India following a meeting with Mr Salman Khurshid, Indian Foreign Minister for External Affairs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking in New Delhi the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to return to India. I am very grateful to my new counterpart, His Excellency, Shri Salman Khurshid, for the warm welcome he has extended to me today. I am pleased to be among the first Foreign Ministers to have the chance to discuss with him the many pressing challenges that we face together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On our election in May 2010, the British government made clear that we would invest significantly in many ways in the UK-India relationship to build a stronger, wider and deeper partnership together. For us this is an essential pillar in our broader strategy to build far closer relations with the powers of the South and the East in the world. As I have often said, I believe that the 21st century more than any previous period will be shaped by India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since 2010, our partnership has truly become stronger, wider and deeper. We are on course to hit our target of doubling trade by 2015. British companies are leading the way, investing in India in key sectors such as energy, telecommunications and education. The largest single foreign investments into India are British, by Vodafone and BP. This is a two-way process. Indian companies have chosen to invest more in the UK than in the rest of the EU combined and with great success, as Tata’s investments in companies such as Jaguar Land Rover have shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Beyond business, the finest minds in our two countries are increasingly working together for the benefit of both our nations, and for the world. Our government-led joint research funding has now passed £100 million compared to £1 million three years ago. I am delighted that each year over 30,000 ambitious young Indians choose the UK for their higher education. As home to four of the world’s top ten universities, I am confident that Britain offers these students the very best in their pursuit of knowledge. I am also pleased by the progress we are making to strengthen our civil nuclear co-operation, both commercially and through our research institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have also agreed a communique to steer our future cooperation on cyber security. This agreement confirms our shared commitment to the core principles of liberty, transparency, freedom of expression and the rule of law in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our diplomatic networks play a vital role in creating opportunities for partnership. Since 2010, we have agreed to open two new Deputy High Commissions in Hyderabad and Chandigarh. The British diplomatic presence in India is now more extensive than that of any other nation. We hope to develop this further over the coming years. And our recent decision to re-engage with the Government of Gujarat now offers us the chance to strengthen our ties across the breadth of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our partnership is not limited to co-operation on British or Indian soil. We have worked increasingly closely together on matters of international security, not only on cyber security but also in areas such as counter-terrorism, and the security of chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear materials. We have also worked closely together with India during her tenure on the United Nations Security Council, and we look forward to the time when she takes up a permanent seat. We also support Indian membership of the international export control regimes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I know we will discuss a range of foreign policy issues including Afghanistan and other issues in India’s neighbourhood, where we greatly value India’s counsel and co-operation. We will also discuss the situation in Syria where the British Government is appalled by the regime’s brutal repression which has led to more than 30,000 people losing their lives. I welcome India’s support for a stronger role for the UN in bringing an end to the violence. We are both committed to pursuing a peaceful political transition and working together to support the work of UN-Arab League Special Envoy Lakhdar Brahimi in his efforts to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So ours is a genuine partnership of equals between the UK and India that we have done a lot to build up over the past two and a half years. There are many more exciting opportunities and we look forward to taking this to the next stage, and to being a partner of choice for India in many areas over the years to come.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35560</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-congratulates-burmese-president-on-reforms"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary congratulates Burmese President on reforms</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague congratulates Burmese President on reforms and highlights concern at violence in Rakhine state.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a meeting with Burmese President Thein Sein on 6 November in the margins of the Asia-Europe Summit in Laos, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was pleased to meet President Thein Sein to follow up our meeting in Burma in January. I congratulated him on the progress Burma has made so far on vital political and economic reforms. I highlighted UK concern at the violence in Rakhine state and the humanitarian situation there, and welcomed what the Government had done to allow our ambassador access to the area. The UK is urging all political parties in Burma to do what they can to end the violence and address the issue of Rohingya citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I encouraged continued cooperation between the UK and Burmese governments to promote responsible trade with and investment in Burma. And I expressed my hope that the President would be able to visit the UK early next year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/35440</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/african-investment-summit"/>
    <title>African Investment Summit</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds gave a speech on investment in Africa.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Xavier for your kind words of introduction and for inviting me here to share my views on Africa.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am only in my second month as a Foreign Office Minister, but I have had a long-standing interest in Africa. I want to highlight my initial impressions of how well positioned we are to take advantage of the business opportunities in Africa.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first impression is that more needs to be done to spread the word of Africa as a continent of opportunity. All of us have a role to play, and this audience is no exception. Others are catching on, but old-fashioned perceptions of Africa persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who closely followed foreign affairs before taking up my position in the Government, I was already conscious of the many positive economic developments emanating from the continent.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But having immersed myself in the subject over the last couple of months, having travelled to several African countries, and having met business representatives, entrepreneurs, investors and politicians,  I have been amazed - not only by the ambition of African countries, by the  scale and diversity of opportunities, but also by the lack of awareness about them. This is most evident among those with no experience of doing business in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Africa’s economic success story is not brand new. Over the first decade of this millennium, six of the world’s ten fastest growing economies were African. Which was the fastest-growing country over those ten years? It wasn’t China. It wasn’t India. It wasn’t Brazil. It was Angola. Of the BRICS, only China made it into the top ten. The rest were crowded out by the likes of Chad, Mozambique and Rwanda, of course, I understand, from a lower base. In terms of annual average GDP growth, African countries have outstripped Asian countries throughout the 21st Century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I suggest that this is not just a flash in the pan. Over the first half of this decade, the trend will continue. Seven of the top ten fastest-growing economies are forecast to be African. But they are not the countries that usually spring to mind. They include - in addition to the ones I’ve mentioned - Niger, Guinea, the Democratic Republic of the Congo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia’s average annual GDP growth has been above 8% since 2001 and is forecast to remain so - making Ethiopia the third fastest growing economy in the world over the next few years. This is impressive. But it is still falling short of its potential. Its rapid growth is being achieved with the lowest internet penetration rate in sub-Saharan Africa: just 0.7%. Imagine how much productivity would be added to the Ethiopian economy with more widespread internet access. A significant proportion of agricultural land remains unproductive or yielding 25% or less of its potential. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It needs to be made clear that African success is not based solely on extractives. Indeed, this is not where the majority of investment is directed. Around 70% of capital being invested into Africa is going into manufacturing and infrastructure. There is growing interest in low-carbon renewable energy - on which, my colleague, Greg Barker, Minister of State for Energy and Climate Change, recently led a business mission to Ethiopia, Kenya and Tanzania. And there is increasing demand for investment in for example health and education, particularly where it relates to driving the achievement of human potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area with huge potential is agri-technology. Well over half the world’s uncultivated cropland lies in Africa. And where land is being used, productivity is only a quarter of the global average. British expertise could help to improve this productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the opportunities in Africa are incredibly diverse - far more diverse than many people realise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghana, which I visited three weeks ago, provides an excellent example. Its economy grew by 14% last year, partly due to oil coming on stream for the first time. And who are leading the development of Ghana’s Jubilee oil field? British-based Tullow Oil. During my visit, I also heard about the great progress that Vodafone is making; took part in an event to celebrate 75 years of British Airways flying to Ghana; and witnessed a new hospital project rising from the ground courtesy of International Hospitals Group. In short, I saw an economy on the move; one which offers huge potential for British investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I realise that I am probably preaching to the converted. I know that there are a significant number of people who are aware of Africa’s potential. But to me it seems like a rather discerning club who attend events like these and only tell one another about the opportunities. So, by explaining to you why I see so much potential in Africa, I want to convince you that we - the Government - understand it and get it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to ask you to spread the word beyond the Africa lecture circuit, and to help others seize the opportunities. There are already many British companies doing excellent business in Africa, but we need to do more to help smaller companies enter the market.  Only 20% of SMEs in sub-Saharan Africa have a line of credit from a financial institution compared, for example, to 44% in Latin America and the Caribbean. I know that Barclays has recently launched an initiative to support the development of the SME sector in Africa, and I hope others will follow. The Financial Services sector, the London Stock Exchange and the city of London have a significant role to play in driving Africa’s economic development and growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain we have the experience and expertise to support Africa’s rise. Our companies are world leaders in sectors as diverse as financial services, communications, education, infrastructure and energy - all of which are needed in the process of economic development. Many of them are listed on the London Stock Exchange. Today, African governments, companies and citizens are crying out for more attention from British business. The appetite is there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a company like Kenya’s Safaricom. Five years ago it launched a new mobile phone-based payment and money transfer service, M-Pesa, following a pilot project supported by Vodafone and the Department for International Development. M-Pesa is now a huge success story, with 17 million subscribers in Kenya alone. This has also shown how we can add value; how British involvement - in this case from both Government and the private sector - can help African business to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of this Government, it is clear that sustainable economic growth will not come from Government spending fuelled by debt, or indeed from domestic demand - at least for now. That means exports are more important than ever. And as growth in our traditional export markets remains sluggish - and you all know what I’m talking about - we need to do more to unlock the opportunities in the new and emerging markets like those in Africa. More trade with Africa will help our own economy and job creation in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have been beating the drum for Africa, I recognise that many problems persist. Conflict and instability endure in some areas. Poverty remains. And it can be difficult to do business - especially where corruption remains a problem. But I believe that trade and investment can help spread stability, alleviate poverty and improve the business environment and reduce the likelihood of conflict. I was pleased to hear President Goodluck Jonathan of Nigeria say this week that more intra African trade is required. That will mean the removal of trade barriers, tariffs and protectionism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As all these elements go in the right direction, so trade and investment will flourish further. African entrepreneurs will look increasingly to the international financial hubs to secure the investment they need to grow their businesses. African governments will be looking to raise funds to build and enhance their infrastructure. We want them to come to London, which is perfectly positioned to match investors with investment opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need me to tell you that the opportunities are very real: African companies are energetic and seeking out investment. London should be leading on this agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise you wouldn’t be here today if you weren’t already interested in Africa. For you, the question is probably ‘what is the Government doing about it?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The honest answer is that we are not yet doing enough. But we are now on the right track. The Prime Minister, Chancellor, Foreign Secretary, Business Secretary, Foreign Office Ministers and our Government colleagues are firmly focused on exports - which we have ambitious plans to expand to one trillion pounds by 2020.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, UK Trade and Investment have been driving forward our commercial agenda in Africa for some time now. But I think it would be fair to say that, in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, we required realignment and re-focus post the 2010 election. So under this Government we are shifting the focus of our work. There is a new emphasis on commercial diplomacy and we are rebalancing our network towards the parts of the world that are growing fastest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, in these tough economic times, we are expanding - not contracting - our diplomatic network in Africa. We have already reopened our Embassy in Cote d’Ivoire, opened a new Embassy in South Sudan and reopened a UKTI office in Mozambique. We have announced our intention to open up in Liberia, to reopen in Madagascar, and - when security permits - to open an Embassy in Somalia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are visiting more, and seeking new opportunities for British outward and inward investment when they do. We are finding innovative new ways to strengthen our commercial links - by creating, for instance, a new network of locally-engaged prosperity officers in six of our West and Central African Posts that do not have a UKTI presence on the ground. And we are working hard to support Africa as it tackles the underlying barriers to prosperity, such as conflict. For example, we are at the forefront of international efforts to bring stability to Somalia, which in the long term will help to create an environment that allows businesses to invest with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I recognise that we need to do more. This is something to which I am personally committed. When I visit Africa and hear about commercial opportunities, I want to ensure that you as representatives of business hear about them too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it isn’t just about information flows and processes: we want to provide practical assistance to help drive forward your commercial interests. UK Trade and Investment is already offering a first-class service to British companies seeking to expand their business in Africa and I would urge you to make use of this network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the key message is not just that Africa is open to investment; but that we in Government know, and will do what we can to help. However, I want to know what more can we do?   What can the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, including UKTI, do to help your company drive investment, wealth and job creation? What more can we do to raise awareness? What, for that matter, can you do to help us drive this forward?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask because successfully building our commercial relationships requires a partnership. I want to hear from you. You can help us measure success too: if our assistance has helped secure contracts or create new jobs, let us know. Because if our approach in the FCO has worked for your company, it may well work for others. And if it hasn’t, why not? And what could we do differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securing Britain’s future in the 21st Century requires us to secure our prosperity. This means harnessing economic growth wherever in the world it is occurring. It means supporting our private sector abroad and ensuring that it can compete in an increasingly competitive global marketplace. It means strengthening our relationships in Africa, deepening our understanding and working together to seize the opportunities that it presents. I want to drive UK investment in Africa to benefit African and UK companies, and the UK economy.  We are here to assist, so use us.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35543</id>
    <published>2012-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-welcomes-indonesian-presidents-state-visit"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary welcomes Indonesian President's state visit</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has expressed his determination to forge strong partnerships with South East Asia</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to Parliament just before the visit the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well having one of the world’s most thriving economies, Indonesia is in the vanguard of the political change shaping Asia. This visit will be an opportunity for us to build on the strong partnership established over the last decade.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In that time Indonesia’s path from dictatorship to democracy alongside growing prosperity has become an important example to the world. In particular President Yudhoyono’s leadership on climate change and other global issues has underscored the values that our two countries share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As it is a key voice in South East Asia I am determined to work with Indonesia and its neighbouring countries so that we continue to turn these shared values into shared action and realise the benefits of greater freedom, prosperity and security together.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foriegn Secretary William Hague met the Foreign Minister of the Republic of Indonesia Dr. R.M. Marty M. Natalegawa  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Queen welcomed President Yudhoyono to the UK during her speech at the State Banquet, she highlighted the common values of Britain and Indonesia and congratulated the President on his work spreading the values of Indonesia’s vibrant democracy through the Bali Democracy Forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royal.gov.uk/LatestNewsandDiary/Speechesandarticles/2012/TheQueensspeechattheIndonesianStateBanquet31Octobe.aspx"&gt;Click here for the full text of the speech.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister met President Yudhoyono at Downing Street today they had constructive discussions on a number of areas. Their talks focused on UK-Indonesian trade and investment and the EU-Indonesia Partnership Agreement which aims to reduce barriers to trade.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/president-yudhoyono-of-indonesia/"&gt;Click her to see read a statement from a spokesperson for the Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South East Asia is a vital engine of global economic growth and in 2012 UK has embraced the opportunities this presents by mounting an unprecedented level of diplomatic engagement in the region. This will continue with the arrival of President Yudhoyono of Indonesia on a state visit to the UK. Then next week the Foreign Secretary will visit Laos, and Thailand including representing the UK at the Asia Europe Meeting (ASEM) Summit in Bangkok on 5-6 November. Also in November the UK expects to welcome Prime Minister Yingluck of Thailand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indonesian President Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono and his wife, First Lady Ani Bambang Yudhoyono will pay a State Visit to the UK from 31 October-2 November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit comes in the context of the increasing global political and economic significance of Indonesia, and of Indonesia’s relations with the UK. Indonesia has the 4th largest population in the world, and has transformed dramatically over the past 15 years to become the world’s largest Muslim democracy. It is currently the 18th largest economy in the world projected to be one of the top 10 economies in 2020 and possibly in the top 7 by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total trade with UK in 2011 was £2.4billion (up 10% year on year). In 2011 exports of goods and services to Indonesia were worth £0.97billion, an increase of 28%, whilst UK imports from Indonesia increased 0.6% to £1.4 bn. Leading British investors include Jardines, BP, Premier Oil, Shell, Unilever, HSBC, Standard Chartered Bank, Prudential, GlaxoSmithKline, and Astra Zeneca. In April 2012 the Prime Minister and President Yudhoyono announced a commitment to double trade (goods &amp;amp; services) by 2015 to £4.4billion. The President is accompanied on this visit by a large business delegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as spending time with the Queen and the Duke of Edinburgh, the President will meet other members of the Royal Family, including the Prince of his Wales and the Duchess of Cornwall. He will meet the Prime Minister David Cameron, and separately, Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg, and the leader of the opposition Ed Miliband. The visit also coincides with the second meeting of the UN High Level Panel on Post 2015 development, which the Prime Minister, President Yudhoyono and Liberian President Sirleaf are co-chairs. Other highlights will be the President giving the Wilton Park annual address on “Indonesia’s role as a regional and global actor” and a lecture at the Royal College of Defence Studies in his capacity as the only Head of State to have served as a UN peacekeeper.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will travel to South East Asia next week where he will open the UK’s embassy in Laos. This will mean that we have an Embassy in every ASEAN nation - vital to our influence in the region. He will also make sure that the UK’s voice is heard at the Europe Asia Meeting Summit, a highly significant platform for building links between Asian and European nations. In Thailand the Foreign Secretary will meet political and business leaders ahead of the Thai Prime Minister’s visit to the UK in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read about the new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinlaos.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=826719082"&gt;British Ambassador to Laos Philip Malone&lt;/a&gt; who has presented his credentials to President Choummaly Sayasone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/35426</id>
    <published>2012-10-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-india-relations-going-from-strength-to-strength"/>
    <title>UK-India: relations going from strength to strength</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire's speech about UK-India relations on 4 October.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me express my gratitude to the IISS for hosting this important dialogue between British and Indian policy formers. This is exactly the sort of event that will help us to strengthen our strategic relations with one another.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is my one month anniversary as Minister of State at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office with responsibilities including India. This is the first policy speech that I am giving in this capacity. I could think of no more appropriate topic, and as an old friend of John Chipman, the Chief Executive of the IISS, I can think of no more appealing venue.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On walking into my new office a month ago, the first thing I noticed amid the dark wood panelling was the gold lettering emblazoned above the huge mirrors behind the desk and above the fireplace opposite.  It spells a single word: India.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I have the fortune of occupying what was formerly the office of the Secretary of State for India - albeit in completely different times and circumstances.  The mirrors, the artwork, the twin doors to the office that were built to accommodate the visits of two Maharajas of equal rank are testament to the impact that India has had - and continues to have - on British history.  I am constantly reminded of our deep roots; our common language and cultural reference points; but also of the complex baggage that has traditionally come with our relationship.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before addressing the topic of our discussion today, I want to look first at the context of our relations.  I would then like to take a step back and consider our overarching interests in the world.  I will suggest that we have more goals in common than is often appreciated.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a social level the links that the UK shares with India are tremendously deep and important.  With around one and a half million people, the Indian diaspora in Britain is bigger than any other minority group.  &lt;br&gt;
And many have become British national cultural treasures: Farrokh Bulsara whose family came from Bulsar in Southern Gujarat grew up to become one of the greatest Rock Stars of all time as Freddie Mercury; Krishna Pandit Bhanji went on to win Oscars, Golden Globes and Baftas as Sir Ben Kingsley.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nasser Hussain, born in Madras, was one of England’s best Test Cricket Captains, and Monty Panesar one of its best spin bowlers.  Though unfortunately Samit Patel  and Ravi Bopara were unable to prevent our unceremonious departure from the World Twenty 20 this week.  I am sure I am not alone in looking forward to the clash of the great Test Cricket titans when England tour India next month.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orbit, designed by Anish Kapoor and funded by Lakshmi Mittal made a permanent mark on the Olympics this summer and will remain one of the sights of London.  And I am wholly convinced that Lord Coe’s successful stewardship of the London Olympics was due in no small part to his Indian heritage!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also unsung heroes across our society: doctors, lawyers, politicians, scientists, and teachers.  Over 700 Indian businesses operate in the UK, accounting for 90,000 jobs.  The Tata Group is the largest corporate employer in the country.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often assume that because of our long shared history, the UK and India have an inbuilt understanding of each other.  However, the deep social links between our societies have not always translated into a shared strategic outlook.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the years after India’s independence, we did not find ourselves on the same side of the Cold War’s ideological divide.  The UK was in NATO, India was a treaty partner of the Soviet Union, and our relations were overshadowed by the memory of the Raj.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1990s saw tremendous strides forward. The collapse of the Soviet Union freed up both sides to reassess aged prejudices.  The 1991 Indian economic reforms reawakened interest in each others’ economies. Narasimha Rao and John Major set up the Indo-British Partnership in 1993, when the Prime Minister was invited as India’s Chief Guest on Republic Day. It marked a decisive break with the past and formed the basis of a ‘modern’ relationship between our two countries.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall not dwell on the previous Government’s record with India, but it is fair to say that the relationship advanced in fits and starts throughout their period of office.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in July 2010 David Cameron opened a new chapter in our relationship. I read recently that ‘It took Gordon Brown ten years to visit India from the moment he first entered Downing Street in 1997 as Chancellor of the Exchequer. It took David Cameron and George Osborne just ten weeks’. In addition to the Chancellor, the Prime Minister brought with him the biggest British delegation in living memory and set out his vision for an enhanced partnership between India and the UK - a new Special Relationship based on shared culture, values, and strategic interests.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We realise that India is re-emerging as one of the world’s great powers. William Hague, our Foreign Secretary, was absolutely right when he said at the launch this year of the Kings College India Institute that “this century will be shaped by India more than any other that has come before it.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are determined to increase our understanding of Indian priorities and concerns. We have already opened a new Deputy High Commission in Hyderabad and another is to follow in Chandigarh.  We are in active discussions with the Indian government to open five new trade offices across India. It is a large country and we want to understand all of it. And as the Foreign Secretary announced at the new Kings College India Institute - which should itself contribute to Britain’s understanding of India - we are forming a new cadre of Foreign Office staff with Indian expertise.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the focus of this session, I shall resist the temptation to go into detail about all the aspects of our flourishing bilateral relationship.  &lt;br&gt;
Suffice it to say that we are well on track to achieving our target of doubling trade by 2015, and that deeper collaboration in areas such as science, education and technology is improving the lives of people in both our countries. For example, a British Council and UK Aid programme has trained one million English teachers across India.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our parliamentary links are growing despite a group of our parliamentarians getting brutally trounced in a cricket match against a group of Indian parliamentarians on their visit to Dharamsala last year - but I shan’t dwell on that; the wounds are still raw!   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This growing collaboration is echoed in our strategic relations.  We have developed a series of official dialogues on the security challenges that will shape the 21st Century, including East Asia, the Middle East, Counter-Terrorism, Disarmament, Cyber Security, and Peacekeeping.  &lt;br&gt;
As a case in point, over the last month we have received visits from Deputy National Security Advisor Latha Reddy and His Excellency Foreign Secretary Ranjan Matthai - with whom I was delighted to have held discussions yesterday. The coming weeks will see visits to India by our Foreign Secretary, William Hague, and our National Security Adviser, Sir Kim Darroch.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On defence, we have close cooperation too. We have in place a comprehensive programme of bilateral exercises across all three services. Our Defence Ministers have annual strategic talks, our military experts visit each other regularly and every year Indian officers come to the UK to attend military courses - three in the Royal College of Defence Studies, three in Shrivenham, and even more at Sandhurst and Cranwell. The British officers who attend equivalent courses in India highly value the experience.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our deepening strategic relations can also be discerned from our strong support for India to have a greater say in international institutions. We have long supported India’s candidacy for a Permanent Seat on the UN Security Council and we also support Indian membership of the international export control regimes. We are delighted that decision making on global governance has expanded to a G20 level and David Cameron has publically proclaimed Prime Minister Singh’s ‘great intellectual leadership in economic matters’ in that forum.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we most certainly have a framework in place for building stronger strategic relations between India and Britain. Our avenues for cooperation are widening. But some remain sceptical about the convergence of our interests. Over the past couple of years we have voted different ways on some Security Council resolutions; we have different approaches to Iran, start from different places on global issues like climate change, and are situated geographically in very different security environments.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a strategic relationship does not mean always agreeing on everything. It is about developing a mature relationship of equals, where we can discuss our problems and concerns like adults, rather than preaching to one another like children. It is about developing a mutual understanding that helps us to cooperate where our interests converge and respect our differences where they do not.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it so happens, I believe that we have far more interests in common than those sceptics give us credit for. Let me give you three important areas in which misunderstandings mask similar ultimate ends: stability in the Middle East, fighting terrorism, and sustainable development.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, we have a common interest in a region that is stable, secure, and economically successful. I understand that there are around six million Indian’s living in the Gulf. Their safety and ability to send remittances home to their families will obviously be of huge concern to the Indian government. Like most countries, Britain has been alarmed by civil unrest across the region, in particular we are deeply disturbed by the gross violations of human rights, state atrocities, and breakdown of law and order that we see today in Syria. And we acknowledge that instability can breed further short term instability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Arab Spring has underlined the importance of democratic transition to the long term stability of the region. Without respect for human rights or transparent and accountable government, pressure will build within societies, increasing the risk of a instability and insecurity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arab Spring has been led by the region. But there is a crucial role for the international community in supporting the people of the region as they build a better future for themselves.  I am convinced that it is in both our countries’ interests to support the fledgling democracies and their economies, and to challenge those who wish to stifle the legitimate aspirations of their people.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the Arab Spring, the stability of the region is being seriously challenged by the prospect of a nuclear armed Iran. Were Iran to acquire nuclear weapons, instability would spread far beyond the Middle East. Both the UK and India have made their concerns clear at the IAEA.&lt;br&gt;
We are completely committed to the diplomatic process that is underway and to finding a peaceful negotiated solution. But we are also committed to intensifying pressure on Iran to bring one about.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our hope that sufficiently comprehensive and targeted economic sanctions will be a serious enough inducement for the Iranian government to address our concerns. Of course, sanctions can harm the sanctioner as well as the sanctioned - especially in this tough economic climate. But their cost would pale in comparison to the cost to the global economy of a nuclear-armed Iran.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful, sanctions need to be coordinated.  And we believe that the international community must isolate the Iranian government, which uses international recognition as a source of legitimacy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may have different views on how to prevent Iran from becoming a nuclear power. But I believe we have a common interest in making Iran see the seriousness of the situation and to persuade it to negotiate with the international community in good faith and in good time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area in which I see a clear convergence of interests is in preventing terrorism. Both our countries have suffered from horrific terrorist attacks over the last decade.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some critics assert that the UK is only interested in threats to its own people. This is utterly false. It is impossible to tackle terrorism alone and it is equally impossible to geographically isolate its effects. There were eight British victims of the Mumbai attacks. I have just come from a meeting with some of the families of the twenty-six British people who were killed in the 2002 Bali bombings which marks its tenth anniversary next Friday. The British death count in the 9/11 attacks was sixty-seven.&lt;br&gt;
We see threats to India as threats to Britain. That is why we proscribed the Indian Mujahidin and pushed for the Laskar-e-Taiba to be added to the UN Consolidated List under Resolution 1267.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we place utmost importance on preventing Afghanistan from being used ever again to stage terrorist attacks against any other country. Another civil war or fractioning between north and south is not an option. We have committed ourselves to Afghanistan beyond the end of our combat mission in 2014 and fully support the important role that neighbours like India continue to play.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me point out that our contributions to the stability of Afghanistan have been mutually reinforcing. The security provided by NATO forces created the conditions in which Indian civilian and development programmes could take place. And India’s assistance has helped to tackle some of the underlying causes of instability in the country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrorism is a common menace, which can only be tackled if like-minded countries stand side-by-side. There is no question that on this, we are like minded. And we are utterly committed to working with India against terrorist threats to both our countries.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth mentioning that the nature of threats is changing. For example, we are increasingly vulnerable to attacks from cyberspace - which can be conducted from anywhere in the world by criminals; states; even geeky children. It is the ultimate globalised threat and will therefore require a tightly coordinated international response.  Our interests in cyber security are mutual and we want to cooperate with India at the Budapest Conference on Cyber Space, which William Hague is opening today, and through our continuing discussion on bilateral cyber issues.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final area on which I want to touch is sustainable development. Both our countries want to create the conditions for long term stable and sustainable growth in our economies.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard accusations that the UK - and the West more broadly - want to deny India and other emerging powers their opportunity to grow, locking in inequality by setting onerous international standards on trade and climate change.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing could be further from the truth.  Not only do we want India to keep up its impressive economic development, we - and the rest of the global economy - depend on it. Our economy relies on India’s for jobs, investment and opportunities like never before.  Economic growth in India is most certainly in our interests.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And growth in other parts of the world is in both our interests.  India and Britain are both outward-looking countries, reliant on open economies and trade governed by common rules and standards. In periods of global economic difficulty, there can be a tendency for countries to turn to short-sighted protectionist policies. I believe that we should be united in resisting such temptations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strategic relationship in the 21st Century cannot focus solely on threats from conflict and terrorism. It must also encompass questions of energy security, climate security, food and water security and global trade policies. We both desire long term global growth and should work not only to increase trade between our two countries but to create the conditions in the global economy for mutual prosperity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, can the UK-India strategic relationship be built further? I certainly believe they can be. The relationship between our two countries is going from strength to strength in so many areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that any accusations that the United Kingdom does not listen to India can be laid to rest once and for all. The last two years have shown that both sides are keen to build a stronger relationship - a partnership of equals based on mutual understanding, respect, and trust.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are putting the institutions in place to support this partnership, and as I have argued, we increasingly have common interests that will drive it. That is not to say that we will always see eye-to-eye on everything or even take similar approaches to common problems. But by talking to one another, listening to one another, learning from one another, and understanding one another better, we can fulfil our potential as close friends and partners.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an extremely impressive array of experience and knowledge in this room. I hope to use this session as a continuation of my own learning experience. So I very much look forward to hearing the perspective of His Excellency, Dr. Bhagwati but I am also interested in hearing from the audience how they assess the UK-India strategic relationship, and how we could build it further.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
