<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing versatile, agile and battle-winning armed forces and a smaller, more professional Ministry of Defence "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57066</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:32:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-secretary-welcomes-defence-reform-annual-report"/>
    <title>Defence Secretary welcomes Defence Reform annual report</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a letter to the Secretary of State, Lord Levene congratulated the Department on strong progress made against the 53 recommendations since the publication of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2" title="Defence Reform Report, June 2011"&gt;Defence Reform Report&lt;/a&gt; in June 2011 and said that he believes the programme is being run with genuine urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full report, with the new annex by Lord Levene, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome Lord Levene’s recognition of the strong progress made to date in implementing his recommendations, and his confidence that we can deliver transition to a new operating model for the Ministry of Defence in April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some of the key changes of Defence Reform are already complete, such as strengthened top-level decision-making and the focus on strategic direction from a newly-constituted Defence Board, which I chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-joint-forces-command-established--2" title="Read more about the establishment of the Joint Forces Command"&gt;The Joint Forces Command has been established&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14926288" title="Read more about the appointment of the first Commander of the UK's Joint Forces Command"&gt;first Commander appointed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many other recommendations are on track for delivery by April 2013, including the delegation of financial and military capability management to give the Service Chiefs greater accountability and freedom to manage their resources and plan for future capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A few recommendations will take longer to complete: I acknowledge that there is more to do in some areas, such as development of the Whole Force Concept and the delivery of improved Management Information, and I value Lord Levene’s continued interest and focus on these important changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am confident, though, that by April [2013] we will have gone a long way towards achieving the aim of the Defence Reform programme: a smaller more professional MOD that is better at supporting the Armed Forces now, and looking forward to Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56853</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:05:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/female-officer-cadet-wins-sandhursts-sword-of-honour"/>
    <title>Female Officer Cadet wins Sandhurst's Sword of Honour</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The top accolade from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/training_education/training/17057.aspx" title="Royal Military Academy Sandhurst"&gt;Royal Military Academy Sandhurst&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Officer Cadet Sarah Hunter-Choat, who received the award during her commissioning at the Sovereign’s Parade on Friday 14 December.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted Sword of Honour is presented to the best overall Officer Cadet out of 200 in the senior term and is personally chosen by the Academy’s Commandant, Major General Timothy Evans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 200 cadets have their performance rigorously monitored throughout the year. Then, going into the final phase of their training, the 3 top candidates, termed ‘blade runners’, are carefully scrutinised then brought before the Commandant for a final interview. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat received the Sword of Honour from Defence Secretary Philip Hammond, who represented Her Majesty The Queen at the Sovereign’s Parade. It has been 6 years since a female officer won, when Angela Laycock was commissioned into the Royal Engineers in December 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat’s success follows in her parents’ footsteps. Her father Brigadier Tony Hunter-Choat had a long, distinguished military career, starting out in the French Foreign Legion before commissioning into the British Army, while her mother is a former RAF officer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56977</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T16:49:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-to-auction-off-radio-spectrum"/>
    <title>MOD to auction off radio spectrum</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radio spectrum refers to the radio waves over which all wireless communication takes place, including radio, television, radar, satellite, mobile voice and data. Under plans announced today, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to auction around 200 Megahertz (&lt;abbr title="Megahertz"&gt;MHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) of its spectrum usage rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes as market demand for extra spectrum is mounting, fuelled by the sharp rise in the use of spectrum-hungry devices such as smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale will give private operators the chance to buy more spectrum to support the introduction of fourth-generation mobile services to people in cities, towns and villages across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively the spectrum could be used by fixed-line operators to provide wireless access to broadband services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum being sold by the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; is all below 15 Gigahertz (&lt;abbr title="Gigahertz"&gt;GHz&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is regarded as the most useful and valuable part of the radio spectrum because of its wide range of applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half of all spectrum below 15GHz is held by the public sector and is used for a broad range of services including defence, emergency services, transport and science. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; holds around three-quarters of all publicly-held spectrum and one-third of all spectrum below 15GHz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome this opportunity to free up much-needed spectrum. We hope that the sale will help drive the roll-out of new generation networks and universal access to broadband, both of which are vital to the UK’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale follows the announcement made in the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/spend_index.htm" title="Spending Review"&gt;2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; that at least 500MHz of public spectrum below 5GHz will be released by 2020 for new mobile communications uses. The spectrum to be sold off is being cleared of military users to contribute towards this target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are expected to start at the end of 2013, with the auction completed by the summer of 2014. Ahead of this, the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; intends to produce an Industry Brochure in early spring 2013 and to host an Industry Day in early summer 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57013</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T23:46:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/chief-of-the-defence-staff-general-sir-david-richards-speech-to-the-royal-united-services-institute-rusi-17-december-2012"/>
    <title>Chief of the Defence Staff General Sir David Richards speech to the Royal United Services Institute (RUSI), 17 December 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you Lord Hutton for your kind introduction.  It is good to see so many friends and colleagues here and may I take the opportunity to thank you all for your strong support to the Armed Forces.  It is hugely appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am feeling slightly cautious this evening.  Our senior Defence Attaché in the Americas tells me that in the Aztec calendar today is the Day of the Lizard.  They say:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘The warrior must be like the lizard, who is not hurt by a high fall but, instead, immediately climbs back to its perch.  These are good days to keep out of sight; bad days to attract attention.’&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So perhaps today isn’t the best time to be standing before you!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In honouring my commitment to this august organisation that plays such an important role in the life of UK Defence, I want to take the opportunity to examine where we are today, what deductions we should draw, and what we are doing to ensure we are prepared for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are all aware of how much change there has been over the past two years.  We have begun to introduce the SDSR, balanced the books and turned a corner in Afghanistan.  Yet much of the world seems less stable and more dangerous than was the case even two years ago; a harsh world in which intra-state conflict can be confused by and for new forms of inter-state conflict.  A world in which governance vacuums present opportunities for extremist groups to perpetrate large-scale violence and disruption, especially as precision-strike capabilities, cyber instruments and bio terror weaponry become inevitably more accessible.  And this in a period when economic fragility makes us both more vulnerable and less able to respond in a confident and timely manner, a reality aggravated by the huge cost differentials between western forces and non-state opponents. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this is demanding much from all of us and is changing the shape and capabilities of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together with my fellow Chiefs I have been examining, as you would expect, how we should best use what we have and what we need for the future.  We have to be hard-nosed realists; accepting we have less than we would wish but that we are still required to protect this nation’s interests through the projection of military force.  We cannot shrug our shoulders and hope the problem will go away.  We have to be ready to fight and fight effectively, often not on our own terms and accepting the constraints we are under.  I have brought this together in a piece of work I will be sharing in the future called How We Will Fight.  And I will look at some of its key deductions in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should be under no illusions; the Armed Forces of tomorrow, like those of today, will be engaged in operations around the world.  They will require the best of their generation as they always have.  People who can think flexibly and with imagination.  As Einstein said, “imagination is more important than knowledge”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These operations will not be carbon copies of Afghanistan or Libya.  But they will require the same skill and dedication that these operations, and all the others we have engaged in since the Cold War, have demanded.  They will require the strength and indeed guile that our Army, Navy and Air Force are famous for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the battle-winning reputation, proven resilience and technological edge of the past decade, I hope you won’t notice some of the tasks the Armed Forces will be doing.  They will be performing a key part of our developing military strategy – deterrence.  Preventing conflict, you may recall, is rightly a principal task of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will come back to this theme later but it is worth remembering that your Armed Forces are often most effective when they are not in the headlines.  Few operations, exercises or training missions are widely reported but each one communicates that we are strong, credible and reliable.  This deters our enemies and reassures our friends.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we should be proud of our nation’s record in this respect.  The relative peace we have enjoyed here in the UK for the past 70 years is not an accident.  It is in large part the result of the quiet work of diplomats building friendships, the skill of our financiers and businessmen in making our economy strong, and the courage of our Armed Forces in deterring and when necessary overcoming threats.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is an example of this lesson.  With our partners in NATO/ISAF and the ANSF we have been more successful than many, regrettably, recognise.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have recently returned from a visit there and, I can tell you, we are meeting the tasks laid on us.  Over the past decade we have:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	closed Al Qaeda’s bolthole ;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	helped underpin a more stable government;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	overseen elections;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	trained an Army and police force;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	and put a country that suffered 30-years of war into a position where industry, education and the rule of law are beginning to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;True, there is a long way to go.  The presidential elections in 2014 will be hugely important.  But we are heading in the right direction and we have proved what can be done with the right resources and with the right support.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I look forward to 2013 seeing us increasingly transition to an Afghan lead as we move from mentoring battalions to supporting brigades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Afghan Army now enjoys the support and trust of 84 percent of the country, only 3 percent less than the British Army in this country.  That is a fantastic achievement, by them and ISAF.  It recognises the integral part they are playing in turning the destiny of a country away from violence and onto a path of peace.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am proud of what our Service men and women have achieved in Afghanistan.  Alongside partners in DFID and the Foreign Office we have given Afghans a chance they couldn’t have dreamt of only a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our operation in Afghanistan does not stand alone.  It is linked to Pakistan and India and the wider region.  In my recent trip to Islamabad, a city I have got to know well, I was very encouraged by the helpful attitude of civilian and military leaders to reconciling the Taliban.  The Taliban, like us, are focussed on Afghanistan’s presidential poll and the end of our combat operations in 2014.  They know that the window of opportunity to play a role in their country’s future is closing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every day the Afghan Army and Police grow in capability and legitimacy.  Every day the government is better able to serve its people and thus better able to marginalise the Taliban.  Now, surely, the time is ripe to take risk in order to find that elusive political solution 10 years of military effort and sacrifice has sought to create the conditions for?  But in order to pull this off, it is vital that Afghan confidence in the West’s long-term commitment to their country is retained.  Why, should this be lost, would they stay the course themselves let alone fight to protect us in 2014 when, absent successful reconciliation, we will be at our most vulnerable?  And why should the Taliban reconcile, if they thought we were ‘cutting and running’?  Retaining Afghan confidence is the campaign’s centre of gravity.  And for the UK, retaining our influence and status within NATO and amongst key allies, is another reason for getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While achieving our goals in Afghanistan, British Armed Forces have been active elsewhere around the world.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Libya we fought in support of a people who wanted to be free from tyranny.  We joined allies from around the world built around a NATO core.  Together, we supplied the air force and the navy.  The people themselves were the army.  They made the change happen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the seas off Somalia we are playing our part in an operation that is controlling the spread of piracy.  Alongside navies from around the world, including Pakistan, India and China, reinforcing the benefit of cooperation.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Closer to home we have also been proud to play our part in HM the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations.  And my fellow Chiefs and I were delighted to receive so many letters of support for the actions of our Regular and Reserve Service men and women during the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It reminded all of us in uniform of the level of support that we enjoy amongst the people of this country.  We are very grateful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this has happened as we have been going through reforms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past two years we have implemented some of the most radical changes to the Ministry of Defence and to the Armed Forces in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SDSR shrank the size of the Armed Forces and changed the governance of the department.  And whilst we are aware that the Autumn Statement has further implications, a balanced budget means we can start from a firm base and better demonstrate what is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new Armed Forces Committee mandates the Chiefs to resolve problems in the interests of Defence as a whole.  It exploits collective military judgment and balances single service requirements in private allowing the CDS to go to the Defence Board with the underpinning authority of a combined Joint service view.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AFC, the Defence Strategy Group chaired jointly by John Thomson the PUS and me, and the new style Defence Board chaired by Philip Hammond enable the MOD to be more agile and decisive in responding at the strategic level to developing threats and trends.  The world is not a safe place.  Some threats to our interests and allies are long term but some are very present.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The immediate danger of the collapse of the Syrian regime is one.  We will support our allies in the region and would all like to see a diplomatic solution but cannot afford to remove options from the table at this stage.  Should chemical weapons be used or proliferate, both President Obama and Prime Minister Cameron have made it clear that a line would have been crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And Syria is linked to Iran.  The regime is backed by Tehran so the fall of Assad’s dictatorship will impact the Iranian government.  What that means for the stability of the region is as yet unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my recent trip to the Manama Dialogue I was struck by the issues that came up.  Our host, Crown Prince Salman of Bahrain, emphasised the threat of nuclear proliferation.  North Korea’s missile test last week aggravates this risk. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kenyan and Ugandan armed forces have been exemplary in bringing order to Somalia but this has not been without cost.  Both have sustained losses, and the retaliation of terrorist groups has endangered Kampala, Nairobi and the Kenyan coast.  We must continue to support both countries, as well as the fledgling Somali government. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To the west, Mali is a major cause for concern.  As still is Yemen, despite President Hadi’s laudable efforts. 
So What?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now reducing these short and long term threats, our task is to evolve a force capable of meeting, with allies, various complex tasks.  By the early 2020s, these plans result in a powerful Joint force that, on the basis of a balanced budget from Planning Round 12, should be able to meet the requirements laid on it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has not been easy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the Secretary of State, building on the work of the SDSR, has ensured that the department is able to squeeze the most from the resources available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2020 we will have kit that many of my fellow NATO Chiefs of Defence, saddled with much more sclerotic budgets than we, are envious of:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	A World Class Carrier Capability with the JSF – Lightning II – on board;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	Type 45 destroyers on patrol;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	Type 26 frigates in production;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	Astute class submarines;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	Chinook Mk 6 bringing the total Chinook fleet to 60;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;f.	Typhoon Tranche 3, as well as the Lightning II;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;g.	Atlas and Voyager air transport and air-to-air refuelling aircraft, underpinned by our now larger C17 fleet;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;h.	Scout vehicles, upgraded Warrior, Challenger, and Apache to give the Army better reconnaissance, mobility and firepower;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i.	Rivet Joint and other critical ISTAR platforms that will ensure we have better situational awareness than ever.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;j.	And much more emphasis on Cyber, to which I will return shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But our most decisive asset will remain our Service men and women.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the private sector puts it, we must look after the ‘talent’. As I see equipment around the world parked with no-one to operate it. Great equipment without talented people counts for little.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must ensure our people have the intelligence and confidence to treat the unexpected as an opportunity to exploit.  They must be capable of informed, independent action; of what has been described as a ‘brains-based approach’ to operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have all heard the common refrain that we must do more with less.  Well, to be frank, that is what we are doing.  At the strategic level, a brains-based approach means deciding to act only when we must and then doing it well, not always kinetically.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This type of thinking has shaped the work I have started on ‘How We Will Fight’.  Assuming the approach I have just outlined, I and my fellow Chiefs have designed our forces to:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	act jointly and with allies, but able to act alone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	be well equipped, but not tied to platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	adapt as the environment changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But we must prioritise.  And as spending has tightened, we must be ruthless in our requirements and getting the most from them.  Effectively targeting limited resources is, in large part, the art of military command in war and in peace through force design.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new UK Joint Expeditionary Force is an expression of this.  The JEF promises much greater levels of integration than previously achieved especially when combined with others, as is already happening with our French allies in the Anglo/French Combined JEF.  The JEF must be genuinely synergistic.  It is the building block to future alliances and independent action.  And we would hope that allies such as Denmark and Estonia, who have fought with distinction in a British formation in Afghanistan, will want to play key roles within the British element of the CJEF.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What it offers is clear: an integrated joint force with capabilities across the spectrum at sea, on land and in the air.  A force that can confidently be allocated a specific slice of the battle space in an allied operation or act alone.  It will be the basis of all our combined joint training.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the capability to ‘punch’ hard and not be a logistical or tactical drag on a coalition, we will be especially welcomed by our friends and feared by our enemies. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF will be of variable size; a framework into which others fit.  It will be the core of the UK’s contribution to any military action, whether NATO, coalition or independent. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together with critical C2 elements such as HQ ARRC and the emphasis placed on the maritime component HQ at Northwood, the JEF is designed to meet our NATO obligations. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Libyan campaign, Jordan, Qatar and the United Arab Emirates were able to play a vital role by bringing their regional expertise into the command structure of a NATO operation.  This provided greater military and political reach.  I look forward to the alliance, perhaps in part through the vehicle of the JEF, working more with non-member states.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Britain’s JEF will be capable of projecting power with global effect and influence.  Nowhere is more important to us than our friends in the Middle East and Gulf and in line with clear political intent we would expect, with other initiatives, for JEF elements to spend more time reassuring and deterring in that region. 
The Royal Navy&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me briefly examine how the How We Fight work affects the single services, starting with the Royal Navy.  As the Prime Minister has put it, the Navy “keeps the arteries of trade of the global economy from hardening.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy will continue to grow in importance.  As our carrier capability comes into service it will be a key part of our diplomatic, humanitarian and military strategy.  Prepared to overcome the toughest military challenges.  This is its raison d’être.  But I know it will be used for much more.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Americans demonstrated through their deployment to Aceh and Haiti that aircraft carriers have huge strategic impact supporting people around the world.  Seeing US military personnel, ships and helicopters playing such a critical role boosted the standing of the US in the world’s most populous Islamic country and undermined extremist rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard power is an essential element of soft power.  In this respect especially, numbers, or mass, still matter.  We must resolve the conundrum at the heart of Bob Gates quip about ‘exquisite technology’.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the future, the Chief of the Naval Staff and I have a vision for a Navy which procures ships differently allowing us to have more, not fewer platforms. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must resist the pressure that has shrunk the number of platforms.  Clearly that will mean rethinking the Navy, including examining the case for ships that may have a limited role in general war.  But this is not new ¬¬¬– remember the corvette over the ages – and is similar to the utility of light and heavy land forces, tailored to task.  And in so doing we will ensure seamanship skills and leadership qualities, so much in demand by our friends and allies, flourish into the long term.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy’s maritime and amphibious components, with 3 Commando Brigade Royal Marines at the core of the latter, will be at the heart of Britain’s JEF.  As the concept develops we will look to acquire ships that range from top-end war fighting elements through potentially to more vessels tailored to discrete but important tasks, to be deployed on a range of routine non-warfighting duties.&lt;br&gt;
The British Army&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army too is changing.  Once we come out of the combat role in Afghanistan at the end of 2014, it will cease to be on permanent rotation with the burdens that imposes.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army will maintain a hard power war-fighting capability while creating the strategic influence, support and engagement ability essential to modern operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the Navy, these land forces must be equipped to pack a punch but war fighting is not all they’re for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conflict prevention, to which I will return in a moment, is not just sensible strategy; it is a military operation requiring appropriately configured and equipped forces. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Army 2020 reforms are a fundamental re-set for the Army, making the best of a regular force a fifth smaller than when I commanded it only three years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we will retain three high-readiness manoeuvre brigades, we will also have ‘adaptable brigades’ to sustain enduring operations and routinely develop partnerships and knowledge around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though more conceptual work is needed, given the importance of the region and clear Prime Ministerial intent, I envisage two or more adaptable brigades forming close tactical level relationships with particular countries in the Gulf and Jordan, for example, allowing for better cooperation with their forces.  Should the need arise for another Libya-style operation, we will be prepared.  This would greatly enhance our ability to support allies as they contain and deter threats and, with our naval presence in Bahrain, air elements in the UAE and Qatar, and traditional but potentially enhanced roles in Oman, Kuwait and Saudi Arabia, would make us a regional ally across the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Africa, brigades would be tasked to support key allies in the east, west and south whilst another might be given an Indian Ocean and SE Asian focus, allowing for much greater involvement in the FPDA, for example. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we are to influence, we must know what drives our friends and how to motivate them.  This is not something that can be done on the eve of an operation.  As these adaptable brigades develop links with countries around their region, this will create opportunities for soldiers and officers to progress their careers through linguistic and cultural specialism.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Defence Engagement Strategy, prepared with the Foreign Office, will provide what I have often referred to as a ‘strategic handrail’ for engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will require tough decisions.  If we are to invest properly in some relationships, others will naturally get less attention.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if we get this right ¬– and we will – we will have deeper links to specific regional partners giving them the confidence to deal with their own problems and, when appropriate, to act in partnership with us.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I have described puts military flesh on the bones of welcome, NSC endorsed, national strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all comes as we are increasing the Reserves and integrating them closer with the Regular forces.  This will do more to increase our own capacity and ability to help friends and allies.
The Royal Air Force&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turning now to the Royal Air Force.  The rate of technological advance is most keenly felt on air platforms.  This is understandable.  These are complex fully networked combat and ISTAR platforms.  This intelligence cuts the time between understanding and reacting.  It allows us better to out-think and out-act our opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, lift, both tactical and global, reduces the number of reserves we need to keep, giving the Armed Forces a flexibility that was unimaginable just a few decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding and exploiting the opportunities technology presents will be decisive in maintaining our advantage – in sufficient numbers – into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remotely piloted air systems and novel anti-air defences have changed our understanding of both what it means to fight and defend.  We must not allow sacred cows – such as the indispensability of on-board pilots – to rule the day.  The Chief of the Air Staff is leading the change.  By giving ‘wings’ to UAV pilots the Royal Air Force is recognising the capability of the platform and skill of the pilot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is a reflection of how early we are in this process of transition that we still refer to remotely-piloted air systems or unmanned aerial vehicles.  How long was it before we stopped referring to the horseless carriage?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all three Services, their role within an integrated CJEF will be the driving force in their force development and training.  Whoever the enemy, wherever the threat, we will need partners.  Building them now is an investment in our own future and our capacity to succeed quickly should war break out.
Cyber&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is a new environment within which we must learn to manoeuvre with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today Facebook, with around a billion users, is the third most populous country in the world.  It exemplifies one of the most extreme changes we have seen in the past decades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberspace is the nervous system of our global economy.  We are reliant on the internet and other networked systems for every aspect of our lives.  It allows bewildering speed of action and global reach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, just as crime has become e-crime, spying has increasingly become cyber espionage.  We have seen nations, their proxies and non-state actors use this new space for terrorism and conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though not conventional assaults, the hostile cyber attacks on Estonia in 2007, Georgia in 2008 and Burma in 2010 were damaging.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, there have been unprecedented levels of cyber attack over the past 24 months.  Israel has reported over 44 million attempts to disrupt its government websites during recent tension around the Gaza strip.  STUXNET demonstrated a new class of threat aimed at process control systems at the heart of modern infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without doubt, actions in cyberspace will form part of any future conflict.  Communication and the control of infrastructure and systems has become a new environment through which combatants will further their objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our immediate priority must be to ensure our networks are secure and defensible, working with partners in industry and around the country to drive up standards and ensure we have robust protocols in place.  This builds on the excellent work done under the National Cyber Security Strategy but Defence has particular challenges as a department, as Armed Forces and through the contractors and partners with whom we work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am determined that the Armed Forces should understand cyberspace, and how it will shape future conflict, as instinctively as we understand maritime, land and air operations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will mean changes in the way we operate: new doctrine; new capabilities; new structures, with Joint Forces Command at their heart.
It will mean a new approach to growing and developing the talent we need to operate in this new, electronic, environment.  Like our Secretary of State, I see an important role for reserves in this domain. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="winding-up"&gt;Winding Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In examining each environment separately I hope I have highlighted some of the key issues on the Chiefs’ plate and how we must respond to them.  But the most important is developing an integrated Joint model.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF is neither the 1980s Canadian model nor, whilst there are some apparent similarities, is it a British version of the US Marine Corps.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of the UK armed forces relies heavily on the different skill-sets and ethos of each single Service.  Each adapted for its environment, and evolving as times and technology change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But a joint conceptual approach, based on lessons from the real world, embedded through force development, in training, on operations and though the cohering glue of modern C3I and cyber is vital to delivering the military capability the nation requires.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is about ensuring single Service skills meld into joint action so that the whole is greater than the sum of the parts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JEF won’t mean we can do more with less; it will mean, through the synergy it provides, that we get the most from what we have.  And doubtless there will be some roles that we continue to leave to others, notably the USA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I close let me draw some lessons from my 41 years in uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some constants which may seem obvious in this room but are often over looked:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a.	The need for military force to influence, secure and protect is as great as ever.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;b.	I joined an Army that was geared to defend Britain by fighting in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;c.	Today life is more complex but the principle is the same.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;d.	9/11, and the 7/7 bombings in London show that we cannot choose our battlefields as we once did.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;e.	The world is not a safer place and the distinction between home and abroad is strategically obsolete.  Today it is part of a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We cannot just stand by and hope we are ignored and danger passes us by.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the Foreign Secretary said in September last year: “the country that is purely reactive in foreign affairs is in decline”. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responses may be based on either soft or hard power, but to divorce the two is strategic blindness.  Soft power is not a substitute for strength.  On the contrary, it is often based on the credible threat of force, either to support a friend or deter an enemy.  Hard power and soft power are intertwined.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is not enough to provide aid or speak kindly.  Our friends want to know we are there when it counts, not just fair-weather friends.  This is the confidence hard power brings.  It drives equipment sales and thus industrial growth, as well as diplomatic treaties, just as it has for centuries.  But hard power also does more than this: it dissuades.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deterrence doctrine has fallen out of fashion so perhaps you will allow me to recall some of the elements.  Sun Tzu’s famous maxim is: “Supreme excellence consists in breaking the enemy’s resistance without fighting”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Too often this is seen as clever posturing on the eve of battle.  It is not.  Training, equipping and partnering with allies enhance the aura of British power.  They give us presence on the world stage and ensure that we are not tested.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is worth being clear: when the Armed Forces train we do not just do it to be ready, we do it to be seen to be ready.  When we succeed on operations, we do not just win a battle.  We prove that we can win a war.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a very real sense, everything the Armed Forces do deters and reassures.  With enough numbers, enough equipment and with good leaders at every level, Britain is a credible threat to our enemies and a reassuring friend to our allies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is cheaper than fighting and more credible than talk.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading the record of how the Soviets saw the Falklands War demonstrates this admirably.  What many saw as post-colonial folie de grandeur, the Soviet leadership, rightly, saw as proof that the British Armed Forces were united with their government and people – Clausewitz’s famous trilogy – and more than a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was far from the only factor, but the increase in Soviet defence spending in the 1980s which ended up contributing to the collapse of the Warsaw Pact was partly due to clarity of their failure to impose their will in neighbouring, occupied countries while Britain could liberate territory some 8,000 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Chief of the Defence Staff I do not wear the burdens of office any more lightly than my predecessors.  I have set out some of my concerns for the coming years and some of the ways we will think and act to meet them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the Prime Minister’s chairmanship, The National Security Council, on which I am privileged to sit, considers all the big strategic issues that I have listed and more.  It is a hugely welcome addition to Whitehall, directing and bringing clarity to national strategy and coordinating cross-government action. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the nature of the world is such that what will later seem obvious, today is opaque and unpredictable.  How will Europe emerge from the Euro crisis?  How will the Arab Spring conclude?  How will global warming affect water supplies?  And what of cyber?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After all, grand strategy, while providing a guide to action in peacetime, is also about being prepared and balanced for what we can never know.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ensuring we have enough left in the bag while actively deterring, and when required defeating, aggression against us and our friends, enough left to succeed against those ‘unknown unknowns’, is ultimately what I and my fellow Chiefs are paid for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;END&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56641</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:36:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-more-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet more Millies heroes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-1---operation-olympics"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 1 - Operation Olympics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympians Victoria Pendleton and Greg Rutherford presented the first of two Judges’ Special Recognition Awards to the Armed Forces for their contribution to the London 2012 Olympics. At its height, more than 17,500 personnel stepped in when G4S were not able to provide sufficient guards for all the venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victoria said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone I’ve met has been incredible; individuals who’ve achieved so much. I feel in awe because all I did was ride round in circles on a wooden track with a bike with no brakes and one gear and this is real life. I can’t not be moved and it makes me feel very proud to be British.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear the military personnel treasured their experiences. Senior Aircraftwoman Afyah Bubb, an RAF medic who volunteered to be part of the security team at the Olympic Park, saw it as a ‘once-in-a-lifetime opportunity’. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were there to do a job but I unexpectedly got the chance to see Ellie Simmonds break some swimming records which was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Brian Fahy added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were really proud to be part of the Games this summer and see the superb performance of our athletes. Who wouldn’t want to be part of the greatest show in town?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic long jump gold medallist Greg Rutherford said backstage: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m hugely proud of the Armed Forces; the whole evening has been a massive highlight and getting involved feels out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5637/award_for_headley_court.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team with their Special Recognition Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a light-hearted moment, Greg joked that he hadn’t packed enough tissues. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I get emotional so easily and seeing videos of these incredible people moves me to tears every time. It’s completely surreal to be here; I’ve got friends in the Armed Forces including my best friend who is now going through training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to be invited to such a prestigious night, and to show our respect and thanks to these guys is an honour. The troops came in with happy smiley faces and gave high fives and absolutely saved the day! A huge thank you, you were absolutely spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-2---complex-trauma-team-headley-court"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 2 - Complex Trauma Team, Headley Court&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second Judges’ Special Recognition Award honoured the Complex Trauma Team at the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/Militarymedicine/Pages/HeadleyCourt.aspx" title="Headley Court"&gt;Headley Court&lt;/a&gt;. It is the remarkable skill and dedication of the 110-strong Trauma Team that help many critically wounded soldiers overcome life-changing injuries so they can get back to leading active lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex trauma manager Anne Brannagan received the award on behalf of Headley Court from actor Kevin Spacey who congratulated and shook hands with each of the 10 team members on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Clare Walton, Commanding Officer at Headley Court, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kevin Spacey was just very complimentary, it was great, and to have someone of his level of superstardom even know who we are is lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony tonight (14 December) on ITV1 at 2100hrs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56556</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:22:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:22:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dr-liam-fox-responds-to-defence-committee-report-on-sdsr"/>
    <title>Dr Liam Fox responds to Defence Committee report on SDSR</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since January, the House of Commons Defence Committee (HCDC) has been reviewing the SDSR and the NSS. It has taken oral evidence from sources including the Defence Secretary, the Armed Forces Minister, the Single Service Chiefs, the Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, the Chief of Defence Materiel, the Deputy Chief of Defence Staff (Personnel), and Lord Stirrup (Chief of the Defence Staff when the SDSR was published). The Department has also provided extensive written evidence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HCDC says the report seeks to establish whether the new National Security Council has led to a more coherent and well-defined security policy in terms of the NSS and the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its report, the HCDC agrees with the logic underpinning the SDSR, including the prioritisation of operational requirements for Afghanistan, the adaptable posture, the validity of Future Force 2020, and the strategic priority and national security imperative of dealing with the budget deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the HCDC also says that it is not convinced that, given the current financial climate and the drawdown of capabilities arising from the SDSR, UK Armed Forces will be able do what is asked of them after 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chair of the Committee, the Right Honourable James Arbuthnot MP, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government appears to believe that the UK can maintain its influence while reducing spending in Defence and at the Foreign Office. We do not agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5603/Liam_Fox_responds_to_Defence_Committee_report_on_SDSR_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Dave Hillhouse, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report also expresses concerns over the realisation of what is called ‘Future Force 2020’ - the Government’s intended shape of the Armed Forces from 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Arbuthnot said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Decisions for post-2015 funding will have to be made in the very near future to ensure progress towards Future Force 2020. If the ambition of a real-terms funding increase is not realised, we will have failed our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Defence Review had not been conducted for 12 years, resulting in an equipment programme that was woefully unaffordable. A multi-billion pound deficit was plaguing Defence, and tough, but necessary, decisions had to be taken. As the Committee rightly acknowledges, dealing with the deficit was a national security imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Committee is also right to say that Future Force 2020 is only achievable with extra funding. That is why I announced two weeks ago that the military equipment budget will rise in real terms by over £3bn between 2015 and 2020, with new helicopters being ordered, new money for our armoured vehicles, the carrier programme, and guaranteed spending on the Joint Strike Fighter. Our future equipment programme is no longer an unfunded aspiration, but one that provides real money for real equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We continue to have the fourth largest military budget in the world and the SDSR has put Defence back on a stable footing with highly capable Armed Forces and certainty for our personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pushing through radical reforms to ensure that the mistakes of the past are not repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we have seen in the US, no country is immune to the global financial problems, and even the world’s biggest military power is now grappling with how to make defence cuts and reform for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Sir David Richards, Chief of the Defence Staff, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SDSR was based on an assessment of the threats we face now and in the future. We have had to take some tough decisions, but as we move towards Future Force 2020 we will remain a formidable fighting force on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will remain capable of sustaining our operations in Afghanistan and Libya before rebalancing will give us the flexibility to maintain our ability to project power across our spheres of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are continually working with our international allies to share operational requirements, including utilising basing and overflight rights for Libya - measures we rightly assessed in the SDSR could be relied upon to mitigate capability gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD will respond formally to the Defence Committee regarding today’s report in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56545</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:55:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:55:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-outlines-reform-of-the-ministry-of-defence"/>
    <title>Liam Fox outlines reform of the Ministry of Defence</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to an audience at the Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors in Westminster, Dr Fox announced that he is launching a full review of how the Ministry of Defence is run and how the Armed Forces can be reformed to ‘produce more efficient provision of defence capability, and generation and sustainment of operations’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech Dr Fox began by describing the background to the changes, highlighting the fact that the country faces a legacy of debt - the interest on which for the next year alone will exceed the budget of the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that it was a ‘disgrace’ that there had not been a Defence Review for 12 years, despite our Armed Forces being committed to conflicts in the Balkans, Sierra Leone, Iraq and Afghanistan and with enormous changes in the global security picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR) will not simply be a random selection of cuts but an objective process by which the shape of the Armed Forces required will be reached by the end of the decade. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The National Security Council has agreed that the overarching strategic posture should be to address the most immediate threats to our national security while maintaining the ability to identify and deal with emerging ones before they become bigger threats to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This flexible, adaptable posture will maintain the ability to safeguard international peace and security, to deter and contain those who threaten the UK and its interests, and where necessary to intervene on multiple fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will also, crucially, keep our options open for a future in which we can expect our highest priorities to change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said we need to ‘invest in programmes that we will require to put our defence on a sound footing for the years ahead and divest ourselves of the capabilities which we are unlikely to need in a world where the moral climate demands precision weaponry and where the battlespace increasingly embraces the unmanned and cyber domains’, adding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are contrasting cost-savings and the capability implications with the risks that we face in the real global security environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This requires assessing any proposed change in a current programme or platform against a series of criteria, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, the cost-saving in years zero to five, five to ten, and beyond ten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Second, the capability implications - what capability will be lost as a result of this decision and what other assets do we possess that might give us the same or a similar capability?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Third, the operational implications - what operations that we currently carry out, or are likely to carry out, will we be unable to undertake as a result of this change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fourth, the ability to regenerate the capability, at what cost and in what timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And fifth, the risk in the real world that this capability currently protects us from or is likely to protect us from in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In alliance with the SDSR Dr Fox said that the Ministry of Defence itself was in need of reform and to this end he announced that a Defence Reform Unit would be established to carry out the required changes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this he said there are two broad principles that would be followed. The first is a structural reform which will see the Department reorganised into the three pillars of Policy and Strategy, the Armed Forces, and Procurement and Estates. The second is a cultural shift which will see a leaner and less centralised organisation combined with devolved processors which carry greater accountability and transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that a logical management structure would be ‘foreign policy leading to a defence strategy, then portfolio management which identified capability gaps, followed by specific programme identification and finally physical procurement’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new three pillar structure is designed to make this easier and to stop the constant over-specification and then re-specification of programmes which has led to cost overruns and programme delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work will be led by the Defence Reform Unit. Dr Fox described this as ‘a heavy-hitting steering group of internal and external experts [who] will guide the hard thinking and challenge preconceptions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene will chair this group and will be supported from outside the MOD by Baroness Sheila Noakes, George Iacobescu, Dr David Allen, Björn Conway and Raymond McKeeve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, it will be supported by a civil service implementation team with a remit to complete their blueprint for reform by September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also announced that there will be a review of how the Armed Forces undertake the tasks of force generation and sustainability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to challenge some of the fundamental assumptions which drive force generation, such as tour lengths and intervals, taking into account the varying pressures on our personnel resulting from widely varying missions to see if we can update our practices and produce greater efficiency while implementing the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State said he will be asking the First Sea Lord, Admiral Sir Mark Stanhope, the Chief of the Air Staff, Air Chief Marshal Sir Stephen Dalton, and the new Chief of the General Staff, General Sir Peter Wall, to begin this review once the SDSR has been completed, with a view to completing their work by the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Defence Reform Unit will work with the Chief of the Defence Staff and the Service Chiefs to find ways of giving greater devolution for the running of the Services themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Department must get away from the over-centralising tendency that has become the hallmark of the MOD in recent years and said they will also consider whether the current senior rank structure across the Services is appropriate for the post-SDSR world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We cannot demand efficiency from the lower ranks while exempting those at the top,” Dr Fox said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded by saying that taken together the SDSR and these changes represent a radical agenda for change and show how the Government is committed to governing not in their own interest, but in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16671</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-defence-secretary-on-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>The Defence Secretary on delivering value for money and innovation in Defence</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking yesterday, Mr Hammond used his speech to talk about how, over the last two-and-a-half years, the Department has set about reforming the way Defence is managed in order to deliver improved efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began by recapping the scale of the reform challenge faced by Defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will rematerialise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two-and-a-half years of the transformation project, the Defence Secretary said we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture so that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said that while Defence needed a solid financial foundation, it was the people that really mattered and made the difference, and therefore an attractive employment package to attract and keep the best was needed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them. And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis. So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life. So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that a new employment model was needed and this would need to be flexible to meet the varying and individual needs of Service personnel: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term and attractive to Service personnel and fair to the taxpayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall, designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that this ‘New Employment Model’, or NEM, isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges, and it is not about overnight transformation but will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer: towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And more stability to Service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners, and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On housing, Mr Hammond said that, in a 22-year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want this to change. As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, the Defence Secretary said we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation. Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence Budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability. That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task, but neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
