<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing versatile, agile and battle-winning armed forces and a smaller, more professional Ministry of Defence "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55714</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T23:07:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T23:07:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/adaptability-crucial-component-of-future-infantry-equipment"/>
    <title>Adaptability 'crucial component' of future infantry equipment</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a speech to the Modern Infantry Conference and Exhibition at Bisley in Surrey, Mr Luff said the quest for the right mix of mobility, protection and firepower will continue to drive infantry equipment acquisition. But added that there will also be differences as the Armed Forces are taken to the next level of fighting effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said there would be a new structure for the Army, new equipment, and a better way of acquiring and supporting that equipment, but that the crucial component would be adaptability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In this volatile world, everyone in Defence - including the infantry - will need to be adaptable as the character of war continues to evolve,” Mr Luff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that the economic environment and previous problems with acquisition had posed problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you want to equip and support them to a first-class standard - which it’s my job to do - then you need a force structure that’s fit for the 21st century, and a defence programme which is affordable and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That’s precisely what the Strategic Defence and Security Review [SDSR] has started to do,” said Mr Luff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For the Army, the vision is a force structure equipped to operate successfully across the range of possible conflicts we are likely to face in the coming decades.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Luff confirmed that by 2020 it is envisaged that the country would have a total trained Army of 112,000, of which roughly 70 per cent will be Regular and 30 per cent Reserves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That will require a reduction in regular manpower, and a potential increase of up to 10,000 trained reservists. Neither the reduction nor the growth is risk or challenge-free. But achieving this is essential if the Army is to adapt to life in a volatile world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A British soldier with a new, up-armoured Warrior infantry fighting vehicle in Afghanistan " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5270/Adaptability__crucial_component__of_future_infantry_equipment2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A British soldier with a new, up-armoured Warrior infantry fighting vehicle in Afghanistan [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister said that the Army, including the infantry, will almost certainly need to engage more broadly overseas in conflict prevention, and be able to assist in relief operations and support the authorities here at home; and the Army’s equipment programme necessarily needs to remain fluid until the future Army structure is agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the Army had often suffered from more ‘salami-slicing’ compared to the other Services due to Army programmes typically spending less time in development, and units are measured in the hundreds or even thousands rather than the longer term small unit programmes of the Navy and Air Force:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is compounded because manpower levels - rather than warship numbers and fast jet fleets - are seen to be the measure of relative Army success or failure in any cuts to Defence,” said Mr Luff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that, although the campaign is far from over, the MOD has also to begin managing the legacy of Afghanistan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For example, as we plan for the drawdown of combat operations, we are considering which Urgent Operational Requirement [UOR] vehicles should be brought into the MOD’s core equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UOR acquisitions have made a vital contribution to the success of Operation HERRICK, and they have typically been brought into service on or before schedule. But now the incoherence - in fact, downside - of UORs becomes clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They were procured for ‘the War’, not ‘a war’. Hard-headed realism will be required as the Army considers how to marry its future core vehicle requirement against the fleets of vehicles already in service. And we must remember that the best must not be the enemy of the good. These are battle-proven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Defence Reform, Mr Luff said that the Service Chiefs now have the power to deliver and will be held rigorously to account for doing so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to the infantry specifically, the Minister conceded that there is a school of thought which believes that the infantry have been relegated to second-class citizens as governments prefer to use Special Forces, but added that he did not believe that’s true:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We all recognise and value the increased role of Special Forces, but they have a specific role which relies on secrecy, stealth and surgical insertion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A counter-insurgency strategy, on the other hand, requires boots on the ground: visible to the local community and engaging with them; visible to the enemy and destroying them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that he recognises that the Army has not been well served over the last couple of decades, but, today, the view that’s reported back to him from Afghanistan is that the British infantryman has never been so well equipped, supported, and protected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That’s a message we need to take proudly to the British people. I don’t rest on these laurels and there are still plenty of enhancements to come. But the point is that the issues of real and serious concern have been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On top of this, new equipment arriving in theatre will have adaptability at its very core. And core capability is precisely what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the examples of Foxhound and the updated Warrior fighting vehicle, Mr Luff said these were the future, now, and showed a capability that is ‘adaptability-heavy’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe we can look at the infantry of today and the infantry of the future with greater confidence than has been the case for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded by saying that Future Force 2020 is the ultimate goal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Getting there will be difficult - at times painful - yet there is no alternative. But the SDSR provides our vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55636</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T19:07:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T19:07:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/last-chance-to-comment-on-coalition-governments-programme"/>
    <title>Last chance to comment on Coalition Government's programme</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Departments will use comments for policy development and the Government will also respond in coming weeks to the most popular areas of feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding Defence, the programme says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes that we need to take action to safeguard our national security at home and abroad. We also recognise that we need to do much more to ensure that our Armed Forces have the support they need, and that veterans and their families are treated with the dignity that they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will maintain Britain’s nuclear deterrent, and have agreed that the renewal of Trident should be scrutinised to ensure value for money. Liberal Democrats will continue to make the case for alternatives. We will immediately play a strong role in the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty Review Conference, and press for continued progress on multilateral disarmament. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will aim to reduce Ministry of Defence running costs by at least 25 per cent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will work to rebuild the Military Covenant by: ensuring that Service personnel’s rest and recuperation leave can be maximised; changing the rules so that Service personnel only have to register once on the Service register; exploring the potential for including Service children as part of our proposals for a pupil premium; providing university and further education scholarships for the children of servicemen and women who have been killed on active duty since 1990; providing support for ex-Service personnel to study at university; creating a new programme, ‘Troops for Teachers’, to recruit ex-Service personnel into the teaching profession; providing extra support for veteran mental health needs; and reviewing the rules governing the awarding of medals. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will double the Operational Allowance for Armed Forces personnel serving in Afghanistan, and include Armed Forces pay in our plans for a fair pay review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will ensure that injured personnel are treated in dedicated military wards. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will look at whether there is scope to refurbish Armed Forces’ accommodation from efficiencies within the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will support defence jobs through exports that are used for legitimate purposes, not internal repression, and will work for a full international ban on cluster munitions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55589</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:32:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:32:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rafs-largest-ever-aircraft-arrives-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>RAF's largest ever aircraft arrives in the UK</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a 60m wingspan, and measuring nearly 60m from nose to tail, Voyager, a dual role air-to-air tanker and transport aircraft based around the Airbus A330 airframe, will replace the long-serving VC-10 and Tristar fleet; with the first due in service by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new aircraft will bring a considerable capability boost, each able to carry 291 troops over 6,000 miles, and to refuel other aircraft, in flight, from a 100,000 litre reservoir - greater than that of two large petrol tankers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MOD pictures show the aircraft at the MOD’s airfield at Boscombe Down in Wiltshire, which will play host to two of the Voyager aircraft during an intensive programme of testing and trials, set to continue into 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the ground and in the air, the aircraft will be tested in the refuelling role, with Tornado, Sentry, Typhoon and Hercules aircraft. Voyager can refuel aircraft at a rate of 5,000 litres per minute; a standard garage forecourt petrol pump delivers fuel at around 40 litres per minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourteen Voyager aircraft and a complete support package are being provided to the RAF under a 27 year £10.5bn Private Finance Initiative contract signed with the AirTanker consortium in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the aircraft, the package will provide training and maintenance, and new purpose-built buildings at RAF Brize Norton, the RAF’s air transport hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Peter Luff, commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The arrival of the first Voyager aircraft in the UK marks an important milestone in the process that will see the Royal Air Force equipped with the best available air-to-air refuelling capability, with the first due in service by the end of the year. “Recent events in Libya and the ongoing requirement for air-to-air refuelling over Afghanistan, clearly demonstrate the essential role that air-to-air refuelling plays in getting our aircraft to where they are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Officer Commanding 2 Group, responsible for combat support, Air Vice Marshal Phil Osborn, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we have seen over the last few weeks, an effective tanker and transport force is an essential ingredient to this era of expeditionary warfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the next few years Voyager will join the versatile A400M transport, C-17 strategic airlifter, and well-proven Hercules transport aircraft to form an RAF fleet that can handle any task that comes its way in the future. I look forward to a successful trials programme that will keep the aircraft on track for delivery at the earliest opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55497</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T18:01:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T18:01:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-typhoon-project-under-control-and-back-on-track"/>
    <title>RAF Typhoon project 'under control and back on track'</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PAC report, published today, claims that problems with the supply of spare parts for the aircraft has led to problems with aircraft availability and pilot training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PAC publication follows a National Audit Office (NAO) report into the same topic last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The NAO’s March report concluded that after years of financial mismanagement and project delays under the previous government, the Typhoon project has been turned around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The project is finally under control and back on track. The PAC Report recognises that the MOD and industry have worked to resolve spares issues and performance targets are now being met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Typhoon is a world-class multi-role weapon system that meets the Defence challenges of the 21st Century. This highly versatile aircraft is operating in the air defence and ground attack roles as part of NATO’s ongoing operation to enforce UNSCR 1973 in Libya, and has destroyed military targets that threatened the civilian population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Typhoon is a world beating air to air fighter and is fast developing a ground attack capability as is being demonstrated in Libya. We have sufficient numbers of qualified ground attack pilots to meet our operational tasks and this number is increasing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the PAC acknowledges, the UK’s operational requirements have changed dramatically since the Typhoon programme began and this has led to tough decisions throughout its life but today it has ‘done well [and] collaboration offers significant potential benefits from sharing costs and developing common capabilities with allies’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am determined that in the future such projects are properly run from the outset, and I have announced reforms to reduce equipment delays and cost overruns. I will also chair regular Major Projects Review Boards to ensure our Armed Forces are well equipped and tax-payers get value for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Still captured from targetting pod footage of a successful RAF Typhoon strike on Libyan main battle tanks" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5115/RAF_Typhoon_project__under_control_and_back_on_track__2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Still captured from targetting pod footage of a successful RAF Typhoon strike on Libyan main battle tanks [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Air Vice Marshal Phil Osborn, Air Officer Commanding 2 Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have sufficient Typhoon aircraft and pilots to undertake the task in Libya with the appropriate training for the systems and weapons carried by the aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We wouldn’t deploy a capability if we couldn’t support it and we weren’t able to execute it in the way that you would expect the RAF to execute it, which is in a proportionate, disciplined, reliable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16671</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-defence-secretary-on-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>The Defence Secretary on delivering value for money and innovation in Defence</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking yesterday, Mr Hammond used his speech to talk about how, over the last two-and-a-half years, the Department has set about reforming the way Defence is managed in order to deliver improved efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began by recapping the scale of the reform challenge faced by Defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will rematerialise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two-and-a-half years of the transformation project, the Defence Secretary said we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture so that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said that while Defence needed a solid financial foundation, it was the people that really mattered and made the difference, and therefore an attractive employment package to attract and keep the best was needed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them. And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis. So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life. So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that a new employment model was needed and this would need to be flexible to meet the varying and individual needs of Service personnel: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term and attractive to Service personnel and fair to the taxpayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall, designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that this ‘New Employment Model’, or NEM, isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges, and it is not about overnight transformation but will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer: towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And more stability to Service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners, and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On housing, Mr Hammond said that, in a 22-year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want this to change. As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, the Defence Secretary said we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation. Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence Budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability. That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task, but neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48933</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:18:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/mod-annual-report-and-accounts-2011-12"/>
    <title>MOD Annual Report and Accounts 2011-12</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Defence Annual Report and Accounts 2011-12 and Sustainability Report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56151</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:20:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/armed-forces-covenant-annual-report-2012"/>
    <title>Armed Forces Covenant Annual Report 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first annual report is the beginning of a process to identify issues and make sure they are addressed. The report highlights progress across all 15 themes of the Covenant and identifies work still to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report covers the following groups: serving personnel; reservists; the wounded, injured and sick; families; the bereaved; service leavers; and veterans. It sets out a number of important achievements and also highlights remaining challenges and makes a series of new commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three leaflets explaining what the Covenant means for Serving personnel, Veterans and Service families&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/34810</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/150-2012-mod-announces-new-46m-contract-for-foxhound-vehicles"/>
    <title>150/2012 -  MOD Announces new £46m contract for Foxhound vehicles</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Minister Philip Dunne MP made the announcement during a visit to General Dynamics: Force Protection’s spares facility in Telford which provides spares for the Foxhound vehicle. The contract announced today is part of an overall investment of £340 million that the MoD has made in Foxhound since 2010. This is helping to sustain jobs at the Telford facility, the General Dynamics: Force Protection (GDLS:FPE) HQ in Leamington Spa and across the UK in the Foxhound supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed and built by GDL:FPE in Britain, Foxhound is one of the Army’s most agile protected vehicle. It uses leading-edge Formula 1 technology to provide unparalleled protection for its weight and class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Foxhounds were deployed to Afghanistan in June 2012 and are now being used by soldiers operating in mentoring and partnering roles with the Afghan National Security Forces. During the visit to the spares facility, Mr Dunne and Major Chris Thoms, the requirements manager for Protected Mobility at the MoD, met with staff who are also providing vital logistical support to the Army in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet with employees at General Dynamics: Force Protection who have helped make Foxhound a real procurement success story, taking only 40 months to develop it from the initial design to deployment in Afghanistan. The work being done by staff here in Telford is ensuring the vehicles can stay on the road and helping our soldiers do the vital job of engaging with Afghan forces and protecting the local population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Balancing the MoD’s budget means we can now confidently invest in equipment like Foxhound, which has the flexibility and adaptability to operate in a wide variety of environments, providing capability for the Army well into the future. This investment shows the MoD playing its part in delivering growth and sustaining jobs in the West Midlands industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in September when Foxhound was first operational in Afghanistan, Chief of Staff for the Bastion Force Protection Wing, Squadron Leader Jim Stewart, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Foxhound is an enormous leap forward in capability; the off-road mobility, enhanced protection and night-vision systems that it offers to the troops on the ground are unmatched in a vehicle of this size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 51 extra Foxhounds announced today are the latest to be ordered from GDLS:FPE as part of the £340 million investment that will provide the Army with a total fleet of 376 vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about Foxhound, contact Beth Cowley at the MoD Press Office on 0207 218 7714. Questions relating to General Dynamics: Force Protection should be directed to Julian Forsyth on 07850 915 164.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
