<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing versatile, agile and battle-winning armed forces and a smaller, more professional Ministry of Defence "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65619</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T14:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T15:05:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-typhoon-aircraft-exercise-in-uae"/>
    <title>RAF Typhoon aircraft exercise in UAE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Typhoon aircraft of 6 Squadron have been exercising with a multinational contingent at Al Dhafra Air Base in the United Arab Emirates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has been the first time that aircraft, engineers and pilots from the squadron, normally based at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars, have deployed together on the Advanced Tactical Leadership Course (&lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;), which runs each year at Al Dhafra Air Base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Mike Baulkwill, Officer Commanding  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/6squadron.cfm" title="6 Squadron RAF web page"&gt;6 Squadron&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been sent out here to conduct this multinational exercise that looks at large scale air operations involving many aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been run over a number of weeks, giving the pilots, ground crew and support staff an opportunity to work alongside other nations. The squadron have been running air interdiction missions, self-escort missions and offensive and defensive counter air missions as part of the exercise. This has required the pilots and aircraft to be quick and reactive in a multi-role platform in all types of operational scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been conducted in 2 parts - one wave of flying per day in support of the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt; missions and one following wave each day where the pilots can fly alongside multinational aircraft to conduct further training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Baulkwill added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen the ground crew and pilots from 6 Squadron lead and operate in a very different environment. Everybody at every rank is learning something from this exercise. We are learning to operate fully combat capable aircraft in a hot and dry environment which is very different to conditions at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senior Aircraftman Sam Norry, an Aircraft Maintenance Mechanic on 6 Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my first detachment and it has been much harder work out here. There are a lot more elements to contend with - temperatures alone are incredible, you have to drink a lot more water. Not only that, on the engineering side of things, you don’t have that instant support that you have in the UK - there are fewer people to work on the aircraft so you really have to work together and work hard to get the jobs done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An RAF Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6026/AUAB_UNC_20121210_239_026.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;To summarise the squadron’s support to the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Wing Commander Baulkwill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been operating huge missions with other nations, sometimes operating an air picture involving 60 aircraft with simulated high threat missions. It has been incredibly hard work for all of the pilots and the ground crew to support this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have found ourselves pushed hard, and the  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon FGR4 web page"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; aircraft has performed exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The systems that it has on board are second-to-none and we have seen the benefit of that - it has been impressive to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65593</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T10:38:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-pistols-for-uk-armed-forces"/>
    <title>New pistols for UK Armed Forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Armed Forces are to be supplied with more than 25,000 new Glock sidearms to replace the ageing Browning pistols currently in service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://us.glock.com/products/model/g17gen4" title="Glock 17 Gen4 pistol web page"&gt;Glock 17 Gen4 pistol&lt;/a&gt; is not only much lighter than the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/forceprotection/browning9mmpistol.cfm" title="Browning 9mm pistol web page"&gt;Browning L9A1&lt;/a&gt;, it is also more accurate and its magazines can carry more bullets. It has an increased magazine capacity of 17 rounds, compared to 13 rounds for the Browning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel across all 3 Services will begin to receive the new 9-millimetre (mm) calibre Glock 17s in the coming weeks and troops deployed to Afghanistan will be among the first to use the new weapon. The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.vikingarms.com/" title="Viking Arms Ltd website"&gt;Viking Arms &lt;abbr title="Limited"&gt;Ltd&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Harrogate, Yorkshire, also includes more than 25,000 holsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Glock 17 pistol (left) and a Browning 9mm pistol" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6012/ArmyHQ-2013-003-052_aGlock_17_pistol_EMBARG_00.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Glock 17 pistol (left) and the Browning the new pistols will replace [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Mark Anderson, Royal Marines, who trialled the new weapon before the contract was awarded, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pistols are vital in close combat and are a key part of a soldier’s armoury. Reliable, light and easy to carry, the Glock inspires confidence and performs exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide our troops with the best possible personal kit available and these new Glock 17s will give them greater firepower and accuracy on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Glock pistol is fired on a range" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6013/Emb_DES-2013-003-0250.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines firearms instructor Sergeant Steve Lord demonstrates the new Glock pistol on the range at Woolwich Barracks in London [Picture: Andrew Linnett, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sidearms are a valuable weapon for servicemen and women on the battlefield, and the new Glock, manufactured in Austria, will complement the wide range of weapons already available to our forces, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA80A2 assault rifles, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light machine guns, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharpshooter rifles, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;general purpose machine guns, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;combat shotguns, which fire 12-gauge cartridges; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sniper systems, which fire 8.59mm rounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Glock pistols will replace the Browning which after being used by the Armed Forces for more than 40 years has become increasingly expensive to maintain. The contract for a replacement pistol was put out to tender 2 years ago and is not in response to any specific or increased threat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65573</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:13:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/marines-train-to-tackle-pirates"/>
    <title>Marines train to tackle pirates </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Marines based on the deployed warship HMS Monmouth have been practising their ship-boarding skills to combat pirates and smugglers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the ship’s company of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; is a detachment of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="The Royal Marines website"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt;, vital for &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s tasking at sea. One of the major roles of the Marines is conducting boarding missions against suspected pirates and smugglers. To hone these skills they used their time on land to visit a specialist ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ facility owned by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5912/20130109commandos02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ recreates a realistic section of a ship in which ‘room clearance’ drills may be practised and perfected with a dramatic sense of realism. High-powered Airsoft simulation weapons are used in the facility, which range from rifles, shotguns and pistols to claymore mines. They really pack a punch, so much so that personal protective equipment must be worn when magazines are fitted and rounds are flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team of Royal Marines are on detachment from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/43-Cdo-Fleet-Protection-Group" title="43 Commando Fleet Protection Group Royal Marines website"&gt;43 Commando Fleet Protection Group&lt;/a&gt;, based at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Clyde" title="Her Majesty's Naval Base Clyde website"&gt;HM Naval Base Clyde&lt;/a&gt;, Faslane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5914/20130109commandos04.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Will Hall, Officer Commanding &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s Royal Marines detachment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My Marines really benefited from the training provided by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard at their facility in Bahrain - the instructors were incredibly hospitable and approachable, whilst the use of Airsoft weapons added a level of realism to the scenarios that is difficult to achieve in the training environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The team are now looking forward to putting their skills to use during boarding operations in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5913/20130109commandos01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Marines’ exercise comes after a busy time at sea over Christmas and has given the rest of the ship’s company time to recharge their batteries in preparation for the challenges of the New Year in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth continues her 7-month deployment of the region, conducting maritime security patrols the Arabian Sea, the northern Indian Ocean and the Gulf of Aden. Whilst deployed, Monmouth will also be carrying out security patrols and exercises with coalition forces in the region to strengthen ties with foreign allies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61168</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:09:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-invites-tenders-for-uk-construction-projects"/>
    <title>MOD invites tenders for UK construction projects</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Ten private sector companies have been invited to tender for a new framework agreement to deliver construction projects across the UK Defence estate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The companies shortlisted for the framework by the Defence Infrastructure Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;) are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.balfourbeatty.com/" title="Balfour Beatty website"&gt;Balfour Beatty Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bam.co.uk/Construction/Construction-Overview.aspx" title="BAM Construction website"&gt;BAM Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.carillionplc.com/our-capabilities/construction-services.aspx" title="Carillion Construction website"&gt;Carillion Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.interserve.com/" title="Interserve website"&gt;Interserve Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kier.co.uk/" title="Kier Group website"&gt;Kier Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lendlease.com/worldwide/capabilities/project-management-and-construction.aspx" title="Lend Lease Construction website"&gt;Lend Lease Construction (EMEA) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millerconstruction.co.uk/" title="Miller Construction website"&gt;Miller Construction (UK) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://construction.morgansindall.com/" title="Morgan Sindall Construction website"&gt;Morgan Sindall plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.skanska.co.uk/" title="Skanska website"&gt;Skanska UK plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wates.co.uk/" title="Wates website"&gt;Wates Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Capital Works Framework will be used for the design and build of construction projects up to a value of £50 million. It will include up to 5 companies who will participate in ‘mini-competitions’ for individual projects. It is due to be awarded before the end of 2013 and will run for an initial 4-year period, with the potential to extend for up to 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework forms part of the &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; Next Generation Estate Contracts (&lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme, and will operate alongside 6 regional capital works frameworks for projects valued below £12 million. It has an estimated value of between £250 million and £400 million over the 4-year period and could be used at any site across the UK estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, the shortlisted companies attended a bidders’ conference at the Defence Academy in Shrivenham focused on the tendering process and on the proposed operating model for the framework. Delegates were also taken step-by-step through a typical Defence construction project, looking at the processes involved, legislative influences, sustainability and other requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tender will be rigorously evaluated based on the company’s approach to commercial and technical matters such as supply chain management, quality assurance, sustainable development, health and safety, and issues relating to the Government Construction Strategy. The tenderers have also been provided with a demonstration construction project and will be evaluated on their proposed approach to its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Rice, Head of the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changes to UK military basing arrangements are expected to generate requirements for new capital works in the years ahead, and it is vital these are met flexibly and cost-effectively, enabling us to provide a Defence estate which meets military needs and supports our Armed Forces. Early in the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme our research determined that framework arrangements were the best mechanism to achieve this, and I am delighted that we have such a strong field of companies in the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Wooden, &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks project manager, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This national framework is designed to deliver a range of potential major construction projects to support the Defence front line. We are determined to ensure firstly that all companies involved in the tendering process have a full and robust understanding of the potential demand, and secondly that we use the evaluation process to identify the best providers to meet that demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks are designed to support the Government Construction Strategy by reducing costs, improving value for money, and incorporating measures such as the ‘&lt;abbr title="New Engineering Contract 3"&gt;NEC3&lt;/abbr&gt;’ form of procurement, more focused performance management, and continuous improvement mechanisms. For all projects contractors will be required to use systems that meet UK Government requirements for Building Information Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework contractors will also be required to observe fair payment practices and - where decided appropriate on a project-by-project basis - project bank accounts will be set up to ensure prompt payment for all supply chain companies involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tenders are due to be returned by mid-February 2013 and it is expected that the National Capital Works Framework agreements will be awarded before the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61178</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T15:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:09:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/keeping-the-uk-military-on-the-map"/>
    <title>Keeping the UK military on the map</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The experts at the Defence Geographic Centre near London are keeping UK Armed Forces worldwide on the right track.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Australian scientists went to have a look at Sandy Island in the South Pacific recently, they discovered that, despite having featured on maps and on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en_uk/earth/index.html" title="Google Earth UK homepage"&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; for years, it doesn’t actually exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts working at the Defence Geographic Centre (&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;) may well have smiled wryly on hearing this. There is no room in their world for such errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; provides geographic information to Defence, predominantly to the Army and the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, but also to other government departments, and works in a world of international collaboration, sharing and co-producing geographical information where a reputation for accuracy matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s geographers, or geospatial analysts as they prefer to be called, know that, if you rely on a map which hasn’t been created from entirely dependable source data, the result can get you into trouble. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A large printer at the Defence Geographic Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5847/Replication.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Defence Geographic Centre has a full range of modern print and production equipment [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even the best maps are the result of compromise and estimate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unless you are on the ground looking at something, geographical information is always an approximation,” said Ian Spencer, Head of Geo Research. “We know how accurate our sources are, and the technical parameters of our sensors, so we know how accurate our products are. We have to work within a defined margin of error for each military product. If it’s outside that margin it’s considered unfit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; augments some of their products with open source material, such as Google Earth pictures, to provide pop-up images of features, but they do it knowing where the risks lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; produces more than just maps, whether on paper or on a screen. After all, a map is just one way of presenting geographical information, and it might not be the best solution for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you might need a database of geographic data to put in a weapons system, or a 3D simulation created from stereoscopic photographs to prepare yourself for the environment through which you may have to fly and control a missile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; specialises in making sense of a huge mass of data and presenting it to the customer in a way that is going to help them make sense of the world, spot relationships, and make informed plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We get 2 types of request,” said Operations Officer Major Jim Danks. “These are ad hoc for a single event or operation, such as disaster relief or support to the Arab Spring operations. And longer term planned work which can include Afghanistan tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5848/Workstation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery to produce simulations [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A request may start as a one-off and then develop into a long-term requirement. When Camp Bastion was established more than a decade ago it started as an ad hoc request. Now, as a home for thousands of troops, it is a standard request requiring the provision of many different types of data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for Lionel Fewson, Head of Collection, are 5 Collection Officers who could be described as the geographic equivalent of Indiana Jones. They scour the globe in search of useful, creditable data, visiting countries of interest gathering information and making new contacts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making maps from scratch is time consuming and very expensive, so international collaboration and data-sharing is very cost effective. Lionel said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have memorandums of understanding with 50 countries and links with many trusted commercial suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the digital side, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is part of a 29-nation programme to capture digital data from various places of interest around the world. In return for their contribution, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; has access to the entire output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of the benefit of co-operation is the award-winning work producing image-based mapping of compounds in Helmand province to improve battlefield and situational awareness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the US Marine Corps Intelligence Activity, the project has to date captured and referenced more than 200,000 compounds and produced more than 1,100 large-scale maps covering more than 11,000 square kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Defence Geographic Centre personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5849/Research.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Defence Geographic Centre personnel meet to identify sources for new products [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to future products, there is a revolution taking place, and the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is leading the way. The move is towards making more use of human geography in an ordered way. Ian Spencer said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to develop standards with our overseas partners to define database structures so that we can start capturing information like ethnicity demographics, economics, religion and water control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you go on the internet you will see lots of people doing things in different disciplines, but at the moment it isn’t connected. We want to pull all this information together in a systematic way so that decision makers and analysts have a better understanding of what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we have the basic geographic foundation we can overlay that with all kinds of human activities. Once data is organised then you can share it and exploit it, and when it has a spatial element you can model these factors and see what effect their interaction has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian believes that marrying physical and social sciences will open up a new world of understanding, as long as you take into account the assumptions and approximations that have been made. Asking how does factor A affect element B is OK as long as you keep an eye out for any more fictitious islands on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="this-report-by-ian-carr-appears-in-the-december-2012january-2013-issue-of-defence-focus---the-magazine-for-everyone-in-defence"&gt;This report by Ian Carr appears in the December 2012/January 2013 issue of Defence Focus - the magazine for everyone in Defence.&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61086</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/playful-pup-newest-recruit-to-irish-guards"/>
    <title>Playful pup newest recruit to Irish Guards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An Irish Wolfhound puppy called Domhnall is the new regimental mascot for the 1st Battalion Irish Guards.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To the untrained eye, he is just a rather large, playful puppy. But in a few months, Irish Wolfhound Domhnall will be leading the way as the new regimental mascot for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23990.aspx" title="The Irish Guards website"&gt;1st Battalion Irish Guards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based at Mons Barracks in Aldershot, Hampshire, the five-month-old is already training for the moment he dons a special silver collar and a scarlet tunic to join the guardsmen in their ceremonial role at occasions such as the Queen’s Birthday Parade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domhnall, whose name means ‘World Leader’ in Gaelic, came to the regiment from Northern Ireland untrained. He and handler Drummer David Steed are on a steep learning curve to make sure they look the part when Domhnall first fulfills the role of mascot at the regiment’s grand St Patrick’s Day parade in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5843/LAND-2012-212-IRISH_GDS_MASCOT_-087_copy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall, in festive spirit [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In just 2 months, ‘blank canvas’ Domhnall has already been housetrained and obedience-trained, Drummer Steed said, with his ceremonial training in London due to start in the near future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This will involve being with the regimental band, taking him out on Queen’s Guard mounts to get him used to the noises and the sights and sounds of London, as well as taking him to Knightsbridge for his horse-friendly training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because ceremonial duties are with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/28071.aspx" title="Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment website"&gt;Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment&lt;/a&gt;, it’s making sure that the horses aren’t startled by him and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drummer Steed admitted that training the hyperactive puppy - whose favourite occupation is chasing cyclists - is hard work for both of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But this kind of training the two of us are undergoing is something slightly different - it’s different from marching down the road carrying a rifle to suddenly having a four-legged friend by your side that you’ve got to control as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Benjamin Irwin-Clark, Adjutant of the 1st Battalion Irish Guards, said an Irish Wolfhound has been the regimental mascot for over a century:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quite early in our regiment’s history, in 1902, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iwcni.co.uk/" title="Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland website"&gt;Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; offered to provide an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot to the Irish Guards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regiment accepted, and, ever since then, I think with a few gaps, there has been an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5844/LAND-2012-212_Irish_Guards_Mascot_075.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mascots are traditionally named after Irish chieftains and have a ceremonial role in the regiment, parading with guardsmen during ceremonial duties and state occasions in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Irwin-Clark added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the moment we’re just putting him through a sort of inoculation of the bagpipes, among other things, and I think it’s going to take a little time for him to get comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60863</id>
    <published>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-forces-mark-christmas-in-helmand"/>
    <title>British Forces mark Christmas in Helmand </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British forces in southern Afghanistan mark Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;British forces serving in southern Afghanistan have been marking Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province today (25 December).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities took place as the troops completed a full day of operational duties.  Many soldiers from the UK-led Task Force Helmand spent the day on patrol in support of the Afghan security forces, yet still most found time to open presents and ring home – and enjoy a freshly-prepared Christmas lunch with all the trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-post"&gt;Christmas post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last-minute festive cheer was provided by the Post and Courier Squadron as tonnes of mail arrived at a number of forward locations, delivered by Chinook helicopter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing last minute festive cheer on Christmas morning, 78 sacks of post (1 tonne) arrived by helicopter in Main Operating Base (&lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) Lashkar Gah – home to the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; (‘Black Rats’) headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5819/Xmas_post_delivery_helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province, Afghanistan&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a chilly Christmas morning, in &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; over 100 soldiers and civilians took part in the ‘Lash Dash’ 5km run around the base.  Many completed the course in fancy dress, with proceeds from the event split between two charities: the Lashkar Gah Orphanage and The Black Rat Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the male and female winners were Danish soldiers. The Brits fared better in the fancy dress competition with Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant’s General Corps, Royal Military Police) winning by running dressed as a well-wrapped Christmas present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5818/LashDash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant General Corps, Royal Military Police) won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="working-day"&gt;Working day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, is another working day for all military here in Helmand. As the sun rose on Christmas morning, troops from the Royal Dragoon Guards and the Royal Military Police set off on patrol to the Provincial Police Headquarters to train Afghan Police. The ‘train the trainer’ course sees Afghan Police qualifying to teach police skills. This will allow British troops to step back as the Afghan Security Forces take the lead in training their own forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-lunches-and-all-the-trimmings"&gt;Christmas lunches and all the trimmings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full Christmas lunch, including all the trimmings, was served in the cookhouses of Camp Bastion, &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; Lashkar Gah and patrol bases across Helmand. Even the troops manning the security towers or sangars surrounding Camp Bastion were not forgotten and enjoyed personal deliveries of hot food.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5820/Xmas_dinner_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Baldwin kitchen manager from KBR in Camp Bastion said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is the full Christmas celebration for the troops in Bastion.  This includes a traditional Christmas lunch consisting of roast beef, pork, turkey, sprouts, roast potatoes and pudding and mince pies. We are cooking for roughly about 4,000 people - ranging from 140 joints of beef, 200 turkeys, 120 gammons – that’s what it take to feed these guys.  Also using 40 boxes of brussel spouts, 150 bags of potatoes, it’s on a massive scale.  It also includes litres of gravy, tomato soup – it’s a big operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="presents-for-all-serving-personnel"&gt;Presents for all serving personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5821/Xmas_presents_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing a little Christmas cheer to forces overseas every year is the UK based charity called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4uThanks!"&gt;uk4uThanks!&lt;/a&gt;  This is an organisation funded by money donated by members of the public. The presents (affectionately known as the ‘square stocking’) act as a gift from the nation to all those serving in the UK Armed Forces overseas away from their families and loved ones on Christmas Day.  The boxes, containing a host of goodies from business sponsors and bought with money donated from members of the public, were delivered in time to be opened on Christmas Day.  Much speculation abounds as to the contents of the boxes and it is never a disappointment as much thought is put into providing amusing and useful gifts away from home at Christmas time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60566</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-diamond-arrives-home-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Diamond arrives home in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Diamond has returned home to Portsmouth today following her maiden deployment to the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyer&lt;/a&gt; sailed more than 31,000 miles (50,000 kilometres) on security and counter-piracy patrols in the Indian Ocean, Gulf of Oman and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; left Portsmouth in June shortly after launching the nation’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations with a ceremonial entry into the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth" title="Portsmouth Naval Base"&gt;naval base&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After travelling through the Mediterranean she transited the Suez Canal before taking over from sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Daring" title="HMS Daring"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Daring&lt;/a&gt;. Diamond then spent the following 5 months as part of the Combined Task Force, a 27-nation partnership promoting security in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship worked with the French Carrier Group in the Mediterranean and three United States Carrier Strike Groups (&lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Middle East, including the escort of the US carriers through the Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s fighter controllers exercised with the US Navy’s F18 Hornets and controlled F22 Raptor and F15 Strike Eagle aircraft from the United States Air Force. The ship’s Lynx aircraft also demonstrated its ability to conduct air intercepts for the task groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also exercised with the navies of Australia, Canada, France, Kuwait, and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While conducting counter-piracy operations the ship’s specialist embarked military force carried out assurance visits to local fishermen and traders and held boarding training with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Commander Ian Clarke is greeted by his family" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5814/FX120552013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond's Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, is greeted by his wife, Joanne, and daughter Rebecca, aged 3 [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have achieved a tremendous amount this deployment and I pay tribute to my fantastic ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have provided reassurance in the Middle East, under the Combined Maritime Forces, worked closely with regional allies and three US &lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt; and really pushed the air defence capability of these fantastic new destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also worked alongside other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; assets, such as minehunters based out of Bahrain and their support ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Bay-Class-Landing-Ships/RFA-Cardigan-Bay" title="RFA Cardigan Bay"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Cardigan Bay&lt;/a&gt;. Helicopters of the Fleet Air Arm were also involved - with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-ASaC" title="Sea King Mk7 Airborne Surveillance and Control"&gt;Sea King Mark 7&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/854" title="854 Squadron"&gt;854 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; making its first ever landing on a Type 45 - while Merlin aircraft also interacted with Diamond at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as time at sea in the region, she has visited Bahrain, Jordan, Kuwait, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, as well as Gibraltar and Crete and the cities of Athens and Barcelona while on transit to and from the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer David Turner said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a busy few months but working with the other navies has been enjoyable, as have all the fascinating places we have visited. Although what we have achieved has been immensely rewarding, after six months away it is good to know that we are back in time to be reunited with our loved ones for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore The Hon Michael Cochrane, Commander Portsmouth Flotilla, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome Diamond back after what has been an exciting and high-profile deployment for the ship’s company, whose work has seen them entering new fields of interest for the air defence community. I am sure they will enjoy their well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond is the third of the UK’s fleet of six Type 45 destroyers. She was launched in 2007, arrived in Portsmouth in the autumn of 2010 and was commissioned in the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
