<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing versatile, agile and battle-winning armed forces and a smaller, more professional Ministry of Defence "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56641</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:36:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-more-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet more Millies heroes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-1---operation-olympics"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 1 - Operation Olympics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympians Victoria Pendleton and Greg Rutherford presented the first of two Judges’ Special Recognition Awards to the Armed Forces for their contribution to the London 2012 Olympics. At its height, more than 17,500 personnel stepped in when G4S were not able to provide sufficient guards for all the venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victoria said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone I’ve met has been incredible; individuals who’ve achieved so much. I feel in awe because all I did was ride round in circles on a wooden track with a bike with no brakes and one gear and this is real life. I can’t not be moved and it makes me feel very proud to be British.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear the military personnel treasured their experiences. Senior Aircraftwoman Afyah Bubb, an RAF medic who volunteered to be part of the security team at the Olympic Park, saw it as a ‘once-in-a-lifetime opportunity’. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were there to do a job but I unexpectedly got the chance to see Ellie Simmonds break some swimming records which was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Brian Fahy added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were really proud to be part of the Games this summer and see the superb performance of our athletes. Who wouldn’t want to be part of the greatest show in town?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic long jump gold medallist Greg Rutherford said backstage: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m hugely proud of the Armed Forces; the whole evening has been a massive highlight and getting involved feels out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5637/award_for_headley_court.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team with their Special Recognition Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a light-hearted moment, Greg joked that he hadn’t packed enough tissues. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I get emotional so easily and seeing videos of these incredible people moves me to tears every time. It’s completely surreal to be here; I’ve got friends in the Armed Forces including my best friend who is now going through training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to be invited to such a prestigious night, and to show our respect and thanks to these guys is an honour. The troops came in with happy smiley faces and gave high fives and absolutely saved the day! A huge thank you, you were absolutely spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-2---complex-trauma-team-headley-court"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 2 - Complex Trauma Team, Headley Court&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second Judges’ Special Recognition Award honoured the Complex Trauma Team at the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/Militarymedicine/Pages/HeadleyCourt.aspx" title="Headley Court"&gt;Headley Court&lt;/a&gt;. It is the remarkable skill and dedication of the 110-strong Trauma Team that help many critically wounded soldiers overcome life-changing injuries so they can get back to leading active lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex trauma manager Anne Brannagan received the award on behalf of Headley Court from actor Kevin Spacey who congratulated and shook hands with each of the 10 team members on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Clare Walton, Commanding Officer at Headley Court, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kevin Spacey was just very complimentary, it was great, and to have someone of his level of superstardom even know who we are is lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony tonight (14 December) on ITV1 at 2100hrs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56556</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:22:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:22:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dr-liam-fox-responds-to-defence-committee-report-on-sdsr"/>
    <title>Dr Liam Fox responds to Defence Committee report on SDSR</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since January, the House of Commons Defence Committee (HCDC) has been reviewing the SDSR and the NSS. It has taken oral evidence from sources including the Defence Secretary, the Armed Forces Minister, the Single Service Chiefs, the Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, the Chief of Defence Materiel, the Deputy Chief of Defence Staff (Personnel), and Lord Stirrup (Chief of the Defence Staff when the SDSR was published). The Department has also provided extensive written evidence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HCDC says the report seeks to establish whether the new National Security Council has led to a more coherent and well-defined security policy in terms of the NSS and the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its report, the HCDC agrees with the logic underpinning the SDSR, including the prioritisation of operational requirements for Afghanistan, the adaptable posture, the validity of Future Force 2020, and the strategic priority and national security imperative of dealing with the budget deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the HCDC also says that it is not convinced that, given the current financial climate and the drawdown of capabilities arising from the SDSR, UK Armed Forces will be able do what is asked of them after 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chair of the Committee, the Right Honourable James Arbuthnot MP, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government appears to believe that the UK can maintain its influence while reducing spending in Defence and at the Foreign Office. We do not agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5603/Liam_Fox_responds_to_Defence_Committee_report_on_SDSR_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Dave Hillhouse, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report also expresses concerns over the realisation of what is called ‘Future Force 2020’ - the Government’s intended shape of the Armed Forces from 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Arbuthnot said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Decisions for post-2015 funding will have to be made in the very near future to ensure progress towards Future Force 2020. If the ambition of a real-terms funding increase is not realised, we will have failed our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Defence Review had not been conducted for 12 years, resulting in an equipment programme that was woefully unaffordable. A multi-billion pound deficit was plaguing Defence, and tough, but necessary, decisions had to be taken. As the Committee rightly acknowledges, dealing with the deficit was a national security imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Committee is also right to say that Future Force 2020 is only achievable with extra funding. That is why I announced two weeks ago that the military equipment budget will rise in real terms by over £3bn between 2015 and 2020, with new helicopters being ordered, new money for our armoured vehicles, the carrier programme, and guaranteed spending on the Joint Strike Fighter. Our future equipment programme is no longer an unfunded aspiration, but one that provides real money for real equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We continue to have the fourth largest military budget in the world and the SDSR has put Defence back on a stable footing with highly capable Armed Forces and certainty for our personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pushing through radical reforms to ensure that the mistakes of the past are not repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we have seen in the US, no country is immune to the global financial problems, and even the world’s biggest military power is now grappling with how to make defence cuts and reform for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Sir David Richards, Chief of the Defence Staff, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SDSR was based on an assessment of the threats we face now and in the future. We have had to take some tough decisions, but as we move towards Future Force 2020 we will remain a formidable fighting force on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will remain capable of sustaining our operations in Afghanistan and Libya before rebalancing will give us the flexibility to maintain our ability to project power across our spheres of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are continually working with our international allies to share operational requirements, including utilising basing and overflight rights for Libya - measures we rightly assessed in the SDSR could be relied upon to mitigate capability gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD will respond formally to the Defence Committee regarding today’s report in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56545</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:55:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:55:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-outlines-reform-of-the-ministry-of-defence"/>
    <title>Liam Fox outlines reform of the Ministry of Defence</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to an audience at the Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors in Westminster, Dr Fox announced that he is launching a full review of how the Ministry of Defence is run and how the Armed Forces can be reformed to ‘produce more efficient provision of defence capability, and generation and sustainment of operations’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech Dr Fox began by describing the background to the changes, highlighting the fact that the country faces a legacy of debt - the interest on which for the next year alone will exceed the budget of the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that it was a ‘disgrace’ that there had not been a Defence Review for 12 years, despite our Armed Forces being committed to conflicts in the Balkans, Sierra Leone, Iraq and Afghanistan and with enormous changes in the global security picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR) will not simply be a random selection of cuts but an objective process by which the shape of the Armed Forces required will be reached by the end of the decade. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The National Security Council has agreed that the overarching strategic posture should be to address the most immediate threats to our national security while maintaining the ability to identify and deal with emerging ones before they become bigger threats to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This flexible, adaptable posture will maintain the ability to safeguard international peace and security, to deter and contain those who threaten the UK and its interests, and where necessary to intervene on multiple fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will also, crucially, keep our options open for a future in which we can expect our highest priorities to change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said we need to ‘invest in programmes that we will require to put our defence on a sound footing for the years ahead and divest ourselves of the capabilities which we are unlikely to need in a world where the moral climate demands precision weaponry and where the battlespace increasingly embraces the unmanned and cyber domains’, adding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are contrasting cost-savings and the capability implications with the risks that we face in the real global security environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This requires assessing any proposed change in a current programme or platform against a series of criteria, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, the cost-saving in years zero to five, five to ten, and beyond ten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Second, the capability implications - what capability will be lost as a result of this decision and what other assets do we possess that might give us the same or a similar capability?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Third, the operational implications - what operations that we currently carry out, or are likely to carry out, will we be unable to undertake as a result of this change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fourth, the ability to regenerate the capability, at what cost and in what timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And fifth, the risk in the real world that this capability currently protects us from or is likely to protect us from in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In alliance with the SDSR Dr Fox said that the Ministry of Defence itself was in need of reform and to this end he announced that a Defence Reform Unit would be established to carry out the required changes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this he said there are two broad principles that would be followed. The first is a structural reform which will see the Department reorganised into the three pillars of Policy and Strategy, the Armed Forces, and Procurement and Estates. The second is a cultural shift which will see a leaner and less centralised organisation combined with devolved processors which carry greater accountability and transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that a logical management structure would be ‘foreign policy leading to a defence strategy, then portfolio management which identified capability gaps, followed by specific programme identification and finally physical procurement’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new three pillar structure is designed to make this easier and to stop the constant over-specification and then re-specification of programmes which has led to cost overruns and programme delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work will be led by the Defence Reform Unit. Dr Fox described this as ‘a heavy-hitting steering group of internal and external experts [who] will guide the hard thinking and challenge preconceptions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene will chair this group and will be supported from outside the MOD by Baroness Sheila Noakes, George Iacobescu, Dr David Allen, Björn Conway and Raymond McKeeve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, it will be supported by a civil service implementation team with a remit to complete their blueprint for reform by September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also announced that there will be a review of how the Armed Forces undertake the tasks of force generation and sustainability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to challenge some of the fundamental assumptions which drive force generation, such as tour lengths and intervals, taking into account the varying pressures on our personnel resulting from widely varying missions to see if we can update our practices and produce greater efficiency while implementing the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State said he will be asking the First Sea Lord, Admiral Sir Mark Stanhope, the Chief of the Air Staff, Air Chief Marshal Sir Stephen Dalton, and the new Chief of the General Staff, General Sir Peter Wall, to begin this review once the SDSR has been completed, with a view to completing their work by the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Defence Reform Unit will work with the Chief of the Defence Staff and the Service Chiefs to find ways of giving greater devolution for the running of the Services themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Department must get away from the over-centralising tendency that has become the hallmark of the MOD in recent years and said they will also consider whether the current senior rank structure across the Services is appropriate for the post-SDSR world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We cannot demand efficiency from the lower ranks while exempting those at the top,” Dr Fox said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded by saying that taken together the SDSR and these changes represent a radical agenda for change and show how the Government is committed to governing not in their own interest, but in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16671</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-defence-secretary-on-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>The Defence Secretary on delivering value for money and innovation in Defence</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking yesterday, Mr Hammond used his speech to talk about how, over the last two-and-a-half years, the Department has set about reforming the way Defence is managed in order to deliver improved efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began by recapping the scale of the reform challenge faced by Defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will rematerialise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two-and-a-half years of the transformation project, the Defence Secretary said we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture so that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said that while Defence needed a solid financial foundation, it was the people that really mattered and made the difference, and therefore an attractive employment package to attract and keep the best was needed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them. And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis. So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life. So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that a new employment model was needed and this would need to be flexible to meet the varying and individual needs of Service personnel: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term and attractive to Service personnel and fair to the taxpayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall, designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that this ‘New Employment Model’, or NEM, isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges, and it is not about overnight transformation but will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer: towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And more stability to Service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners, and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On housing, Mr Hammond said that, in a 22-year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want this to change. As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, the Defence Secretary said we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation. Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence Budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability. That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task, but neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48933</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:18:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/mod-annual-report-and-accounts-2011-12"/>
    <title>MOD Annual Report and Accounts 2011-12</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Defence Annual Report and Accounts 2011-12 and Sustainability Report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56151</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:20:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/armed-forces-covenant-annual-report-2012"/>
    <title>Armed Forces Covenant Annual Report 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first annual report is the beginning of a process to identify issues and make sure they are addressed. The report highlights progress across all 15 themes of the Covenant and identifies work still to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report covers the following groups: serving personnel; reservists; the wounded, injured and sick; families; the bereaved; service leavers; and veterans. It sets out a number of important achievements and also highlights remaining challenges and makes a series of new commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three leaflets explaining what the Covenant means for Serving personnel, Veterans and Service families&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/34810</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/150-2012-mod-announces-new-46m-contract-for-foxhound-vehicles"/>
    <title>150/2012 -  MOD Announces new £46m contract for Foxhound vehicles</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Minister Philip Dunne MP made the announcement during a visit to General Dynamics: Force Protection’s spares facility in Telford which provides spares for the Foxhound vehicle. The contract announced today is part of an overall investment of £340 million that the MoD has made in Foxhound since 2010. This is helping to sustain jobs at the Telford facility, the General Dynamics: Force Protection (GDLS:FPE) HQ in Leamington Spa and across the UK in the Foxhound supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed and built by GDL:FPE in Britain, Foxhound is one of the Army’s most agile protected vehicle. It uses leading-edge Formula 1 technology to provide unparalleled protection for its weight and class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Foxhounds were deployed to Afghanistan in June 2012 and are now being used by soldiers operating in mentoring and partnering roles with the Afghan National Security Forces. During the visit to the spares facility, Mr Dunne and Major Chris Thoms, the requirements manager for Protected Mobility at the MoD, met with staff who are also providing vital logistical support to the Army in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology, Philip Dunne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet with employees at General Dynamics: Force Protection who have helped make Foxhound a real procurement success story, taking only 40 months to develop it from the initial design to deployment in Afghanistan. The work being done by staff here in Telford is ensuring the vehicles can stay on the road and helping our soldiers do the vital job of engaging with Afghan forces and protecting the local population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Balancing the MoD’s budget means we can now confidently invest in equipment like Foxhound, which has the flexibility and adaptability to operate in a wide variety of environments, providing capability for the Army well into the future. This investment shows the MoD playing its part in delivering growth and sustaining jobs in the West Midlands industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in September when Foxhound was first operational in Afghanistan, Chief of Staff for the Bastion Force Protection Wing, Squadron Leader Jim Stewart, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Foxhound is an enormous leap forward in capability; the off-road mobility, enhanced protection and night-vision systems that it offers to the troops on the ground are unmatched in a vehicle of this size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 51 extra Foxhounds announced today are the latest to be ordered from GDLS:FPE as part of the £340 million investment that will provide the Army with a total fleet of 376 vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about Foxhound, contact Beth Cowley at the MoD Press Office on 0207 218 7714. Questions relating to General Dynamics: Force Protection should be directed to Julian Forsyth on 07850 915 164.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39704</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:35:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-launched-on-the-future-of-britains-reserve-forces"/>
    <title>Consultation launched on the future of Britain's Reserve Forces</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation, ‘Future Reserves 2020: Delivering the Nation’s Security Together’, proposes more training for reservists, a ‘kitemark-type’ award for supportive employers, and the idea of changing the Territorial Army’s name to reflect their enhanced role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals there will be a new relationship between reservists, employers and government, and a transparent approach whereby employers are given more certainty about the timing of possible mobilisations and more notice when they occur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures will create a fully integrated force of regulars and reservists, using similar equipment and training together. It will mean that the Reserves not only provide individual augmentees to regular units, but also deploy as formed units and sub-units. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Royal Marines Reserve" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1435/Consultation_launched_on_the_future_of_Britain_s_Reserve_Forces2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Royal Marines Reserve received a rare opportunity to form the Guard at Edinburgh Castle recently
[Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of trained Reserves will grow to around 35,000 across all three Services by 2020, aligning the mix of regular and reserve components with many of our closest allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army will see the biggest change, with 30,000 trained Reserves, creating a total land force of about 120,000. And the plans are backed by an extra £1.8bn in funding over the next ten years for new equipment, uniforms and training for the Reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• increasing the number of days Army reservists are required to train from 35 to 40 days a year  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• a change of name from Territorial Army to Army Reserve - better reflecting the future role and tasks  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• encouraging more ex-regulars to become reservists - making it easier for them to transfer to the Reserves and developing incentives for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This transformation of the Reserves will see a radical shift in the way in which we use them, with units deployed as formed units or sub-units as well as delivering individual augmentees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Increased training, better equipment and extra investment in our Reserves are all integral to our vision of a formidable, adaptable and flexible Armed Forces, with a reserve/regular balance more in line with our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government has committed £1.8bn to rebuilding our Reserves. The consultation I have launched today is about working with reservists, their families and employers to use that money to design the Reserve Forces of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir Nick Houghton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since 2003 there have been over 25,000 reservists mobilised, fighting alongside their regular counterparts. 29 have paid the ultimate price for their country and just this summer we saw 2,000 reservists provide a pivotal security role at the London 2012 Games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the future we will become even more reliant on our Reserves. But this increased reliance means that there are key issues that we have to tackle - like our relationship with employers and the notice period ahead of mobilisation - to get this right. I want to encourage everyone to get involved in this consultation and have their say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run until 18 January 2013 and following this we will publish a White Paper in Spring 2013 setting out this new relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
