<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-versatile-agile-and-battle-winning-armed-forces-and-a-smaller-more-professional-ministry-of-defence/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing versatile, agile and battle-winning armed forces and a smaller, more professional Ministry of Defence "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-04T11:09:19+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61168</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:09:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-invites-tenders-for-uk-construction-projects"/>
    <title>MOD invites tenders for UK construction projects</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Ten private sector companies have been invited to tender for a new framework agreement to deliver construction projects across the UK Defence estate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The companies shortlisted for the framework by the Defence Infrastructure Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;) are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.balfourbeatty.com/" title="Balfour Beatty website"&gt;Balfour Beatty Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bam.co.uk/Construction/Construction-Overview.aspx" title="BAM Construction website"&gt;BAM Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.carillionplc.com/our-capabilities/construction-services.aspx" title="Carillion Construction website"&gt;Carillion Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.interserve.com/" title="Interserve website"&gt;Interserve Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kier.co.uk/" title="Kier Group website"&gt;Kier Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lendlease.com/worldwide/capabilities/project-management-and-construction.aspx" title="Lend Lease Construction website"&gt;Lend Lease Construction (EMEA) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millerconstruction.co.uk/" title="Miller Construction website"&gt;Miller Construction (UK) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://construction.morgansindall.com/" title="Morgan Sindall Construction website"&gt;Morgan Sindall plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.skanska.co.uk/" title="Skanska website"&gt;Skanska UK plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wates.co.uk/" title="Wates website"&gt;Wates Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Capital Works Framework will be used for the design and build of construction projects up to a value of £50 million. It will include up to 5 companies who will participate in ‘mini-competitions’ for individual projects. It is due to be awarded before the end of 2013 and will run for an initial 4-year period, with the potential to extend for up to 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework forms part of the &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; Next Generation Estate Contracts (&lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme, and will operate alongside 6 regional capital works frameworks for projects valued below £12 million. It has an estimated value of between £250 million and £400 million over the 4-year period and could be used at any site across the UK estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, the shortlisted companies attended a bidders’ conference at the Defence Academy in Shrivenham focused on the tendering process and on the proposed operating model for the framework. Delegates were also taken step-by-step through a typical Defence construction project, looking at the processes involved, legislative influences, sustainability and other requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tender will be rigorously evaluated based on the company’s approach to commercial and technical matters such as supply chain management, quality assurance, sustainable development, health and safety, and issues relating to the Government Construction Strategy. The tenderers have also been provided with a demonstration construction project and will be evaluated on their proposed approach to its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Rice, Head of the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changes to UK military basing arrangements are expected to generate requirements for new capital works in the years ahead, and it is vital these are met flexibly and cost-effectively, enabling us to provide a Defence estate which meets military needs and supports our Armed Forces. Early in the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme our research determined that framework arrangements were the best mechanism to achieve this, and I am delighted that we have such a strong field of companies in the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Wooden, &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks project manager, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This national framework is designed to deliver a range of potential major construction projects to support the Defence front line. We are determined to ensure firstly that all companies involved in the tendering process have a full and robust understanding of the potential demand, and secondly that we use the evaluation process to identify the best providers to meet that demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks are designed to support the Government Construction Strategy by reducing costs, improving value for money, and incorporating measures such as the ‘&lt;abbr title="New Engineering Contract 3"&gt;NEC3&lt;/abbr&gt;’ form of procurement, more focused performance management, and continuous improvement mechanisms. For all projects contractors will be required to use systems that meet UK Government requirements for Building Information Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework contractors will also be required to observe fair payment practices and - where decided appropriate on a project-by-project basis - project bank accounts will be set up to ensure prompt payment for all supply chain companies involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tenders are due to be returned by mid-February 2013 and it is expected that the National Capital Works Framework agreements will be awarded before the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61178</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T15:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:09:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/keeping-the-uk-military-on-the-map"/>
    <title>Keeping the UK military on the map</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The experts at the Defence Geographic Centre near London are keeping UK Armed Forces worldwide on the right track.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Australian scientists went to have a look at Sandy Island in the South Pacific recently, they discovered that, despite having featured on maps and on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en_uk/earth/index.html" title="Google Earth UK homepage"&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; for years, it doesn’t actually exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts working at the Defence Geographic Centre (&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;) may well have smiled wryly on hearing this. There is no room in their world for such errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; provides geographic information to Defence, predominantly to the Army and the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, but also to other government departments, and works in a world of international collaboration, sharing and co-producing geographical information where a reputation for accuracy matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s geographers, or geospatial analysts as they prefer to be called, know that, if you rely on a map which hasn’t been created from entirely dependable source data, the result can get you into trouble. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A large printer at the Defence Geographic Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5847/Replication.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Defence Geographic Centre has a full range of modern print and production equipment [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even the best maps are the result of compromise and estimate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unless you are on the ground looking at something, geographical information is always an approximation,” said Ian Spencer, Head of Geo Research. “We know how accurate our sources are, and the technical parameters of our sensors, so we know how accurate our products are. We have to work within a defined margin of error for each military product. If it’s outside that margin it’s considered unfit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; augments some of their products with open source material, such as Google Earth pictures, to provide pop-up images of features, but they do it knowing where the risks lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; produces more than just maps, whether on paper or on a screen. After all, a map is just one way of presenting geographical information, and it might not be the best solution for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you might need a database of geographic data to put in a weapons system, or a 3D simulation created from stereoscopic photographs to prepare yourself for the environment through which you may have to fly and control a missile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; specialises in making sense of a huge mass of data and presenting it to the customer in a way that is going to help them make sense of the world, spot relationships, and make informed plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We get 2 types of request,” said Operations Officer Major Jim Danks. “These are ad hoc for a single event or operation, such as disaster relief or support to the Arab Spring operations. And longer term planned work which can include Afghanistan tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5848/Workstation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery to produce simulations [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A request may start as a one-off and then develop into a long-term requirement. When Camp Bastion was established more than a decade ago it started as an ad hoc request. Now, as a home for thousands of troops, it is a standard request requiring the provision of many different types of data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for Lionel Fewson, Head of Collection, are 5 Collection Officers who could be described as the geographic equivalent of Indiana Jones. They scour the globe in search of useful, creditable data, visiting countries of interest gathering information and making new contacts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making maps from scratch is time consuming and very expensive, so international collaboration and data-sharing is very cost effective. Lionel said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have memorandums of understanding with 50 countries and links with many trusted commercial suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the digital side, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is part of a 29-nation programme to capture digital data from various places of interest around the world. In return for their contribution, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; has access to the entire output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of the benefit of co-operation is the award-winning work producing image-based mapping of compounds in Helmand province to improve battlefield and situational awareness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the US Marine Corps Intelligence Activity, the project has to date captured and referenced more than 200,000 compounds and produced more than 1,100 large-scale maps covering more than 11,000 square kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Defence Geographic Centre personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5849/Research.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Defence Geographic Centre personnel meet to identify sources for new products [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to future products, there is a revolution taking place, and the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is leading the way. The move is towards making more use of human geography in an ordered way. Ian Spencer said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to develop standards with our overseas partners to define database structures so that we can start capturing information like ethnicity demographics, economics, religion and water control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you go on the internet you will see lots of people doing things in different disciplines, but at the moment it isn’t connected. We want to pull all this information together in a systematic way so that decision makers and analysts have a better understanding of what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we have the basic geographic foundation we can overlay that with all kinds of human activities. Once data is organised then you can share it and exploit it, and when it has a spatial element you can model these factors and see what effect their interaction has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian believes that marrying physical and social sciences will open up a new world of understanding, as long as you take into account the assumptions and approximations that have been made. Asking how does factor A affect element B is OK as long as you keep an eye out for any more fictitious islands on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="this-report-by-ian-carr-appears-in-the-december-2012january-2013-issue-of-defence-focus---the-magazine-for-everyone-in-defence"&gt;This report by Ian Carr appears in the December 2012/January 2013 issue of Defence Focus - the magazine for everyone in Defence.&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61086</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/playful-pup-newest-recruit-to-irish-guards"/>
    <title>Playful pup newest recruit to Irish Guards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An Irish Wolfhound puppy called Domhnall is the new regimental mascot for the 1st Battalion Irish Guards.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To the untrained eye, he is just a rather large, playful puppy. But in a few months, Irish Wolfhound Domhnall will be leading the way as the new regimental mascot for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23990.aspx" title="The Irish Guards website"&gt;1st Battalion Irish Guards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based at Mons Barracks in Aldershot, Hampshire, the five-month-old is already training for the moment he dons a special silver collar and a scarlet tunic to join the guardsmen in their ceremonial role at occasions such as the Queen’s Birthday Parade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domhnall, whose name means ‘World Leader’ in Gaelic, came to the regiment from Northern Ireland untrained. He and handler Drummer David Steed are on a steep learning curve to make sure they look the part when Domhnall first fulfills the role of mascot at the regiment’s grand St Patrick’s Day parade in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5843/LAND-2012-212-IRISH_GDS_MASCOT_-087_copy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall, in festive spirit [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In just 2 months, ‘blank canvas’ Domhnall has already been housetrained and obedience-trained, Drummer Steed said, with his ceremonial training in London due to start in the near future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This will involve being with the regimental band, taking him out on Queen’s Guard mounts to get him used to the noises and the sights and sounds of London, as well as taking him to Knightsbridge for his horse-friendly training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because ceremonial duties are with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/28071.aspx" title="Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment website"&gt;Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment&lt;/a&gt;, it’s making sure that the horses aren’t startled by him and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drummer Steed admitted that training the hyperactive puppy - whose favourite occupation is chasing cyclists - is hard work for both of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But this kind of training the two of us are undergoing is something slightly different - it’s different from marching down the road carrying a rifle to suddenly having a four-legged friend by your side that you’ve got to control as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Benjamin Irwin-Clark, Adjutant of the 1st Battalion Irish Guards, said an Irish Wolfhound has been the regimental mascot for over a century:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quite early in our regiment’s history, in 1902, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iwcni.co.uk/" title="Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland website"&gt;Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; offered to provide an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot to the Irish Guards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regiment accepted, and, ever since then, I think with a few gaps, there has been an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5844/LAND-2012-212_Irish_Guards_Mascot_075.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mascots are traditionally named after Irish chieftains and have a ceremonial role in the regiment, parading with guardsmen during ceremonial duties and state occasions in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Irwin-Clark added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the moment we’re just putting him through a sort of inoculation of the bagpipes, among other things, and I think it’s going to take a little time for him to get comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60863</id>
    <published>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-forces-mark-christmas-in-helmand"/>
    <title>British Forces mark Christmas in Helmand </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British forces in southern Afghanistan mark Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;British forces serving in southern Afghanistan have been marking Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province today (25 December).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities took place as the troops completed a full day of operational duties.  Many soldiers from the UK-led Task Force Helmand spent the day on patrol in support of the Afghan security forces, yet still most found time to open presents and ring home – and enjoy a freshly-prepared Christmas lunch with all the trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-post"&gt;Christmas post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last-minute festive cheer was provided by the Post and Courier Squadron as tonnes of mail arrived at a number of forward locations, delivered by Chinook helicopter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing last minute festive cheer on Christmas morning, 78 sacks of post (1 tonne) arrived by helicopter in Main Operating Base (&lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) Lashkar Gah – home to the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; (‘Black Rats’) headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5819/Xmas_post_delivery_helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province, Afghanistan&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a chilly Christmas morning, in &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; over 100 soldiers and civilians took part in the ‘Lash Dash’ 5km run around the base.  Many completed the course in fancy dress, with proceeds from the event split between two charities: the Lashkar Gah Orphanage and The Black Rat Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the male and female winners were Danish soldiers. The Brits fared better in the fancy dress competition with Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant’s General Corps, Royal Military Police) winning by running dressed as a well-wrapped Christmas present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5818/LashDash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant General Corps, Royal Military Police) won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="working-day"&gt;Working day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, is another working day for all military here in Helmand. As the sun rose on Christmas morning, troops from the Royal Dragoon Guards and the Royal Military Police set off on patrol to the Provincial Police Headquarters to train Afghan Police. The ‘train the trainer’ course sees Afghan Police qualifying to teach police skills. This will allow British troops to step back as the Afghan Security Forces take the lead in training their own forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-lunches-and-all-the-trimmings"&gt;Christmas lunches and all the trimmings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full Christmas lunch, including all the trimmings, was served in the cookhouses of Camp Bastion, &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; Lashkar Gah and patrol bases across Helmand. Even the troops manning the security towers or sangars surrounding Camp Bastion were not forgotten and enjoyed personal deliveries of hot food.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5820/Xmas_dinner_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Baldwin kitchen manager from KBR in Camp Bastion said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is the full Christmas celebration for the troops in Bastion.  This includes a traditional Christmas lunch consisting of roast beef, pork, turkey, sprouts, roast potatoes and pudding and mince pies. We are cooking for roughly about 4,000 people - ranging from 140 joints of beef, 200 turkeys, 120 gammons – that’s what it take to feed these guys.  Also using 40 boxes of brussel spouts, 150 bags of potatoes, it’s on a massive scale.  It also includes litres of gravy, tomato soup – it’s a big operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="presents-for-all-serving-personnel"&gt;Presents for all serving personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5821/Xmas_presents_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing a little Christmas cheer to forces overseas every year is the UK based charity called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4uThanks!"&gt;uk4uThanks!&lt;/a&gt;  This is an organisation funded by money donated by members of the public. The presents (affectionately known as the ‘square stocking’) act as a gift from the nation to all those serving in the UK Armed Forces overseas away from their families and loved ones on Christmas Day.  The boxes, containing a host of goodies from business sponsors and bought with money donated from members of the public, were delivered in time to be opened on Christmas Day.  Much speculation abounds as to the contents of the boxes and it is never a disappointment as much thought is put into providing amusing and useful gifts away from home at Christmas time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60566</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-diamond-arrives-home-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Diamond arrives home in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Diamond has returned home to Portsmouth today following her maiden deployment to the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyer&lt;/a&gt; sailed more than 31,000 miles (50,000 kilometres) on security and counter-piracy patrols in the Indian Ocean, Gulf of Oman and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; left Portsmouth in June shortly after launching the nation’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations with a ceremonial entry into the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth" title="Portsmouth Naval Base"&gt;naval base&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After travelling through the Mediterranean she transited the Suez Canal before taking over from sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Daring" title="HMS Daring"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Daring&lt;/a&gt;. Diamond then spent the following 5 months as part of the Combined Task Force, a 27-nation partnership promoting security in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship worked with the French Carrier Group in the Mediterranean and three United States Carrier Strike Groups (&lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Middle East, including the escort of the US carriers through the Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s fighter controllers exercised with the US Navy’s F18 Hornets and controlled F22 Raptor and F15 Strike Eagle aircraft from the United States Air Force. The ship’s Lynx aircraft also demonstrated its ability to conduct air intercepts for the task groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also exercised with the navies of Australia, Canada, France, Kuwait, and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While conducting counter-piracy operations the ship’s specialist embarked military force carried out assurance visits to local fishermen and traders and held boarding training with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Commander Ian Clarke is greeted by his family" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5814/FX120552013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond's Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, is greeted by his wife, Joanne, and daughter Rebecca, aged 3 [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have achieved a tremendous amount this deployment and I pay tribute to my fantastic ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have provided reassurance in the Middle East, under the Combined Maritime Forces, worked closely with regional allies and three US &lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt; and really pushed the air defence capability of these fantastic new destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also worked alongside other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; assets, such as minehunters based out of Bahrain and their support ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Bay-Class-Landing-Ships/RFA-Cardigan-Bay" title="RFA Cardigan Bay"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Cardigan Bay&lt;/a&gt;. Helicopters of the Fleet Air Arm were also involved - with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-ASaC" title="Sea King Mk7 Airborne Surveillance and Control"&gt;Sea King Mark 7&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/854" title="854 Squadron"&gt;854 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; making its first ever landing on a Type 45 - while Merlin aircraft also interacted with Diamond at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as time at sea in the region, she has visited Bahrain, Jordan, Kuwait, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, as well as Gibraltar and Crete and the cities of Athens and Barcelona while on transit to and from the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer David Turner said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a busy few months but working with the other navies has been enjoyable, as have all the fascinating places we have visited. Although what we have achieved has been immensely rewarding, after six months away it is good to know that we are back in time to be reunited with our loved ones for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore The Hon Michael Cochrane, Commander Portsmouth Flotilla, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome Diamond back after what has been an exciting and high-profile deployment for the ship’s company, whose work has seen them entering new fields of interest for the air defence community. I am sure they will enjoy their well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond is the third of the UK’s fleet of six Type 45 destroyers. She was launched in 2007, arrived in Portsmouth in the autumn of 2010 and was commissioned in the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60139</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-choir-a-year-with-the-military-wives"/>
    <title>The Choir: a year with the Military Wives</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Choirmaster Gareth Malone and key members of the Military Wives Choir reflect on their extraordinary journey in a Christmas Day television special.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, Gareth Malone went to the military base at Chivenor to set up a choir for the wives left at home alone while their men are on duty for months at a time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html" title="The Choir: a year with the Military Wives"&gt;the Christmas Day show&lt;/a&gt;, we hear from Gareth and key members of the choir as they reflect on their extraordinary journey including their performance of a song, specially written by royal composer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paulmealor.com/" title="Paul Mealor website"&gt;Paul Mealor&lt;/a&gt;, at The Royal Albert Hall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rehearsals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5783/choirpractise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gareth Malone and Military Wives rehearse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film shows the women as they launch their first single, which topped the Christmas charts, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="10 Downing Street website"&gt;10 Downing Street&lt;/a&gt;, perform at the Golden Jubilee and win a Classical Brit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also hear of the legacy of the original choir - the setting up of a charitable foundation that provides the support for a growing network of over 60 military wives choirs in bases across the UK, Europe and the Falkland Islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soloist Sam Stevenson says: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was Gareth’s dream and it came true and not many people can say their dreams have come true in life. I don’t even think I could express to Gareth how grateful we all are for it, it’s just, he’s really changed our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html"&gt;The Choir: A year with the Military Wives&lt;/a&gt; will be on Christmas Day, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo" title="BBC Two website"&gt;BBC2&lt;/a&gt; at 8.45pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60323</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-gives-blueprint-to-potential-infrastructure-partners"/>
    <title>MOD gives blueprint to potential infrastructure partners</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Defence Infrastructure Organisation (DIO), the Ministry of Defence's (MOD) property and services provider, has issued the document which allows the three short-listed teams to prepare detailed bids to potentially become its Strategic Business Partner (SBP).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Invitation to Negotiate (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt;) asks each team to further prove it can provide the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; with a proposal to bring the right skills and expertise, before the organisation makes a final decision regarding its preferred option next summer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organisation, which manages the delivery of infrastructure projects and services for the UK Armed Forces and its civilian support staff, will introduce new ways of working from Spring 2013. However, procuring a &lt;abbr title="Strategic Business Partner"&gt;SBP&lt;/abbr&gt; could realise further savings to benefit Defence as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Manley, Chief Executive, &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s principle objective is to support our military personnel in its Standing Commitments and in preparing for operations. We do this by providing and maintaining the places where they live, work and train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In addition &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; is central to supporting the Government’s wider objectives in construction, property management and the delivery of supporting the services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changing the way we deliver infrastructure services offers a real opportunity to build a leading-edge infrastructure delivery organisation that will serve the needs of our Armed Forces long into the future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are striving to create a high-performing and innovative enterprise. Our search for a Strategic Business Partner is expected to extend our capability by allowing &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; further access to private sector skills and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; has been working to ensure that the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a robust platform to effectively explore the use of private sector expertise. However, a contract will only be awarded if it can be found to provide value for money to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a robust procurement exercise, launched in May 2012, three teams were selected to participate in the next stage of the competition. They consist of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.telerealtrillium.com/" title="Telereal Trillium website"&gt;Telereal Trillium&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kpmg.com/uk/en/pages/default.aspx" title="KPMG website"&gt;KPMG&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.macegroup.com/" title="Mace website"&gt;Mace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.serco.com/" title="Serco website"&gt;Serco&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dtz.com/UK" title="DTZ website"&gt;DTZ&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bechtel.com/" title="Bechtel website"&gt;Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.capita.co.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Capita website"&gt;Capita&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.urscorp.com/" title="URS website"&gt;URS&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paconsulting.co.uk/" title="PA Consulting website"&gt;PA Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60274</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T17:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T17:04:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/princess-royal-attends-naval-cadets-passing-out-parade"/>
    <title>Princess Royal attends naval cadets' passing out parade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Her Royal Highness The Princess Royal has attended a parade performed by cadets passing out from Britannia Royal Naval College (BRNC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royal.gov.uk/thecurrentroyalfamily/theprincessroyal/theprincessroyal.aspx" title="The Princess Royal"&gt;The Princess Royal&lt;/a&gt;, accompanied by her husband, Vice Admiral Sir Tim Laurence, was the guest of honour at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s final passing-out-parade of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rain eased off, and with the Royal Marines band playing festive tunes, the Princess Royal was invited to inspect the cadets and take the salute during the march past. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parade signified the end of 30 weeks’ intensive training for the 67 Officer Cadets who can now enjoy Christmas with their families before embarking on the next stage of their Royal Navy careers. Among those passing out were cadets from 10 overseas nations who regularly send their personnel to &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; for training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Captain Jerry Kyd, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were very honoured to have Her Royal Highness visit us for our final parade of the year. These cadets have been given a thorough induction into the Royal Navy and worked hard to earn their place on the parade ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Princess Royal chats to cadets" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5796/DSC_0146.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Princess Royal chats to one of the cadets during the parade [Picture: Copyright Craig Keating]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They spent the last 9 weeks of their training at sea. Some were assigned to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Illustrious&lt;/a&gt;, while others were on board the fleet flagship, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/the-fleet/ships/assault-ships/hms-bulwark" title="HMS Bulwark"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Bulwark&lt;/a&gt;. Both warships were involved in the Royal Navy’s Cougar 12 deployment working as part of the UK’s Response Force Task Group, exercising with a multitude of other nations in the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was an excellent opportunity for the cadets to see at first hand the Royal Navy in operation, working in partnership with our allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Princess Royal has a long association with the Royal Navy. She holds the rank of Admiral as Chief Commandant for Women in the Royal Navy and has special relationships with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class/HMS-Talent" title="HMS Talent"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Talent&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Albion" title="HMS Albion"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Albion&lt;/a&gt;. The Princess Royal is also Commodore-in-Chief for Portsmouth and last attended a parade at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2002, when she represented Her Majesty The Queen at the Lord High Admiral’s Divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total 237 &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and cadets at varying stages of their training were on parade, with music provided by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalmarinesbands.co.uk/reference/band_ply.htm" title="The Band of Her Majesty's Royal Marines Plymouth"&gt;Band of Her Majesty’s Royal Marines Plymouth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a period of leave, the College will reopen in January 2013 for what will be the 150th year of Royal Navy officer training in Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60282</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T16:02:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:02:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-launches-new-skynet-satellite"/>
    <title>MOD launches new Skynet satellite</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new satellite which will provide secure military communications for UK Armed Forces has been successfully launched into space.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The extra lines of communication will benefit personnel deployed in Afghanistan and other parts of the world, including the Falklands, Cyprus and on ships at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; pictures show the moment that Skynet 5D was launched from French Guiana, South America. It is the fourth satellite of the Skynet 5 project to be put into space since 2007 under a £4bn Private Finance Initiative (&lt;abbr title="Private Finance Initiative"&gt;PFI&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.astrium.eads.net/" title="Astrium website"&gt;Astrium&lt;/a&gt;, who built the satellite and service providers &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.astriumservices.com/" title="Astrium Services"&gt;Astrium Services&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Skynet project sustains approximately 800 jobs between the company’s sites in Stevenage, Portsmouth and Corsham, Wiltshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in space, Skynet 5D will travel at speeds of around 10,000 kilometres per hour and is expected to cover around 1.2 billion kilometres during its time in orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Skynet 5D satellite is launched from French Guiana" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5790/Decollage_Toucan_010.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Skynet 5D satellite is launched from French Guiana in South America [Picture: S Martin. © ESA-CNES-ARIANESPACE / Optique vidéo du CSG]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colonel Mike Griffiths, Head of Networks for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/defence-equipment-and-support" title="Defence Equipment and Support page on GOV.UK"&gt;Defence Equipment and Support&lt;/a&gt; organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Skynet programme provides vital support to the Armed Forces. The launch of this latest satellite will deliver additional global communications capacity to support our operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-hammond" title="Read about Defence Secretary Philip Hammond"&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of Skynet 5D marks another milestone in this very successful programme. These satellites provide essential secure communication channels for our Armed Forces in Afghanistan and allow all three Services to communicate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of the satellites, Skynet 5A, was launched in March 2007, followed by Skynet 5B in November 2007, and Skynet 5C in June 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
