<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making it easier to set up and grow a business "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56643</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:05:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-business-link-helpline"/>
    <title>Assessment of the Business Link helpline</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether the Business Link helpline is performing effectively against its strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’, in which more businesses are assisted online rather than through other higher cost provision (for example face-to-face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the research has assessed the value of the service being provided to callers and how far actual demand has matched expectations. The findings are being used to help inform plans for continual improvement of the service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is based on interviews with helpline staff, analysis of monitoring data, call case studies and a customer survey that consisted of 657 telephone interviews that were completed with customers of the helpline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56755</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T10:13:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-online-business-support-offer-growth-and-improvement-service-my-new-business"/>
    <title>Assessment of the online business support offer: Growth and Improvement Service, My New Business</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether online business support services provided by Business Link have performed effectively against the strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’.  That is to successfully assist businesses through a website rather than through higher cost services (for example face to face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study also makes an early assessment of the value of the services provided to new users, with a focus on cost effectiveness and effective referral to other appropriate business support services in the public, private and third sectors. The support services include the comprehensive start-up service provided by My New Business, and online tools provided by the Growth Improvement Service, enabling businesses to identify and solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54863</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:31:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/analysis-of-the-distribution-of-private-sector-enterprises-by-turnover"/>
    <title>Analysis of the distribution of private sector enterprises by turnover</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counts of private sector enterprises by turnover from Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) June 2012. Published by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48220</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementing-the-recommendations-from-the-breedon-review-a-progress-report-november-2012"/>
    <title>Implementing the recommendations from the Breedon Review: a progress report (November 2012)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides an update for each recommendation made by the industry taskforce on non-bank lending led by Tim Breedon. See also See 12/668 for the taskforce report, and 12/669 for the government response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56389</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-school-mid-sized-business-msb-collaboration-supporting-growth-in-the-uks-mid-sized-businesses"/>
    <title>Business school/mid-sized business (MSB) collaboration: supporting growth in the UK's mid-sized businesses</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarises findings and recommendations from the business school mid-sized business (MSB) task force set up by BIS in November 2011. While the Task Force has uncovered many examples of effective business school engagement with MSBs, there is much more that both sides can do to foster stronger, more sustainable relationships. The report is a call to action for business schools to proactively engage with MSBs, and for MSBs to improve their own management capability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47151</id>
    <published>2012-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/global-entrepreneurship-week-2012"/>
    <title>Global Entrepreneurship Week 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The campaign to celebrate entrepreneurialism takes place from 12-18 November in over 115 countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s theme is ‘pass it on’. The aim is to pass on practical help and support to start-ups and people who are thinking about getting into business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Global-Entrepreneurship-Week-Ministers-recruit-entrepreneur-advisors-during-biggest-ever-celebration-of-enterprise-68300.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Ministers recruit entrepreneur advisors during biggest ever celebration of enterprise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are taking part in events during the week and making a number of announcements. Read Business Minister &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/blog/2012/11/09/supporting-global-entrepreneurship-week/"&gt;Michael Fallon’s blog&lt;/a&gt; on some of the events he’ll be involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year over 900 partner organisations got involved in the week here in the UK, reaching 213,000 people through 2,305 activities. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gew.org.uk/about/what_happened_in_2011"&gt;Read more about the 2011 campaign. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of GEW is to create a collaborative, local and practical week which enables people to learn more about the wealth of support that is available to entrepreneurs in the UK. This includes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encouraging people who are not yet entrepreneurs to think about starting up their own business. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving entrepreneurship skills for aspiring entrepreneurs and start-ups. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping people access practical support - locally, regionally and nationally. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government is also running the Business in You campaign that promotes the range of existing support services to help people start or grow their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to find out how exports can help grow your business? Next week UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment are also running &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.exportweek.ukti.gov.uk/full/"&gt;Export Week (12-16 November)&lt;/a&gt; with over a hundred events organised across the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gew.org.uk/home"&gt;Global Entrepreneurship Week 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/enterprise-and-business-support"&gt;Enterprise and business support at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/enterprise-and-business-support/entrepreneurial-culture"&gt;Entrepreneurial Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48187</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-copyright-licensing"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: copyright licensing</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to copyright licensing. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48188</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-debtor-petition-reform"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: debtor petition reform</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to reform of the process by which an individual may apply for his or her own bankruptcy. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
