<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making it easier to set up and grow a business "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54863</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:31:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/analysis-of-the-distribution-of-private-sector-enterprises-by-turnover"/>
    <title>Analysis of the distribution of private sector enterprises by turnover</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counts of private sector enterprises by turnover from Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) June 2012. Published by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48220</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementing-the-recommendations-from-the-breedon-review-a-progress-report-november-2012"/>
    <title>Implementing the recommendations from the Breedon Review: a progress report (November 2012)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides an update for each recommendation made by the industry taskforce on non-bank lending led by Tim Breedon. See also See 12/668 for the taskforce report, and 12/669 for the government response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48210</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-school-mid-sized-business-msb-collaboration-supporting-growth-in-the-uks-mid-sized-businesses"/>
    <title>Business school/mid-sized business (MSB) collaboration: supporting growth in the UK's mid-sized businesses</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarises findings and recommendations from the business school mid-sized business (MSB) task force set up by BIS in November 2011. While the Task Force has uncovered many examples of effective business school engagement with MSBs, there is much more tha&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47151</id>
    <published>2012-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/global-entrepreneurship-week-2012"/>
    <title>Global Entrepreneurship Week 2012</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The campaign to celebrate entrepreneurialism takes place from 12-18 November in over 115 countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s theme is ‘pass it on’. The aim is to pass on practical help and support to start-ups and people who are thinking about getting into business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Global-Entrepreneurship-Week-Ministers-recruit-entrepreneur-advisors-during-biggest-ever-celebration-of-enterprise-68300.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Ministers recruit entrepreneur advisors during biggest ever celebration of enterprise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are taking part in events during the week and making a number of announcements. Read Business Minister &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/blog/2012/11/09/supporting-global-entrepreneurship-week/"&gt;Michael Fallon’s blog&lt;/a&gt; on some of the events he’ll be involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year over 900 partner organisations got involved in the week here in the UK, reaching 213,000 people through 2,305 activities. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gew.org.uk/about/what_happened_in_2011"&gt;Read more about the 2011 campaign. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of GEW is to create a collaborative, local and practical week which enables people to learn more about the wealth of support that is available to entrepreneurs in the UK. This includes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encouraging people who are not yet entrepreneurs to think about starting up their own business. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving entrepreneurship skills for aspiring entrepreneurs and start-ups. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping people access practical support - locally, regionally and nationally. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government is also running the Business in You campaign that promotes the range of existing support services to help people start or grow their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to find out how exports can help grow your business? Next week UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment are also running &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.exportweek.ukti.gov.uk/full/"&gt;Export Week (12-16 November)&lt;/a&gt; with over a hundred events organised across the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gew.org.uk/home"&gt;Global Entrepreneurship Week 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/enterprise-and-business-support"&gt;Enterprise and business support at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/enterprise-and-business-support/entrepreneurial-culture"&gt;Entrepreneurial Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48187</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-copyright-licensing"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: copyright licensing</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to copyright licensing. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48188</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-debtor-petition-reform"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: debtor petition reform</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to reform of the process by which an individual may apply for his or her own bankruptcy. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48156</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/no-stone-unturned-chambers-of-commerce-international-comparisons"/>
    <title>No stone unturned: chambers of commerce international comparisons</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Study of chambers of commerce by Lord Heseltine that compares the support systems available to private sector in competing economies. Based on a survey of  practices overseas, the report includes origins, comparisons of public and private chamber models,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54938</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/no-stone-unturned-in-pursuit-of-growth"/>
    <title>No stone unturned: in pursuit of growth. Lord Heseltine review</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine has set out a comprehensive economic plan to improve the UK’s ability to create wealth. His independent report makes the case for a major rebalancing of responsibilities for economic development between central and local government, and between government and the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report ‘No stone unturned in pursuit of growth’ makes 89 recommendations which aim to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inject stability into the economy &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create the conditions for growth, and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maximise the performance of the UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the proposals are measures to unleash the potential of local economies and leaders and enable every part of the UK economy to raise its game. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition Lord Heseltine has produced No stone unturned: chamber of commerce - international comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine presented his report to the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Business Secretary Vince Cable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="heseltine-review-a-new-partnership-for-growth"&gt;Heseltine review: ‘A new partnership for growth’&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government provided a first response Lord Heseltine’s Review at Autumn Statement focusing on local economic growth with a fuller response to come in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response sets a direction for the devolution of government spending to local areas and responds to other parts of Lord Heseltine’s recommendations. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;empowering Local Economic Partnerships (LEPs) and devolution of some central funding streams into a single pot from 2015 onwards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regional Growth Fund; government will provide a further £350 million for the Regional Growth Fund, of which £100 million is being contributed from existing budgets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined Local Authorities; government will support local authorities who wish to create a combined authority or collaborations, including ensuring the existing legislation is fit for purpose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a package of regulatory changes to improve how regulations that affect businesses of all kinds are enforced; in addition, government will operate a One-In Two-Out rule on regulation from January 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information on the initial government response can be found in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_chapter_1b.pdf"&gt;Autumn statement 2012 chapter 1b: growth&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48171</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-and-regulatory-reform-bill-policy-paper"/>
    <title>Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill: policy paper</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains why the Government is undertaking the measures contained in this Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill, and explains what each measure aims to achieve. Also provides more detail on the clauses of the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
