<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-it-easier-to-set-up-and-grow-a-business--6/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making it easier to set up and grow a business "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59921</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T14:07:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-home-business-guide"/>
    <title>The Home Business Guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A guide to starting and growing a business from home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57424</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The government has today published new data detailing lending by specific banks through the Enterprise Finance Guarantee scheme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past 5 years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/57077</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:38:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"/>
    <title>Update on Enterprise Finance Guarantee lending  </title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by Minister for Business and Enterprise Rt Hon Michael Fallon on new data detailing lending by specific banks.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures by individual bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to ensuring that viable small and medium-size enterprises can obtain the finance they need for working capital and investment. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; plays an important part in this, with over 9,900 &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; being offered loans with a value in excess of £1 billion since May 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has made a number of important changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme during the last twelve months. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans are now available to an additional 3,800 businesses with an increase in the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million. The maximum £1 million lifetime scheme limit has been replaced by a rolling £1 million limit. We also raised by 7%, the level of lenders &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; annual loan portfolios to which the Government guarantee applies from 13% to 20%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was made to address the legitimate concern of lenders that they would breach their annual claim limit. In doing this, the Government committed to a more even share of the risk of default with the lenders, with the aim of removing that as a barrier to lending &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; is a demand led scheme, accounting for one to two per cent of overall &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; lending. While utilisation is directly linked to subdued demand for credit in the wider economy, overall &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending levels are disappointing. There have been some positive signs, with a number of the main banks increasing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending this financial year, albeit from a low level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that banks lend responsibly and make use of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; when it is appropriate to do so, but it is clear from the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures that a number of lenders could and should be doing more. The publication of individual bank &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures is intended to help achieve this. In parallel, we are exploring with the banks ways of flexing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; to address debt serviceability, which is the principal reason behind loan declines. Further detail will be provided in the New Year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, already publishes a wide range of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures, which are updated on a quarterly basis. Publication of individual &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures will further enhance this, allowing business customers to identify which banks are making most use of the scheme, and also enable participating lenders and new market entrants to identity new opportunities, thus increasing choice and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a further step towards greater transparency in bank lending, specifically to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"&gt;The full list of available &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60156</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T13:08:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"/>
    <title>Number and value of Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) scheme loans drawn.</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number and value of EFG loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60131</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New Innovation Vouchers for businesses who want to use public open data to develop new ideas, improve processes and target new markets.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next 3 years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;growing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;seeking intellectual property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the agri-food, built environment, space industries, energy, water and waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for agri-food, built environment and space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;intellectual property advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56643</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:05:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-business-link-helpline"/>
    <title>Assessment of the Business Link helpline</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Provides an early understanding of how effectively the Business Link helpline is performing. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether the Business Link helpline is performing effectively against its strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’, in which more businesses are assisted online rather than through other higher cost provision (for example face-to-face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the research has assessed the value of the service being provided to callers and how far actual demand has matched expectations. The findings are being used to help inform plans for continual improvement of the service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is based on interviews with helpline staff, analysis of monitoring data, call case studies and a customer survey that consisted of 657 telephone interviews that were completed with customers of the helpline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56755</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T10:13:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assessment-of-the-online-business-support-offer-growth-and-improvement-service-my-new-business"/>
    <title>Assessment of the online business support offer: Growth and Improvement Service, My New Business</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Assesses whether the new Business Link website services were performing effectively in their strategic role of digital transformation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study provides the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) with an early understanding of whether online business support services provided by Business Link have performed effectively against the strategic objective of ‘digital transformation’.  That is to successfully assist businesses through a website rather than through higher cost services (for example face to face contact). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study also makes an early assessment of the value of the services provided to new users, with a focus on cost effectiveness and effective referral to other appropriate business support services in the public, private and third sectors. The support services include the comprehensive start-up service provided by My New Business, and online tools provided by the Growth Improvement Service, enabling businesses to identify and solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/54863</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T13:31:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/analysis-of-the-distribution-of-private-sector-enterprises-by-turnover"/>
    <title>Analysis of the distribution of private sector enterprises by turnover</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counts of private sector enterprises by turnover from Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) June 2012. Published by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/39716</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T08:23:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-2012"/>
    <title>Autumn Statement 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Chancellor of the Exchequer, George Osborne, has delivered his 2012 Autumn Statement to Parliament.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement is one of two major statements the Treasury has to give to parliament every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Statement provides an update on the Government’s plans for the economy based on the latest forecasts from the Office for Budget Responsibility. These forecasts are published alongside the Autumn Statement on 5 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From today’s update of the government’s spending plans, the Department for Business has secured £2.4 billion of additional funding to support growth, with a focus on skills and science projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money reinforces the government’s commitment to plan for medium and long term recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will aid the development of an industrial strategy to shape and rebalance our economy, in partnership with business. This will drive growth, create the jobs of the future and help us get ahead in the global race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="main-announcements-for-bis"&gt;Main announcements for BIS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional £600 million for science, research and innovation, which takes the total investment since the 2010 spending review to an additional £1.5 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £270 million to be spent on laboratories, classrooms and other facilities in our Further Education colleges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1 billion confirmed for the business bank, which will address the long-term structural gap in lending to small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extra £120 million invested in supply chains, to encourage companies to invest here in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Regional Growth Fund will also receive an additional £350 million, bringing the total available in 2012-13 to £2.75 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first stage of the government’s response to Lord Heseltine’s independent review on economic growth, ‘No Stone Unturned’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra money for the Employer Ownership Pilot, taking it to £340 million overall and giving businesses funding so they can design and develop their own training programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased funding of £140 million for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) to help small and medium sized business export abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£1.5 billion to help our smallest companies to access growing markets overseas. For the first time UK Export Finance, the Government’s export credit agency, will be able to issue loans to overseas customers and buyers wanting to purchase goods from UK businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A package of measures to cut back red tape that business has told government stops them from growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="science-and-innovation"&gt;Science and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the Spending Review in 2010 the yearly £4.6 billion funding for science and research programmes has been protected in cash terms and ring-fenced during the spending review period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £600 million announced today will be invested in facilities for technological research and development and Research Council infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This amounts to an additional £1.5 billion of capital funding for science, research and innovation since the beginning of the Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will support the development of innovative technologies and strengthen the UK‘s competitive advantage in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data and energy efficient computing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about how the £600 million will be spent will be published in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science budget will continue to be protected and ring-fenced for the rest of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2012_index.htm"&gt;HM Treasury - Autumn Statement 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
