<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/reducing-greenhouse-gases-and-other-emissions-from-transport/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-greenhouse-gases-and-other-emissions-from-transport/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/reducing-greenhouse-gases-and-other-emissions-from-transport/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Reducing greenhouse gases and other emissions from transport"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T11:11:06+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61045</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:11:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-project-summaries"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund project summaries</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Local Sustainable Transport Fund project summary information.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has awarded Local Sustainable Transport Fund (&lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport Fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt;) funding in 3 streams. Tranche 1 and key component projects were awarded in July 2011. This was followed by 2 funding announcements in May and June 2012, for large projects above £5 million and tranche 2 of smaller projects. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61052</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:11:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-sustainable-transport-fund-application-process-and-bidding-guidance"/>
    <title>Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process and bidding guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance on the Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These documents were produced to support the Local Sustainable Transport Fund application process. They were published and made available to all project teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56725</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:32:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"/>
    <title>Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation guidance for suppliers</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Seeking views on revised guidance about complying with the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation which take latest legislation into account.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of it comes from sustainable renewable sources. Guidance has been in place to assist suppliers with compliance since the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; was first introduced. Obligated suppliers are consulted each year on revisions to the guidance. These have taken into account the latest European and domestic legislative developments and experience in operating the obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"&gt;Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/57003</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:29:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"/>
    <title>Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An assessment of the tallow market and impacts caused by changes to the way renewable energy targets are counted by EU member states.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport asked Ecofys to produce a report on the current animal fat (tallow) market to assess whether there has been any impact from allowing double counting of biodiesel produced from category 1 tallow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to explain the issue, the risks, and the available data relating to the tallow market to enable the department to set out its approach to monitoring impacts and also seek stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"&gt;Consultation about the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation suppliers’ guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17618</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T09:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/green-bus-fund-round-4"/>
    <title>Green Bus Fund round 4</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance and bidding documents for bus operators and local authorities to submit bids for the 4th round of the Green Bus Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Bus Fund supports bus companies and local authorities in England to help them buy new low carbon buses. Its main purpose is to support and speed up the introduction of hundreds of low carbon buses across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bidding guidance and documents are intended for bus operators and local authorities who want to submit bids for grant under the 4th round of the government’s Green Bus Fund. The bidding guidance explains the eligibility terms, the bidding process and how bids should be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16537</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T11:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-uk-bus-awards-lunch-speech"/>
    <title>2012 UK Bus Awards lunch speech</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also for inviting me along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pleasure to be here today at my third consecutive UK Bus Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s one for every Transport Secretary since I became a Minister at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I’m lucky enough to be sharing the stage with Jane (Jane Hill – BBC News).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A journalist and a newsreader, a TV anchor and a radio presenter - Jane is one of the country’s most familiar faces and familiar voices.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have it on good authority that Jane is a big fan of Radio 4’s “The Archers”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A drama come soap opera that seems to have been around forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters that not too many of the public would recognise in the street&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And people living in a make-believe world which critics claim bears little resemblance to everyday life in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say this all sounds a bit like the House of Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="speaking-up-for-the-bus-industry"&gt;Speaking up for the bus industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I hope I’ve not just been the consistent Ministerial face at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; - I’ve also tried to be a consistent voice when it comes to speaking up for the bus industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve said it before and I’ll keep on saying it - Britain’s buses matter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are a few familiar facts and figures that prove why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bus travel accounts for 63% of all public transport journeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last year in Great Britain buses clocked up 5.2 billion passenger journeys &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, as well as contributing more than £2 billion a year to the economy, the bus industry provides 124,000 direct jobs and supports an estimated 83,000 jobs through the supply chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buses also open up access to vital public services such as health and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, they provide a transport link between worker and workplace, with some two and a half million jobs accessed every day by bus, which is more than by all other forms of public transport combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, increasingly, buses are also helping to safeguard our environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, thanks to this government’s “&lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/background-to-the-green-bus-fund"&gt;Green Bus Fund&lt;/a&gt;” we’re seeing more and more low emission buses on our streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buses that emit around 30 per cent fewer greenhouse gas emissions than standard diesel buses and use around a third less fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And earlier this month I was pleased to announce an extra £20 million for what is now the 4th round of the Green Bus Fund, bringing the total support for this initiative to £95 million since its launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As highlighted in Greener Journey’s “Buses and Economic Growth Report” not only are buses the backbone of our public transport system, they can also boost economic growth and cut carbon by reducing congestion and replacing car journeys. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-industry-equal-to-testing-times"&gt;An industry equal to testing times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This then is an industry that makes a difference. But it’s also an industry that isn’t short of challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; and concessionary travel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;abbr title="Bus Service Operators Grant"&gt;BSOG&lt;/abbr&gt; I of course recognise that the rate was cut by 20% from April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also think it’s worth remembering that the Government realised the importance of giving you plenty of time to get ready for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why we gave the bus market 18 months advance notice of the change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me say this on the issue of concessionary travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve made sure that bus operators will be reimbursed so that they are “no better and no worse off” by carrying concessionary passengers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because, we want the processes surrounding this to be as fair as possible, we’ve also speeded up the appeals mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I know that it’s not easy for operators right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluctuating fuel prices and the backdrop of a tough economic climate make these testing times for businesses and families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show bus patronage was down 0.3% in non-metropolitan areas and while this is unwelcoming it is far from the apocalypse scene commentators were predicting. Indeed overall, bus patronage across England rose by 0.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also pleased to see that 85% of bus passengers are satisfied with their service. And even in the area of lowest satisfaction it was still 79%. I haven’t seen the latest comparable figures for satisfaction with politicians and journalists but I’m told it’s not quite that high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, these may be testing times but, once again, the industry is showing itself to be equal to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="green-light-for-better-buses"&gt;Green Light for Better Buses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I sense a mood of quiet optimism that was especially tangible at the recent 2012 Euro Bus Expo, which I was delighted to open and where I was able to speak with many in the industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know that there is more to do. Now is not the time for the engine to tick over at the bus stop, we have to keep moving forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why earlier this year I set out my vision for buses in the &lt;a href="/government/publications/green-light-for-better-buses"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; policy document, “Green Light for Better Buses.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this report will help provide stability in the industry by reforming subsidy, improving competition and Incentivise partnership working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its heart is a shared vision for a bus service that is reliable and flexible, efficient and innovative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that offers competitive prices and smarter ticketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that gives taxpayers real value for money and passengers a travel option they want to use time and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that is successful and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bus service that people want to use, not one they use because they have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="young-people"&gt;Young People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that one of the best ways to ensure success and sustainability over the long-term is to encourage much greater bus travel among that section of the market that is literally the future of the industry - young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a challenge that cannot be side-stepped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, just this month the Youth Select Committee published its report on “Transport and Young People.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That report called for the age at which young people start paying full fares to be set at 18 across England and for the introduction of a national concessionary scheme to provide a discounted bus travel card for those younger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I am looking at this report very seriously and I really do want to work with operators, and also local authorities, to improve the deal for our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as I said, this is a challenge we have to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also an opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s think about all the ways we can use bus services to help young people access employment and training opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make bus travel easy and attractive for young people by building on initiatives like CPT’s  (Confederation of Passenger Transport) excellent “Bus for Us” interactive website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that, since I launched it, over 80 of the UK’s bus operators are already signed up to “Bus for Us”  - equivalent to 85% of the bus market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to see all operators on board in the near future. There’s room on top for the rest. My message to the remaining 15% is “don’t miss the bus”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also be innovative about the fare deals and the discounts on offer to young people…and the great work done by Trent Barton in this area shows it can be done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s deliver some consistency too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, TCA- led youth concessions are offered in 28 TCAs outside London, and a commercial youth concession is available in 80 TCAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are some good things going on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is it that in some places there are no concessions at all? And how can it be that in one area a 16 year old might get free bus travel while, in another, a 14-year old pays full adult fare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s come together and work together to support our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, let’s win over the next generation of bus passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pay-tribute-to-all-the-nominees"&gt;Pay tribute to all the nominees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let me return to the reason why we are all here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I’m proud to be the bus champion in government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m also just as proud of the people and organisations working in the bus industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, this afternoon, we rightly take the time to recognise some of the brightest and the best in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty two categories in this year’s awards: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individuals and teams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local authorities and  operators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cities and shires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small projects and big projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All making today’s shortlist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all with something in common….excellence and achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, these awards show that the hallmarks of your industry are innovation, professionalism and sheer hard work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also show that, at its heart, your industry is all about people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can talk about investment. And we can debate the pros and cons of one policy versus another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when push comes to shove, it’s the people in the bus industry who make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference because they understand the needs of the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference because they want to provide a first class service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the difference by delivering real improvements on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who, and what, we are honouring today….and so I pay tribute to all of this year’s nominees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. They do say that making a speech is a bit like having a fight – any fool can start one, the real skill is knowing when and how to end it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I know you’re keen to get on with handing out those awards, so you’ll be pleased to hear that the “when” has arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for “how to end it” it simply remains for me to thank you for your hospitality, to thank you for listening and to wish all those waiting to hear if they’ve won the very best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you and hopefully I’ll see you all next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15105</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T12:52:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"/>
    <title>Low carbon bus calculator</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This toolkit can be used to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (LCEB).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise that the benefits of purchasing a low carbon bus will be different for each operator and will depend on the way in which the bus in service is used. So, Department for Transport economists have produced a transparent, user-friendly toolkit to be used by bus operators and local authorities to calculate the likely benefits on investing in a low carbon emission bus (&lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;). Your assessment should always compare the &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; to an equivalent diesel bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit allows you flexibility in changing the input assumptions to those most relevant to you. You will be able to assess the financial implications of purchasing a &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt;, based on the fuel savings on offer (as advised by &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;LCEB&lt;/abbr&gt; manufacturers or experienced in trials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet tool is intended to provide indicative estimates only and &lt;abbr title="low carbon emission bus"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; does not vouch for the accuracy of such estimates. Please note that the Department for Transport does not accept any liability for any decisions that may be taken on the basis of such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit will be routinely updated and refined. Details of any updates or changes that are made will be outlined in the ‘Intro’ worksheet of the toolkit. We therefore encourage you to visit this website regularly and download the toolkit to ensure you are using the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16656</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T15:54:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/suffolk-sustainable-transport-forum"/>
    <title>Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jYG7r0lJIaE&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA" title="Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum"&gt;Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me to talk to your forum today. It seems fitting that I should be with you virtually to discuss our collective goals of creating growth whilst cutting carbon at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome the development of the Suffolk Sustainable Transport Forum and the involvement of Hutchison Ports UK, BT and Suffolk County Council. This is a great example of joint working, both across business sectors and also between business and local government. I also understand that the New Anglia Local Enterprise Partnership is also working across the private and public sector on their Green Economy Pathfinder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low carbon transport plays a key role in the wider drive towards sustainable economic growth, this is as true on the local level as it is on the national and international level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we allocated a new £600 million Local Sustainable Transport funding for local projects which create growth and cut carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will be aware, Suffolk received £5 million for their Lowestoft Local Links project. This package includes improved pedestrian and cycle infrastructure, increased bus services, improvements to transport interchange hubs, enhanced travel planning provisions, and more. I was pleased to visit Lowestoft this time last year and get a sense of how this will be transforming access to and around the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also investing more widely in green public transport, for example through our national programme of rail electrification or the £30 million Green Bus Fund. Each year, every low-carbon bus outside London saves around 22 tonnes of CO2 compared with its diesel equivalent. Anglian Bus Ltd in Suffolk has been awarded £624,000 to fund 13 low carbon buses, and I look forward to seeing these roll out of the garages and on to the roads, they offer a more comfortable, more reliable and much greener experience for bus passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses have been closely involved in the planning and delivery of Local Sustainable Transport projects in Suffolk, and indeed across the 96 projects in 77 authorities that are going ahead because of the Fund.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses are doing this because they realise the benefits of an integrated transport system that allows easy access to workplaces; because of the reduced absenteeism that results from employees choosing a more active lifestyle; and because of the transformation of the local urban and rural environments that can result from an increased uptake of sustainable modes of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are also showing support by embracing alternatives to travel in their day-to-day office environments. Endorsing the use of technology, such as video speeches and teleconferencing, and supporting greater uptake of flexible working amongst staff can bring about an array of benefits. Reducing business flights and consolidating office space can lead to notable cost savings. And both research and experience have shown that employee productivity and wellbeing can be improved when we take a more flexible approach to the working day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympics proved a challenge and opportunity in this regard. Businesses and government understood that transport would be much busier than usual and that change was necessary. So employees came in to work and left for home earlier to escape the rush hour, they hopped on their bikes rather than hopping on the tube to escape the underground, or they stayed home and logged on rather than getting behind the wheel of a car, escaping the office altogether. The result was not just one of the most successful Games in history, but also one where transport was universally praised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the department is also investing more widely in transport infrastructure in the region, for example through the £22 million transport package for Ipswich. This is an innovative and exciting programme of work that will see Ipswich town centre become a thriving sustainable transport hub, and has the potential to transform the way people travel in and around Ipswich. Indeed, residents are already benefiting from new traffic management measures and cycle and pedestrian facilities, facilitating access to Suffolk College.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just about providing policies and funding for transport. We also need to invest in relationships. And that is why I  support fora like this which discuss common challenges, build partnerships,  share best practice and generate solutions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thank you for inviting me, and good luck with your work. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16285</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/biofuels-the-renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-progress-on-adoption-and-the-next-generation"/>
    <title>Biofuels: the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation, progress on adoption and the next generation </title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Norman Baker MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the Westminster Energy, Environment and Transport forum for inviting me to speak at your event this morning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to have the chance to talk to you about the possible next steps on biofuels policy. First though, I want to talk a bit about how we got to where we are today, and in particular about developments over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition government has stuck by its commitment to cut the carbon footprint of road transport by implementing measures which promote the use of renewable energy, including of course biofuels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concerted effort has not only contributed towards the European Renewable Energy Directive and Fuel Quality Directive targets, but also, in the case of sustainable biofuels, to our international obligations on climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took an important step towards the goal of truly sustainable biofuels when we implemented the transport elements of the Renewable Energy Directive last December. The introduction of mandatory sustainability criteria means that to benefit from incentives under the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) biofuels must now, with some exceptions, deliver greenhouse gas savings of at least 35% compared to fossil fuels. They also cannot be sourced from areas of high biodiversity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes we made to the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; last year also introduced double counting. This provides a further incentive for biofuels made from wastes and residues, in recognition that these feedstocks are unlikely to compete with food production or contribute to indirect land use change. In the first 4 years of the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;, the proportion of biofuels produced from wastes, rather than crops, increased from 12% to 49%.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am confident that we have already made significant progress towards ensuring that biofuels used in the UK are sustainable. Indeed, in my view it is imperative that the UK biofuel industry continues to invest and grow.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be able to open the Agri Energy biodiesel plant in Bootle in Liverpool this year….a large new investment that will see the collection of wastes turned into biodiesel.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it is vital that we keep seeing profitable investments like this which produce low carbon energy, provide jobs and help us to meet our ambitious carbon reduction targets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while biofuels should be a key means of achieving carbon reduction targets, we also know that some biofuels still carry sustainability risks. We remain very concerned that studies have demonstrated that some biofuels can even produce greater carbon emissions than fossil fuels, particularly when indirect land use change (or &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt;) is factored in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have consistently made clear at European level that &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt; needs to be addressed urgently to ensure that people can be confident that available biofuels mean genuine &lt;abbr title="greenhouse gas"&gt;GHG&lt;/abbr&gt; savings.  It is very much in the interests of the biofuel industry itself that we reach this point, and do so as soon as we can.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is helpful that the long awaited &lt;abbr title="indirect land use change"&gt;ILUC&lt;/abbr&gt; proposal was adopted and published by the European Commission last month. My officials and I are currently analysing the proposal and its implications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s proposal sets a 5% cap on the level of contribution food-crop-based feedstocks can make to our 10% &lt;abbr title="Renewable Energy Directive"&gt;RED&lt;/abbr&gt; transport target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal also includes additional support for advanced biofuels, seeking to encourage further development in feedstocks which do not compete for food, feed or land.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to ensure that we have a settled policy framework based on good scientific evidence, and I hope that these European developments can move towards this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime though, I genuinely do not believe that setting further short term interim targets can provide the clarity industry continues to demand.  It might give the veneer of certainty over a body of doubt.  Although I fully appreciate that industry needs clarity on future policy to plan investment, it is equally crucial that government’s policy achieves what it is meant to deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I have adopted a cautious approach in setting future biofuel targets within the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation.  Better in my view to go slower in a direction that is certain rather than to go fast and have to change direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been too many examples of government moving too quickly forward on a policy which they have later had to pull back on.  Furthermore, industry tells me that it is certainty they want, not an impression of certainty which turns out to be vacuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I can assure you that we will continue to investigate potentially helpful options, such as the advanced biofuels, which I believe offer a real opportunity for investment and growth for the whole economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the longer term the advancement of the biofuels industry will surely rely on the development and commercialisation of many of these new technologies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also interested in the potential to use biofuels in sectors where, at present, there are limited options to decarbonise…. such as in aviation and &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, I recognise the importance of biomethane made from waste as a sustainable renewable transport fuel, particularly in the heavy goods vehicle sector where there are real market barriers to uptake of low emission technologies such as hybrid, electric and gas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support the use of lower emission &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; technologies, the Department for Transport has made available over £11 million capital funding to trial low carbon lorries and their supporting infrastructure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 projects, trialling over 300 vehicles between them, will receive funding towards the cost of low emission &lt;abbr title="heavy goods vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; technologies.  The funding is also being used to help establish gas refuelling infrastructure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This initiative will increase the number of low carbon lorries on the road but it will also provide vital information on the performance of these vehicles in the real world….something that will help encourage wider uptake of lower carbon lorries and promote the use of biomethane as a sustainable fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also keen to develop this technology for buses, and am doing so through the Green Bus Fund.
Biofuels are of course just 1 part of a wider strategy to encourage growth and cut carbon.  For example, we are also committed to supporting the uptake of ultra low carbon vehicles in the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spending Review announced provision of over £400 million to support the development of the ultra low emission vehicle market work to 2015.  This support package includes funding;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for recharging infrastructure  schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote the uptake of ultra-low emission cars through the Plug-In Car and Van Grants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of £82 million to support for research and development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition UKH2Mobility was launched last January. This joint undertaking with key industry stakeholders will evaluate the potential for hydrogen as a fuel for ultra low carbon vehicles in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biofuels have become an important part of the UK economy, of our national infrastructure and of efforts to meet our international emission and energy targets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we are focused on ensuring that this national resource is used appropriately and that the full consequences of growing biofuels are considered and assessed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coalition government believes that it is possible both to safeguard the environment and support the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that these goals are not incompatible. Quite the reverse. They are in fact 2 sides of the same coin. You can cut carbon and boost growth and our work with biofuels is proof of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK biofuels industry continues to lead the world in sustainable and renewable fuels and I am proud of the efforts and achievements the industry has made so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain our lead in this industry and to address barriers to supply, we need to continue to work closely with suppliers and to listen to concerns raised about the social and environmental sustainability of biofuels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way not only will we get the best deal for the industry, the taxpayer and the consumer… we will get the right policies for our the transport sector, the economy and the environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14385</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T13:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T13:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/double-boost-for-carbon-cutting-buses"/>
    <title>Double boost for carbon cutting buses</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An extra £20 million is being made available for the government’s Green Bus Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An extra £20 million is being made available for the government’s Green Bus Fund Transport Minister Norman Baker has announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in a second boost for low carbon buses Mr Baker has today launched an easy-to-use toolkit to allow local authorities and bus operators to make informed decisions on investing in carbon cutting buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million funding will be the fourth round of the Green Bus Fund, bringing the total support for this initiative to £95 million since its launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional funding has been found from an underspend in the Department for Transport’s budget and those wishing to buy green buses will be able to apply for the round four support this financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cutting carbon emissions from transport is not a choice, it is a necessity and that is why I am prioritising green buses and giving operators and local authorities an extra £20 million to deliver on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our new toolkit will be indispensible in allowing those considering investment in low carbon buses to see the advantages for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new online low carbon bus calculator will make it easier to quickly work out the savings that can be made over time through cheaper running costs and fuel efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details on the bidding process and eligibility will be published soon on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new low carbon bus toolkit will help operators and local authorities work out how the finances might stack up, with or without support from the Green Bus Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those wanting to work out how long it will take for a low carbon bus to pay for itself can now go online and use the new calculator which will allow them to quickly work this out using assumptions around capital costs and fuel efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While buses using low carbon technologies tend to be more expensive than conventional buses many are eligible for government support and running costs are usually lower so that, over time, they are actually the more economical choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toolkit launched today will allow councils and operators to see at a glance how quickly they can expect a return on investment in low carbon buses using a variety of carbon saving technologies such as hybrid or electric buses. It also shows operators and local authorities the savings on offer through reduced running costs from low carbon buses compared with running a bus using conventional fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toolkit also allows the user to tailor the calculation of costs to their specific circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/low-carbon-bus-calculator"&gt;toolkit is available&lt;/a&gt; on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Round 4 of the Green Bus Fund was launched on the 6 November 2012. Bidding and eligibility guidance for the 4th round will be issued shortly on the Department for Transport website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland is holding a separate £3 million competition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The budget for round 4 of the Fund is £20 million with the funding coming from an underspend in the department’s budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the fourth round of the government’s grant. Round one was launched in 2009 and paid up to 100 per cent of the difference, with round two paying up to 90 per cent and round three up to 80 per cent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further details on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/background-to-the-green-bus-fund"&gt;fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buses funded through the Green Bus Fund are eligible for the Bus Service Operators Grant (BSOG) Low Carbon Bus incentive of 6p for every kilometre operated in service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous rounds of the Green Bus Fund have part funded diesel hybrid buses, which run on a combination of diesel and a battery, fully electric buses and biomethane-fuelled gas buses. Eligibility for the 4th round will be published shortly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each year, every low carbon bus in London saves around 26 tonnes of CO2 compared with its diesel equivalent, with buses outside London estimated to save around 22 tonnes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/investment-in-green-buses"&gt;Investment in Green Buses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
