<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making sure Council Tax payers get good value for money"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13405</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-when-dwellings-should-not-be-liable-to-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: when dwellings should not be liable to the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions that will allow a billing authority to charge an empty homes premium to provide a stronger incentive to get homes back into productive use and remove the blight of such properties on local neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premium was subject to a consultation, ‘Technical Reforms to Council Tax’, which ended on 29 December 2011. The government published its response on 28 May 2012, which confirmed its intention to proceed with the premium and stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will not be payable until a dwelling has been empty and unfurnished for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the maximum premium that an authority will be able to charge will be 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the government’s proposals on exceptions to the premium: dwellings which may otherwise be liable for the premium, but which are subject to circumstances that mean that it would not be appropriate for it to apply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13401</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: caluclating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12786</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-referendums-to-veto-excessive-council-tax-increases"/>
    <title>Local referendums to veto excessive Council Tax increases</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coalition programme for government included a commitment to give residents a veto over excessive increases in their Council Tax bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation document sets out the basic principles underpinning the proposed scheme, and seeks views on the practicality and technical feasibility of the mechanisms for triggerring and holding a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12785</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/council-tax-student-discounts"/>
    <title>Council Tax: student discounts</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on a proposal to allow persons who are undertaking a full-time course of education with an educational establishment situated in any Member State of the European Union to be treated as students resident in the UK for Council Tax purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note this is a joint consultation with the Welsh Assembly Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12761</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-councils-funding-community-and-voluntary-groups"/>
    <title>Local councils: funding community and voluntary groups</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department is consulting on new best value guidance, setting out some reasonable expectations of the way local councils should work with voluntary and community groups when facing difficult funding decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would welcome comments from any organisations and individuals affected by the new guidance and any others with an interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12749</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-pension-scheme-proposed-changes-to-employee-contribution-and-accrual-rates"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme: proposed changes to employee contribution and accrual rates</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper sets out the government’s draft proposals to achieve short-term savings of £900 million within the local government pension scheme by 2014-15, equivalent to the 3.2% contribution increases in the unfunded public service pension schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12737</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"/>
    <title>Technical reforms of Council Tax</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper discusses options in relation to the Council Tax liabilities of second home owners, and of the owners of empty properties, in England, including proposals which would require primary legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also covers potential reforms of several details of the Council Tax system including modernising arrangements for payment of Council Tax by instalments, for delivering the information to be supplied with demand notices, and the treatment of annexes to dwellings; and some broadly administrative matters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12144</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:47:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-hanham-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Baroness Hanham praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and the state of the art library, which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medallist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medallists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torchbearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. This will save Wiltshire’s Council Tax payers at least £85 million. As two-thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14747</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Minister praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a visit to Wiltshire Council Baroness Hanham saw first-hand the significant achievements made by the council whose trailblazing assets management strategies are protecting frontline services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and state of the art library which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medalist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medalists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torch bearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will save Wilstshire’s council tax payers at least £85 million. As two thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images from Baroness Hanham’s visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631902676938/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
