<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making sure Council Tax payers get good value for money"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16714</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: calculating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16890</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T14:26:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/weekly-collection-saved-as-government-scheme-delivers-for-6-million-families"/>
    <title>‘Weekly collection saved’ as government scheme delivers for 6 million families </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is thanks to the government’s £250 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/supporting-pages/bins-and-waste-collection"&gt;Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best 90 projects, from 85 councils, have today been selected from an over-subscribed scheme to share in the funding. Ministers are concerned that without the fund weekly bin collections could have all but disappeared by 2015, as is happening in other parts of the United Kingdom, such as Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Disraeli’s Public Health Act 1875 which first introduced a duty on local authorities to collect rubbish; this duty was enhanced by the Public Health Act 1936 obliging councils to collect household waste weekly. Weekly collections were the norm for decades, but started disappearing from 2000 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, 41 schemes will offer genuine rewards (such as shopping vouchers or loyalty points) for recycling so more families can go green without facing punitive fines and taxes, meeting an important coalition agreement pledge. It is hoped that such new schemes will encourage further take-up across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund was set up in February to support comprehensive and cost effective weekly collections that harness innovation, use new technology and spread reward schemes to increase recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils already receive funding for bin collections through central government formula grant and from the money raised locally via Council Tax: in total, council spending will be £114 million this year. A further 4 million households continue to provide weekly collections outside the support scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. Another survey found that two-thirds of the public thought government should mandate weekly collections; that weekly collections were better; and that problems with flies and smells were much worse with fortnightly collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government has already scrapped bin taxes plans via the Localism Act; reversed Audit Commission rules which marked down councils for not adopting fortnightly rubbish collections; and abolished Whitehall targets which created perverse incentives to downgrade waste collection services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will continue to work with Defra to spread best practice on weekly collections, challenge poor procurement or unpopular approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every Englishman has a basic right to have their household rubbish taken away each and every week - it is the most visible council service people get. Yet under the previous administration weekly bin collections halved while their Council Tax bills doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over 6 million families will breathe a sigh of relief tonight because we have put a stop to the fetid fortnightly rot and saved many weekly collections from extinction, all while increasing recycling rates by hundreds of thousands of tonnes to boot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Weekly Collection Support Scheme encourages councils to focus on 4 things: better weekly collections, cost effective bids, environmental improvements and better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment. 118 councils submitted final bids. For more information, see the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15038/Weekly_Collection_Support_Scheme_-_successful_bids.xls"&gt;list of 90 winning bids&lt;/a&gt;, which gives a short description of what each of the schemes will do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence: opinion research they carried out actually found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. (Ipsos-MORI, ‘Weekly or fortnightly: Public attitudes to waste collections’, July 2008.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fortnightly collections rose from just 13 councils across the United Kingdom in 2000 to 225 in 2008 (Alternate weekly collections conference, aspects of alternate weekly collection, July 2008). In Northern Ireland, as of 2010 to 2011, 92% of local authorities offer a fortnightly collection; in Scotland 72%, and Wales 77% according to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wrap.org.uk/" title="WRAP"&gt;WRAP’s&lt;/a&gt;, local authority waste and recycling information portal, statistics for 2010 to 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Sauce-Icaro attitudes to waste and recycling in Great Britain, December 2011 found that two-thirds (67%) agreed with the statement the government should mandate weekly collections. Weekly collections had higher satisfaction levels than fortnightly (83% compared to 74%). Reports of problems with flies and smells for fortnightly collections were more than double that for weekly (14% compared to 6%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What next: in the weeks to come the department will begin working with councils, the Local Government Association and Defra to support them to work together to procure the best deals as consortiums or groups to ensure value for money for the taxpayer. This means the department has provided a synopsis of each successful bid, but will not be disclosing further specific bid details as this would have an adverse effect on competition between prospective companies and potentially put local authorities in a disadvantageous position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16636</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-when-dwellings-should-not-be-liable-to-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: when dwellings should not be liable to the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; allows a billing authority to charge an empty homes premium to provide a stronger incentive to get homes back into productive use and remove the blight of such properties on local neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premium was subject to a consultation, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"&gt;Technical Reforms to Council Tax&lt;/a&gt;’, which ended on 29 December 2011. The government published its response on 28 May 2012, which confirmed its intention to proceed with the premium and stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will not be payable until a dwelling has been empty and unfurnished for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the maximum premium that an authority will be able to charge will be 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation invited views on the government’s proposals on exceptions to the premium: dwellings which may otherwise be liable for the premium, but which are subject to circumstances that mean that it would not be appropriate for it to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary of responses was published on 21 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16427</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2012-in-england"/>
    <title>Council Taxbase 2012 in England</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2008 to 2012 updating those &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2011-in-england"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; previously issued on 16 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="number-of-dwellings"&gt;Number of dwellings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In England there were 22.4 million dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list liable for council tax as at 10 September 2012. This is an increase of 1% compared with 2011 and an increase of 3% compared with 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of dwellings on the valuation list that are exempt from council tax increased by 2% compared with 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;35% of all exemptions from council tax are class C (short term vacant dwellings). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A further 27% of all exemptions are class M or N (student related exemptions). Of these, class M exemptions have increased by more than 48% in the period 2008 to 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of class L exemptions (unoccupied dwellings repossessed by a mortgage lender) again fell between September 2011 and September 2012 to 9,400, the four consecutive annual fall. There are now 6,500 (or 41%) fewer class L exemptions than the peak in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7.7 million dwellings were entitled to a discount as a result of being occupied by single adults. This represents 33% of all dwellings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.7 million Band A dwellings (50% of all dwellings liable to Band A council tax) were entitled to a single adults discount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The total number of dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list in England as at 10 September 2012 was 23.2 million, an increase of 143,000, or 1% compared with 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="empty-properties"&gt;Empty properties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 2011 and 2012 the number of long-term empty dwellings subject to a discount fell by 28,000 (or 22%). In the same period the number of long-term empty dwellings not subject to a discount increased by 8,000 (or 5%). This gives a net reduction of 20,000, or 7%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2011 and 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of long term empty dwellings that were subject to a discount has fallen by 86,000, or 47%, between 2008 and 2012. In the same period the number of long term empty dwellings that do not receive a discount has increased by 18,000 or 13%. This gives a net reduction of 68,000, or 21%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2008 and 2012. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since the introduction of the New Homes Bonus in the summer of 2010 a large number of authorities have taken the opportunity to review the empty properties and second homes in their area. A number have also altered the level of discount awarded with many abolishing the discount for empty properties altogether.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12144</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:47:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-hanham-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Baroness Hanham praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and the state of the art library, which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medallist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medallists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torchbearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. This will save Wiltshire’s Council Tax payers at least £85 million. As two-thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14747</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Minister praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a visit to Wiltshire Council Baroness Hanham saw first-hand the significant achievements made by the council whose trailblazing assets management strategies are protecting frontline services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and state of the art library which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medalist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medalists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torch bearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will save Wilstshire’s council tax payers at least £85 million. As two thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images from Baroness Hanham’s visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631902676938/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/1735</id>
    <published>2012-10-11T23:06:16+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-11T23:06:16+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/250-million-fund-to-herald-return-of-better-weekly-collections"/>
    <title>£250 million fund to herald return of better weekly collections</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A fund of up to quarter of a billion pounds to help support councils to deliver better, more environmentally friendly weekly bin collections for residents is now open, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September last year the Government announced its intention to introduce a new weekly collection support scheme for councils that retain or reinstate weekly residual waste and recycling services. The new scheme will deliver benefits to the environment and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe that waste services have become too complex, leaving residents anxious about following the rules and possible penalties. They think councils should focus on 3 things: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better weekly collections&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better contracts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is additional funding to local government, financed from savings made to the Department for Communities and Local Government’s central budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new fund will help support reward schemes (for example, those like Windsor and Maidenhead’s Recyclebank scheme and Birmingham’s Nectar points scheme), where families are rewarded for recycling, delivering on a Coalition Agreement pledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also explicitly intends to tackle ‘bin blight’ and the proliferation of bins, by supporting new technology where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund will promote innovation, better procurement and joint working across local authorities. It intends to support a range of local initiatives to increase recycling and deliver weekly collections. It will seek to prioritise bids which support comprehensive weekly rubbish and recycling collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rubbish collections are the most visible service that people get for their £120 a month Council Tax bill. But barmy bin rules have made putting out your rubbish more complicated than solving a Rubik’s cube. The public are fed up of all the bin do’s and bin don’ts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People just want a comprehensive service in return for their Council Tax, which is why this Government is working with councils to increase the frequency and quality of rubbish and recycling collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caroline Spelman, Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to help people to go green by making it easier for them to do the right thing. This scheme will encourage councils to provide the services we believe residents really want, without sacrificing the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew Farrow, the Environmental Services Association’s Director of Policy, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Waste management companies want to collect and manage waste in ways which are both user friendly for the householder and benefit the environment. So we welcome the way in which the fund prioritises environmental criteria and services that meet the needs of householders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also support the encouragement given to local authorities to think innovatively and to work with the private sector. We look forward to working with their local authority customers to help them make best use of the opportunities the fund provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14718</id>
    <published>2012-10-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/third-year-of-council-tax-freeze-announced"/>
    <title>Third year of Council Tax freeze announced</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer has today announced new support for local authorities in England to help them freeze council tax for a further year and assist in keeping those bills down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government will set aside an extra £450 million to help freeze council tax bills in England. The support for local authorities means that taxpayers living in an average Band D home in England could save up to £72 on a five per cent rise in council tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years the Government has provided grants of around £2billion to help freeze council tax. A freeze in council tax in 2013-14 would represent a real terms cut of around two per cent and a fall of nine per cent in real terms over the past three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government’s council tax freeze has cut council tax in real terms over the last two years. A third-year’s freeze will mean the combined effect is potentially worth over £200 to Band D residents. Freezing bills again will really help hard working families and those on fixed incomes, such as pensioners with their cost of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £450million will be made available, through a new grant scheme, to local authorities who decide to freeze or reduce their council tax next year. If they do, councils, police and fire authorities will stand to receive £225million of funding in both financial years 2013-14 and 2014-15, equivalent to raising their 2012-13 council tax by one per cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, in 2013-14 the Government will propose to lower the local authority tax referendum threshold to two per cent. This would mean if a local authority seeks to raise its relevant basic amount of council tax by more than two per cent, local people would have the right to keep council tax bills down through a binding referendum veto. The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government will formally set out the detail on this in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A freeze in council tax this year will save families £72 compared to a five per cent rise, on top of the savings already made in 2011-12 and 2012-13. A freeze in 2013-14 represents a real terms cut of around two per cent, compared to latest inflation forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government will shortly write to all English local authorities with full details of the scheme, including providing an indicative breakdown of estimated grants to help local authorities with budget planning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The detail on the tax referendum thresholds will be formally set out by the Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government alongside the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement in December. The House of Commons will be asked to endorse the threshold levels before councils set their annual budgets in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The council tax freeze offer will apply separately to each billing and major precepting authority in England (rather than to each council tax bill issued). Billing authorities include shire districts, metropolitan districts, London Boroughs and unitary authorities and major precepting authorities include county councils, fire and rescue authorities, police authorities and the Greater London Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If an authority sets its basic amount of council tax (i.e. its Band D council tax) in 2013-14 at a level which is no more than its basic amount of council tax in 2012-13, it will receive a grant equivalent to a one per cent increase on the 2012-13 figure in both financial years 2013-14 and 2014-15. Police, Crime Commissioners and fire authorities will also receive a grant equivalent to one per cent of their 2012-13 basic amount of council tax.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An unringfenced grant in support of the scheme will be paid to each eligible billing and major precepting authority based on the formula. Payments to authorities will be made through the grant-making powers in section 31 of the Local Government Act 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local authorities who wish to reduce their council tax in absolute cash terms are still also eligible to receive the grant. Local authorities who choose to increase their council tax will not be eligible for the grant scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the Spending Review we have made available £1975million of funding to local authorities to freeze their council tax in 2011-12 and again in 2012-13. In 2011-12 every local authority in England took up the scheme, and council tax in England was frozen. In 2012-13 Government offered to help local authorities in England freeze their council tax again and 85 per cent of local authorities accepted. This limited increases in council tax across England to 0.3 per cent, the lowest increase since council tax was introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Average Band D council tax and percentage change between 1993-94 and 2012-13 are shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devolved Administrations will receive £43million of Barnett consequentials in both 2013-14 and 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
