<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making sure Council Tax payers get good value for money"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T16:59:13+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60063</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T16:59:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T16:59:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>"Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles spelled out 50 sensible savings, a Council Tax freeze and a fair funding deal as the “right road” for councils to protect residents and local services, as a major shake up of local finance was initiated today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister signalled the watershed moment for councils as he unveiled a new look local government finance settlement that will reward councils that strive to improve their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dramatic shift in spending power from Whitehall to the town hall means an estimated 70% of council income will now be raised locally compared to 56% under the centrally distributed ‘begging-bowl’ formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013 councils can channel this greater local control into encouraging local jobs and local firms via a new business rate retention incentive that rewards them for growth. It could potentially add £10 billion to the economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, councils account for a quarter of all public spending - with English councils still spending £114 billion - so it is vital they continue to play their part tackling the inherited budget deficit by making sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help councils in that regard a document containing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;50 practical ways to make sensible savings&lt;/a&gt; was published today. It shows how a culture change by councils can unearth significantly more taxpayer savings and help make services more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must keep doing their bit to tackle the inherited budget deficit because they account for a quarter of all public spending and still get through over £114 billion of taxpayers money each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement is a fair funding deal that will reward councils ready to strive for their communities and gives them another year to get their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must do 3 things to get on the right road for their residents: put our fair funding deal to work; do every single one of our 50 ways to save; and accept our Council Tax freeze offer. Councils that cry wolf without having done all of this are letting their residents down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils that put their thinking caps on now can save precious taxpayer pennies next year by cutting out waste and transforming frontline services that vulnerable people rely on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s fair funding deal arms councils with an average spending power of £2,240 per household. Local authorities have been protected from further spending reductions for 2013 to 2014. Overall the average spending power reduction for councils in 2013 to 2014 is expected to be limited to just 1.7% per household, less than last year’s comparable figure of 3.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe this important concession gives councils the time they need to transform service delivery, build up their local business rate income, improve procurement and comprehensively complete the suggested 50 savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total start-up funding assessment for councils 2013 to 2014 apportions £26 billion in a fair and sustainable way that ensures the smallest reductions for the councils most reliant on government support. More weighting has been given to areas with the highest levels of assessed need. For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is setting aside an extra £450 million over the next 2 years to help local government in England to freeze their Council Tax, equivalent to a 1% rise. A third year’s combined Council Tax freeze is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government confirmed today that where a council rejects the freeze, the majority will have to secure electoral agreement through a ‘local tax lock’ referendum to hike band D bills by more than 2%. Smaller authorities with a track record of low Council Tax will be given slightly more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘50 ways to save’ include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing back offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting Community Budgets to bring staff and money together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using transparency to cut waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clamping down on corporate charge cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting special spending controls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling the £2 billion of local fraud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising £16 billion of non-school reserves creatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve collection rates to reduce the £2.4 billion of uncollected Council Tax across England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage direct debit and e-billing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve property management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close subsidised council canteens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing senior pay and posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut spending on consultants and agency staff which had risen to £4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stop translating documents into foreign languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut expensive travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce printing costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hire out the town hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; for the full list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 to 2014 spending power calculation includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£26.07 billion start up funding assessment (which includes £10.9 billion of locally retained business rates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£23.9 billion in Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£859 million for NHS funding to support social care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£661 million via New Homes Bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£240 million for 2013 to 2014 Council Tax freeze grant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition local authorities will also benefit from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£112 million via the Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£33.5 million via New Burdens for Council Tax Support in 2013 to 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39394/Local_Authority_briefing_table_201314.xls"&gt;Spending power data by local authority for 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;No authority will see a spending power reduction of more than 8.8% because of decisions taken by ministers to make an efficiency support grant available. The ‘per household’ figures are calculated using total spending power a combination of the new start up funding assessment and Council Tax, and the number of dwellings by Council Tax band for each administrative area in England. The counts are calculated from data for England extracted from the Valuation Office Agency’s database on 12 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/plainenglishguide.pdf"&gt;plain English guide&lt;/a&gt; to cut through Whitehall jargon and explain the new settlement system is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a period of statutory consultation on the settlement which runs to 15 January 2013. Ministers will then finalise their proposals and the settlement for 2013 to 2014 will be debated in Parliament in February in time for councils to set their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement committed the government to relinquishing control over excessive Council Tax increases and giving that democratic power directly to local communities. This was legislated for through the Localism Act. The government has today published the Council Tax principles it is proposing for 2013 to 2014. Council Tax increases would trigger a referendum, if they exceed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2% for most principal authorities; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 (which ever is higher) in the case of shire district councils, police and crime commissioners and fire and rescue authorities that set the lowest quartile of Council Tax in their class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final principles for 2013 to 2014 will be set out in a report for the approval of the House of Commons early next year, at the same time as the final report on the local government finance settlement. No equivalent principles are being proposed for town and parish councils for 2013 to 2014, although they may in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical data for the 2013-14 Local Government Finance Settlement can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;Local Government Finance site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have been protected with savings back loaded to allow time for sensible savings; they have also benefited from the protection to local government in 2013 to 2014. In addition the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, has been asked to carry out a review to pinpoint ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money. The government intends to announce the breakdown of £140 million of capital grant money to fire and rescue authorities. The money for 2013 to 2015 will be distributed by a combination of formula and for projects to fire and rescue authorities that have been successful through bidding. All fire and rescue authorities will receive some capital funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/59917</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:47:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"/>
    <title>50 ways to save: examples of sensible savings in local government</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out 50 examples of sensible savings that councils could make and contains practical tips and guidance, highlighting ways that councillors can challenge officers to deliver savings, and ways that taxpayers can challenge councillors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60020</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:33:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-finance-settlement-oral-statement"/>
    <title>Local government finance settlement oral statement</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission Mr Speaker, I should like to make a statement on finance for English local authorities for 2013 to 2014 and 2014 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement sets out how the coalition government is putting our public finances back on track [political content removed].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has shown great skill in reducing its budgets. Committed local authorities have protected front line services. Little wonder then that at a time of retrenchment satisfaction in council services has gone up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s settlement will see council expenditure fall in a controlled way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English local government accounts for £1 of every £4 spent on public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It spends £114 billion - that’s twice the defence budget and more than the NHS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this settlement recognises the responsibility of local government to find sensible savings and make better use of its resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It marks a new settlement for local government based on self determination and financial independence. A move from the begging bowl to pride in locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begins the biggest shake up of local finance in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are shifting power from Whitehall direct to the town hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April, authorities will directly retain nearly £11 billion of business rates instead of returning them to the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Striving councils will benefit by doing the right thing by their communities. If they bring in jobs and business they will be rewarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, New Homes Bonus remunerates councils for building more homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year the Bonus will be worth more than £650 million and even more in 2014 to 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our reforms an estimated 70% of local authority income will be raised locally compared to a little over half under the current formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A giant step for localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start-up funding assessment, which gives each council a share of the funding - confirmed in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement - will see £26 billion shared between councils across the country - with the smallest reductions for councils most reliant on government funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted local authorities on our proposals over the summer. And we’ve listened to what they told us. They told us that there should be less money held back from the settlement. So we’ve reduced the amounts that we are setting aside for New Homes Bonus, for the safety net and for academies funding. In total that means an additional £1.9 billion for local authorities upfront in 2013 to 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities also told us that they wanted a stronger growth incentive. We were happy to respond. So we’ve made the scheme more generous, ensuring that at least 25 pence in every pound of business rate growth will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement leaves councils with considerable total spending power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall reduction in spending power next year is just 1.7%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small number of authorities will require larger savings to be made but no councils face a loss of more than 8.8% in their spending power thanks to a new efficiency support grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, to qualify councils will have to improve services to qualify. It is unfair on the rest of local government to expect them to subsidise other councils’ failure to embrace modernity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is not about what councils can take. It’s about what they can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the settlement continues protecting fire and rescue as a blue light emergency service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we have announced £140 million of capital grant money to fire authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictably the doom mongers have been consulting their Mayan calendars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issuing dire warnings of the end of the world as we know it on Friday. A billion pound black hole in the local budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have shamefully predicted riots on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nostradamus needn’t worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because all those Malthusian predictions have come to naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns that the poorest councils or those in the north would suffer disproportionately are well wide of the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spending power for places is in the north compares well to those in the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also maintained the system of ‘damping’ - where government sets a ‘floor’ below which council funding will not fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s average grant reduction for the most dependent upper tier authorities will be less than 3%, compared to 8.7% for the wealthiest. That’s more support and protection than last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also confirm today that local authorities will be able to use the receipts from assets sales raised from 2012 to 2013 onwards to fund outstanding equal pay claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of what I’ve announced today, the Secretary of State for Health will in due course be confirming public health funding for local councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his Autumn Statement the Chancellor recognised the sector has risen to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, unlike most of central government, local government was exempted from the 1% top slice next year - worth approximately £240 million to councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as it looks to 2014 and beyond, local government needs to continue finding better, more efficient, ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There remains scope for sensible savings. With the exception of a handful of authorities, nobody has got to grips with procurement. More can also be done to share offices, share services, cut fraud and provide more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also asked the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, to pinpoint practical ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money and protect the quality and breadth of frontline fire services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is disappointing that the Shadow Fire Minister has signalled his opposition. It has been noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, and today, true to my Yorkshire roots, I’ve published 50 ways to save, setting out practical ways for councils to save money, big and small. But it all adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if councils merged their back offices like the Tri-Borough initiative in London, they could save £2 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement fraud costs taxpayers almost a billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils are sitting on £16 billion of reserves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils aren’t collecting over £2 billion of council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better property management could save £7 billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have also announced today that further savings will be made by the abolition of pensions for councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors should be champions of the people, not the salaried staff of the town hall state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s guide gives more power to the elbow and the public to challenge crude cuts and champion sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year’s exemption will give local authorities time to put their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s remind ourselves what this is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;safeguarding vital public services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protecting families and pensioners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ending the something for nothing culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is why, despite financial pressures, we will continue supporting for the third year running, those who insulate residents from further council tax hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have set aside an extra £550 million for local authorities to support council tax: £450 million over the next 2 years for the freeze and an additional £100 million for council tax support will be available in new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All councils have a moral duty to freeze council tax.
It doubled under Labour. It became unsustainable. 
We’ve cut it in real terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear this years freeze grant goes into base for the spending review period and has the same status as every other item in base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who would prefer to carry on with increases and see residents miss out should be ready to answer to their local taxpayers and not dodge them by setting the increase just below the threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For next year we have set the referendum threshold at 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also introduce a flexibility to support small district, police and fire authorities that have kept council tax low for years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Rt Hon friend the Local Government Minister has set out the details in a Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is democracy in action: if you want to hike taxes, put it to the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would contrast the action we have taken to freeze council tax with the new housing tax being introduced in the Republic of Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the deficit helps keep taxes down.
If you deny the deficit, taxes on everyday families will rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, to those who want to play the politics of division - let me say this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fair settlement - fair to north and south, rural and urban, shire and metropolitan England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is also a watershed moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in a generation, striving councils now have licence to go full steam ahead and grab a share of the wealth for their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stand tall, and seize the opportunities of enterprise, growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60073</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-government-finance-settlement-2013-to-2014-and-related-matters"/>
    <title>Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014 and related matters</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is about the local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014 and related matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information relating to this consultation and the local government finance settlement, view the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles" title='Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles'&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; from 19 December 2012 and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm" title="Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014"&gt;Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60082</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T19:30:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-plain-english-guide"/>
    <title>Business rates retention and the local government finance settlement: a plain English guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A guide explaining the changes to business rates and what the proposals mean for councils, local residents, businesses, charities, developers, and the police and fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16973</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:34:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/localising-support-for-council-tax-council-tax-base"/>
    <title>Localising support for Council Tax: Council Tax base</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localising Council Tax support is part of a wider set of reforms to the welfare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals to provide certainty to local precepting authorities by allowing the Council Tax base for those areas to be calculated excluding localised Council Tax support reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s proposals for providing certainty for the funding of local precepting authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether proposals for providing certainty to local precepting authorities should also be applied for all special items&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the draft amending statutory instrument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16714</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:40:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: calculating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17061</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T14:26:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/weekly-collection-saved-as-government-scheme-delivers-for-6-million-families"/>
    <title>‘Weekly collection saved’ as government scheme delivers for 6 million families </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is thanks to the government’s £250 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/supporting-pages/bins-and-waste-collection"&gt;Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best 90 projects, from 85 councils, have today been selected from an over-subscribed scheme to share in the funding. Ministers are concerned that without the fund weekly bin collections could have all but disappeared by 2015, as is happening in other parts of the United Kingdom, such as Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Disraeli’s Public Health Act 1875 which first introduced a duty on local authorities to collect rubbish; this duty was enhanced by the Public Health Act 1936 obliging councils to collect household waste weekly. Weekly collections were the norm for decades, but started disappearing from 2000 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, 41 schemes will offer genuine rewards (such as shopping vouchers or loyalty points) for recycling so more families can go green without facing punitive fines and taxes, meeting an important coalition agreement pledge. It is hoped that such new schemes will encourage further take-up across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund was set up in February to support comprehensive and cost effective weekly collections that harness innovation, use new technology and spread reward schemes to increase recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils already receive funding for bin collections through central government formula grant and from the money raised locally via Council Tax: in total, council spending will be £114 million this year. A further 4 million households continue to provide weekly collections outside the support scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. Another survey found that two-thirds of the public thought government should mandate weekly collections; that weekly collections were better; and that problems with flies and smells were much worse with fortnightly collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government has already scrapped bin taxes plans via the Localism Act; reversed Audit Commission rules which marked down councils for not adopting fortnightly rubbish collections; and abolished Whitehall targets which created perverse incentives to downgrade waste collection services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will continue to work with Defra to spread best practice on weekly collections, challenge poor procurement or unpopular approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every Englishman has a basic right to have their household rubbish taken away each and every week - it is the most visible council service people get. Yet under the previous administration weekly bin collections halved while their Council Tax bills doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over 6 million families will breathe a sigh of relief tonight because we have put a stop to the fetid fortnightly rot and saved many weekly collections from extinction, all while increasing recycling rates by hundreds of thousands of tonnes to boot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Weekly Collection Support Scheme encourages councils to focus on 4 things: better weekly collections, cost effective bids, environmental improvements and better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment. 118 councils submitted final bids. For more information, see the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15038/Weekly_Collection_Support_Scheme_-_successful_bids.xls"&gt;list of 90 winning bids&lt;/a&gt;, which gives a short description of what each of the schemes will do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence: opinion research they carried out actually found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. (Ipsos-MORI, ‘Weekly or fortnightly: Public attitudes to waste collections’, July 2008.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fortnightly collections rose from just 13 councils across the United Kingdom in 2000 to 225 in 2008 (Alternate weekly collections conference, aspects of alternate weekly collection, July 2008). In Northern Ireland, as of 2010 to 2011, 92% of local authorities offer a fortnightly collection; in Scotland 72%, and Wales 77% according to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wrap.org.uk/" title="WRAP"&gt;WRAP’s&lt;/a&gt;, local authority waste and recycling information portal, statistics for 2010 to 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Sauce-Icaro attitudes to waste and recycling in Great Britain, December 2011 found that two-thirds (67%) agreed with the statement the government should mandate weekly collections. Weekly collections had higher satisfaction levels than fortnightly (83% compared to 74%). Reports of problems with flies and smells for fortnightly collections were more than double that for weekly (14% compared to 6%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What next: in the weeks to come the department will begin working with councils, the Local Government Association and Defra to support them to work together to procure the best deals as consortiums or groups to ensure value for money for the taxpayer. This means the department has provided a synopsis of each successful bid, but will not be disclosing further specific bid details as this would have an adverse effect on competition between prospective companies and potentially put local authorities in a disadvantageous position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16636</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T13:00:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-when-dwellings-should-not-be-liable-to-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: when dwellings should not be liable to the empty homes premium</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2012/17/introduction/enacted"&gt;Local Government Finance Act 2012&lt;/a&gt; allows a billing authority to charge an empty homes premium to provide a stronger incentive to get homes back into productive use and remove the blight of such properties on local neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premium was subject to a consultation, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"&gt;Technical Reforms to Council Tax&lt;/a&gt;’, which ended on 29 December 2011. The government published its response on 28 May 2012, which confirmed its intention to proceed with the premium and stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will not be payable until a dwelling has been empty and unfurnished for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the maximum premium that an authority will be able to charge will be 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation invited views on the government’s proposals on exceptions to the premium: dwellings which may otherwise be liable for the premium, but which are subject to circumstances that mean that it would not be appropriate for it to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary of responses was published on 21 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
