<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/widening-participation-in-higher-education--4/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/widening-participation-in-higher-education--4/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/widening-participation-in-higher-education--4/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Widening participation in higher education"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48175</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tracking-the-decision-making-of-high-achieving-higher-education-applicants"/>
    <title>Tracking the decision-making of high achieving higher education applicants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 86. Presents findings from research into the decision-making process of high achieving A level students. Analyses the attributes of high achieving applicants to higher education (HE) in comparison to the attributes of the wider appl&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48296</id>
    <published>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/methodological-review-of-the-student-income-and-expenditure-survey"/>
    <title>Methodological review of the student income and expenditure survey</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS research paper no. 29. Report of a review commissioned by BIS. Examines the methods used for the last two student income and expenditure surveys (SIESs) and the feasibility of alternative approaches. Looks at current thinking, knowledge and experience&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48295</id>
    <published>2012-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/widening-participation-in-higher-education-august-2012"/>
    <title>Widening participation in higher education: August 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides information on the estimated number of 15 year olds in receipt of free school meals who progress to higher education (HE) by age 19 by 2008/09. Gives data on the number of young people taking A levels or equivalent qualifications who progress to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47107</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/inspiring-the-future-launches"/>
    <title>Inspiring the Future launches</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 Jul 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new scheme to send an army of volunteers into state schools to give inspirational talks about their careers has been launched by Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg today.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister was joined by an array of famous faces and people with interesting jobs who are backing the plan, including entrepreneur Karren Brady, actor Joanna Lumley, Glamour magazine editor Jo Elvin, radio presenter Margherita Taylor and head chef at The Ivy restaurant Gary Lee.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone remembers the person who inspired them to follow their chosen career, but independent schools have much stronger links with businesses than schools in the state sector. Research published today by the Education and Employers Taskforce, an independent charity, shows that 80 per cent of independent schools regularly bring external speakers into their schools to boost the career aspirations of their students. 85 per cent involve employers in giving careers advice to students, through Careers Fairs or regular careers talks. Many state schools lack the alumni links to give their students the same opportunities. The ‘Inspiring the Future’ initiative, run by the Education and Employers Taskforce, will play a key role in plugging this gap by connecting inspiring speakers with local schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="link"&gt;Link&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/deputy-prime-minister-launches-inspiring-future"&gt;Read the press notice in full - Deputy Prime Minister Launches Inspiring the Future&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.inspiringthefuture.org/"&gt;Volunteer through the Inspiring the Future programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47105</id>
    <published>2012-06-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reforms-to-higher-education-sector-announced"/>
    <title>Reforms to Higher Education sector announced</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;11 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans to put students at the heart of the system were announced by Ministers today, as they set out their response to the Higher Education White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/g/12-890-government-response-students-and-regulatory-framework-higher-education"&gt;Government response to ‘Students at the heart of the system’ and ‘A new regulatory framework for the HE sector’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red-tape barring some smaller specialist institutions from being awarded the title of ‘university’ will be ditched. Previously, institutions needed 4,000 students to become a university, but from today this limit will drop to 1,000 - sweeping away an arbitrary piece of regulation that was preventing excellent institutions using the title. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change will come into effect immediately. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be a review into how existing quality assurance arrangements affect alternative providers, including further education colleges offering higher education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Reforms-to-higher-education-sector-announced-today-67b20.aspx"&gt;Press notice: Reforms to higher education sector announced today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18290</id>
    <published>2011-08-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/widening-participation-statistics-released"/>
    <title>Widening participation statistics released</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//analysis/statistics/higher-education/official-statistics-releases/widening-participation-in-higher-education/analysis-of-progression-rates-for-young-people-in-england-by-free-school-meal-receipt"&gt;Widening Participation in Higher Education: Analysis of progression rates for young people in England by free school meal receipt and school type&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New statistics show that a greater proportion of students receiving free school meal went on to university between 2005/06 and 2008/09. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap between the progression rates of those receiving and not receiving free school meals was 18 per cent in 2008/09. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the statistics, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These figures show how far we have to go to ensure that young people with the ability to go onto Higher Education have the opportunity to do so. While the progress to widen participation at our universities is welcome, more progress is needed - particularly at the most selective institutions. That is why we have expected universities to put more ambitious outreach programmes in place for 2012 - and they will be reviewed annually for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our reforms ensure there are no financial barriers in the way of bright young people from the most disadvantaged backgrounds attending university. There are no upfront fees, more financial support while studying, as well as a more generous package of scholarships and fee waivers.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These statistics are being published as part of the social mobility strategy, Opening Doors, Breaking Down Barriers (April 2011), and replace the previous Full-Time Young Participation by Socio-Economic Class (FYPSEC) measure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18284</id>
    <published>2011-08-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/next-stage-of-the-he-consultation-opens"/>
    <title>Next stage of the HE consultation opens</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;BIS has launched a consultation on details of the regulatory system for the future of higher education today, following publication of the higher education white paper.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent White Paper Higher Education: Students at the Heart of the System (June 2011) set out a commitment to introduce a new, fit-for-purpose regulatory framework to establish the Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE) as lead regulator. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new consultation launched today is a technical consultation, and to be read alongside the White Paper. It informs what changes in procedures, powers and duties will need to be considered, particularly in forthcoming legislation, in order to protect the student interest and provide a high quality experience.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/hereform/technical-consultation/"&gt;Take part in the consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/46226</id>
    <published>2011-08-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:29:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/new-regulatory-framework-for-higher-education-technical-consultation"/>
    <title>New regulatory framework for higher education: technical consultation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Closed consultation that sought views on technical aspects of regulatory reform of higher education, building on the proposals set out in the white paper ‘Higher education: students at the heart of the system’ (URN 11/944). Aims to inform what changes in procedures, powers and duties will need to be considered, particularly in forthcoming legislation, to protect the student interest and provide a high quality experience. Responses were due by 27 October 2011. See 12/890 for the government response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18275</id>
    <published>2011-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/access-agreements-for-universities"/>
    <title>Access agreements for universities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office for Fair Access (OFFA) has today announced it has approved 2012-13 Access Agreements for 139 institutions - 123 higher education institutions and 16 further education colleges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also announced that English universities and colleges charging above £6,000 for their courses plan to boost their spending on access measures to £602 million a year by 2015-16, up from £407 million in 2011-12. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This figure rises to £738 million a year when the Government’s contribution to the National Scholarship Programme (NSP) is included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.offa.org.uk/press-releases/universities-and-colleges-to-increase-their-spending-on-access-to-600-million-a-year/"&gt;Read OFFA’s announcement in full.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government is determined that no-one with the ambition and ability, whatever their background, should face barriers to accessing higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Progress over the past few years in securing fair access to the most selective universities has been inadequate. Only around 40 pupils out of the 80,000 on free school meals currently make it to Oxbridge at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government therefore tasked OFFA with setting more demanding tests than in previous years. We are satisfied that universities and colleges are showing their determination to improve. Indeed, by 2015, we expect the sector’s investment in access to be more than £600m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be monitoring performance on fair access closely every year to ensure we see tangible progress in opening the doors of our universities to the most disadvantaged.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities and Science Minister David Willetts went on to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We told universities to be much more ambitious with their plans for attracting people from low income backgrounds in exchange for charging students more. This will result in a step change in social mobility with university investment in programmes such as summer schools, scholarships and fee waivers reaching more than £600 million annually by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The majority of students will not be paying £9,000. No one should be put off going to university for financial reasons. No first time undergraduate will have to pay up front costs and there is a very generous package of financial support. Graduates will make lower monthly repayments than they do now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420351&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;BIS press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://studentfinance-yourfuture.direct.gov.uk/"&gt;University - make your future happen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/higher-education"&gt;Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18259</id>
    <published>2011-06-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/putting-students-at-the-heart-of-higher-education"/>
    <title>Putting students at the heart of higher education</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In future, graduates will pay more towards the cost of their degrees, but - in return - the Government’s proposals will improve their experience as students, expand their choices and make universities more accountable to students than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals contained in ‘Students at the Heart of the System’ cover four broad areas: reforming funding; delivering a better student experience; enabling universities to increase social mobility; and reducing regulation and removing barriers for new providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms will ensure that universities are held accountable for an improved student experience. The HE White Paper published today will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure better information for students before they apply, better teaching while at university, greater transparency in areas such as feedback on their work and better preparation for the job market &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask Professor Sir Tim Wilson to undertake a review into how university-industry collaboration can excel. The review will look at how the decline in sandwich courses can be reversed. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage universities to engage actively with employers to accredit or “kitemark” courses to indicate to students that they are valued by them. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make universities more accountable to students on teaching quality, who can trigger quality reviews where there are grounds for concern. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review the extent to which Student Charters are adopted and whether they should be made mandatory in the future. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free up student number controls by making around 85,000 places contestable among universities in 2012/13: through unrestrained recruitment of high-achieving students who typically get AAB grades, and by creating a flexible margin of places to reward quality providers charging an average of £7,500 or less for tuition. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensure that the Office for Fair Access is properly resourced so that it can go further and faster to drive fair access for students from lower income families and widen participation. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable a wider range of providers to join the sector to offer more choice for students. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Promise less regulation and bureaucracy for universities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper comes as part of the wider government agenda to put more power in the hands of the consumer. The Government has launched a major programme for public sector modernisation by cutting waste and bringing choice, encouraging competition and opening the market up to new providers. For higher education, this means that in future funding will follow the choices of the student.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Business, Innovation and Skills, Vince Cable, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our university sector has a strong history with some world-class institutions attracting students from across the globe. Higher Education is a successful public-private partnership; combining Government funding with institutional autonomy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This white paper builds on that record, while doing more than ever to put students in the driving seat. We want to see more investment, greater diversity, including innovative forms of delivery from further education colleges and others, and less centralised control over student numbers. But, in return, we want to the sector to be more accountable to students, as well as to the taxpayer.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities Minister, David Willetts, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government will reform the financing of higher education, promote a better student experience and foster social mobility. Our overall goal is a sector that is freed to respond in new ways to the needs of students.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Responding to student demand means enabling a greater diversity of provision. This may mean more higher education going on in a wider range of different settings, such as Further Education colleges and other alternative providers offering innovative types of course.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must move away from a world in which the number of students allocated to each university is determined in Whitehall. But universities will be under competitive pressure to provide better quality and at lower cost.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420160&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;full press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/hereform"&gt;Higher Education reform website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Higher Education White Paper - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/h/11-944-higher-education-students-at-heart-of-system.pdf"&gt;Students at the Heart of the System (PDF, 711 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
