<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/working-with-local-partners-to-plan-for-and-respond-to-emergencies/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-with-local-partners-to-plan-for-and-respond-to-emergencies/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/working-with-local-partners-to-plan-for-and-respond-to-emergencies/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Working with local partners to plan for, and respond to, emergencies"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:07+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56832</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:05:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-protective-security-strategy-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue protective security strategy 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy is a refresh of the 2009 protective security strategy for fire and rescue authorities. It outlines 6 key deliverables to enhance protective security for fire and rescue authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17107</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-3-rescues-from-lifts-and-escalators"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.3: rescues from lifts and escalators</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescues from lifts and escalators to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.3 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to fire service personnel, the personnel of other agencies and members of the public when attending incidents involving lifts, escalators and moving walkways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17112</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T15:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-5-7-incidents-involving-explosives"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 5.7: incidents involving explosives</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about incidents involving explosives to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 5.7 examines the hazards, risks and control measures relating to incidents involving ‘commercial’ explosives, while in manufacture, storage or transportation. It does not cover improvised explosive devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the guidance published in November 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16737</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T16:26:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/hazardous-materials-operational-guidance-for-the-fire-and-rescue-service"/>
    <title>Hazardous materials: operational guidance for the fire and rescue service</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Best practice guidance to help fire and rescue authorities to resolve incidents involving hazardous materials safely and efficiently.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document provides comprehensive yet flexible guidance that can be adapted to the nature, scale and requirements of the incident. It consolidates the content of over 500 items of previously published subject related documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16759</id>
    <published>2012-09-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fire-and-rescue-bulletin-25-2012"/>
    <title>Fire and rescue bulletin: 25/2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Fire and rescue bulletins cover issues of interest and relevance to fire and rescue authorities. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fire and rescue bulletin for September 2012 covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consultation on changing the name of Bedfordshire and Luton combined fire authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to fire and rescue incident records in England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publication of the government response to the exercise watermark report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14666</id>
    <published>2012-08-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-secretary-eric-pickles-responds-to-the-riots-1-year-on"/>
    <title>Communities Secretary Eric Pickles responds to the riots 1 year on</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Anyone who disrupts the communities and livelihoods of our citizens will face the full force of justice. Since last August the Government has sent the strongest possible signal that mindless criminality will not be tolerated ever. Over 1,900 people were swiftly brought to justice and the average sentence was over four times longer than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Government made millions of pounds available to councils to quickly help reopen shops and rebuild communities affected by the riots, and made sure the police continue to build positive relationships with those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to see our young people given the best start in life. We are supporting those most in need via the Youth Contract which will provide support worth almost £1 billion, to young people, including wage incentives for ‘youth unemployment hotspots’ - and are going into the homes of 120,000 of the nation’s most troubled families to address root causes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;At this time we must also remember the acts of selfless kindness shown by the many people who stood up and joined the ‘broom brigade’, which were in stark contrast to the reckless criminal minority that perpetrated this disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14639</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/councils-to-get-100-help-to-clear-up-after-floods"/>
    <title>Councils to get 100% help to clear up after floods</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government has set out the help that it is giving to councils following the record breaking rainfall over recent weeks that has had a devastating effect on many parts of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in the Department for Communities and Local Government said that they would look sympathetically on councils where they have costs as a result of the floods, and announced that they would reimburse councils for 100 per cent of their clearing-up expenditure under the Bellwin scheme. Councils have a vital role, along with the emergency services, in responding to such events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I know that many households and businesses have been disrupted by the floods that have affected parts of the country. That is why we have announced that we will reimburse councils 100 per cent of their costs under the Bellwin scheme which will help councils clear-up streets removing debris from roads and footpaths, shore up buildings and remove dangerous trees.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am writing to all councils affected to see what practical support they need and the Government is continuing to monitor the situation carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activation of the Bellwin scheme was announced in a Written Ministerial Statement to Parliament by the Environment Secretary Caroline Spelman, recording that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government is activating the Bellwin Scheme of Emergency Financial Assistance to help local authorities with their immediate costs associated with protecting life and property in their areas. Exceptionally, the scheme will reimburse local authorities for 100 per cent of their eligible costs above threshold. This is in recognition of the particular circumstances around these floods and will give the affected local authorities assurance that such costs will be reimbursed. Government officials will also be discussing the recovery arrangements with local authorities in the areas affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils, police, fire and National park authorities are eligible for Bellwin reimbursement when they have spent more than 0.2 per cent of their calculated annual revenue budget on works that have been reported to the Department as eligible for grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has decided that on this occasion it will reimburse 100 per cent of the costs above the threshold, instead of the standard 85 per cent as stated in the Bellwin scheme guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1774767.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1774767.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9709</id>
    <published>2012-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-see-riot-recovery-underway-in-greenwich-manchester-and-salford"/>
    <title>Ministers see riot-recovery underway in Greenwich, Manchester and Salford</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers have visited more towns that were badly affected by the riots, to see progress six months on and meet the local people, traders and council workers getting their communities back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Secretary of State Eric Pickles visit to Tottenham last week, Local Government Minister Bob Neill visited Woolwich and Communities Minister Andrew Stunell headed to Manchester and Salford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the riots the Government acted quickly to make available a multi-million pound package of support to enable councils to act swiftly and confidently to restore communities and get support to local people and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="woolwich"&gt;Woolwich&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Neill returned to Woolwich to see first hand how the community is using the support available to restore, rebuild and improve the town centre. He was first there in the immediate aftermath of the riots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling into local businesses, Mr Neill talked to traders about the impact of the riots and how the community rallied round to help get them get back on their feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local council leader Chris Roberts and Chief Executive Mary Ney accompanied the Minister. The council set up the Greenwich Backing Local Business fund and opened a special advice surgery for more than 60 businesses to drop in to get expert advice and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The picture here in Woolwich is very different to the one I saw in the immediate aftermath of the riots. Despite the attempts of a few to wreak havoc, the community in Woolwich have pulled together to restore their town.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The progress well underway in Woolwich is symbolic of a community that is proud of their local area, their local businesses and determined to see their town thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="manchester-and-salford"&gt;Manchester and Salford&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting local people, traders and council workers in Manchester and Salford, Communities Minister Andrew Stunell praised the energetic way communities came together in the aftermath of the riots and pointed to the true examples of community spirit in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst the actions of a small minority determined on causing destruction caught our attention for a moment, it is the examples of true community spirit that will endure; the ‘broom armies’, the campaigns to support local businesses, the messages of pride in the area posted on shop fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It’s been great to meet the people that paint the real picture of community life in Manchester and Salford and see that recovery and progress is well underway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Stunell also met with council leaders in both areas to discuss the impact of the riots and the support improvement in the areas. An ‘I love Salford’ campaign was launched to build up the community spirit and invite people to show their support for their area by shopping locally and wearing campaign badges. In Manchester a campaign group called ‘Eye on Manchester’ rallied support from locals to help in the clean up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11254</id>
    <published>2012-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/guidance-to-the-fire-and-rescue-authorities-aircraft-incidents"/>
    <title>Guidance to the fire and rescue authorities: aircraft incidents</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for the Fire and Rescue authorities on responding to aircraft incidents</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this guidance is to assist emergency responders to make safe, risk assessed, efficient and proportionate responses when attending and dealing with operational incidents involving aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a priced publication available from TSO (The Stationery Office), PO Box 29, Norwich NR3 1GN. Order through the Parliamentary Hotline (Lo-call): 08457 023 474, fax: 0870 600 5533, textphone 0870 240 3701, email: book.orders@tso.co.uk or visit www.tsoshop.co.uk to buy online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16611</id>
    <published>2011-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generic-risk-assessment-2-6-rescue-of-trapped-persons"/>
    <title>Generic risk assessment 2.6: rescue of trapped persons</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Generic risk assessment about rescue of trapped persons to help fire and rescue authorities to draw up their own risk assessments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generic risk assessment 2.6 examines the hazards, risks and control measures that relate to incidents where persons are trapped and require release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
