<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/countering-weapons-proliferation/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Countering weapons proliferation "</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-01T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17576</id>
    <published>2012-12-01T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:02:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-north-koreas-proposed-satellite-launch"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns North Korea's proposed satellite launch </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on North Korea’s plans to launch a satellite, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We condemn the announcement by North Korea’s Central News Agency that North Korea intends to launch a satellite between 10-22 December. The United Nations Security Council made clear in April that any attempts by North Korea to launch a satellite using ballistic missile technology would be a serious violation of UN Security Council resolution 1874. We therefore call on the North Korean authorities to abandon this plan. Failure to do so must lead to a further response by the international community, and will damage the prospects for peace and stability on the Korean Peninsula.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35568</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-a-global-arms-trade-treaty"/>
    <title>Support for a global Arms Trade Treaty</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday UN Member States voted overwhelmingly in support of a UN General Assembly Resolution that secured a resumption of negotiations on the Arms Trade Treaty. The Resolution convened a further UN conference from 18 to 28 March 2013 in New York. Speaking today, Minister responsible for the Arms Trade Treaty, Alistair Burt said:            &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday in New York, 157 countries pledged their support for a global Arms Trade Treaty. An overwhelming majority of states, including the US, China and India, voted for a return to UN negotiations in 2013 to finalise work on a Treaty that will save lives, reduce human suffering and bring consistency to the global trade in conventional arms. The UK has led the international efforts towards an Arms Trade Treaty since 2006 and, with the majority of the world alongside us, will redouble our efforts to secure a Treaty that will make a difference to millions of lives around the world. Agreement on an Arms Trade Treaty is closer than ever, and the UK will be at the forefront of efforts to finally secure this. I appreciate the public support which has underlined our approach and helped to secure this positive outcome.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35448</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--96"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indonesia State Visit&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague met Indonesian President Yudhoyono this week during his state visit to the UK. The Foreign Secretary said: “This visit will be an opportunity for us to build on the strong partnership established over the last decade.” President Yudhoyono also met with the Queen, members of the royal family and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/president-yudhoyono-of-indonesia/"&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron&lt;/a&gt;. He also attended the UK High Level Panel meeting and gave a Wilton Park address on Indonesia’s role as a regional and global actor. The Indonesian Foreign Minister Marty Natalegawa wrote a guest post about the visit for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/williamjhague"&gt;The Foreign Secretary’s facebook page&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit to hospital where Malala Yousafzai is receiving treatment.&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Emirati Foreign Minister and the Pakistani Interior Minister visited the hospital where Malala Yousafzai is receiving treatment in the UK. Malala was shot by the Taliban after campaigning for girls’ right to education in Pakistan.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=827742682"&gt;Click here to read more about the visit.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arab Partnership&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt attended an event at the Foreign Office with DFID Minister Alan Duncan to mark the second anniversary of the Arab Partnership. He said: “We must have the strategic patience to partner with the region over the long term, to build the institutions needed for the long-term stability that will benefit all.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=829164082"&gt;Click here for more information about the Arab Partnership.&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism (GICNT)&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt spoke at the GICNT symposium on the detection of nuclear material. He said: “We must prevent access to nuclear devices, materials and expertise by those who would seek to do us harm, while not impeding legitimate peaceful uses.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=Speech&amp;amp;id=830142382"&gt;Read the full text of the speech.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
** &lt;br&gt;
Nasrin Sotoudeh**   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt urged the Iranian authorities to review the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=829620782"&gt;case of Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt; who remains imprisoned in Iran.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Also this week&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a first for the Foreign Office the British Ambassador to Lebanon Tom Fletcher took part in a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PQm34fFJ79w&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;google+ hangout on Syria&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt welcomed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=830285282"&gt;new Libyan Cabinet.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire met the Burmese Charge d’Affairs to discuss concerns about the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=828723582"&gt;violence in Burma&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/35438</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/global-initiative-to-combat-nuclear-terrorism"/>
    <title>Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Professor Clary for your kind introduction. And my thanks to the co-chairs of the Global Initiative and our partners in this event, notably Atomic Weapons Establishment, the Ministry of Defence and our colleagues from the Defence Threat Reduction Agency (DTRA) in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would first like to extend my appreciation to everyone here for taking the time from your busy schedules join us at Lancaster House to discuss one of the most important issues of our time: nuclear terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My portfolio as Minister in the Foreign Office covers 32 countries, ranging from the Middle East and North Africa to parts of South Asia. I have responsibility for our Counter-Proliferation, Counter-Terrorism and Counter-Piracy efforts. In the past year I have seen the continuous evolution of security challenges facing the UK; both conventional and non-conventional, domestic and international.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional conflict and instability have potential implications for wider peace and stability, which is why the UK’s National Security Strategy identified nuclear terrorism as a primary danger to Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear terrorism is a real and global threat. A successful attack, no matter where in the world it came, would be catastrophic. Catastrophic for the immediate devastation and terrible loss of life, and for the far-reaching consequences - psychological, economic, political, and environmental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an attack was unthinkable just a generation ago. But it is now a possibility we need to confront with the utmost vigilance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear material is becoming more available - partly because more countries are deciding to adopt the benefits of nuclear energy. That is a sovereign right and a positive choice, and one which the UK will continue to support. We also recognise that some countries have chosen not to go down the path of nuclear energy. But this all means that we need together to ensure that, as nuclear materials and technology spread, we keep our people safe and secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in today’s world of modern communication, information is spreading faster. Like nuclear energy, this brings huge benefits, but it also brings significant risks. There is more information about nuclear weapons on the internet than there ever has been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is the case in cyberspace, the danger is stateless in geographical space. It is impossible for any national government or police force, no matter how advanced, to contain on its own. Global smuggling networks are thriving. Criminal cells operate across borders and across continents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are here today to renew our drive for the global response we need. We must prevent access to nuclear devices, materials and expertise by those who would seek to do us harm, while not impeding legitimate peaceful uses. Together we can agree and enforce the rules, secure the cooperation, and develop the capabilities and practices, to ensure that a nuclear terror attack never happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our determination to tackle this issue head on is the reason why, at the Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism Plenary in South Korea last year, we announced that we would host this symposium. It is a clear demonstration of the UK’s commitment to this most important of issues, and our commitment to implementing the founding principles of the Global Initiative.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago the UK joined the Global Initiative, along with 12 other countries.  We were brought together through the strong leadership of the United States and Russia. Today the Global Initiative membership counts more than 85 nations and four official observers - all committed to strengthening the global capacity to prevent, detect, and respond to nuclear terrorism.  Gathered at this symposium are some of the world’s leading experts on non-proliferation, counter proliferation and counterterrorism.&lt;br&gt;
The more I have read about the fight against nuclear material trafficking, the more I have appreciated the real difficulties you are working to address. Detecting the radioactive signature of heavy elements in nuclear contraband is challenging, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your fight against nuclear terrorism has introduced me to a fascinating - and, I must admit, mysterious - world filled with Muons, Cosmic-rays, and Large Hadron Colliders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology has come a long way. From its beginning in 1960s, when the Nobel prize winning physicist, Luis Alvarez, set up Muon detectors in a chamber beneath the second pyramid of Chephron in Egypt to look for hidden chambers.  To the development of Drift Tubes at the Los Alamos National Laboratory, and on to the creation of the gas electron multipliers.  Now nuclear detection systems are being developed that only take up a cubic meter of space and can produce three-dimensional images. I do not pretend to understand fully the physics behind these technologies. And indeed, when a Muon was explained to me as a “heavy electron” I recall thinking that I did not find that description particularly illuminating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the serious point is that you here turn what sounds to the layperson like science fiction into tangible technologies that will help to prevent nuclear terrorism. Since the issue of illicit trafficking of nuclear material was first recognised the UK has been at the forefront of trying to combat this threat.  And, of course, it was an issue very much at the forefront of our security preparations for our hosting of a successful London Olympics this summer. You will hear more about this, and about the UK’s border monitoring system, Cyclamen, later in this symposium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only six months ago I would not have been able to openly discuss Britain’s work on detection as I am doing with you now. But building on the UK’s commitment to openness in this area and the work that we first revealed at the Seoul Nuclear Security Summit in March, I am especially pleased that I can publicly commend and promote the UK’s Atomic Weapons Establishment, or AWE as they are known, for their work in this area. This is a rare opportunity to publically acknowledge that their work has been central to the defence of the United Kingdom for over 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the creation of a broad programme that covers passive detection, active detection and Muon-based detectors is being led by AWE in partnership with the UK’s world-leading academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is delivering a range of prototypes in each area that will allow us to advance our research on this challenging problem. A particular success is the production of a Muon-based detector using novel technologies, providing both a test bed for advanced detection methods and also arms control verification tools. Again, I know you will hear more on this later in the symposium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the nuclear forensics domain we have built on AWE’s excellent resources and created a dedicated world-class nuclear forensics analytical capability that will allow the UK to investigate criminal acts involving nuclear materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the recently-opened Conventional Forensic Analysis Capability, which allows us, for the first time in Britain, to examine traditional forensic evidence, DNA, Fingerprints, and more, that is contaminated with Radiological, Nuclear and Explosive material.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me repeat again that it is a pleasure to be here today. I have learnt a lot in the short time I have had to discuss these fascinating issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we are here to help strengthen, widen and deepen the co-operation between our countries to stop nuclear material trafficking.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This symposium is an important contribution to this ambition. It is important not only for the security of our nations, but for the partnership that we are forging across the board to make the world a more prosperous, stable and secure place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/35652</id>
    <published>2012-09-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nuclear-terrorism-remains-one-of-the-greatest-threats-to-our-global-peace-and-security"/>
    <title>“Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security”</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nuclear  terrorism remains one of the greatest threats to our global peace and security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful attack, no matter where in the world it came, would be catastrophic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism (ICSANT) is one of the cornerstones of the international effort to counter this threat.  It provides a legal basis for international cooperation in the investigation, prosecution and extradition of those involved in the preparation or execution of terrorist acts involving radioactive material or a nuclear device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK ratified the Convention in September 2009, demonstrating our commitment to maintaining the highest possible international standards in countering the threat from nuclear terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the crucial element of co-operation that I want like to focus on today.  International cooperation to combat nuclear terrorism has been tremendous.  The recent Nuclear Security Summit in Seoul once again catalysed the political will and technical expertise necessary to fulfil commitments made in Washington, two years earlier.  53 countries made over 100 new commitments to improving global nuclear security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, at least 14 countries have ratified the convention since the 2010 Summit and a further 15 announced plans to do so in the 2012 Summit to ratify this convention and/ or the Amendment to the Convention on the Physical Protection on Nuclear Material, another essential element of the global nuclear security architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise there are some challenges in promoting universal adherence to the UN Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A  perception among some States that they may not have to implement effective controls on nuclear and other radioactive material if they do not possess nuclear weapons or hold only limited quantities of materials for peaceful purposes; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A  possible lack of awareness within governments of this convention  and its requirements and obligations; and a limited capacity and resource to draft, implement or enforce the necessary laws and regulations;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But against these challenges I would like to offer a brief reminder of the significant advantages of adhering to this convention.  States that adhere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are better able to investigate, prosecute and punish any acts relating to nuclear or radiological terrorism by non-State actors;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will enhance their national security and public health and safety;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demonstrate to others, including potential investors that they are a safe and responsible location for activities involving nuclear and other radioactive material;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;comply effectively with their international reporting requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Co-operation, assistance and advice are available to all States who want or need it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highlight Security Council Resolution 1540 in this context, in particular the [1540] Committee of Experts, whose role is to monitor and assist states in adopting and effecting appropriate laws and activity to better prevent proliferation in or through their territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK will also be focussing on the effective implementation of Resolution 1540 as a priority for our 2013 Chair of the Global Partnership against the Spread of Weapons and Materials of Mass Destruction.  Looking ahead, the 2014 Nuclear Security Summit, complemented by efforts such as the Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism, will continue to provide the momentum, political will, co-ordination and expertise, necessary to strengthen nuclear security still further.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encourage countries, where appropriate to do so, to engage with international nuclear security initiatives and Conventions, and for those that have yet to ratify the UN International Convention on the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism, to do so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27955</id>
    <published>2012-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-declaration-on-mongolias-nuclear-weapon-free-status"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister welcomes declaration on Mongolia's Nuclear-Weapon-Free Status</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking following the adoption, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome today’s declaration by the P5 and by Mongolia as a further contribution to global and regional peace and security. I congratulate Mongolia on this achievement. By endorsing this declaration, the P5 agree to respect the nuclear weapon free status of Mongolia and not to contribute to any act that would violate it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This marks a further milestone in the UK’s commitment to support nuclear non-proliferation and disarmament, and in particular fulfilling the 2010 Non Proliferation Treaty Action Plan. The UK believes that it is important to establish greater trust between Nuclear and Non-Nuclear Weapon States and is actively contributing to efforts to reduce the number of nuclear weapons worldwide.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27951</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-iaea-board-resolution-sends-clear-message-to-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister: "IAEA board resolution sends clear message to Iran"</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The resolution was sponsored by the five permanent members of the UN Security Council, plus Germany, (P5+1) and received overwhelming backing from the countries on the IAEA Board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the resolution Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the International Atomic Energy Agency’s Board of Governors’ Resolution adopted yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The IAEA’s latest report confirmed that Iran is expanding its uranium enrichment capacity in direct contravention of IAEA Board and Security Council resolutions, and that it is failing to cooperate with the Agency to address the possible military dimensions of its nuclear programme. These facts provide no assurance of Iran’s stated peaceful intentions. The overwhelming support for the IAEA Board’s Resolution yesterday sends a clear message to Iran about the international community’s determination that Iran must now urgently address the serious concerns about its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We seek a negotiated solution with Iran. The P5+1 continues to pursue negotiations with Iran in good faith. The onus is on Iran to take concrete steps to co-operate fully with the Agency and comply with all its international obligations.  Until it does, the international pressure on Iran will only increase.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/28369</id>
    <published>2012-09-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/arms-trade-treaty"/>
    <title>Arms Trade Treaty</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to update the House on the outcome of the UN Conference on the Arms Trade Treaty (ATT) which took place in New York from 2 to 27 July 2012.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conference followed six years of work in the UN to secure a legally binding Treaty to regulate the international trade in conventional arms. The illegal, or poorly regulated, trade in conventional arms costs lives and blights futures.  More than 740,000 men, women and children die each year as a result of armed violence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has led international efforts to secure an ATT over the last six years, and last month the UN Conference came close to reaching an agreement on a Treaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Delegation was led by the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, and comprised of representatives from the Ministry of Defence, the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, the Department for International Development and a representative from the UK Defence Industry. I and the Minister of State for International Development also travelled to New York during the negotiations to help sustain the momentum of the process.  The UK Delegation played a leading role in the negotiations, co-ordinating closely with civil society, and supported by Ministers and officials from across Whitehall and by the UK’s extensive network of international Posts. I pay tribute to all the individuals involved.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four weeks of difficult and complex negotiations led to a robust and balanced Treaty text which the United Kingdom and the vast majority of other states felt able to support.  However on the final day of the Conference a small number of countries asked for more time to consider the text, meaning that the Conference ended without agreement.  As the Foreign Secretary made clear in his statement of 28 July, we were disappointed that the negotiations did not reach a conclusion.  However we recognise that to be fully effective the Treaty will need broad and ideally universal participation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an end to the Arms Trade Treaty process. We are absolutely committed to securing a robust and effective Treaty, and will continue to devote significant diplomatic efforts to this goal. We will continue our work on the basis of the draft Treaty considered at the Conference. The UN General Assembly will be the next opportunity for us to address the issue amongst the whole UN membership. Whilst there is still work to be done, we remain optimistic that a meaningful and coherent ATT that will make a positive difference to millions of lives is in reach, and our goal will be its agreement during the next UN General Assembly session in 2012 - 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27834</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-ministers-fully-committed-to-taking-work-on-arms-trade-treaty-forward-urgently"/>
    <title>UK Ministers "fully committed to taking work on Arms Trade Treaty forward urgently"</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They wrote:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the dust settles after four tough weeks of negotiations in New York on an Arms Trade Treaty, we thought we should write to you with our reactions to what happened and thoughts on where we go from here. Firstly, we would like to thank you for your commitment to securing a robust ATT and for the close working relationship we have established, which was very evident in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the Government has made clear, we are disappointed that the negotiations did not reach a conclusion. This was not the result we wanted or which we worked to achieve. Like the overwhelming majority of states, we supported the Conference President’s draft Treaty text and we were ready to agree to it last week.  It is unfortunate that a small number of states pushed for more time to consider the proposals. This was disappointing but we recognise that to be fully effective, the Treaty will need broad - ideally universal - participation. Our judgement is that the text provides enough to work with. Whilst it reflects the compromises necessary to bridge the wide variety of national positions, it is robust and if still adopted, would bring about a very significant improvement on the current situation by establishing, in particular:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A global first in setting universal commitments on national arms export controls. A global baseline for regulating arms exports;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first ever international legally binding agreement on the transfer of small arms and light weapons;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mandatory requirement for arms exports  - including ammunition and military parts and components - to be assessed on the basis of certain criteria including human rights, and a mandatory refusal if they pose unacceptable risks;Inclusion of sustainable development and anti-corruption into arms export controls;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A requirement for countries to regulate brokering;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mandatory reporting on authorisations or actual transfers of conventional arms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We exerted every effort to secure a strong agreement. Ministers and officials in London, New York and across our network of Embassies and High Commissions worked tirelessly around the clock over the last month, and in the period leading up to it, to give these negotiations the best chance of success. We both travelled to New York and, along with other Ministers including the Deputy Prime Minister, the Foreign Secretary and the International Development Secretary, lobbied key states by phone and in person.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well as participating constructively in the Plenary, Main Committees and informal consultations, our delegation was highly active behind the scenes, working to find ways forward and to promote agreement. As we made clear going into these negotiations, while we recognised the need for flexibility and compromise, we would not accept or sign a weak Treaty. We held strictly to these principles throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were delighted with the close collaboration between NGOs and our delegation and valued the regular dialogue we had with such organisations both before and during negotiations. We sincerely hope this can continue over the coming months.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So, where do we go from here? We remain fully committed to taking this work forward urgently to secure the strongest and widest possible agreement as soon as this is feasible. A period of reflection and consultation with key governments and stakeholders, including yourselves, is the first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UN General Assembly in the autumn, to which the Conference President is sending his report, will be the next opportunity to address the issue amongst the whole UN membership. Our priority will be to bank the progress we’ve made and sustain momentum to agree a Treaty. We remain optimistic, and it is worth noting that those countries who asked for more time nevertheless spoke in positive terms about the text on the table. Civil society will continue to have a key role to play in influencing the sceptics and ensuring that the progress achieved last month is not diluted. In this we hope to work ever more closely with you, and we look forward to meeting you at the earliest opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We firmly believe that an ATT is coming and we will keep working until it is agreed. The human cost of the uncontrolled arms trade is too high not to.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/27803</id>
    <published>2012-07-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-disappointed-at-the-outcome-of-the-arms-trade-treaty-negotiations"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary 'disappointed' at the outcome of the Arms Trade Treaty negotiations</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the the Arms Trade Treaty negotiations, the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am disappointed that negotiations to secure agreement on an effective treaty to regulate international trade in conventional arms did not reach a conclusion yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over the last six years, the UK has played a leading role in building support for a strong Arms Trade Treaty. In the last month, Ministers and officials in London and New York and our diplomats overseas have worked tirelessly for a positive outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is not the result we wanted. But we have made huge progress. The Chair’s draft treaty has our full support as well as that of the great majority of other states. But to be fully effective, the Treaty will need very broad - ideally universal - participation. It is clear that more time is needed to reach the widest possible agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We now need to maintain the momentum and to complete this crucial work as soon as possible, taking the issue to the UN General Assembly. An Arms Trade Treaty is coming. It will not be this week but we will succeed. When we do, the world will be a safer place.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
