<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/taking-international-action-to-mitigate-climate-change/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Taking international action to mitigate climate change"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16449</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:40:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/climate-public-private-partnership-cp3"/>
    <title>Climate Public Private Partnership (CP3)</title>
    <category>Case Study</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; will invest £130 million in 2 commercial private equity funds, which will aim to leverage private co-investment. These funds will be run on a strictly commercial basis by professional fund managers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an equity investment of £110 million, the project will include technical assistance to support the development of the project pipeline and facilitate pioneering projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/News/Latest-news/2012/Private-investment-to-help-tackle-climate-change/"&gt;Private investment to help tackle climate change press release.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/5720-business-case-for-icf-support-for-the-climate-publ.pdf"&gt;Business case for ICF support of the Climate Public Private Partnership.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16444</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:39:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/asian-development-bank-solar-loan-guarantee-facility"/>
    <title>Asian Development Bank Solar Loan Guarantee Facility</title>
    <category>Case Study</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.decc.gov.uk"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; contributed £6 million to this scheme, which works by offsetting part of the financing cost of using &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.adb.org/"&gt;Asian Development Bank (ADB)&lt;/a&gt; guarantees on commercial loans for small-scale solar plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected to stimulate an estimated £265 million of private sector investment in clean energy generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/11/tackling-climate-change/international-climate-change/4781-business-case-for-india-solar-power-generation-gua.pdf"&gt;Business case for India Solar Power Generation Guarantee Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:CaseStudy/16453</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T08:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/partnership-for-market-readiness-pmr"/>
    <title>Partnership for Market Readiness (PMR)</title>
    <category>Case Study</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/"&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change (DECC)&lt;/a&gt; has given £7 million to the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;, which is a grant-based trust fund that helps middle-income countries develop and pilot market-based policies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt; brings together policy makers from governments with experts and stakeholders to provide a platform for piloting these market-based policies. It builds on developing countries’ own mitigation priorities and recipient countries include Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Mexico, China, Indonesia, Thailand, Turkey and the Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thepmr.org/"&gt;More about the &lt;abbr title="Partnership for Market Readiness"&gt;PMR&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/pn_036/pn_036.aspx"&gt;Press notice: UK government to support developing countries in reducing their carbon emissions.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/assets/decc/internationalclimatechange/5528-icf-support-for-world-bank-partnership-for-market-.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Climate Fund"&gt;ICF&lt;/abbr&gt; support for World Bank’s Partnership for Market Readiness.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46920</id>
    <published>2010-07-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/google-earth-zooms-in-on-dangerous-climate-change"/>
    <title>Google Earth zooms in on dangerous climate change</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/climate-change/priorities/science/"&gt;View the interactive map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map highlights some of the changes that may occur if the global average temperature rises by 4°C above the pre-industrial climate average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Google Earth layer features videos of climate scientists from the UK explaining the latest scientific research behind the climate impacts demonstrated on the layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map also includes examples of FCO and British Council climate change projects currently taking place around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Parsons, Geo Spatial Technologist at Google said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘This is a great example of the benefits of using the latest web technology to visualise scientific information and promote better understanding of the potential human impacts of climate change. Allowing scientists to talk about their research to the general public is a way to enable the public to fully understand how the process of scientific investigation works.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched by FCO Minister Henry Bellingham and Climate Change Minister Greg Barker alongside Chief Government Scientist, Professor John Beddington, the map was developed using peer-reviewed science from the Met Office Hadley Centre and other leading impact scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Bellingham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The threat from climate change has not gone away and this Government is committed to doing what it can to take action. We are committed to being the ‘greenest’ Government ever. As the Foreign Secretary set out recently in his first major foreign policy speech, he is keen to engage with new audiences. This Google Earth map supports that commitment to tackling climate change and will hopefully communicate with a bigger audience globally about why the UK Government is being active in championing the transition to a low carbon economy.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Government is committed to keeping global temperatures as low as practical to avoid dangerous levels of climate change and is working to secure an ambitious global deal which achieves this. The Copenhagen Accord already commits countries to limiting average global temperature increases to 2°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department of Energy &amp;amp; Climate Change Minister State Greg Barker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘This map reinforces our determination to act against dangerous man-made climate change.?? We know the stakes are high and that’s why we want to help secure an ambitious global climate change deal.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vicky Pope from the Met Office said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘If greenhouse gas emissions continue to rise, global average temperatures could increase by 4°C by the end of the century, and possibly as early as 2060.  This new mapping onto Google Earth illustrates some of the potential impacts of such a rise. It uses the latest climate and impacts science to highlight the consequences of not reducing emissions.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/46879</id>
    <published>2010-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/europe-latin-america-and-caribbean-climate-progress"/>
    <title>Europe, Latin America and Caribbean climate progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving energy efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing the intensity of greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;addressing the economic, social, environmental and other challenges posed by climate change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;following low emission sustainable development strategies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;implementing adaptation and mitigation measures and actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;limiting the potential increase in the global temperature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreements built upon commitments pledged by the regions at the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) in Copenhagen in December 2009. Further discussions in the region support this progress.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regions are now working towards transparent and inclusive negotiations at the Conference of the Parties (COP16) in Mexico in November 2010. The goal is to achieve a comprehensive, ambitious and effective legally binding deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
