<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-labour-market-more-flexible-efficient-and-fair/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making the labour market more flexible, efficient and fair"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56260</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:35:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/growth-and-infrastructure-bill-clause-23-employer-owners-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Growth and Infrastructure Bill Clause 23 [employer owners]: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact for businesses and individuals of proposed legislation to give companies greater choice about the contracts they can offer to individuals, whilst ensuring appropriate levels of protection are maintained. The government is creating a new employment status of ‘employee owner’, where employee owners receive shares but will not have certain employment rights relating to unfair dismissal flexible working and training, and statutory redundancy pay. See also the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-implementing-employee-owner-status--2"&gt;consultation on this employee ownership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56254</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:28:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/implementing-employee-owner-status-government-response-to-consultation"/>
    <title>Implementing employee owner status: government response to consultation</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarises responses received and provides the government response to the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-implementing-employee-owner-status--2"&gt;consultation on how the government will implement employer owner status&lt;/a&gt;. This aims to give businesses greater choice about the contracts they can offer employees, whilst ensuring appropriate levels of protection are maintained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16719</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:34:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tupe-a-guide-to-the-2006-regulations"/>
    <title>TUPE - a guide to the 2006 regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revised Transfer of Undertakings (Protection of Employment) Regulations came into force in 2006. These regulations provide rights to employees when their employer changes when a business is transferred to a new owner. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This publication provides guidance to employers, employees and their representatives to help them understand the regulations and comply with their legal requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note, this is general guidance; it should not be taken as a complete or authoritative statement of the law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56419</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/regional-growth-fund-confirmatory-due-diligence"/>
    <title>Regional Growth Fund confirmatory due diligence</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for regional growth fund (RGF) round 3 that explains who is eligible to be a due diligence provider to prepare a confirmatory due diligence report for RGF bids. This is required to confirm that their project or programme represents value for money and that it will deliver the benefits set out in their application. The scope of the due diligence report must be agreed by BIS and the bidder, and the Department must approve an applicant’s choice of due diligence provider. This guide also explains how due diligence providers can be engaged as an approved organisation and outlines the scope of the due diligence required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56331</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/modern-workplaces-consultation-government-response-on-flexible-parental-leave"/>
    <title>Modern workplaces [consultation]: government response on flexible parental leave</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government response to flexible parental leave elements of the closed consultation on modern workplaces (URN 11/699). Summarises public responses to the consultation and explains how the government will implement measures to encourage fathers to take a greater role in caring for their babies. These measures will also enable working families to be able to share the leave and pay that is currently only available for the mother. See 12/1268 for the related impact assessment and 12/1271 for the equality impact assessment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56339</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/modern-workplaces-consultation-government-response-on-flexible-parental-leave-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Modern workplaces [consultation]: government response on flexible parental leave. Impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of proposals on extending flexible parental leave in the closed consultation on modern workplaces (URN 11/699). The new system of flexible parental leave aims to give parents more choice and flexibility in how they care for their child in the first year, encourage more fathers to play a greater caring role, and increase flexibility for employers and employees to reach agreement. See also 12/1267 for the government response and 12/1271 for the equality impact assessment. Underlying data for this publication is available in a machine processable format on the Transparency/Report Data webpage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56357</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/modern-workplaces-consultation-government-response-on-flexible-working-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Modern workplaces consultation: government response on flexible working. Impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact of proposals to extend the right to request flexible working to all employees. These proposals aim to facilitate the employee-employer information exchange that can increase the availability and take-up of flexible working, provide all employees with the same access to flexible working, and improve the functioning of the labour market. Relates to the closed consultation on modern workplaces (URN 11/699). See also 12/1269 for the government response and 12/1271 for the equality impact assessment.Underlying data for this publication is available in a machine processable format on the Transparency/Report Data webpage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47150</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reform-of-flexible-parental-leave"/>
    <title>Reform of flexible parental leave</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;13 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg has announced reforms that will allow parents to share up to a year’s leave after the birth of a child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government plans to legislate on this next year, and will introduce the changes to flexible working in 2014 and to flexible parental leave in 2015. Under the new system, parents will be able to choose how they share the care of their child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employed mothers will still be entitled to 52 weeks of maternity leave. However, working parents will have much greater flexibility about how they ‘mix and match’ their leave. They may take it in turns or take it together, providing it is not more than 52 weeks in total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="greater-choice"&gt;Greater choice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers will have to take at least the initial two weeks of leave after birth as a recovery period, but can then choose to end the maternity leave and the parents can opt to share the remaining leave. It will be up to both parents to decide how they share the remaining weeks. Nick Clegg welcomed the announcement, saying;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reform is long overdue and the changes we are making will shatter the perception that women have to be the primary care-givers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the future, both mothers and fathers will be able to take control of how they balance those precious first months with their child and their careers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is good news not only for parents and parents-to-be, but employers too who will benefit from a much more flexible and motivated workforce.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="engaged-employees"&gt;Engaged employees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employers will benefit from being able to make the most of the entire talent pool that the increased flexibility allows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Employment Relations, Jo Swinson, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If we are to deliver sustainable, strong growth we need to get the best out of both men and women in the workforce.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Current arrangements are old-fashioned, inflexible and gender-biased. People should have the right to choose how they balance their work and family commitments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposals bring good news for business - not least a more motivated and productive workforce. Employers will be able to recruit and retain staff from a wider pool of talent in turn helping to diversify our economy and drive growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Extending the right to request flexible working will enable all employees to discuss flexible working with their employer, and move the discussion away from why the employee needs to work flexibly, and onto how flexible working will work for the business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Mums-and-dads-will-share-parental-leave-68330.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Mums and dads will share parental leave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/modern-workplaces?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;Consultation on Modern Workplaces - closed with response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/employment-matters"&gt;Employment matters at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/employment-matters/rights"&gt;Employment rights at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/employing-people"&gt;GOV.UK - guidance on employing people&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56375</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/modern-workplaces-consultation-government-response-equality-impact-assessment-eqia-on-flexible-parental-leave-and-flexible-working"/>
    <title>Modern workplaces consultation: government response. Equality impact assessment (EQIA) on flexible parental leave and flexible working</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the equality impacts of proposals to make employment practices in the UK more flexible and family-friendly. See URN 11/699 for the closed consultation and 12/1267-12/1270 for related government response documents and impact assessments. Underlying data for this publication is available in a machine processable format on the Transparency/Report Data webpage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56387</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-parental-leave-eu-directive-regulations-2013-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>The Parental Leave (EU Directive) Regulations 2013: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assesses the impact from draft regulations (URN 12/1284) that extend UK parental leave legislation to comply with EU Directive 2010/18 on Parental Leave by 2013. It intends to implement the Parental Leave Directive to encourage shared parenting and maintain attachment to the labour market whilst minimising burdens to business. This supports the proposed new system of flexible parental leave due to be introduced in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
