<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Managing, improving and investing in the road network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16037</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:35:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultation-to-scrap-motor-insurance-certificates-launched"/>
    <title>Consultation to scrap motor insurance certificates launched</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drivers could benefit from less motor insurance red tape after a government consultation to scrap the legal requirement to issue certificates was launched today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8 week exercise will seek the views of the industry, motorists and other stakeholders on the benefits of moving towards a purely online system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under current law, insurance companies must issue a paper or electronic certificate when agreeing a policy. However, many organisations, including the police and vehicle rental companies, already rely on information stored on the Motor Insurer’s Database (MID) as evidence of valid insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More and more people are using technology to organise their everyday lives so it is only right we look at how we can make life easier for motorists and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are launching a consultation to scrap the legal requirement for insurance certificates to be issued and consolidate a system whereby all information is online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has the potential to make significant savings down the line which I hope will be passed on to policyholders. It will also make the lives of motorists and police easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to moving to an online system include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motorists will no longer be forced to retain certificates as details will be accessible online. This will remove the legal requirement whereby vehicle owners are required to return their certificates to insurance companies in order to cancel the policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;police and the commercial motor industry would be better able to check details at source, instead of relying on policyholder documents which can be forged. The Police already use a download of the MID to identify uninsured drivers on the road.
If the consultation is successful then the Department would look to repeal the current law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposal is part of the government’s Red Tape Challenge, which invited the public and stakeholders to give their views on which regulations should stay, be improved, or be scrapped altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"&gt;consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available on the DfT website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department proposes to amend s147 (1) of the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue motor insurance certificates (whether issued as a paper document or electronically)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Association of British Insurers (ABI) estimate the cost of producing each certificate is about £1 and around 34.2 million insurance documents are issued per annum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15074</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T10:29:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:29:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/removal-of-motor-insurance-certificates"/>
    <title>Removal of motor insurance certificates</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on amending the Road Traffic Act 1988 to remove the need for insurers to issue a motor insurance certificate when an insurance policy is taken out. At present the certificate is used as evidence of valid insurance cover and there are circumstances when it must be produced by the insured to demonstrate they have valid cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurers are required by law to enter details of all motor insurance policies onto the motor insurance database (&lt;abbr title="motor insurance database"&gt;MID&lt;/abbr&gt;). This consultation document considers using the &lt;abbr title="motor insurance database"&gt;MID&lt;/abbr&gt; as the single source for checking if insurance cover is in place and considers what further changes and developments are needed to make this work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15068</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:21:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/driver-and-vehicle-licensing-agency-13-november-2012"/>
    <title>Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency 13 November 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has recently run a competition to procure a front office counter service provider for its face to face motoring services from next April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will award Post Office Ltd® a contract to build on the existing counter operation to provide a wider range of services and better accessibility for motorists. The contract will run for 7 years with an option to extend for up to another 3 years. This contract will allow the Post Office to fully develop better services with the requirements of customers at the heart. Under the contract Post Office Ltd® will offer &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; services at over 4,700 outlets for road tax and vehicle transactions, 750 of which will also cater for driver licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new contract provides value for money for the taxpayer resulting in savings of between £13 million and £15 million a year. The contract also gives scope for the Post Office to provide front office counter services for other government departments, to increase efficiencies across government and provide better value for the tax payer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14285</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T12:35:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T12:35:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/evesham-to-benefit-from-new-8-2-million-bridge"/>
    <title>Evesham to benefit from new £8.2 million bridge</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to replace the Abbey Bridge over the River Avon in Evesham can now start after the proposals received final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridge and viaduct need to be replaced as they are in poor condition and the current structures are already subject to a 7.5 tonne weight restriction. If the structures are not replaced then even lower restrictions would be needed in the near future along with the possibility of full closure to all traffic soon after. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When completed, the new bridge will allow the current weight limit to be removed bringing the bridge up to current national standards and allowing it to be used by HGVs, coaches and buses. The replacement bridge will improve access to Evesham town centre from the south for local residents and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This excellent scheme will restore the full capacity of this important route and provide a boost to the local economy by ensuring that access to the town centre for bus passengers and lorries is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The £5.6 million we are putting into this project shows that the Coalition Government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth both locally and nationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Abbey Bridge replacement scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work can now start on construction with the new bridge scheduled to open in December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants Full (final) Approval to the Abbey Bridge replacement scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The scheme, promoted Worcestershire County Council, is scheduled to open in December 2013. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department will provide a maximum of £5.59 million towards the full scheme cost of £8.2 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10586</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T16:19:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/provision-of-road-de-icing-salt"/>
    <title>Provision of road de-icing salt</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; Request for as much detail as possible for orders of grit during winter 2010-11, winter 2009-10 and winter 2008-09.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12311</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T09:39:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T09:39:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/road-user-charging-scheme-regulations"/>
    <title>Road user charging scheme regulations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department is seeking views on a proposal to provide for the fair and effective enforcement of road user charging schemes. The provisions contained in the proposal will be put into effect through regulations made under the Transport Act 2000, the Road User Charging Schemes (Enforcement) (England) Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations will allow enforcement actions such as the issuing of penalty charge notices, the examination of vehicles and equipment and the immobilisation, removal, storage and disposal of vehicles. Provisions will also cover arrangements for pursuing debt through the courts and adjudication. We consider that the consultation is of interest specifically to local transport authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14304</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T11:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T09:44:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/consultations-launched-for-dartford-free-flow"/>
    <title>Consultations launched for Dartford free-flow</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two consultations in support of a project to improve traffic flow and ease congestion at the Dartford - Thurrock River Crossing are being launched on Monday. Both consultations will lay the legal foundations for changes to how road user charges will be collected and enforced under a free-flow operation at Dartford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free-flow technology will allow motorists to use the Dartford Crossing without having to stop at barriers to hand over payment. It will allow the remote collection of payment through a variety of methods including telephone, text message, online, and at retail outlets – giving motorists greater flexibility in how and when they pay the charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two consultations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ‘Charging Scheme Order’ is being led by the Highways Agency and is a chance for local residents, authorities, businesses and emergency services to comment on proposals to give drivers options to pay the charge after they have used the Crossing, and the proposed enforcement measures that would be used under free-flow when it comes into effect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Enforcement Regulations’ is being run by the Department for Transport and is aimed at possible charging authorities which would include local authorities and the Highways Agency. It aims to &lt;a href="/government/consultations/road-user-charging-scheme-regulations"&gt;collect views on how road user charges should be enforced&lt;/a&gt;, ahead of free-flow being introduced at Dartford.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Free-flow charging is part of a package of planned improvements being carried out by the Government to improve motorists’ experiences in using the Dartford Crossing. Discounts will remain in place for those that set up an account and pay in advance and for those that qualify for the Local Residents’ Discount Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roads Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By removing the barriers at the crossing congestion will be reduced and traffic flow will improve for all motorists – but that means the way payment is collected will change.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We need to make sure we have steps in place to allow enforcement against drivers who do not pay their road user charge. How and what will happen needs to be decided and that is exactly what the Enforcement Regulations consultation will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Gray, Highways Agency senior project manager, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Dartford Crossing is a crucial piece of national infrastructure that brings economic benefits to the region and the whole country. We understand how frustrated motorists are and that is why tackling congestion here is an absolute priority.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The draft order sets out how the charge at Dartford will operate and how we propose to enforce it under a free-flow charging arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road users will be encouraged to pay the charge in advance of their use of the crossing. Proposals detailed in the Charging Scheme Order consultation set out the charges that will apply, and will allow road users to pay at the standard rate up to midnight on the day of using the crossing or at the standard charge plus 20% on the following day. After this the proposed penalty charge for non-payment would be £70, with a reduced rate of £35 if paid within 14 days. If the penalty is not paid within 28 days it is proposed that it would increase to £105.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A statutory public notice has been published by the Highways Agency in the technical and local press ahead of the ‘Charging Scheme Order’ consultation opening on Monday. Consultees have until Monday 28 January 2013 to make their comments. Both consultations will be available from Monday 5 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Charging Scheme Order can be viewed on the consultation page of the Highways Agency’s website, and at Dartford Borough Council and Thurrock Council offices. The Enforcement Regulations consultation will be available on the Department for Transport’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Highways Agency is an executive agency of the Department for Transport. We manage, maintain and improve England’s motorways and other strategic roads on behalf of the Secretary of State.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Dartford – Thurrock River crossing is a vital transport link over the lower Thames estuary to the east of London. Comprising of two tunnels (each carrying two lanes northbound) and a four lane cable stayed bridge for southbound traffic, it is one of the busiest transport gateways in the country, carrying around 150,000 vehicles every day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tackling congestion at the Crossing is a priority for the Government.  Improvements include suspending the charges during periods of heavy congestion following an incident, introducing free-flow charging to tackle congestion and improve journey times at the Crossing, and continuing work on analysing the options for a new Lower Thames crossing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The introduction of free-flow charging at Dartford is being progressed to the following timescale:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer 2012, start procurement process for customer charging and enforcement management services contract (underway)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autumn 2012, start public consultation on secondary legislation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Winter 2012/13, invite tenders for customer charging and enforcement management services contract&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Summer 2013, Statutory Instrument laid before parliament&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autumn 2013, contract award of customer charging and enforcement management services &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Summer 2014, technical go-live, controlled testing and integration&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autumn 2014, full operation of free-flow charging at Dartford&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A statutory public notice regarding consultation for the draft new Charging Scheme Order that would support free flow charging was published today (1 November) in the London Gazette and Dartford Messenger and will be published in tomorrow’s Thurrock Gazette (Friday 2 November)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statutory consultees, as well as other public bodies, organisations or businesses, and members of the public are invited to comment on the plans, which are specifically related to the Dartford Crossing, and set out how the charge will be collected, and how it will be enforced under a free-flow charging arrangement. The consultation will run for 12 weeks, until 28 January 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neither consultation asks consultees to comment on the Dartford road user charge rates.  DfT consulted in 2011 on proposals to revise the road user charge at the Dartford Crossing, and published their response to this consultation in May 2012. No further changes to the road user charge rates at the Dartford Crossing are proposed for the new Charging Scheme Order or the Enforcement Regulations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real-time traffic information for England’s motorways and other strategic roads is available:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;from the web at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/traffic"&gt;www.highways.gov.uk/traffic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;by phone from the Highways Agency Information Line on 0300 123 5000 at any time. (Calls to 0300 numbers will cost no more than 5p per minute from a standard BT residential landline. Call charges from other landlines and mobile networks may vary, but will be no more than a standard geographic call and will be included in all inclusive minutes and discount schemes). Make sure it’s safe and legal before you call. Before using any mobile, find a safe place to park. Never stop on the hard shoulder of a motorway except in an emergency.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on an iPhone app which will automatically select the region you are in. Free to download from the iTunes store or search for Highways Agency on your device.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;from Twitter – there are eight feeds with live traffic information provided by region. For information on roads in the south east region follow us &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/@HAtraffic_seast"&gt;@HAtraffic_seast&lt;/a&gt; or for the full index visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/twitter"&gt;www.highways.gov.uk/twitter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Receive our national and regional press releases by RSS and get the latest headlines straight to your desktop the moment we publish them to our website. Choose to receive a national press feed or one of our regionalised feeds - go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/rssnews"&gt;www.highways.gov.uk/rssnews&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Issued by the Highways Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information on the  Charging Scheme Order please contact Jane Manning, James Wright or Andrew Broughton. Tel: 01306 878110, 878442 or 01883 745364.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information on the Enforcement Regulations please contact Melanie Purkis at the Department for Transport press office on 0207 944 4604.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media enquiries out of hours should be made to the Highways Agency National Press Office (24hrs) on 0844 693 1448.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14355</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/amending-regulation-8-of-the-local-authorities-traffic-orders-exemptions-for-disabled-persons-england-regulations-2000"/>
    <title>Amending Regulation 8 of the Local Authorities' Traffic Orders (Exemptions for Disabled Persons) (England) Regulations 2000</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on amending one aspect of the legislation which covers the Blue Badge parking concessions. The amendment seeks to put beyond doubt the fact that local authorities are not required to allow Blue Badge holders to park in loading bays or on yellow lines when there is a ban on loading or unloading in force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14765</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-the-transport-elements-of-the-renewable-energy-directive"/>
    <title>Implementation of the transport elements of the Renewable Energy Directive</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Energy Directive (RED) requires the UK to ensure that 10% of the energy used in transport is from renewable sources in 2020, as well as requiring the introduction of mandatory sustainability criteria for biofuels. This consultation seeks views on proposed amendments to the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (RTFO) scheme in order to implement the RED and changes that aim to improve administration of the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14757</id>
    <published>2012-10-28T19:52:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-28T19:52:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/fees-for-hgv-and-psv-testing-and-operator-licensing-for-2011"/>
    <title>Fees for HGV and PSV testing and operator licensing for 2011</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultation on proposals for changes to Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) fees in Great Britain for statutory periodic and certain other tests and operator licensing for heavy goods vehicles (&lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGVs&lt;/abbr&gt;) and public service vehicles (&lt;abbr title="Public Service Vehicles"&gt;PSVs&lt;/abbr&gt;), eg buses and coaches used for hire or reward) and charges for voluntary checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultation also includes fees for Reduced Pollution Certificates (&lt;abbr title="Reduced Pollution Certificates"&gt;RPC&lt;/abbr&gt;) charged by &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; in Great Britain and by the Driver and Vehicle Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Agency"&gt;DVA&lt;/abbr&gt;) in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="final-impact-assessment"&gt;Final impact assessment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/fee-hgv-psv-testing-licensing/"&gt;Impact assessments of changes for 2012/13 to fees collected by the Vehicle and Operator Services Agency (&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) for &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicles"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Public Service Vehicles"&gt;PSV&lt;/abbr&gt; testing and operator licensing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
