<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Managing, improving and investing in the road network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T10:08:15+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56406</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:08:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agency-s-motorway-and-a-road-network"/>
    <title>Reliability of journeys on the Highways Agency’s motorway and A road network</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Impact indicator, disaggregated by junction, published monthly from May 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-impact-indicator"&gt;DfT Business plan impact indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geographical coverage: England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information broken down by: national level aggregation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provisional data show that 81.9% of journeys made on Highways Agency managed roads between December 2011 and November 2012 were ‘on time’. This is 0.4 percentage points lower than the previous rolling year, ending in October 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During November 2012, provisional data show that 76.6% of journeys on Highways Agency’s motorway and ‘A’ road network were ‘on time’. This is 4.7 percentage points lower than the equivalent figure for November 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The annual reliability measure consistently increased up to March 2012, but has fallen in the last eight months, and is now at a similar level to that observed in mid-2011. 2012 was the second wettest year since records began with substantial rainfall during the final three quarters of the year. Significant amounts of rainfall compared to 2011 will have led to slower speeds on the network, slower journeys and thus a fall in reliability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#01"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Percentage of journeys on Highways Agency motorways and A roads deemed ‘on time’: monthly from June 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="percentage-of-journeys-on-time"&gt;Percentage of journeys ‘on time’&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year ending&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Month&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year ending percentage points change&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;June 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;83.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;July 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;83.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;August 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;September 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;October 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;November 2012&lt;sup&gt;P&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-0.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source: Highways Agency Traffic Information System (HATRIS) Database&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;P&lt;/sup&gt; = provisional&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indicator monitors the reliability of journeys made on Highways Agency’s motorway and A road network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The indicator is measured by the percentage of ‘journeys’ on these roads that are ‘on time’. For this measure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a ‘journey’ represents travel between adjacent junctions on the network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an ‘on time journey’ is defined as one which is completed within a set reference time, drawn from historic data on that particular section of road&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reference journey times are updated for the April data each year - further information on the impact of updating reference times can be found in section 3 of the latest &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/road-congestion-and-reliability-statistics"&gt;statistical release&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At present, information about the reliability of journeys on individual routes, or between particular junctions on the network, are not sufficiently robust to be presented as official statistics. This is due to the range of different sources used to calculate journey times across the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has been working with the Highways Agency to address these issues of comparability. As a result we will be making a number of methodological changes to improve the quality of the reliability measure from the publication of the January 2013 statistics (in March). More detail on these changes will be provided in updated technical guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journey time reliability data for individual road sections is currently published by the Highways Agency through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.gov.uk"&gt;data.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: monthly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: 10 January 2013&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: 14 February 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agencys-motorway-and-a-road-network-november-2012"&gt;Reliability of journeys on Highways Agency’s motorway and ‘A’ road network: November 2012 - statistical release page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats#road-congestion-and-reliability-statistics"&gt;An introduction into the Department for Transport’s congestion statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats#road-congestion-and-reliability-statistics"&gt;Methodology for calculation of reliability on Highways Agency’s motorway and ‘A’ road network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For further information on this impact indicator, please contact: &lt;a href="mailto:jay.symonds@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jay.symonds@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/64205</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:16:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"/>
    <title>Stopping up and diversion orders: reform of the application process for local highways</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the ‘Penfold review’, this consultation details proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up and diversion of a highway where this is required for the purpose of property development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose to permit applications for a stopping-up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission for the proposed development (whereas under the existing legislation the developer can only apply after securing planning permission), and options for devolving decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 9 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--2"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 18 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review"&gt;Implementation of the Penfold review, written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 16 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64032</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Explaining the Secretary of State's decision about the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This letter gives details about the Secretary of State’s decision on the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It explains that the Secretary of State has decided to confirm the order subject to a specified modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector’s report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64036</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T08:55:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Luton Borough Council's compulsory purchase order for Station House: inspector's report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report was written by the inspector who held an inquiry into the Luton Borough Council (Station House, Midland Road) compulsory purchase order 2011. It contains recommendations to amend words in the order and then confirm it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk//government/publications/luton-borough-councils-compulsory-purchase-order-for-station-house-decision-letter"&gt;Luton Borough Council’s compulsory purchase order for Station House: decision letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/64307</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:03:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"/>
    <title>Implementation of the Penfold Review</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Proposals to simplify the process of stopping up or diverting a highway will be announced in a consultation response today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a government response to the consultation that closed on 24 August detailing proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up or diversion of a highway, where this is required for the purposes of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main options presented in the consultation were to permit applications for a stopping up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission and to devolve decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided not to devolve the stopping up and diversion order process to a local level. Consultation responses suggested that any devolution should be accompanied by a charging regime; additional costs and charges would be borne by both local authorities and those making applications, with no guarantee of a simpler or faster process. The government does not feel that placing additional burdens on local authorities and costs on developers is right at this time. And the government is aware that the speed of processing applications for stopping up or diversion orders has increased considerably in the last year. Additionally, we do not propose to reform or encourage a greater use of section 116 of the Highways Act 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government continues to support the first option, to allow stopping up and diversion applications to be made alongside planning applications. The government considers this will remove a significant barrier to growth, by speeding up the process and allowing a reduction of burdens on both applicants and local authorities, as both applications can be considered concurrently. Legislation currently in Parliament, as part of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, will give effect to this measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government response will be available in the libraries of both Houses and on the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"&gt;department’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60990</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-pinch-point-fund-application-pack"/>
    <title>Local Pinch Point Fund application pack</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These documents make up the application pack for the Local Pinch Point Fund. As part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2011_index.htm"&gt;2012 Autumn Statement&lt;/a&gt; the government announced the creation of a Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network which are impeding growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application pack consists of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;guidance about how to apply for this funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an application form &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme impact pro forma for small project bids &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61037</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T08:52:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"/>
    <title>TAL 1/13: Reducing sign clutter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Advice on the removal of unnecessary traffic signs to highway authorities in Great Britain.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="traffic-advisory-leaflet-tal-113"&gt;Traffic advisory leaflet (&lt;abbr title="Traffic advisory leaflet"&gt;TAL&lt;/abbr&gt;) 1/13&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over-provision of traffic signs can have a detrimental impact on the environment and can dilute more important messages if resulting in information overload for drivers. This leaflet, gives practical advice on reducing sign clutter. It emphasises that designers should use their engineering judgement and local knowledge to complement guidance to ensure signing solutions are effective. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60311</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/clear-up-initiative-saving-economy-millions-by-reopening-roads-quicker"/>
    <title>Clear-up initiative saving economy millions by reopening roads quicker</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An initiative to improve incident clear-up times is saving the economy tens of millions of pounds annually.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and the economy are seeing huge benefits from a government-led initiative to reopen motorways and roads quickly following major incidents, Roads Minister Stephen Hammond announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;’ (collision, lead, evaluate, act and reopen) initiative - launched by the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) last year to improve incident clear-up times – is helping to save the economy tens of millions of pounds annually, with even more savings to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key achievement has been the success of 38 &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;/police-funded 3D laser scanners which allow police forces to capture evidence quickly following collisions - helping to reopen major roads and motorways more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show an average time saving of 44 minutes per investigation – a 5 minute improvement on test estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other initiatives include the launch of a new hands-free smart phone app that notifies users of incidents and congestion, as well as the planned roll out of incident screens to shield collisions and prevent rubber necking. Time savings associated with screens alone can be up to several hundred thousand pounds per incident.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is confident these measures will help reduce the estimated £750 million cost to the economy that incidents cause on the strategic road network in England annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more frustrating than being stuck in a traffic jam for hours on end.  There is also the shocking cost of those lost hours for our economy. That is why we are improving the clear-up of incidents so we can get our motorways and major roads re-opened as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now witnessing even greater than expected time savings as a result of the roll out of laser scanning programme. This and other elements of the initiative, such as the use of incident screens, will help to keep traffic moving and save the economy tens of millions of pounds a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very encouraged by the cooperation shown by the Highways Agency, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Police and other emergency services, and fully expect these initiatives to result in further time and cost savings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief Constable Sean White, lead on collision investigations for the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This equipment allows police to manage critical events in a more efficient way and present the most accurate and detailed evidence to criminal, civil and coroners’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The time saved by using this technology is more economically friendly and reduces disruption on the roads, while allowing for thorough investigations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the success of this equipment, which has reduced delays for road users and proved extremely important in police investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Highways Agency signing a memorandum of understanding to facilitate data sharing about heavy goods vehicles. Studies have shown this type of vehicle is involved in a high proportion of the longest incidents. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working closely with operators to make sure problems are addressed   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the roll out by the Highways Agency of new towing equipment (load cells) to remove heavier vehicles obstructing live lanes and spill kits to clear spillages from motorway lanes. Time savings associated with the use of load cells have been estimated at several million pounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the production and distribution of a &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet to emergency responders outlining the roles and responsibilities of key organisations involved in managing incidents on the strategic road network. The Highways Agency has also produced a film reinforcing the booklet’s messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of emergency response guidance, training and learning to take on board &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of the 2007 Road Death Investigation Manual (RDIM) – the guiding doctrine of &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the 43 police forces of England and Wales to investigate and report on collisions that have resulted in a death. This is expected to be published in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report which sets out the next steps of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; is currently being finalised for publication next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laser-scanners"&gt;Laser scanners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laser Scanning Technology (LST) saves time by quickly making a 3D image of the whole incident scene, rather than investigators painstakingly surveying multiple sections of a scene. This digital image of the site can then be viewed on a computer screen remotely allowing investigators to take measurements of where vehicles are in relation to each other and examine other important evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009, the Highways Agency carried out an independent trial of 3D laser scanning technology using results from separate trials conducted by the Metropolitan Police Service and Humberside Police. The trials found that on average using laser scanners saved a total of 39 minutes on investigation time per incident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;38 laser scanners were funded by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Police for use by 27 police authorities at a cost of £4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest figures relate to information compiled from incidents over 4 months from forces using them on the strategic road network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clear"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2010 the Police, Highways Agency, Ambulance and Fire Services, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and related sponsoring departments came together to review evidence and knowledge about the handling of motorway incidents, and to make recommendations for improvement  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/review-of-investigation-and-closure-procedures-for-motorway-incidents-preliminary-report/review-of-investigation-closure-procedures-motorway-incidents.pdf"&gt;resultant report, published in May 2011 as the ‘Review of investigation and closure procedures for motorways incidents’ (PDF, 345KB)&lt;/a&gt;, made 10 recommendations and came together as the &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; initiative. The recommendations included further analytical work and some more immediate actions around, for example, supporting the wider roll out of laser scanning technology for the police to assist in speeding up incident investigation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congestion on the strategic road network is estimated to cost the economy £3 billion each year, 25% of which is caused by incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single incident that closes a 3 lane motorway for 4 hours can cost several million pounds in lost time, and there are some 80,000 incidents that impact at least one motorway lane each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; makes just 5% difference to the cost of congestion on the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Road Network"&gt;SRN&lt;/abbr&gt; it could save over £30 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="incident-screens"&gt;Incident screens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 105 sets of incident screens which will be made available for use by the Highways Agency next year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each set has 30 screens which are loaded onto purpose-built trailers and can screen up to 75 metres if used end-to-end (the individual screens are approximately 2.1 by two metres high)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They cost £2.3 million with each set costing £22,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="smart-phone-app"&gt;Smart phone app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	The Highways Agency app received 5,000 hits within the first 2 months of its launch. Further &lt;a rel="external" href="http://press.highways.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Hands-free-traffic-app-makes-Highways-Agency-data-available-to-road-users-ready-for-summer-67e24.aspx"&gt;information is available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spill-kits"&gt;Spill kits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Highways Agency"&gt;HA&lt;/abbr&gt; traffic officers will be equipped with spill kits to clear up small spillages such as fuel or other fluids which leak onto the carriageways from vehicles. The spill kits will absorb small spills and will allow the road to be safely re-opened while reducing damage to the carriageway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="load-cells"&gt;Load Cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load cells will be fitted to the tow straps used by traffic officers and will allow them to clear live lanes - moving heavier or damaged vehicles to the nearest place of safety.  The load cell acts as a strain gauge and will ensure that the safe towing load is not exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
