<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/managing-improving-and-investing-in-the-road-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Managing, improving and investing in the road network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/49794</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/dft-red-tape-challenge-and-logistics-growth-review-commitments"/>
    <title>DfT red tape challenge and logistics growth review commitments</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are seeking views on the implementation of three deregulatory commitments in the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/road-transport-red-tape-challenge"&gt;Red tape challenge road transportation regulations and actions consultation response&lt;/a&gt;’, about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) taking up the final exemption allowed in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; drivers’ hours rules for vehicles carrying cash/valuables&lt;br&gt;
(b) adopting the European timescales for downloading digital data from a tachograph&lt;br&gt;
(c) removing 3 regulations from the statute book  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, this consultation is seeking views on the commitment in the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/logistics-growth-review"&gt;Logistics growth review&lt;/a&gt;’ to explore opportunities to support green technologies through the operator licensing regime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/50140</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T10:57:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/integrated-transport-block-funding"/>
    <title>Integrated Transport Block funding</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We seeks views on the future calculation and distribution of the Integrated Transport Block. This is capital funding given to local authorities in England, outside of London, for small transport improvement schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/31807</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T10:58:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/removal-of-public-rights-of-way-over-land-held-for-planning-purposes"/>
    <title>Removal of public rights of way over land held for planning purposes</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Orders under &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1990/8/section/251"&gt;Section 251 of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990&lt;/a&gt; allow the removal of rights of way over land that local authorities hold for planning purposes (carriageway and footway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the local authority is going to acquire the land through compulsory purchase, that order and the 251 order can be carried out at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the outcome is that both orders are confirmed, the local authority must notify the Secretary of State that the land acquisition has occurred before the 251 order can be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/stopping-up-and-diversion-of-highways"&gt;247 application form and guidance notes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"&gt;Stopping up and diversion orders: reform of the application process for local highways&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/legislation-administered-by-the-department-for-transport"&gt;Legislation administered by the Department for Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/28520</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T16:05:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:05:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-huge-boost-for-transport"/>
    <title>Autumn statement: huge boost for transport</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor announced funding for the following transport projects as part of the Autumn statement 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scheme-a1-leeming-to-barton-improvements"&gt;Scheme: A1 Leeming to Barton improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £314 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upgrading the A1 between Leeming to Barton to motorway standard by upgrading a dual carriageway to a three lane road&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will create a continuous motorway standard route from Leeds to Newcastle and London to Newcastle (via M1/A1M)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will also improve journey times between Leeming and Barton and over 60 years is predicted to save around 100 lives and prevent around 650 serious casualties as well as helping speed up the time it takes to clear up traffic incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;during construction it is estimated that at its peak up to 750 new jobs will be created in the construction industry over the three year construction period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;completion of the scheme will support the economic competitiveness of the north-east and improve access to regional employment areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the reduction in journey times of some 20% will directly benefit business users, improving the attractiveness of these areas for future development and growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;works are planned to start in 2013/14 with the scheme open for traffic by 2016/17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a5-m1-link-dunstable-northern-bypass"&gt;Scheme: A5-M1 link (Dunstable northern bypass)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £126.6 million (Department for Transport (DfT) contribution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new dual two-lane road between the A5 (western end) and the M1 (eastern end) north of Dunstable and Houghton Regis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will remove through traffic between Dunstable and the M1 speeding up longer distance north south trips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will also unlock the development of 7,000 houses and 40 hectares of employment land – potentially providing 4,000 jobs – at Houghton Regis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work will start in 2014/15 with the scheme open for traffic in 2015/16.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a1-lobley-hill-improvement"&gt;Scheme: A1 Lobley Hill improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £64 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new roads in both directions parallel to the existing A1 between Lobley Hill and A184 in Gateshead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will provide an alternative route for local traffic improving congestion and accident rates on one of the most congested sections of the network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the government made a commitment through the Newcastle ‘City Deal’ process to work with local partners on considering proposals to address congestion on the A1 Newcastle/Gateshead western bypass – including proposals to deliver the Lobley Hill improvements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it also helps support local regeneration and development, including the creation of up to 22,000 new jobs, as the congestion is considered as a major constraint to expansion of regional employment and housing &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work is planned to start in 2014/15 with the scheme open for traffic by 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-highways-maintenance"&gt;Scheme: Highways maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £333 million &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated fund for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend life of road network in England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges, or repair damage caused by weather events, like recent floods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the money will be split between Highways Agency and local authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;details of how each area will benefit from this additional investment will be announced shortly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-strategic-road-pinch-point-fund"&gt;Scheme: Strategic road pinch point fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £100 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;additional funding for the Highways Agency’s pinch point fund to improve congestion and safety at bottlenecks on the strategic road network and facilitate local economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will be used for improvements such as road widening and junction improvements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes delivered as part of this programme will facilitate the creation of jobs and housing, improve access to enterprise zones and transport gateways that are within the vicinity of the scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Highways Agency will now work on identifying the specific projects that will benefit and make an announcement shortly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;Scheme: Local pinch point fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £170 million &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fund to remove bottlenecks and support development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes delivered as part of this programme will facilitate the creation of jobs and housing development, improve access to enterprise zones and transport gateways - this could include new access roads, junction improvements or bridge strengthening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is open to local transport authorities in England - guidance on how to apply for funding and timescales will be published shortly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes considered will be ones that can be delivered quickly delivering an immediate impact on growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a30-temple-to-carblake"&gt;Scheme: A30 Temple to Carblake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £60 million (£30 million DfT contribution and £30 million Cornwall Council contribution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 2.6 mile dualling of the existing single carriageway section of the A30 between Temple and Higher Carblake including changes to existing junctions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will relieve congestion and improve journey times - it will also attract business growth and inward investment to Cornwall by improving links the rest of England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cornwall Council is proposing to deliver and part-fund the scheme on behalf of the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work will start in 2014/2015 (subject to the completion of planning processes and funding agreements between Cornwall Council) with the scheme open for traffic in 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-accelerated-national-road-projects"&gt;Scheme: Accelerated national road projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £95 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the acceleration of three major motorway upgrades for M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey, M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands and M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire to deliver the improvement schemes by spring 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will result in increased capacity of 73 miles and reduced congestion through use of the hard shoulder as an extra lane&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vital improvements to the A160/A180 route to the port of Immingham will also be brought forward to start construction in the summer of 2015 (subject to the completion of statutory processes), with completion in autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-development-of-future-national-road-projects"&gt;Scheme: Development of future national road projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £42 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continuing the development (detailed design, modelling and preparatory work) of future major road projects to maintain a pipeline of major road infrastructure proposals for delivery in the next spending review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development work will put in place the necessary preparatory work and analysis to ensure the Department for Transport can plan its future investments and ensure it is in a position to deliver vital future infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development funding provides a contribution to UK job creation as it will be delivered in part through the transport supply chain &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department has previously identified a number of future national road proposals and will announce in due course which schemes will have their development work funded, following a process of prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-cycling-infrastructure-improvements"&gt;Scheme: Cycling infrastructure improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £42 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this funding will support infrastructure improvements that make it easier and safer for people get around their local areas by bicycle  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this could include more cycle lanes or tracks, improvements to junctions and signals, and cycle parking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local authorities will design solutions best for their areas while keeping a strong focus on economic growth and carbon reduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-m25-junction-30-improvements"&gt;Scheme: M25 junction 30 improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £150 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improved interface between M25 junction 30 and the A13 making the Thames Gateway more attractive to prospective developers, and improving access to the Lakeside shopping centre and the Port of Tilbury &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Highways Agency will now work up detailed plans for the scheme but options being considered are widening of the A13 and increased capacity at the junction roundabout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will need to take account of the location of an additional crossing over the Lower Thames&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following scheme was also announced but will be funded from existing Highways Agency budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scheme-m40-j12-improvement"&gt;Scheme: M40 J12 improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £10 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the layout at J12 of the M40 near Jaguar Land Rover’s (JLR) facility which includes their Research and Development Centre and the Aston Martin Lagonda site &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme includes realignment of the slip roads and a local side road and the installation of traffic signals at the top of the slip roads -it will assist traffic using the M40 which includes over 6,000 vehicles travelling to and from the JLR site and improve safety at the junction by alleviating traffic queuing back onto the M40 at peak times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme supports local economic growth and will benefit the national economy by reducing localised congestion on this strategic route between the Midlands and the south-east - it will also improve safety &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme is being funded from existing Highways Agency budgets &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17573</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T09:31:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/traffic-authorisations"/>
    <title>Traffic authorisations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Freedom of Information response letter concerns traffic authorisations given to Westminster City Council between 1 January 2000 and 31 December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/17387</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:56:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/speed-limit-exemption-for-life-saving-services"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemption for life-saving services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proposals to allow drivers from a wider range of emergency services to break the speed limit in order to save lives, have been published today for consultation by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance services are already allowed to exceed speed limits in the course of their emergency response duties and this is not changing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3 month consultation exercise will examine the possibility of extending the exemption to other services including those carrying organs for transplant, bomb disposal units and coastguard vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at amending road safety legislation so that emergency drivers would be required by law to complete high-speed training before exceeding the limit. But this will not place any additional burden on police, fire and ambulance services which already run an effective voluntary training scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance service drivers are highly trained individuals who are at times required to exceed the speed limit in order to save lives. It is only right that we look at allowing other services whose duties can mean the difference between life and death to exceed the speed limit when responding to emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also time to look at the legal requirements of emergency vehicle training so we can build on the rigorous standards the police, fire and ambulance services have already applied through their code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While emergency service drivers are not exempt from the offences of dangerous and careless driving, the current legislation allows drivers in some circumstances to break speed limits legally as well as exempting them from certain traffic regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be viewed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"&gt;DfT website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services currently exempt from speed limits include Police, the Fire Service, the Ambulance Service and the Serious Organised Crime Agency (shortly to be replaced by the National Crime Agency)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The full list of services who have expressed an interest in being exempt are listed within section 5 of the consultation document, they include Ministry of Defence bomb disposal units, fire (other than for fire and rescue authorities which are covered), conveyance of human tissue for transplant, blood transfusion, mountain rescue, mine rescue, radiation emergencies, coastguard and lifeboat launching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The emergency services set up a joint emergency services’ speed limit exemption driver training group to develop their procedures. It also includes representatives from the Driving Standards Agency, the Institute of Advanced Motoring and the Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents. It has developed a Code of Practice which is based around current best practice for each of the exempt organisations and reflects what is being taught there, recognising that there are organisation specific competencies. The consultation proposes using this Code of Practice as the basis for the regulated standards for the mandatory training courses to be used following the proposed legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation includes a set of criteria designed to establish the rationale of each request, balancing the operational need for the exemption against any potential road safety risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation proposes amending the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984 and make any legal exemption dependent on drivers attaining the core competencies identified in the Emergency Services’ Code of Practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"&gt;Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles&lt;/a&gt; written statement by Stephen Hammond MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/17020</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:53:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department has today published a consultation paper on Speed Limit Exemptions for vehicles used for emergency purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper proposes that Section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) is brought into effect. Section 19 allows the Secretary of State for Transport to designate other vehicle purposes as being exempt from speed limits in certain circumstances and if drivers of said vehicles complete successfully a “high-speed training course”.  Section 19 replaces Section 87 of the Road Traffic Regulation Act (1984) in relation to exemptions from speed limits for certain vehicle purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department recognises that there are certain vehicle purposes that the wider public may well consider as having a speed limit exemptions but which do not currently.  These include, for example, vehicles used to carry human tissue for transplant, mountain rescue teams, bomb disposal squads and others listed in the consultation document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branches of the Emergency Services (Police, Fire Service &amp;amp; Ambulance Service) are currently exempt from speed limits and provide appropriate training to their staff.  No additional requirements will be placed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has worked with representatives of the police, fire and rescue, NHS ambulance services, the Serious Organised Crime Agency and road safety stakeholders on the development of standards for driver training.   This led to the creation of a code of practice based on the principles applied in each organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department seeks to identify the core competencies specified in the code of practice and include them in regulations. It also proposes that the Driving Standards Agency (DSA) will take responsibility for the accrediting and quality assuring training providers seeking to provide high speed driver training courses, against the competences identified in the code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further consideration within the consultation document is to exempt paramedics and other medical personnel from the requirements to wear seatbelts in the back of ambulances, particularly when providing emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/17623</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:52:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemptions</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes that section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) be brought into effect. This would replace section 87 of the Road Traffic Regulation Act (1984) in relation to exemptions from speed limits for certain vehicle purposes. Regulations are needed to bring it into effect and set out the detail of how it would work. This document contains the department’s proposed approach to implementing the regulations in Section 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes would have two major effects. Firstly it will allow certain other vehicle purposes to be included in speed limit exemption regulations. Secondly it will prescribe a high speed training course that drivers must undertake (or be in the process of taking) before they are permitted to exceed speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation document also considers regulations related to 5 other exemptions from road traffic laws (related to signals, signalled crossings, certain signs and motorway hard shoulders) It includes proposals to amend some of these other provisions at the same time that section 19 is commenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document will also seek views about the planned introduction of a further exemption from seat belt requirements related to the treatment of patients in the back of ambulances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/43721</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T09:27:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link inspector's report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This inspector’s report was written by the inspector who held inquiries following the publication of Cornwall Council’s side roads order and compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gov.uk/government/publications/camborne-pool-redruth-stage-1-east-west-link-decision-letter/" title="decision letter"&gt;Camborne-Pool-Redruth Stage 1 East-West Link decision letter, 22 November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
