<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/supporting-economic-development-projects-in-coastal-and-seaside-areas--4/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-development-projects-in-coastal-and-seaside-areas--4/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-economic-development-projects-in-coastal-and-seaside-areas--4/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Supporting economic development projects in coastal and seaside areas"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-08-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14672</id>
    <published>2012-08-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/six-seaside-towns-get-money-to-kick-start-year-round-jobs"/>
    <title>Six seaside towns get money to kick-start year round jobs</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six seaside projects that will create vital new jobs and local enterprises are the first to receive Government backing to help their coastal town prosper, Communities Secretary Eric Pickles announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £24million Coastal Communities Fund was launched earlier this year to provide coastal towns with money to help pay for projects that can transform and diversify seaside economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles made the announcement on a visit to Bournemouth today to see first hand how one project will use the grant to create Europe’s first National Coastal Tourism Academy that will help create hundreds of jobs in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding can be used for a variety of projects including skills training, apprenticeship schemes and enterprises that rejuvenate seaside assets or that exploit emerging industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s first round of successful schemes in England will receive grants of up to £2million each to use on projects that creates local jobs, that supports coastal tourism and development and that boosts the inshore fisheries industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also revealed that next year the Coastal Communities Fund will be increased by £4million to £28million, a 17 per cent increase on this year. The fund is open to coastal towns across the United Kingdom and is funded by the Exchequer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is huge potential in our coastal towns that goes way beyond them only being places we visit for seaside day trips and holidays. We are seeing opportunities being developed all the time by new industries and the Government is determined to help our coastal towns make the most of them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This money will help those towns tap into these enterprises and create the skills and jobs that will benefit the whole community. We cannot afford to waste this chance which is why the Government is committed to increasing the fund next year.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The successful projects in this first round have enormous potential to make a real difference to their communities that will be far reaching. And this is just the beginning with our fund set to help many more coastal towns in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Secretary to the Treasury, Danny Alexander, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This first round of successful awards under the Coastal Communities Fund will directly support local communities to regenerate their local area. The fund will enable councils, businesses, charities and social enterprises to create and protect jobs and training opportunities for thousands of people across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We are today able to announce that the fund will expand again next year to £28million. It is right that the contribution these communities make to the development of the Crown Estate’s marine assets is recognised and rewarded and I look forward to another round of successful, innovative bids later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-round-winners"&gt;First round winners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful first round winners and their fund allocation are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Barrow in Furness&lt;/strong&gt; - £900,000 to support the ‘Unleashing Growth in Coastal Furness’ initiative which aims to create 275 full-time jobs and more than 85 part time jobs;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bournemouth Borough Council&lt;/strong&gt; - £2million over two years to create Europe’s first National Coastal Tourism Academy (NCTA). They will also use funds for activities including support for coastal tourism businesses, a resort wide customer care programme and coastal tourism research and development. The project aims to create 165 tourism jobs over three years in Bournemouth and 2,100 nationwide;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;National Lobster Hatchery, Padstow, Cornwall&lt;/strong&gt; - £150,500 to provide four new jobs and 15 training and volunteering opportunities at this social enterprise which maintains and develops the stock of a commercial species of lobster and runs a visitor centre which promotes sustainable and responsible marine management.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;RAK Maritime Project in East Anglia&lt;/strong&gt; - £757,000 to provide maritime training to 63 young people each year over two years to support the renewable energy industry in East Anglia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;South East Food Group Partnership&lt;/strong&gt; - £25,000 from their £80,000 bid to support the in-shore fisheries industry of South East England under the name ‘Local Fish for Local People’. The project will create 15 full-time sales posts for fishermen or family members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Suffolk County Council&lt;/strong&gt; - £762,000 to create 200 new employer-led apprenticeships to develop skills needed in the low carbon energy sector in coastal communities in Norfolk, Suffolk and Essex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further successful seaside town bidders will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund is financed by the Government. Money is allocated to England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland on the basis of revenue generated by the Crown Estate’s marine assets and is administered and distributed in partnership with the Big Lottery Fund’s ‘BIG Fund’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been enormous interest in the fund from projects in England with 129 expressions of interest received for this first initial round of funding and a further 501 expressions received for a future round which covers more complex bids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The creation of a UK-wide Coastal Communities Fund was announced by the Government last year to provide grants on a bid basis to support the economic development of coastal communities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fund is equal to 50 per cent of the revenues generated by the Crown Estate’s marine assets. Based on the Crown Estate’s Marine revenues in 2010/11 (£47.4million) the overall fund is worth £23.7million beginning in 2012. Funds can be used to support both capital and revenue projects and communities are encouraged to match funds with other pots of money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fund is directly linked to the revenue raised in each country. In April 2013 the fund will be broken down as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland each have country specific arrangements and work in partnership with the BIG Fund, the non-Lottery funding operation of the Big Lottery Fund, to deliver the money. The Big Lottery Fund has powers to deliver funding from non-lottery sources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those eligible to bid for funds include charities, social enterprises, local authorities, local enterprise partnerships and development agencies in the Devolved Administrations, and private sector companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14667</id>
    <published>2012-08-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympics-legacy-minister-returns-to-weymouth-and-portland-and-supports-local-business"/>
    <title>Olympics Legacy Minister returns to Weymouth and Portland and supports local business</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill, Olympics Legacy and Growth Minister, visits Weymouth and Portland on Tuesday, 7 August to watch sailing events on the Nothe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include the Men’s and Women’s RS:X (windsurfing) medal races, and the Women’s Elliot 6m quarter finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is absolutely fantastic that team GB are doing so well at the Games, and I’m thrilled to be here again in Weymouth and Portland to experience the sailing events first hand. The local area has had a real buzz over the last few days with Ben Ainslie striking gold and the superb race that Iain Percy and Andrew Simpson gave to win their silver medal on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My visit has also provided a wonderful opportunity to visit the town and see, first hand, some of the key local projects including the sports arena on the beach, where children are getting the chance to try a wide range of sports.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The fact that so many people are enjoying both the sailing and the free events here shows these really are Great Britain-wide games. If anyone is looking for something fun to do in their holidays this week and beyond, I can whole heartedly say that Weymouth and Portland is a splendid place to visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2195769.jpg" alt="Bob Neill visits the Dorset Ice Cream Company"&gt;Bob Neill visits the Dorset Ice Cream Company&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the Minister will also visit local businesses including the innovative pop-up store ‘Quba’ in Brewers quay. And he will watch some of the Olympic events on the large screens on the Live site on the beach with the thousands of local supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a huge effort from people across the UK to ensure that everything is ready for the Games, and Weymouth and Portland has played a key role. The whole Olympics package on offer in the local area is a great chance to show off Weymouth and Portland, and celebrate the role that people, places and businesses from the region are playing in London 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. South West and Sport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South West region has hosted more than 40 pre-Games training camps for many of the world’s sailing teams who have trained at the new Weymouth and Portland Sailing Academy, the Castle Cove Sailing Club and Weymouth College. The University of Bath has hosted the Chinese swim team and the Malaysian Olympic team and will host the British and Danish Paralympic teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic and Paralympic athletes from the region include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ben Ainslie CBE (Sailing)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tom Daley (Diving)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liam Tancock (Swiming)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anne Dunham (Paralympian - Equestrian)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. South West and the Olympic Park&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 60 local businesses have played a role in the construction of the Olympic Park, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Structural Metal Decks in Poole - supplied metal decking and studs for the Olympic Stadium&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Riise in Plymouth - which provided underfloor heating for the Athlete’s Village&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;B&amp;amp;B Moulds near Ilminster in Somerset - supported the concrete casting on the Olympic Stadium&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blom UK - an aerial photography firm which has captured images of the Olympic Park developing over time&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than £12 million worth of Olympic Park contracts were won by businesses based in the South West, with further benefits cascading down the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. South West and Torch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Torch was in the region for eleven days, taking in key landmarks such as St Michael’s Mount Cornwall and Royal Crescent in Bath, Stonehenge and Durdle Door on the Jurassic Coast. It also travelled by Rainforest Balloon at the Eden Project and was carried by Vintage Boats in Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. South West and Inspire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 270 community projects have been awarded the Inspire Mark, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Community Action Through Sport (CATS) in Bude, Cornwall, which encourages troubled teenagers to do voluntary work by offering surfing courses which help them gain accredited surfing and beach safety awards&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dance in Devon, a group encouraging the county to don their dancing shoes in a series of events and activities - among them a ‘Dancing on Dartmoor’ extravaganza featuring live music and traditional dancing at Haytor in Dartmoor National Park&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RELAYS (Regional Educational Legacy in Arts and Youth Sport) - a project delivered through universities in the south west of England. It aims to inspire young people and their communities to participate in, create and promote cultural and sporting activities. Successful festivals, events, collaborations and mentoring have been delivered through the three strands of the RELAYS programme: sport, cultural and business support.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. South West and Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been more than 100 locally funded and managed cultural projects officially inspired by London 2012 in the South West, including Teenage Rampage which supports young musicians across the region and played a starring role at the unveiling of the Olympic Rings at St Pancras in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the major cultural highlights include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give me tomorrow - (19 May - 23 Sep), a new exhibition at Tate St Ives by one of the most important and respected living American artists, Alex Katz, covering all six decades of his career&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Piercing Brightness (Penzance 24 Jun - 29 Sep), an exhibition of new work by internationally acclaimed Shezad Dawood presented in two venues in Penzance&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Music Nation (March), which saw the BBC Concert Orchestra working with children and families across Devon and Cornwall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14644</id>
    <published>2012-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bob-neill-visits-weymouth-and-portland-as-olympic-flame-visits-dorset"/>
    <title>Bob Neill visits Weymouth and Portland as Olympic flame visits Dorset</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and Olympic Legacy Minister Bob Neill, was in Weymouth and Portland on 12 July to meet local partners and community leaders to thank them for all the valuable work they have been doing to support the Olympic and Paralympic Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2180978.jpg" alt="Bob Neill holding an umbrella"&gt;Bob Neill and the Mayor of Chickerell watch the Torch Relay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit he toured the athletes’ village at the Olympic and Paralympic sailing venue which after the Games will made available to the public as affordable housing. He then went to visit the town of Chickerell to see the Olympic Flame as it entered the Weymouth and Portland area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Weymouth and Portland has worked incredibly hard to make sure that everyone who comes to the borough to experience the sailing events has a fantastic time and to ensure that they maximise the legacy opportunities created by the Games. It’s great to see local authorities working so well together to support the Games.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Despite today’s torrential rain, the enthusiasm about the arrival of the Olympic Flame has been unwavering and I am sure that this passion will continue right until the middle of September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Weymouth Mr Neill also took the opportunity to visit Dorset Fire and Rescue service personnel at Weymouth Community Fire Station and thanked them for their work in helping local communities cope with immediate effects of the floods in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’d like to thank the Dorset Fire Service for their work during the recent floods which have hit Dorset severely in recent days. The professionalism and support of that the fire service in dealing with these incidents is of great comfort and reassurance to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9868</id>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/seaside-town-rejuvenation-24-million-fund-opened"/>
    <title>Seaside town rejuvenation: £24 million fund opened</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new fund to help support much loved seaside towns create new jobs and prosperity was launched today by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Chief Secretary Danny Alexander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £23.7million Coastal Communities Fund has been created to provide struggling coastal communities all across the country with money to support new opportunities that can make their town prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today a variety of organisations are being invited to apply for the funding, first announced by the Chief Secretary, to diversify and transform seaside economies by allowing them to rejuvenate traditional assets or exploit new emerging industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seaside groups could use the money to start programmes that can deliver skills training, offer apprenticeships to school leavers, create new workspaces or support small-scale transport improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful applicants can expect to get a grant of between £50,000 and £2million. Mr Pickles said he would especially like to see quality bids come in from social enterprises, charities, local businesses or local enterprise partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Seaside towns and coastal communities have huge potential for economic growth that we simply can’t afford to waste - this fund can make all the difference to these places we all know and love.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This is a great opportunity for long overlooked seaside towns, large and small, to grab a chance to grow through imaginative and innovative projects that create, skilled workers, and provide year round jobs that build stronger local economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Secretary to the Treasury, Danny Alexander, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having grown up in a coastal community in Scotland, I am only too aware of the vital role these communities play in the UK. It is fair that we share the Crown Estate’s marine revenues equally and I am delighted to launch the Coastal Communities fund prospectus today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We look forward to receiving innovative bids from charities, businesses, social enterprises and local organisations, which support the economic development of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fund will be financed by the Government from revenues from the Crown Estate’s marine assets. The Fund will be UK wide, with funding allocated to England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland on the basis of revenue generated by these marine assets. The Fund will be delivered by the Big Lottery Fund’s ‘BIG Fund’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of the Department of Finance and Personnel in Northern Ireland, Sammy Wilson, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Northern Ireland Executive is committed to rebuilding and rebalancing the local economy and economic, social and physical renewal is an important part of that. Northern Ireland is renowned for its natural beauty along our coastal routes and this new initiative will provide some welcome funding for a number of local development projects in coastal communities which have much to offer in terms of natural and sustainable tourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A prospectus setting out eligibility, suggestions of how to use funds and details of how to bid was published today: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/coastalfundprospectus"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/coastalfundprospectus&lt;/a&gt;. Applications will be accepted in April.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each country will have a country specific board who will work with Big Fund, the non-Lottery funding operation of the Big Lottery Fund, to deliver the money. The Big Lottery Fund has powers to deliver funding from non-lottery sources for charitable purposes or purposes connected with health, education or the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fund will be equal to 50 per cent of the revenues generated by the Crown Estate’s marine assets. Based on the Crown Estate’s Marine revenues in 2010/11 (£47.4million) the overall fund will be worth £23.7million beginning in 2012. Funds can be used to support both capital and revenue projects and communities will be encouraged to match funds with other pots of money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9146</id>
    <published>2011-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bob-neill-hails-the-great-british-seaside-at-international-coastal-conference"/>
    <title>Bob Neill hails the Great British seaside at international coastal conference</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Bob Neill spoke about the enormous economic potential of the Great British seaside in a speech at the first ever international conference for coastal communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held in the seaside setting of Clacton, the conference discussed how seaside towns can become economic hubs and shared success stories from as far a field as France, Italy, and Malta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was hosted by Tendring District Council, Essex County Council and the Council of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Event’s like this are an important way to highlight to unique role coastal areas and seaside towns play in Britain’s history, culture and economy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Come rain or shine we all have fond memories of trips to the Great British Seaside, but they are more than holiday destinations we also need to ensure they are great places to live and work. Many seaside towns are showing how they can become year round places of business given the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to rebalancing local economies through local enterprise partnerships and small business tax breaks as well as by putting local people back in charge of their own economic growth through neighbourhood plans and community incentives like the New Homes Bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Stock, Leader of Tendring District Council, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Businesses are willing to invest if they get the right messages from the public sector. It is up us to create the right environment for them to operate and draw in the money which will lead to more jobs and regeneration in Tendring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="communities-back-in-control"&gt;Communities back in control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting local authorities and communities back in charge and giving them the freedom to drive their own economic development and growth is a key priority for the Government:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through the Localism Bill, the Government is devolving greater powers to councils and neighbourhoods, so local communities are able to shape their own future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government has invited local business and local councils to come together and take charge of their local economy and establish local enterprise partnerships. The new network of 35 Local Enterprise partnerships covers 95 per cent of all businesses and 96 per cent of the population in England.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kent, Greater Essex and East Sussex local enterprise partnerships, who attended the conference, are already working together and have set up a new group to look at some of the issues facing the coastal towns in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To further encourage investment across the country the Government is creating 21 new Enterprise Zones to be developed within the local enterprise partnerships. Businesses in Enterprise Zones will benefit from superfast broadband, lower business tax rates, low levels of regulation and planning controls, and reduced business rates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9682</id>
    <published>2011-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/localism-to-spark-growth-revival"/>
    <title>Localism to spark growth revival</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill is unashamedly pro-growth and will once and for all deal with the problems that have led to a crisis in development in this country, Decentralisation Minister Greg Clark has said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Clark said the single most important test for each provision in the Bill was whether it helped to promote and unlock growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of tinkering around the edges, the Bill was designed to fundamentally overhaul a flawed system that has pitted communities against development, with housebuilding at its lowest level in any peacetime year since 1924, Mr Clark said in a speech to the Adam Smith Institute (see link, top right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Clark said the major obstacle to growth has been a planning system that has led to a rising tide of resistance to development by shutting communities out of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill will be a huge opportunity to reboot the planning system making it pro-growth and pro-development, by allowing much greater involvement of communities from the outset to shape their neighbourhood and to share directly in the rewards of growth, not just the costs, Mr Clark said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every home built, the local authority will get six years of matched council tax funding, through the new homes bonus - to use locally whether to keep council tax at an affordable level, invest in homes, or improve services, Mr Clark said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And councils will be required to ensure that a significant proportion of the charge raised through the Community Infrastructure Levy is spent in the neighbourhood where the development takes place, to improve parks and schools, playgrounds and cycle-paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Clark said the Bill will restore meaningful public participation in planning by stripping out the regional bureaucracy that imposed decisions on communities. New neighbourhood plans will allow communities to shape a vision for their area - where new homes, schools and shops will go - and be able to bring it into force through a local referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Localism Bill is unashamedly pro-growth. Everything within it is designed to unlock the barriers to growth that have led to a crisis in development, with housebuilding at its lowest level in any peacetime year since 1924.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The huge opportunity of the Bill is to reboot the planning system so it is no longer one of the major obstacles to growth. We have got into a disastrous situation where communities have become pitted against development by being shut out of the process and seeing only the costs, never the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;By allowing communities to share directly in the rewards of growth and giving them the chance to shape a positive future for their areas, the Bill will create the conditions where people begin to welcome rather than resist growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside changes to increase efficiency in the planning system, measures in the Localism Bill will give local government a stronger financial stake in the local economy, helping rebalance the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils will be more entrepreneurial and better placed to attract local business through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;flexibilities to grant discretionary business rate discounts;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;making small business tax breaks easier to take advantage of;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;giving affected businesses a greater say in rate supplements; and&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cancelling certain backdated business rates including port taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, ministers are pursuing a programme of reform to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the burden of regulations on the housebuilding sector;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establish a growing network of Local Enterprise Partnerships, helping to create a fairer and more balanced economy driven by private sector strength; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;examine options to enable councils to retain their locally-raised business rates, providing incentives for them to promote economic growth through the business rates system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last November, the Government also launched the Growth Review to provide a fundamental assessment of what each part of Government is doing to provide the conditions for private sector success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
