<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the rented housing sector"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60137</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-200-million-build-to-rent-fund-will-boost-housebuilding"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk: £200 million Build to Rent fund will boost housebuilding</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new £200 million fund will boost the construction of new homes specifically for private rent, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Build to Rent fund aims to cut the risk for developers more traditionally used to building homes for sale who are looking to branch out into building homes for private rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By financing the construction of rental homes until they are built, let out and managed, the fund will give developers the freedom to build homes specifically for that market with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management companies will have the chance to invest in these new rental developments, and developers will then repay the investment from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the new fund, the Housing Minister described it as yet another step to support housebuilding which will help boost the economy, create jobs and strengthen the housing market by providing people with a broader housing choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reviving-the-rental-market"&gt;Reviving the rental market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that Build to Rent follows recommendations contained in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment" title="Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment"&gt;Montague report&lt;/a&gt; into rented homes earlier this year and will help address the varying level of quality across the nation’s private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of private rental landlords are small-scale, individual investors. This fund will redress the balance, by stimulating the market in private rented homes for large-scale housing organisations that will in turn help set a new benchmark for landlords across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kickstart this new, larger scale market for privately rented homes, the minister said that Build to Rent will fund ‘demonstration’ projects to show how it might work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expert taskforce will also work to boost investor awareness of the fund and offer practical support to those interested in this new market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A healthy rental housing market must have a broad range of choice across the board. But for it to grow and develop, we must first attract new investors. The Build to Rent fund will support this, helping to build homes specifically for private rent and breathing new life into the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by driving this market in housebuilding, the fund will also help create new jobs, build the homes that families need and local people want, and support economic growth across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor of London Boris Johnson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The private rented sector now houses a quarter of Londoners and has the potential to support the delivery of a huge number of new homes in the future. I welcome this funding and I will continue to make the case that investment in London’s housing infrastructure is one of the best ways to deliver much needed construction jobs and economic growth now, while at the same time laying the foundations for our economic growth for years to come.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greater London Authority will lead on assessing the expressions of interest for sites in London. Shortlisting decisions will be made by DCLG, the Homes and Communities Agency and the Greater London Authority. The Homes and Communities Agency will undertake due diligence, contracting and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £200 million Build to Rent Fund is now open for bids, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/private-rented-sector" title="Build to Rent Fund prospectus"&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt; has been published on the HCA website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fund has been developed to support purpose built, private rented demonstration schemes across England which have the potential to attract investors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has appointed two non-executive members following open competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16882</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:46:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/housing-capital-receipts-exemptions-from-regulations"/>
    <title>Housing capital receipts: exemptions from regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities applying to use receipts from the disposal of council housing assets in ways not prescribed in regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of receipts arising from the disposal of housing assets (ie assets held under part 2 of the Housing Act 1985 and for which account is made in the Housing Revenue Account) is governed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/1324/made"&gt;Local Authorities (Capital Finance and Accounting) (England) Regulations 2003 (as amended.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations require that, in short: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receipts arising from Right to Buy (and similar sales may be retained to cover the cost of transacting the sales and to cover the debt on the properties sold, but a proportion of the remainder must be surrendered to central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receipts arising from all other disposals may be retained in full provided they are spent on affordable housing, regeneration or the paying down of housing debt (each of which is defined in the regulations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, section 11(6) of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents"&gt;Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; (as inserted by section 174 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;) permits the secretary of state to enter into agreements with local authorities with the effect that any requirement imposed by these regulations does not apply, or is modified in its application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enter into such an agreement it is necessary for any interested authority to make an application to the secretary of state. This guidance sets out the Department for Communities and Local Government’s policy on such exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister, Mark Prisk, to the Council of Mortgage Lenders' annual conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17139</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T08:26:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment"/>
    <title>Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An independent review of the private rented housing sector carried out by Sir Adrian Montague.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report summarises the results of Sir Adrian Montague’s review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes. It examines how best to encourage greater investment in rental properties and explores the factors that might encourage institutions to invest in new homes for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector"&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; was included in the housing and planning package announced on 6 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17203</id>
    <published>2012-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T08:26:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment-call-for-evidence"/>
    <title>Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment - call for evidence</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>A call for evidence for the independent review of the private rented housing sector carried out by Sir Adrian Montague.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is Sir Adrian Montague’s formal call for evidence to support the independent review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadline for responses was 30 March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment"&gt;final report&lt;/a&gt; summarising the results of the review was published on 23 August 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56475</id>
    <published>2011-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T01:40:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/power-shift-from-whitehall-to-communities-gets-underway"/>
    <title>Power shift from Whitehall to communities gets underway</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An era of Whitehall control has ended with a historic shift in power back to local people, as the Localism Bill becomes law.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; will trigger the biggest transfer of power in a generation, releasing councils and communities from the grip of central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flagship legislation, which late yesterday afternoon received Royal Assent, puts a raft of new rights and powers at the disposal of local people to take charge of their future, delivering on more than 30 coalition agreement commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key measures to increase the power of local government through the Act include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing a new general power of competence, giving councils unprecedented freedom to work together to improve services and drive down costs; councils are now free to do anything, provided they do not break other laws&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opening the door for the transfer of power to our major cities to develop their areas, improve local services, and boost their local economies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ending the ineffective system for overseeing the behaviour of councillors by abolishing the Standards Board&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarifying the rules on predetermination in order to free up councillors to express their opinions on issues of local importance without the fear of legal challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to return to the committee system of governance, if they wish, regardless of their size; centrally set rules interfering in how councils set up their own affairs are being scrapped&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving councils greater control over business rates. Councils will have the power to offer business rate discounts, which could help attract firms, investment and jobs. The Act cancels unfair backdated business rates, which threatened to cripple key businesses. It stops plans to impose a business rate supplement on firms if a simple majority of those affected do not give their consent, and simplifies the process for claiming small business rate relief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing new planning enforcement rules, giving councils the ability to take action against people who deliberately conceal unauthorised development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increasing powers for councils to remove illegal advertisements and graffiti and prevent fly-posting, and giving planning authorities stronger powers to tackle abuses of the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reforming homelessness legislation to enable councils to provide good quality private rented homes where appropriate, freeing up social homes for people in need on the waiting list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing councils to keep the rent they collect and use it locally to maintain social homes through the abolition of the housing revenue account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;passing greater powers over housing and regeneration to local democratically elected representatives in London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key measures to increase the power of local communities include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid"&gt;Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, which will give residents the opportunity to take over treasured local assets like shops and pubs and keep them part of local life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-challenge"&gt;Right to Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, making it much easier for local groups with good ideas to put them forward and drive improvements in local services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consigning bin taxes to the dustbin of history, by removing the ability of councils to charge families for overfilling their bin and to introduce extra tariffs for taking away household waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increasing transparency on local pay, by requiring councils to publish the salaries of senior officials working in local authorities, enabling local people to understand how public money is being spent in their area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving communities the right to veto excess Council Tax rises. Previously only central government had the power to ‘cap’ increases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a new right to draw up a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood plan&lt;/a&gt;, giving local people a real voice to say where they think new houses, businesses and shops should go - and what they should look like&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling communities to bring forward proposals for development they want - such as homes, shops, playgrounds or meeting halls, through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freeing home sellers and buyers from red tape through the abolition of Home Information Packs (&lt;abbr title="Home Information Packs"&gt;HIPs&lt;/abbr&gt;);  the Act removes &lt;abbr title="Home Information Packs"&gt;HIPs&lt;/abbr&gt; once and for all from the statute books&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling people to swap their social home, for example because they wish to move jobs. A national home swap scheme will give access to details of all other tenants who may be a match&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving social tenants stronger tools to hold their landlords to account. Landlords will be expected to support tenant panels - or similar bodies - so tenants can carefully examine the services being offered; the Tenant Services Authority will be abolished&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requiring developers to consult local communities before submitting certain applications; this gives people a chance to comment while there is still scope to make changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ending decision-making by unaccountable officials on important infrastructure projects such as train lines and power stations; the Act abolishes the Infrastructure Planning Commission, and restores responsibility for taking decisions to elected, accountable ministers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Local Government and Communities Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today marks the beginning of an historic shift of power from Whitehall to every community to take back control of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Localism Act pulls down the Whitehall barricades so it will no longer call the shots over communities - bug bears like housing targets and bin taxes are gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, local people were held back and ignored because Whitehall thought it knew best. That is changing for good. Councils have their general power of competence and residents have a real power over decisions like Council Tax, town hall pay, planning, community buildings or local services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralisation Minister Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For the best part of a hundred years Parliament has been passing laws that increase the government’s powers at the expense of people and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This historic Act begins to reverse a hundred years of centralisation. It puts power into the hands of citizens, community groups and local councils. It breaks the monopoly on all new policy initiatives having to come from Whitehall by giving a new right of initiative to people in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Localism Act is not the end of the journey towards a more permissive, flexible Britain but it makes a great stride in a direction that the government will continue to travel.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Act marks a huge cultural change not just for those local communities and local councils, but for those in Westminster, and perhaps even more for those in Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There has been gathering frustration at the way in which local communities and local councils have had their decision making taken away from them. We needed to change that culture: it was long overdue change, and this Act makes a start on achieving it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localism-act-2011-overview"&gt;overview to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks and months the measures in the Localism Act will begin to come into effect. Many of the measures are expected to be in place by April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16201</id>
    <published>2011-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/homeswap-direct-offers-fresh-opportunities-for-social-tenants"/>
    <title>HomeSwap Direct offers fresh opportunities for social tenants</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s new national HomeSwap Direct scheme will make it easier for tenants living in a council or housing association home to find a new property in another part of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HomeSwap Direct will mean that for the first time there will be a system in place across the whole of the UK, meaning that tenants looking to move, whether for a job, to be near family or to a property better suited to their needs, will be able to see all the available homes across the whole of the UK, not just those on the website subscribed to by their current landlord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some councils such as Kettering already run localised schemes but  Homeswap Direct will link them all together across England, Scotland, Northern Ireland and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One couple used Homeswapper to find a home closer to the family, who had relocated across the country, meaning a 250 mile round trip every few weeks to see them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It took us less than 3 months to find our perfect home swap. We could have moved sooner but we wanted to make sure the house was perfect as we knew once we had moved closer to the children we would settle there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our new home is very similar our old bungalow, which we loved, but has a very important added benefit; our family are now just around the corner. Without HomeSwapper it could have taken years for us to have been moved nearer to our family. It’s easy and simple and we’d recommend it to anyone looking to move.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-details"&gt;Contact details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abritas&lt;br&gt;
Stephen Oliver, Managing Director,&lt;br&gt;
Tel: 0118 925 5823&lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.abritas.co.uk/"&gt;www.abritas.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locata Housing Services&lt;br&gt;
Peter Riley, Director&lt;br&gt;
Tel: 07545 696362&lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lhs-uk.com/"&gt;www.lhs-uk.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homeswapper&lt;br&gt;
John Carthew, Managing Director, Housing Partners Limited&lt;br&gt;
Tel: 0780 114 2971 or 01905 361 504&lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeswapper.co.uk/"&gt;www.homeswapper.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;House Exchange&lt;br&gt;
Kim Doran&lt;br&gt;
House Exchange Manager&lt;br&gt;
01603 703 516&lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.houseexchange.org.uk/"&gt;www.houseexchange.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16672</id>
    <published>2011-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/top-tips-for-landlords-assured-shorthold-tenancies"/>
    <title>Assured shorthold tenancies: top tips for landlords</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for landlords who have let or who intend to let a property on an assured shorthold tenancy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These tips are for landlords who have let or who intend to let a property on an assured shorthold tenancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your tenant is likely to have an assured shorthold tenancy if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are a private landlord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the tenancy began on or after 28 February 1997&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the house or flat is let as separate accommodation and is your tenant’s main home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are not sure what sort of tenancy your tenant has, see the sources of further information at the bottom of the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16673</id>
    <published>2011-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/top-tips-for-tenants-assured-shorthold-tenancies"/>
    <title>Assured shorthold tenancies: top tips for tenants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for people who are, or are thinking of becoming, an assured shorthold tenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These tips are for people who are, or are thinking of becoming, an assured shorthold tenant. You are likely to be an assured shorthold tenant if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your landlord is a private landlord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the tenancy began on or after 28 February 1997&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the house or flat is let as separate accommodation and is your main home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are not an assured shorthold tenant or are not sure what sort of tenancy you have, see the further information section at the bottom of this leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
