<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the rented housing sector"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2009-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15902</id>
    <published>2009-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assured-and-assured-shorthold-tenancies-a-guide-for-landlords"/>
    <title>Assured and assured shorthold tenancies: a guide for landlords</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This booklet explains the most important features of landlords’ and tenants’ rights and responsibilities but it is only a general guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably need to read this booklet if you are letting, or thinking of letting, a domestic property and the letting began on or after 15 January 1989. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This booklet do not deal with agricultural lettings, or lettings by housing associations, local authorities or other social landlords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you are sharing or are going to share part of your home, you should read our separate booklets called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/letting-rooms-in-your-home-a-guide-for-resident-landlords"&gt;‘Letting rooms in your home: a guide for resident landlords’&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/renting-rooms-in-someones-home-a-guide-for-people-renting-from-resident-landlords"&gt;‘Renting rooms in someone’s home: a guide for people renting from resident landlords’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15907</id>
    <published>2009-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/letting-rooms-in-your-home-a-guide-for-resident-landlords"/>
    <title>Letting rooms in your home: a guide for resident landlords</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should read this booklet if you are letting (or thinking of letting) part of your only or main home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In law, a resident landlord letting is one where the landlord and the person he or she lets to live in the same building. This includes conversions where they live in different parts of the same property (however long ago it was converted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the property is split into purpose built flats, with landlord and occupier in different flats, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you do not live in the same property as the person you let to,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;you should instead read the booklet &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assured-and-assured-shorthold-tenancies-a-guide-for-landlords"&gt;‘Assured and assured shorthold tenancies - a guide for landlords’&lt;/a&gt; if the letting began on or after 15 January 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it began before this date read; &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/regulated-tenancies"&gt;‘Regulated tenancies’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15919</id>
    <published>2009-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/notice-that-you-must-leave-a-brief-guide-for-landlords-and-tenants"/>
    <title>Notice that you must leave: a brief guide for landlords and tenants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This booklet explains the basic rules about bringing a residential tenancy (or licence) to an end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;either by the landlord or tenant serving notice to quit; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by a landlord serving a notice of his or her intention to seek possession&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is divided into three sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;notice by landlords&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;notice by tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;licences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16026</id>
    <published>2009-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assured-and-assured-shorthold-tenancies-a-guide-for-tenants"/>
    <title>Assured and assured shorthold tenancies: a guide for tenants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This booklet explains the most important features of tenants’ and landlords’ rights and responsibilities but it is only a general guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably need to read this booklet if you are renting, or thinking of renting, a domestic property and the letting began on or after 15 January 1989. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This booklet does not deal with agricultural lettings, or lettings by housing associations, local authorities or other social landlords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are sharing or are going to share part of the landlord’s home, you should read our separate booklet called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/renting-rooms-in-someones-home-a-guide-for-people-renting-from-resident-landlords"&gt;‘Renting rooms in someone’s home - a guide for people renting from resident landlords’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15781</id>
    <published>2007-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T19:19:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/strategic-housing-market-assessments-practice-guidance"/>
    <title>Strategic housing market assessments: practice guidance  </title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This practice guidance sets out a framework that local authorities and regional bodies can follow to develop a good understanding of how housing markets operate. It promotes an approach to assessing housing need and demand that can inform the development of local development documents and regional spatial strategy planning for housing policies, as set out in Planning Policy Statement 3: Housing (PPS3).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13488</id>
    <published>2007-04-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/licensing-of-houses-in-multiple-occupation-in-england-a-guide-for-landlords-and-managers"/>
    <title>Licensing of houses in multiple occupation in England: a guide for landlords and managers</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This publication is aimed at landlords and managers who manage a House in Multiple Occupation (HMO), or if you are not sure whether you manage a House in Multiple Occupation. The booklet explains more about HMOS, which HMO’s are required to be licensed and what other if any responsibilities there are in relation to the management of HMOs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13489</id>
    <published>2007-04-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/licensing-of-houses-in-multiple-occupation-in-england-a-guide-for-tenants"/>
    <title>Licensing of houses in multiple occupation in England: a guide for tenants</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This publication is aimed at tenants who live in a House in Multiple Occupation (HMO), or if you are not sure whether you live in a House in Multiple Occupation. The booklet explains more about HMOS, which HMO’s are required to be licensed and what other if any responsibilities there are in relation to the management of HMOs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15896</id>
    <published>2006-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/renting-rooms-in-someones-home-a-guide-for-people-renting-from-resident-landlords"/>
    <title>Renting rooms in someone's home: a guide for people renting from resident landlords</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should read this booklet if you rent (or are thinking of renting) in a property where the landlord also lives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In law, a resident landlord letting is one where the landlord and the person he or she lets to, live in the same building. This includes conversions where they live in different parts of the same property (however long ago it was converted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if the property is split into purpose built flats, with the landlord and you in different flats, or you do not live in the same property as your landlord you should instead read the booklet &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/assured-and-assured-shorthold-tenancies-a-guide-for-tenants"&gt;‘Assured and assured shorthold tenancies - a guide
for tenants’&lt;/a&gt; if the letting began on or after 15 January 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it began before this date read &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/regulated-tenancies"&gt;‘Regulated tenancies’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
