<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Improving the rented housing sector"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/64090</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-social-tenants-to-have-their-say-on-local-services"/>
    <title>Support for social tenants to have their say on local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk today launched a new training programme designed to put power firmly in the hands of social tenants.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He launched the £1.2 million Tenant Training and Support Programme to give residents the skills they need to hold their landlord to account, whether on their own, by setting up a tenant panel, or by taking over the management and maintenance of their homes and neighbourhoods themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boost in funding will offer a way for residents to ensure they get the service they deserve and that landlords offer the best possible value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said this new training programme would empower residents to take the first crucial step to having the necessary know-how to use their powers and take control in their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="empowering-tenants"&gt;Empowering tenants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/"&gt;Tenant Participation Advisory Service&lt;/a&gt;, the programme offers advice, training and support to tenants by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing tenants together from different neighbourhoods to discuss their experiences and inspire new tenant panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping individual tenants to engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offering face-to-face training with expert advisors for around 5,000 tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a tenant training programme to help them make the most of the powers they have, from accredited courses to local training systems and e-learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By doing this, new and existing social tenants will be equipped with the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be able to sign up to Community Cashback, which enables tenants to take over the management of their neighbourhood, from overseeing maintenance and minor repairs to signing up new contractors to run cleaning services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country want to use the powers they have to ensure their needs are reflected in the services they receive. But many simply lack the confidence to challenge the people in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why we’ve put this new tenant training scheme in place, helping make their voices heard and giving people the skills they need to ensure the changes that matter to them are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by playing this enhanced role tenants can help landlords improve the efficiency of local services and their work will help inspire even more communities to take control.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Meakin, Tenant Participation Advisory Service chair said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is exactly the programme we’ve all been waiting for. I urge any tenant who wants to be involved and make a difference in their community to get in touch and take advantage of the free support and training on offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples-of-effective-tenant-involvement"&gt;Examples of effective tenant involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helena Partnerships&lt;/em&gt; has set up the tenant-led customer excellence panel to challenge their landlord on performance and service delivery. It sets its own review programme, commissions mystery shoppers and has unfettered access to Helena’s performance and complaints information, customer surveys, activity-based costing and customer insight data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel carries out tenant-led peer reviews and hosts a series of webinars to engage with other organisations involved in scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works closely with Helena’s young inspectors - a group of under 25’s who play an active role in testing and challenging services while gaining transferable skills for employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel’s work has been responsible for a number of practical changes to Helena services to reflect the needs of tenants and delivered value for money savings, including tailored rent statements, extended repairs appointment times and changes to the complaints service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tower Hamlets, &lt;em&gt;Poplar HARCA&lt;/em&gt; (8,500 homes) is committed to helping social tenants to play a key role in their local housing. Recognising the benefits of tenant empowerment, the association enables democratically elected residents to monitor services on each of the association’s 12 estates, where they have delegated budgets enabling them to make community improvements. Additionally, tenant board members scrutinise the association’s policies and initiatives, challenging senior managers and making recommendations for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents can also use their local knowledge to try to resolve complaints about the association’s services. A youth empowerment board has been set up, comprising 30 young people drawn from across the estates, to ensure that the views of young people are heard. In total, over 300 residents are directly involved in decision making, performance monitoring and complaints handling at the association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding of almost £1.2 million will be made to the Tenant Participation Advisory Service to deliver a training and support programme. For further information on the programme visit their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/tenantcentral"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow DCLG’s Tenant Empowerment Team on Twitter (&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/TenantPower"&gt;@TenantPower&lt;/a&gt;) for all the latest news and updates on this programme and other activities to empower the lives of social tenants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60137</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-200-million-build-to-rent-fund-will-boost-housebuilding"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk: £200 million Build to Rent fund will boost housebuilding</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new £200 million fund will boost the construction of new homes specifically for private rent, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Build to Rent fund aims to cut the risk for developers more traditionally used to building homes for sale who are looking to branch out into building homes for private rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By financing the construction of rental homes until they are built, let out and managed, the fund will give developers the freedom to build homes specifically for that market with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management companies will have the chance to invest in these new rental developments, and developers will then repay the investment from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the new fund, the Housing Minister described it as yet another step to support housebuilding which will help boost the economy, create jobs and strengthen the housing market by providing people with a broader housing choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reviving-the-rental-market"&gt;Reviving the rental market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that Build to Rent follows recommendations contained in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment" title="Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment"&gt;Montague report&lt;/a&gt; into rented homes earlier this year and will help address the varying level of quality across the nation’s private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of private rental landlords are small-scale, individual investors. This fund will redress the balance, by stimulating the market in private rented homes for large-scale housing organisations that will in turn help set a new benchmark for landlords across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kickstart this new, larger scale market for privately rented homes, the minister said that Build to Rent will fund ‘demonstration’ projects to show how it might work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expert taskforce will also work to boost investor awareness of the fund and offer practical support to those interested in this new market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A healthy rental housing market must have a broad range of choice across the board. But for it to grow and develop, we must first attract new investors. The Build to Rent fund will support this, helping to build homes specifically for private rent and breathing new life into the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by driving this market in housebuilding, the fund will also help create new jobs, build the homes that families need and local people want, and support economic growth across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor of London Boris Johnson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The private rented sector now houses a quarter of Londoners and has the potential to support the delivery of a huge number of new homes in the future. I welcome this funding and I will continue to make the case that investment in London’s housing infrastructure is one of the best ways to deliver much needed construction jobs and economic growth now, while at the same time laying the foundations for our economic growth for years to come.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greater London Authority will lead on assessing the expressions of interest for sites in London. Shortlisting decisions will be made by DCLG, the Homes and Communities Agency and the Greater London Authority. The Homes and Communities Agency will undertake due diligence, contracting and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £200 million Build to Rent Fund is now open for bids, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/private-rented-sector" title="Build to Rent Fund prospectus"&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt; has been published on the HCA website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fund has been developed to support purpose built, private rented demonstration schemes across England which have the potential to attract investors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has appointed two non-executive members following open competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16882</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:46:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/housing-capital-receipts-exemptions-from-regulations"/>
    <title>Housing capital receipts: exemptions from regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance for local authorities applying to use receipts from the disposal of council housing assets in ways not prescribed in regulations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use of receipts arising from the disposal of housing assets (ie assets held under part 2 of the Housing Act 1985 and for which account is made in the Housing Revenue Account) is governed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/1324/made"&gt;Local Authorities (Capital Finance and Accounting) (England) Regulations 2003 (as amended.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations require that, in short: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;receipts arising from Right to Buy (and similar sales may be retained to cover the cost of transacting the sales and to cover the debt on the properties sold, but a proportion of the remainder must be surrendered to central government &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receipts arising from all other disposals may be retained in full provided they are spent on affordable housing, regeneration or the paying down of housing debt (each of which is defined in the regulations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, section 11(6) of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/26/contents"&gt;Local Government Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; (as inserted by section 174 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents"&gt;Localism Act 2011&lt;/a&gt;) permits the secretary of state to enter into agreements with local authorities with the effect that any requirement imposed by these regulations does not apply, or is modified in its application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enter into such an agreement it is necessary for any interested authority to make an application to the secretary of state. This guidance sets out the Department for Communities and Local Government’s policy on such exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60897</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T15:49:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-housing-starts-and-completions-funded-by-the-hca-and-the-gla-april-to-september-2012-13"/>
    <title>Affordable housing starts and completions funded by the HCA and the GLA - April to September 2012-13</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Starts and completions of affordable housing for England, bringing together those funded by the HCA and those funded by the GLA.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These statistics have moved and are now available at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/affordable-housing-starts-and-completions-funded-by-the-hca-and-the-gla-april-to-september-2012"&gt;Affordable housing starts and completions funded by the HCA and the GLA: April to September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister, Mark Prisk, to the Council of Mortgage Lenders' annual conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17139</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T08:26:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment"/>
    <title>Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An independent review of the private rented housing sector carried out by Sir Adrian Montague.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report summarises the results of Sir Adrian Montague’s review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes. It examines how best to encourage greater investment in rental properties and explores the factors that might encourage institutions to invest in new homes for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector"&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; was included in the housing and planning package announced on 6 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60968</id>
    <published>2012-07-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-household-report-2010-to-2011"/>
    <title>English housing survey 2010 to 2011: household report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Annual report on households in England, covering themes such as housing needs, housing moves, and vulnerable and disadvantaged groups.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The English housing survey household report is the detailed report of findings from the survey relating to households, and builds on results reported in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-headline-report-2010-to-2011"&gt;‘English housing survey headline report’&lt;/a&gt; published in February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-homes-report-2010"&gt;‘English housing survey homes report 2010’&lt;/a&gt;, formally known as the housing stock report, was also published on 5 July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report includes the following findings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the largest tenure type in 2010 to 2011 was owner occupation, with 14.45 million households (66%); this continued a slight downward trend from a peak of 14.79 million households in owner occupation (71%) in 2005; the private rented sector continued to increase in size, to 3.62 million households (17%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;owner occupiers buying with a mortgage made average weekly mortgage payments of £143, compared to average weekly rent payments of £160 made by privately renting households, and £79 by social renters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;59% of private renters and 23% of social renters said they expected to buy a home in the UK, at some point; of these, 16% had considered applying for a mortgage in the last 12 months; recent first time buyers were 6% of owner occupiers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there were 2 million recently moving households in 2010 to 2011, compared to 1.8 million in 2009 to 2010; of these, 62% were private renters, 22% were owner occupiers and 16% were social renters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;households living in poverty were more likely to live in homes that had significant outstanding repairs and damp problems than households who were not living in poverty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the majority of households were satisfied with their local areas and their accommodation; however, although the majority of people felt their areas had not changed much over the previous 2 years, across all tenures, they were more likely to say their local area had got worse than better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Excel files include the annex tables and the tables and figures for each chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60975</id>
    <published>2012-07-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-homes-report-2010"/>
    <title>English housing survey 2010: homes report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Annual detailed report about the housing stock in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report, formally known as the housing stock report, is the detailed report of findings relating to the housing stock from the English housing survey. It builds on results reported in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-headline-report-2010-to-2011"&gt;‘English housing survey headline report: 2010 to 2011’&lt;/a&gt; published in February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-household-report-2010-to-2011"&gt;‘English housing survey 2010 to 2011: household report’&lt;/a&gt; was also published on 5 July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report includes the following findings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in 2010, there were 22.4 million dwellings in England; 66% of these were owner occupied and the rest were rented, split fairly evenly between the private-rented sector (17%) and social-rented sector (17%); there were slightly more housing association dwellings (2 million) than local authority dwellings (1.8 million)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;52% of the private-rented stock was built before 1945, including 40% built before 1919; also, 15% of private-rented homes were converted flats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the total cost of dealing with basic disrepair (day-to-day maintenance) within the stock was around £31.8 billion at 2010 prices and the average cost of this type of disrepair was £1,418 per dwelling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the proportion of dwellings with damp problems fell from 10% in 2001 to 7% in 2010; this was mainly due to a fall in the incidence of problems caused by penetrating damp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the average energy efficiency (SAP) rating for the whole stock (using SAP09) has increased from 45 in 1996 to 55 in 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the average SAP rating in the social sector in 2010 was around 8 points higher than either owner-occupied or private-rented homes (62 compared with 54)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The excel files include annex tables and tables and figures for each chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61006</id>
    <published>2012-07-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:34:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-homes-statistics-2010"/>
    <title>English housing survey 2010: homes statistics</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Statistics to accompany the English housing survey 2010 homes report.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This volume presents the English housing survey homes web tables which are published to accompany the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-housing-survey-homes-report-2010"&gt;‘English housing survey 2010: homes report’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tables provide a set of detailed findings from the survey organized around 7 topic areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
