<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13532</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:58:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/changes-to-the-audit-commission-board"/>
    <title>Changes to the Audit Commission Board</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of appointment for 7 commissioners comes to an end on 31 December 2012. The Secretary of State has taken the decision, with support from the chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Audit Commission"&gt;Audit Commission&lt;/a&gt;, to offer reappointment 4 of the existing board members, and a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publicappointments.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Public Appointments website"&gt;recruitment exercise&lt;/a&gt; has commenced to find 3 new members of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new commissioners will work alongside other board members to achieve an efficient and effective closedown and, in the lead up to closure, oversee the smaller Commission’s remaining duties and the transfer of continuing functions to other bodies. The full programme of reforms to local audit and inspection, and the closure of the Commission, will bring in a more localist approach and are expected to save £650 million in public money over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13413</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-it-easier-to-set-up-new-town-and-parish-councils-discussion-paper"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils: discussion paper</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils. This discussion paper presents a range of proposals that would help achieve this. We would like your views on these, as well as any other comments or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14744</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/localism-in-action-making-it-easier-to-set-up-parish-councils"/>
    <title>Localism in action - making it easier to set up parish councils</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government’s revolution to hand power back to local communities moves one step further today under proposals to makes it easier to set up new town and parish councils announced by Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/parishdiscussionpaper"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; launched today is part of government plans to open up public services. It proposes amending existing guidance to speed up the process, clarifying how local authorities should consider local opinion, and making it easier for neighbourhood forums to start the process for creating a new parish council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cracking down on pointless bureaucracy and freeing local people who want to play an active part in society to create successful and thriving communities is a top priority for this government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes where the creation of a new parish council has the support of local people, the local authority should work with the community to achieve it. This will enable decision making to be devolved to the lowest appropriate level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Parishes are popular with people and for too long communities have battled with burdensome bureaucracy to get them created.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Our proposal to remove red tape, simplify and streamline the current process to create Parish councils is commonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We want to give local people a real sense of community control in their areas, giving them freedom to make changes and improvements which best serve their community and area.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parish councils have a highly significant role in the Government’s agenda for promoting localism and open public services. They have a close understanding of what their communities want and can tailor a wide range of local services including grants to local organisations and financing projects such as new community buildings and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the proposals Councillor Michael Chater, Chair of the National Association of Local Councils (NALC) said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We welcome the creation of more new local (parish and town) councils to deliver wider services to local communities and be the voice of local people. We agree with the proposal to consult on how local councils could be given more power to deliver grassroots services and looking forward to hearing of innovative and radical approaches on how this will happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The consultation &lt;em&gt;Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils&lt;/em&gt; can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/parishdiscussionpaper"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/parishdiscussionpaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parish and town (local) councils in England and community and town (local) councils in Wales are the first tier of local government. There are around 10,000 local councils in England and Wales, made up of nearly 100,000 councillors.
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nalc.gov.uk/About_NALC/What_is_a_parish_or_town_council/All_about_local_councils.aspx"&gt;www.nalc.gov.uk/About_NALC/What_is_a_parish_or_town_council/All_about_local_councils.aspx&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More details on what Parish councils are can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_councils_in_England"&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_councils_in_England&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details about Queen’s Park residents voting in favour of establishing London’s first parish council in fifty years can be found on the link below: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.westminster.gov.uk/press-releases/2012-05/london-s-first-parish-council-on-its-way-as-quee/"&gt;www.westminster.gov.uk/press-releases/2012-05/london-s-first-parish-council-on-its-way-as-quee/&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13412</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/improving-local-government-transparency"/>
    <title>Improving local government transparency</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the publication of the ‘Code of recommended practice for local authorities on Data Transparency’ in September 2011, ministers would now like to make the code a legal requirement via regulations, subject to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has the power to enforce the code through regulations via the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1980/65/contents" title="Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980"&gt;Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980&lt;/a&gt;, Section 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers wish to hear from all those local authorities listed in paragraph 4 of the code. They would also like to hear from relevant bodies, open data experts, developers, citizen activists and other interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14738</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/town-hall-transparency-to-expose-car-parking-charges"/>
    <title>Town hall transparency to expose car parking charges</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government action to enshrine Town Hall transparency as an everyday activity will now also open up punitive parking charges to public scrutiny, Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/makingthecode"&gt;asking for views&lt;/a&gt; on plans to make it a legal requirement for councils to open up every aspect of its business through the regular publication of a transparency inventory that will reveal data on pay, perks, spending, charities and now parking. Overall council parking income totalled £1.27billion in 2010-11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposed amendments to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/transparencycode"&gt;The Code of Recommended Practice for Local Authorities on Data Transparency&lt;/a&gt; will also introduce new transparency standards on parking charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils will have to publish soon as it is produced the number of off-street parking places and the revenue raised from them; the number of on-street parking places and the revenue they raise; as well as the revenue from parking fines and the number of free parking spaces available in line with the Portas Review of the High Street recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent survey found that almost seven in ten people intentionally avoided shopping areas with high parking prices. Two thirds said they would return to the high street if parking was more affordable. One in five felt there were not enough spaces available. It also found that four out of five people pay up to £150 per month for parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are ending an era of bureaucratic accountability and replacing it with a more open era of democratic accountability. It is right that taxpayers get to see how Town Halls spend their hard earned taxes so they can properly hold local politicians to account.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Finally all councils have taken up the £500 transparency challenge but publication is only happening in fits and starts. By writing Town Hall transparency into law we can make certain every citizen gets open and equal access to information about local public expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“As part of that we will expose a great council cash cow cover-up unmasking punitive parking practices that hit residents in the pocket. We’re calling time on local war against motorists - now, more than ever, we need to see the back of this shopping tax and encourage more people onto the high street.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals mean that all local authorities would be required to openly publish their spending over £500 online including, tenders, contracts, senior pay, councillor expenses, voluntary sector funding, meetings, and frontline service data so that ‘armchair auditors’ can clearly see the decisions being made on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This department has been publishing details of all goods and services spent over £500 matching the level required of councils since August 2010. As one of Government’s transparency trailblazers that is now being extended to include all transactions above a new low threshold of £250. ‘Can do’ councils have been challenged to match that threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minimum the code states that the public data that should be released in every council’s transparency inventory is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expenditure over £500, (including costs, supplier and transaction information). Any sole trader or body acting in a business capacity in receipt of payments of at least £500 of public money should expect such payments to be transparent;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;senior employee salaries, names (with the option for individuals to refuse to consent for their name to be published), job descriptions, responsibilities, budgets and numbers of staff. ‘Senior employee salaries’ is defined as all salaries which are above £58,200 and above (irrespective of post), which is the Senior Civil Service minimum pay band. Budgets should include the overall salary cost of staff reporting to each senior employee;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an organisational chart of the staff structure of the local authority including salary bands and details of currently vacant posts;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the ‘pay multiple’ - the ratio between the highest paid salary and the median average salary of the whole of the authority’s workforce;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councillor allowances and expenses;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;copies of contracts and tenders to businesses and to the voluntary community and social enterprise sector;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grants to the voluntary community and social enterprise sector should be clearly itemised and listed;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;policies, performance, external audits and key inspections and key indicators on the authorities’ fiscal and financial position;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the location of public land and building assets and key attribute information that is normally recorded on asset registers; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data on democratic running of the local authority including the constitution, election results, committee minutes, decision - making processes and records of decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Provision of public data should become integral to local authority engagement with residents so that it drives accountability to them. Its availability should be promoted and publicised so that residents know how to access it and how it can be used. Presentation should be helpful and accessible to residents and other interested persons. Publication should be in open and machine-readable formats. It should be published as soon as possible following production even if it is not accompanied with detailed analysis. Where practical, local authorities should seek to publish in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State published &lt;em&gt;The Code of Recommended Practice for Local Authorities on Data Transparency&lt;/em&gt; on 29 September 2011. The Code asks councils to follow three principles of transparency when publishing data they hold; responding to public demand; releasing data in open formats available for re-use; and, releasing data in a timely way. This includes data on senior salaries and the structure of their workforce. The code can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/transparencycode"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/transparencycode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The consultation is open until 20 December 2012 and can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/makingthecode"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/makingthecode&lt;/a&gt;. Subject to the consultation and introduction of regulations a binding code would take effect later next year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Public data should be published in a format and under a licence that allows open re-use, including for commercial and research activities, in order to maximise value to the public. The Open Government Licence published by The National Archive should be used as the recommended standard: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/"&gt;www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/doc/open-government-licence/&lt;/a&gt; (external link). Where any copyright concerns exist with public data these should be made clear.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local Authorities will also have a statutory duty to maintain and publish other lists of assets for example, lists of assets of community value and lists of those assets nominated but not deemed by the local authority to meet the definition of an asset of community value. Local authority assets will be on land and building property assets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires local authorities to be transparent about how senior salaries are set through the publication of annual pay statements. This will help to ensure that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - provide value for money for the whole of the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government’s associated guidance on &lt;em&gt;Openness and Accountability in Local Pay&lt;/em&gt; states that authorities should review the terms of senior appointments, particularly where arrangements could be perceived as seeking to minimise tax payments. It specifically states that councils should vote on salary packages for employees greater than £100,000 a year. Councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses, above inflation pay rises, or the recruitment of staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/guidancelocalpay"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/guidancelocalpay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data on gross sales, fees and charges income from parking is part of the &lt;em&gt;Local Authority Revenue Outturn 2010-11&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/revenue201011finaloutturn"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/revenue201011finaloutturn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full details of the parking survey can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.confused.com/press/releases/brits-fork-out-nearly-8bn-a-year-on-over-priced-parking-places"&gt;www.confused.com/press/releases/brits-fork-out-nearly-8bn-a-year-on-over-priced-parking-places&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13432</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dclg-continuous-improvement-strategy"/>
    <title>DCLG continuous improvement strategy</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the expenditure over £250 for the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Centre for July to September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13429</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accountability-system-statement-for-the-greater-london-authority"/>
    <title>Accountability system statement for the Greater London Authority</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the financial accountability system for the Greater London Authority. It has been signed off by Sir Bob Kerslake as accounting officer for the Department for Communities and Local Government. It sets out the financial relationship between the Greater London Authority and the Department and sets out the checks and balances including via the elected London Assembly and through various statutory controls which forms the system at present. The statement also signposts changes which are expected to be made during the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Statement is a sister document to the System Accountability Statement for Local Government published in March 2012. Owing to the unique governance arrangements in the capital, with a strong executive Mayor and elected Assembly, the funding streams and accountability systems are sufficiently different to warrant a bespoke Accountability System Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13427</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-government-pension-scheme-funds-for-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Local Government Pension Scheme Funds for England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details of the Local Government Pension Scheme in England in 2011-12 were announced on 17 October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12 and updates those statistics previously released on 12 October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local Government Pension Scheme expenditure on benefits in 2011-12 was £7.5xbillion, compared with £6.7 billion in 2010-11, an increase of 12 per cent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Income from employees’ contributions to the Local Government Pension Scheme in 2011-12 was £1.8 billion, a decrease on 2010-11 of more than 6 per cent. Income from employers’ contributions to the scheme in the same period also decreased, albeit by just 0.4 per cent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2011-12, total expenditure accounted for 74 per cent of the Local Government Pension Scheme income, up from 58 per cent in 2007-08.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Income from investments rose by 13 per cent on 2010-11 to £3.0 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The market value of the funds at end of March 2012 was £148 billion. This represents an increase of 4 per cent on March 2011 and an increase of 52 per cent on March 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were less than 1.6 million employees in the Local Government Pension Scheme at the end of March 2012, a 66 thousand, or 4 per cent, decrease over the figure for March 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of people leaving the Local Government Pension Scheme in 2011-12 because of redundancy was more than 27,400, an increase of more than 55 per cent over the 2010-11 figure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of former employees entitled to deferred benefits rose to 1.4 million in 2011-12, an increase of 7 per cent over 2010-11 and an increase of 35 per cent over 2007-08.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13425</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-wiltshire-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Wiltshire Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement Notice issued to Wiltshire Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
