<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56567</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:42:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-barnsley-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/18644</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T12:10:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-revenue-expenditure-and-financing-england-2010-to-2011-individual-local-authority-data--5"/>
    <title>Local authority revenue expenditure and financing England: 2010 to 2011 individual local authority data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data in the above spreadsheets have been used to compile the final outturn estimates of local authority revenue expenditure and financing for the financial year April 2010 to March 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of the original final outturn statistical release (4 April 2012), the data in these spreadsheets have been revised on 27 November 2012. The changes over the previously published figures are generally small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16424</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:37:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-authorities-in-england-2011-12-update"/>
    <title>National non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England 2011-12 (update)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An updated statistical release giving details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12 was published on 20 November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provided updated information on figures that were announced on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-councils-in-england-2011-to-2012"&gt;15 August 2012&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the net rate yield (after allowances for changes in respect of previous years and reliefs) increased by 9.1% to £21 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contribution to the pool (net rate yield after allowances for collection costs including losses) also increased by 9.2% to £20.7 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 2007-08 and 2011-12 the contribution to the pool from the local lists increased by £3.5 billion or 21%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London accounts for 29% of the contribution to the national pool while having only 15% of the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16401</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:19:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-blackpool-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16406</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:18:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-walsall-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13532</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:58:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/changes-to-the-audit-commission-board"/>
    <title>Changes to the Audit Commission Board</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of appointment for 7 commissioners comes to an end on 31 December 2012. The Secretary of State has taken the decision, with support from the chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Audit Commission"&gt;Audit Commission&lt;/a&gt;, to offer reappointment 4 of the existing board members, and a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publicappointments.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Public Appointments website"&gt;recruitment exercise&lt;/a&gt; has commenced to find 3 new members of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new commissioners will work alongside other board members to achieve an efficient and effective closedown and, in the lead up to closure, oversee the smaller Commission’s remaining duties and the transfer of continuing functions to other bodies. The full programme of reforms to local audit and inspection, and the closure of the Commission, will bring in a more localist approach and are expected to save £650 million in public money over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56561</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:44:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-london-borough-of-bexley"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to London Borough of Bexley</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to London Borough of Bexley by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56566</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:44:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-royal-borough-of-kingston-upon-thames"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Royal Borough of Kingston upon Thames</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Royal Borough of Kingston upon Thames by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
