<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/64074</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T15:51:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/dclg-draft-statistics-plan-for-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>DCLG draft statistics plan for 2011 to 2012</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation on the Department for Communities and Local Government's proposals for collecting and publishing official statistics in 2011 to 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft statistics plan describes the Department for Communities and Local Government’s proposals for collecting and publishing official statistics over the period April 2011 to March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;users’ reactions to our proposals and their views on whether our planned deployment of resources will meet their needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggestions for the development of any new statistics, products or services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggestions for any further reductions in the amount of data we collect and publish (beyond those already submitted in the context of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/supporting-pages/single-data-list"&gt;‘single data list’&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information from users about the particular uses to which they put our statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60026</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:07:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-pension-scheme"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>This is a written ministerial statement about the abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions for councillors from April 2014.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 September 2001, the then Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions announced plans to give taxpayer-funded pensions to councillors, through access to the local government pension scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals came into force in 2003. The Councillors’ Commission report of the last administration noted that 912 councillors in England had joined that pension scheme by 2004. A Taxpayers’ Alliance survey in February 2009, across the whole United Kingdom, found that 3,527 councillors had pensions as of 2007 to 2008; a further survey in January 2012 found that figure had increased to 4,548 councillors by 2010 to 2011. The trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="abolition-of-taxpayer-funded-pensions"&gt;Abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in this government take a fundamentally different view to the last administration. We do not believe that taxpayer-funded pensions are justified. Councillors are volunteers undertaking public service; they are not and should not be employees of the council dependent on the municipal payroll. They are not professional, full-time politicians, nor should they be encouraged to become so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors do not receive a salary; rather, they receive allowances to compensate for their out-of-pocket expenses. Yet following changes made by the last administration, allowances have slowly become a form of salary, a situation worsened by the state-funded pensions. This is a corrosive influence on local democracy and independent thought, blurring the distinction between council staff and councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bit of the public sector needs to do its bit to help pay off the deficit inherited from the last administration. Local government grants are being reduced. Ministers have cut and then frozen their salaries. Public sector pensions, including parliamentary pensions, are being reformed to reduce the burden on taxpayers. It is only right that councillors do their bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that an occupational pension scheme intended for employees, and paid for by taxpayers, is an appropriate vehicle for councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="existing-pension-rights"&gt;Existing pension rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to consultation, we propose that there will be no access for councillors to the local government pension scheme in England from April 2014. In the interests of fairness, those councillors already in the scheme would have their accrued rights up to April 2014 fully protected, but would not be able to accrue any further benefits after that date in the existing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not prevent councillors contributing to a personal pension: if they put aside part of their (taxable) allowances into such a pension, then that is a matter for them; they will continue to receive income tax relief like any ordinary member of the population, subject to the prevailing tax rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although central records on councillors’ participation in the scheme are not held by my department, initial rough estimates suggest that this could save £7 million a year in taxpayers’ money. There is absolutely no case for increasing councillor allowances to compensate. Instead, councils may want to consider earlier, voluntary closure of the scheme to their councillors as a sensible saving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="civic-duty"&gt;Civic duty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility regulations for the local government pension scheme are overseen by my department. Although this is a centrally mandated change (as was its original introduction), we believe these reforms will assist localism and local democracy by encouraging a greater separation between councillors and officers. Robust local scrutiny of council spending requires councillors to be substantively independent of means and of thought from the body they are overseeing. Civic duty should not be bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe it will have any detrimental effect on people choosing to become councillors. The best thing we can do to encourage more people to take part in municipal public life is to decentralise power to local communities so being a councillor is a meaningful and rewarding role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="elected-mayors"&gt;Elected mayors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there is a greater expectation that an elected mayor is a full-time position. We therefore propose to consult on allowing elected mayors to remain in the scheme as a voluntary option (but not as an expectation), subject to local scrutiny, challenge and determination. The salaries of the mayor of London, members of the Greater London Assembly and police and crime commissioners will remain pensionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="timing"&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory consultation is required and will commence in due course, as part of the planned consultation on the wider reform of the local government pension scheme. We will consult with the Welsh Assembly government in respect of access to the local government pension scheme for councillors in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I would like to pay tribute to their often unsung and ongoing work in standing up for their local residents. We hope these reforms will further strengthen the integrity and independence of councillors and increase the respect within their communities for the voluntary work they undertake as champions of the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60885</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T11:16:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-practitioners-guide"/>
    <title>Business rates retention and the local government finance settlement: a practitioners guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>An overview of the calculations set out in the local government finance settlement report 2013 to 2014 and the draft report 2014 to 2015.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide provides an overview of the calculations set out in the local government finance settlement report 2013 to 2014 and the draft local government finance settlement report 2014 to 2015. It sets out how the business rates retention scheme has been set up and how it will operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide is aimed at local authority practitioners and is intended to be read alongside both local government finance reports and supporting documents which can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm" title="Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014"&gt;local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt; website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glossary explaining the terminology used in the reports and in this document can be found at annex A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56567</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:42:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-barnsley-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>A report setting out the progress the government is making to 'decentralise' power from Whitehall across the country.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/18644</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T12:10:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-revenue-expenditure-and-financing-england-2010-to-2011-individual-local-authority-data--5"/>
    <title>Local authority revenue expenditure and financing England: 2010 to 2011 individual local authority data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data in the above spreadsheets have been used to compile the final outturn estimates of local authority revenue expenditure and financing for the financial year April 2010 to March 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of the original final outturn statistical release (4 April 2012), the data in these spreadsheets have been revised on 27 November 2012. The changes over the previously published figures are generally small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60942</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2012-in-england"/>
    <title>Council Taxbase 2012 in England</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Estimate of the number of properties liable for Council Tax.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2008 to 2012 updating the statistics &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2011-in-england"&gt;‘Council Taxbase 2011 in England’&lt;/a&gt; previously issued on 16 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="number-of-dwellings"&gt;Number of dwellings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main points are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in England there were 22.4 million dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list liable for Council Tax as at 10 September 2012; this is an increase of 1% compared with 2011 and an increase of 3% compared with 2008&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of dwellings on the valuation list that are exempt from Council Tax increased by 2% compared with 2011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;35% of all exemptions from Council Tax are class C (short-term vacant dwellings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a further 27% of all exemptions are class M or N (student-related exemptions); of these, class M exemptions have increased by more than 48% in the period 2008 to 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of class L exemptions (unoccupied dwellings repossessed by a mortgage lender) again fell between September 2011 and September 2012 to 9,400, the fourth consecutive annual fall; there are now 6,500 (or 41%) fewer class L exemptions than the peak in 2008&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7.7 million dwellings were entitled to a discount as a result of being occupied by single adults; this represents 33% of all dwellings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.7 million band A dwellings (50% of all dwellings liable to band A Council Tax) were entitled to a single adult’s discount&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the total number of dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list in England as at 10 September 2012 was 23.2 million, up 143,000 (or 1%) compared with 2011 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="empty-properties"&gt;Empty properties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main points are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;between 2011 and 2012 the number of long-term empty dwellings subject to a discount fell by 28,000 (or 22%); in the same period the number of long-term empty dwellings not subject to a discount increased by 8,000 (or 5%), giving a net reduction of 20,000, or 7%, in the total number of long-term empty dwellings between 2011 and 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of long-term empty dwellings that were subject to a discount has fallen by 86,000, or 47%, between 2008 and 2012; in the same period the number of long-term empty dwellings that do not receive a discount has increased by 18,000 or 13%, giving a net reduction of 68,000, or 21%, in the total number of long-term empty dwellings between 2008 and 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;since the introduction of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt; in the summer of 2010 a large number of authorities have taken the opportunity to review the empty properties and second homes in their area; a number have also altered the level of discount awarded with many abolishing the discount for empty properties altogether&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16424</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:37:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-authorities-in-england-2011-12-update"/>
    <title>National non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England 2011-12 (update)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An updated statistical release giving details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12 was published on 20 November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provided updated information on figures that were announced on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-councils-in-england-2011-to-2012"&gt;15 August 2012&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the net rate yield (after allowances for changes in respect of previous years and reliefs) increased by 9.1% to £21 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contribution to the pool (net rate yield after allowances for collection costs including losses) also increased by 9.2% to £20.7 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 2007-08 and 2011-12 the contribution to the pool from the local lists increased by £3.5 billion or 21%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London accounts for 29% of the contribution to the national pool while having only 15% of the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16401</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:19:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-blackpool-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16406</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:18:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-walsall-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
