<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-local-councils-more-transparent-and-accountable-to-local-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making local councils more transparent and accountable to local people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60026</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:07:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-pension-scheme"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 September 2001, the then Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions announced plans to give taxpayer-funded pensions to councillors, through access to the local government pension scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals came into force in 2003. The Councillors’ Commission report of the last administration noted that 912 councillors in England had joined that pension scheme by 2004. A Taxpayers’ Alliance survey in February 2009, across the whole United Kingdom, found that 3,527 councillors had pensions as of 2007 to 2008; a further survey in January 2012 found that figure had increased to 4,548 councillors by 2010 to 2011. The trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="abolition-of-taxpayer-funded-pensions"&gt;Abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in this government take a fundamentally different view to the last administration. We do not believe that taxpayer-funded pensions are justified. Councillors are volunteers undertaking public service; they are not and should not be employees of the council dependent on the municipal payroll. They are not professional, full-time politicians, nor should they be encouraged to become so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors do not receive a salary; rather, they receive allowances to compensate for their out-of-pocket expenses. Yet following changes made by the last administration, allowances have slowly become a form of salary, a situation worsened by the state-funded pensions. This is a corrosive influence on local democracy and independent thought, blurring the distinction between council staff and councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bit of the public sector needs to do its bit to help pay off the deficit inherited from the last administration. Local government grants are being reduced. Ministers have cut and then frozen their salaries. Public sector pensions, including parliamentary pensions, are being reformed to reduce the burden on taxpayers. It is only right that councillors do their bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that an occupational pension scheme intended for employees, and paid for by taxpayers, is an appropriate vehicle for councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="existing-pension-rights"&gt;Existing pension rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to consultation, we propose that there will be no access for councillors to the local government pension scheme in England from April 2014. In the interests of fairness, those councillors already in the scheme would have their accrued rights up to April 2014 fully protected, but would not be able to accrue any further benefits after that date in the existing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not prevent councillors contributing to a personal pension: if they put aside part of their (taxable) allowances into such a pension, then that is a matter for them; they will continue to receive income tax relief like any ordinary member of the population, subject to the prevailing tax rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although central records on councillors’ participation in the scheme are not held by my department, initial rough estimates suggest that this could save £7 million a year in taxpayers’ money. There is absolutely no case for increasing councillor allowances to compensate. Instead, councils may want to consider earlier, voluntary closure of the scheme to their councillors as a sensible saving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="civic-duty"&gt;Civic duty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility regulations for the local government pension scheme are overseen by my department. Although this is a centrally mandated change (as was its original introduction), we believe these reforms will assist localism and local democracy by encouraging a greater separation between councillors and officers. Robust local scrutiny of council spending requires councillors to be substantively independent of means and of thought from the body they are overseeing. Civic duty should not be bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe it will have any detrimental effect on people choosing to become councillors. The best thing we can do to encourage more people to take part in municipal public life is to decentralise power to local communities so being a councillor is a meaningful and rewarding role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="elected-mayors"&gt;Elected mayors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there is a greater expectation that an elected mayor is a full-time position. We therefore propose to consult on allowing elected mayors to remain in the scheme as a voluntary option (but not as an expectation), subject to local scrutiny, challenge and determination. The salaries of the mayor of London, members of the Greater London Assembly and police and crime commissioners will remain pensionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="timing"&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory consultation is required and will commence in due course, as part of the planned consultation on the wider reform of the local government pension scheme. We will consult with the Welsh Assembly government in respect of access to the local government pension scheme for councillors in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I would like to pay tribute to their often unsung and ongoing work in standing up for their local residents. We hope these reforms will further strengthen the integrity and independence of councillors and increase the respect within their communities for the voluntary work they undertake as champions of the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60081</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T19:00:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-practitioners-guide"/>
    <title>Business rates retention and the local government finance settlement: a practitioners guide</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide provides an overview of the calculations set out in the local government finance settlement report 2013 to 2014 and the draft local government finance settlement report 2014 to 2015. It sets out how the business rates retention scheme has been set up and how it will operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide is aimed at local authority practitioners and is intended to be read alongside both local government finance reports and supporting documents which can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.communities.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm" title="Local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014"&gt;local government finance settlement 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt; website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glossary explaining the terminology used in the reports and in this document can be found at annex A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56567</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:42:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-barnsley-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17148</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-an-assessment-of-progress"/>
    <title>Decentralisation: an assessment of progress</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report by the Rt Hon Greg Clark MP provides an assessment of how 12 government departments are decentralising power and puts forward personal recommendations for next steps. It shows strong progress across all of the domestic policy agenda, but also calls for continued reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes the case for decentralisation (sustainable growth, better public services, a stronger society), setting out the gold standard for decentralisation, based on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decentralisation-and-the-localism-bill-an-essential-guide--2"&gt;guide to decentralisation and the Localism Bill&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in December 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/18644</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T12:10:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/local-authority-revenue-expenditure-and-financing-england-2010-to-2011-individual-local-authority-data--5"/>
    <title>Local authority revenue expenditure and financing England: 2010 to 2011 individual local authority data</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data in the above spreadsheets have been used to compile the final outturn estimates of local authority revenue expenditure and financing for the financial year April 2010 to March 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of the original final outturn statistical release (4 April 2012), the data in these spreadsheets have been revised on 27 November 2012. The changes over the previously published figures are generally small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16424</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:37:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-authorities-in-england-2011-12-update"/>
    <title>National non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England 2011-12 (update)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An updated statistical release giving details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12 was published on 20 November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provided updated information on figures that were announced on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-councils-in-england-2011-to-2012"&gt;15 August 2012&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the net rate yield (after allowances for changes in respect of previous years and reliefs) increased by 9.1% to £21 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contribution to the pool (net rate yield after allowances for collection costs including losses) also increased by 9.2% to £20.7 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 2007-08 and 2011-12 the contribution to the pool from the local lists increased by £3.5 billion or 21%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London accounts for 29% of the contribution to the national pool while having only 15% of the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16401</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:19:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-blackpool-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16406</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T13:18:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-walsall-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14434</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T17:19:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-acts-to-limit-town-hall-chiefs-golden-goodbyes"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles acts to limit town hall chiefs' golden goodbyes</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slow and costly bureaucracy that requires councils to appoint an independent person, usually a Queen’s Counsel, to review dismissal and disciplinary cases for chief executives is to be changed. The Isles of Scilly Council has recently suspended its chief executive pending one of these investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils seeking to dismiss a chief executive for misconduct or poor performance often pay out inflated lump sums to avoid the cost of taking this bureaucratic route. Eric Pickles intends to remove this expensive roadblock, which does not exist in other parts of government or the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government estimates the review process can cost between £100,000 and £250,000 in legal fees not counting independent investigation costs and salary for the suspended officer. One case cost £420,000 and took 16 months to adjudicate. Ministers believe decisions by full council ensure proper democratic accountability, without the need for a centrally dictated process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post of chief executive is not set in statute, which means there are no central barriers to removing the role. It only takes a simple democratic decision by the council. Several councils have done this in the past year. The statutory head of paid service role can be done by another senior officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles has also today written to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.gov.uk/" title="Local Government Association"&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/a&gt; to urge them to take steps to improve their performance management of senior posts. Better management can make it easier and quicker to tackle performance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A town hall chief executive costs a lot of money, but if they are simply not up to the job, councillors must be able to get rid of them quick smart without having to throw away thousands in parachute pay-offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is ridiculous that councils feel forced to give bumper pay offs to dismiss inadequate chief executives simply to avoid these unnecessary golden goodbye reviews from expensive lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Scrapping this bizarre bureaucratic ritual will save taxpayers money and put the decision firmly back in democratically elected hands.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act requires councils to publish their pay policies so that local remuneration arrangements - particularly for chief officers - are out in the open and provide value for money for local taxpayers. The associated guidance states councils should vote on pay deals over £100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles announced he intends to toughen up the guidance before councils publish their pay policies for next year. For example, if smaller councils do not pay staff above £100,000 they should consider setting a lower vote threshold. Ministers will reserve the right to regulate should councils not act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also states that councils should also publicly justify any big bonuses; above inflation pay rises; hiring staff already in receipt of public sector retirement or severance money; and avoid any perceptions of minimising tax payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a public worried about the cost of living and all parts of the public sector looking to make deficit savings, ministers believe these steps will show taxpayers that value for money is being fully considered for top paid staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13532</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:58:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/changes-to-the-audit-commission-board"/>
    <title>Changes to the Audit Commission Board</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of appointment for 7 commissioners comes to an end on 31 December 2012. The Secretary of State has taken the decision, with support from the chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Audit Commission"&gt;Audit Commission&lt;/a&gt;, to offer reappointment 4 of the existing board members, and a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://publicappointments.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Public Appointments website"&gt;recruitment exercise&lt;/a&gt; has commenced to find 3 new members of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new commissioners will work alongside other board members to achieve an efficient and effective closedown and, in the lead up to closure, oversee the smaller Commission’s remaining duties and the transfer of continuing functions to other bodies. The full programme of reforms to local audit and inspection, and the closure of the Commission, will bring in a more localist approach and are expected to save £650 million in public money over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
