<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60830</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-freedom-for-local-councils-to-prevent-unauthorised-traveller-sites--2"/>
    <title>Greater freedom for local councils to prevent unauthorised traveller sites</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposals to give councils more freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites have been published for consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be given greater freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites being set up and prevent long, drawn-out stalemates like Dale Farm, under proposals published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="temporary-stop-notices"&gt;Temporary Stop Notices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals would allow councils greater freedom to use temporary stop notices in relation to caravans that are in breach of planning control, and are used as a person’s main residence. This would be backed up with the potential for heavy fines of up to £20,000 on indictment or an unlimited fine on summary conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the current system councils are constrained as to when they can use these powers against caravans that are main residences, which can result in long delays and high costs to stop unauthorised development of this kind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long a small minority have abused the planning system, often at the expense of local communities who are forced to put up with unauthorised development in their area. This government believes in fair play, with everyone abiding by the same rules. These proposals will assist local councils in taking effective action against those who don’t.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-powers"&gt;Stronger powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporary Stop Notices enable councils to take action with immediate effect against unauthorised development without having to wait three days for a Stop Notice, or 28 days for an enforcement notice to come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to the outcome of the consultation, today’s proposals would remove restrictions on the use of temporary stop notices so councils can act quickly against new unauthorised sites, and save on the costs of enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60566</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-diamond-arrives-home-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Diamond arrives home in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Diamond has returned home to Portsmouth today following her maiden deployment to the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyer&lt;/a&gt; sailed more than 31,000 miles (50,000 kilometres) on security and counter-piracy patrols in the Indian Ocean, Gulf of Oman and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; left Portsmouth in June shortly after launching the nation’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations with a ceremonial entry into the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth" title="Portsmouth Naval Base"&gt;naval base&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After travelling through the Mediterranean she transited the Suez Canal before taking over from sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Daring" title="HMS Daring"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Daring&lt;/a&gt;. Diamond then spent the following 5 months as part of the Combined Task Force, a 27-nation partnership promoting security in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship worked with the French Carrier Group in the Mediterranean and three United States Carrier Strike Groups (&lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Middle East, including the escort of the US carriers through the Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s fighter controllers exercised with the US Navy’s F18 Hornets and controlled F22 Raptor and F15 Strike Eagle aircraft from the United States Air Force. The ship’s Lynx aircraft also demonstrated its ability to conduct air intercepts for the task groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also exercised with the navies of Australia, Canada, France, Kuwait, and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While conducting counter-piracy operations the ship’s specialist embarked military force carried out assurance visits to local fishermen and traders and held boarding training with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Commander Ian Clarke is greeted by his family" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5814/FX120552013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond's Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, is greeted by his wife, Joanne, and daughter Rebecca, aged 3 [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have achieved a tremendous amount this deployment and I pay tribute to my fantastic ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have provided reassurance in the Middle East, under the Combined Maritime Forces, worked closely with regional allies and three US &lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt; and really pushed the air defence capability of these fantastic new destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also worked alongside other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; assets, such as minehunters based out of Bahrain and their support ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Bay-Class-Landing-Ships/RFA-Cardigan-Bay" title="RFA Cardigan Bay"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Cardigan Bay&lt;/a&gt;. Helicopters of the Fleet Air Arm were also involved - with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-ASaC" title="Sea King Mk7 Airborne Surveillance and Control"&gt;Sea King Mark 7&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/854" title="854 Squadron"&gt;854 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; making its first ever landing on a Type 45 - while Merlin aircraft also interacted with Diamond at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as time at sea in the region, she has visited Bahrain, Jordan, Kuwait, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, as well as Gibraltar and Crete and the cities of Athens and Barcelona while on transit to and from the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer David Turner said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a busy few months but working with the other navies has been enjoyable, as have all the fascinating places we have visited. Although what we have achieved has been immensely rewarding, after six months away it is good to know that we are back in time to be reunited with our loved ones for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore The Hon Michael Cochrane, Commander Portsmouth Flotilla, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome Diamond back after what has been an exciting and high-profile deployment for the ship’s company, whose work has seen them entering new fields of interest for the air defence community. I am sure they will enjoy their well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond is the third of the UK’s fleet of six Type 45 destroyers. She was launched in 2007, arrived in Portsmouth in the autumn of 2010 and was commissioned in the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60750</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:56:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"/>
    <title>Planning practice guidance should be simpler</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An external review of planning practice guidance has recommended rationalising advice and making it easier to use.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review group, lead by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system but did not review planning policy. They were not tasked with revaluating green belt policy or other countryside protections, which continue to be safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that the existing guidance is unwieldy in its current form and recommends that it be shorter but retain key elements, and be more accessible to be useful to everyone using the planning system. They stated that guidance is important to ensuring planning decisions are properly informed but should not place undue burdens on users of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that a vast range of materials are being considered guidance, and that ‘living documents’ intended to be updated on a regular basis had not been amended since publication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; to consider the group’s recommendations was launched today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is very clear that the old way of doing things is no longer fit for purpose. We have made recommendations for a modern web-based resource that is clear, up-to-date, coherent and easily usable, not just by planners and developers, but the public too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very grateful to the group for all the work they have done on this. We will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and I would urge other users of the planning system to have their say by responding to the consultation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group consists of Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones. They are sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;External review of government planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;Review of planning practice guidance - consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt;, Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60139</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-choir-a-year-with-the-military-wives"/>
    <title>The Choir: a year with the Military Wives</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Choirmaster Gareth Malone and key members of the Military Wives Choir reflect on their extraordinary journey in a Christmas Day television special.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, Gareth Malone went to the military base at Chivenor to set up a choir for the wives left at home alone while their men are on duty for months at a time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html" title="The Choir: a year with the Military Wives"&gt;the Christmas Day show&lt;/a&gt;, we hear from Gareth and key members of the choir as they reflect on their extraordinary journey including their performance of a song, specially written by royal composer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paulmealor.com/" title="Paul Mealor website"&gt;Paul Mealor&lt;/a&gt;, at The Royal Albert Hall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rehearsals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5783/choirpractise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gareth Malone and Military Wives rehearse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film shows the women as they launch their first single, which topped the Christmas charts, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="10 Downing Street website"&gt;10 Downing Street&lt;/a&gt;, perform at the Golden Jubilee and win a Classical Brit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also hear of the legacy of the original choir - the setting up of a charitable foundation that provides the support for a growing network of over 60 military wives choirs in bases across the UK, Europe and the Falkland Islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soloist Sam Stevenson says: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was Gareth’s dream and it came true and not many people can say their dreams have come true in life. I don’t even think I could express to Gareth how grateful we all are for it, it’s just, he’s really changed our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html"&gt;The Choir: A year with the Military Wives&lt;/a&gt; will be on Christmas Day, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo" title="BBC Two website"&gt;BBC2&lt;/a&gt; at 8.45pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60323</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-gives-blueprint-to-potential-infrastructure-partners"/>
    <title>MOD gives blueprint to potential infrastructure partners</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Defence Infrastructure Organisation (DIO), the Ministry of Defence's (MOD) property and services provider, has issued the document which allows the three short-listed teams to prepare detailed bids to potentially become its Strategic Business Partner (SBP).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Invitation to Negotiate (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt;) asks each team to further prove it can provide the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; with a proposal to bring the right skills and expertise, before the organisation makes a final decision regarding its preferred option next summer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organisation, which manages the delivery of infrastructure projects and services for the UK Armed Forces and its civilian support staff, will introduce new ways of working from Spring 2013. However, procuring a &lt;abbr title="Strategic Business Partner"&gt;SBP&lt;/abbr&gt; could realise further savings to benefit Defence as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Manley, Chief Executive, &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s principle objective is to support our military personnel in its Standing Commitments and in preparing for operations. We do this by providing and maintaining the places where they live, work and train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In addition &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; is central to supporting the Government’s wider objectives in construction, property management and the delivery of supporting the services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changing the way we deliver infrastructure services offers a real opportunity to build a leading-edge infrastructure delivery organisation that will serve the needs of our Armed Forces long into the future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are striving to create a high-performing and innovative enterprise. Our search for a Strategic Business Partner is expected to extend our capability by allowing &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; further access to private sector skills and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; has been working to ensure that the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a robust platform to effectively explore the use of private sector expertise. However, a contract will only be awarded if it can be found to provide value for money to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a robust procurement exercise, launched in May 2012, three teams were selected to participate in the next stage of the competition. They consist of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.telerealtrillium.com/" title="Telereal Trillium website"&gt;Telereal Trillium&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kpmg.com/uk/en/pages/default.aspx" title="KPMG website"&gt;KPMG&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.macegroup.com/" title="Mace website"&gt;Mace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.serco.com/" title="Serco website"&gt;Serco&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dtz.com/UK" title="DTZ website"&gt;DTZ&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bechtel.com/" title="Bechtel website"&gt;Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.capita.co.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Capita website"&gt;Capita&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.urscorp.com/" title="URS website"&gt;URS&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paconsulting.co.uk/" title="PA Consulting website"&gt;PA Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60310</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/david-cameron-visits-troops-in-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>David Cameron visits troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Prime Minister praised armed forces success during visit to Camp Bastion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister flew into Afghanistan yesterday morning, 20 December. He visited Camp Bastion, where he met with military commanders before joining troops for an early Christmas dinner and a carol service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s visit came a day after he told &lt;abbr title="Members of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Parliament that troop numbers will almost halve to around 5,200 by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron meets troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5805/PMmeetstroops.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;David Cameron visits Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told journalists on the trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is still a difficult and dangerous place but we’ve made real progress. It is tough, it is difficult, and we’ve paid a high price but their efforts have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander Task Force Helmand, reiterated confidence in the growing capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is now absolutely appropriate we hand more and more control over to the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Cameron met troops who he praised for their service in Afghanistan and thanked them for making the country “prouder than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a message to the armed forces, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well it is a good time to come to Afghanistan and say a really big thank you to our troops for everything they do, and particularly at Christmas time when they’re away from loved ones.  But I think it’s an opportunity to say to all our forces all over the world…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You make us incredibly proud; we’re always proud of you, and this year perhaps prouder than ever for your extraordinary work in Afghanistan, for the amazing things you do over the whole of Africa to keep us safe from terrorism and piracy, for the extraordinary things you did at the Olympics where the military stepped up, put a smiling face on the greatest show on earth, won a lot of medals too and made the country very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military really are the best of the best and we can’t thank them enough for what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60313</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:29:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/change-of-governor-of-the-falklands-islands"/>
    <title>Change of Governor of the Falklands Islands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Mr Colin Roberts CVO has been appointed Governor of the Falkland Islands and Commissioner of South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will succeed Mr Nigel Robert Haywood CVO, who will be transferring to another Diplomatic Service appointment. Mr Roberts will take up his appointment during April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Roberts joined the FCO in 1989. He is currently Director for Eastern Europe and Central Asia having served as Director for the Overseas Territories from  2008-2012. His FCO career has covered a wide range of roles including European Union affairs, security policy, Eastern Europe and the Far East as well as the Overseas Territories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment as Governor of the Falkland Islands, Mr Roberts has said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be appointed as Governor of the Falkland Islands and HM Commissioner for South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands. I am a great admirer of the achievements of the people of the Falkland Islands. I look forward to working with the community and their elected representatives for a secure and prosperous future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="curriculum-vitae"&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full name:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Colin Roberts&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Married to:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Camilla&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Children:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oliver (b. 2002), Alexander (b.2004)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012 – present&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director, Eastern Europe and Central Asia Directorate&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008 – 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director, Overseas Territories Directorate, Her Majesty’s Commissioner, British Antarctic Territory and Her Majesty’s Commissioner, British Indian Ocean Territory&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2004 – 2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Her Majesty’s Ambassador, Vilnius&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001 – 2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, Political Counsellor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1998 – 2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head, EU Common Foreign and Security Policy Department&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1997 – 1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paris, First Secretary for Politico-Military Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995 – 1996&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head of Justice and Home Affairs Section, European Union Department (Internal)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head of Gibraltar Section, European Union Department (Internal)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1993 – 1994&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, First Secretary for Political Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990 – 1992&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, Second Secretary for Economic and Financial Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Economic Advisers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1989 – 1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Desk officer for the Republic of Ireland&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60283</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-for-transports-boost-to-train-builders"/>
    <title>Department for Transport's boost to train builders</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New train carriages procured by Southern Railway. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train builders have received a year-end boost as the government announces its backing for two new train orders, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of government support, Southern Railway has now procured 40 new carriages from Bombardier based in Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 40 carriages, the government is also supporting Southern’s tendering process for 116 new electric carriages with the option for a further 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our support for Southern will not only boost capacity but help secure British jobs. The deal for the 40 new carriages, helped along by my department, demonstrates the government’s ongoing commitment to invest in Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My officials are working with Southern to accelerate their procurement process for up to 256 carriages because our ambitious electrification plans requires additional rolling stock on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2011 Southern Railway, with government support, announced its plans to buy 130 carriages from Bombardier to run on services in south London, Surrey, Sussex and Kent. Southern expects these will be in service by December 2013. As part of this deal Southern had the option to buy the additional 40 carriages at a later stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July the government announced the biggest programme of rail modernisation since the Victorian era. At the heart of the scheme was the electrification of the Midland Main Line, from London to Sheffield, with additional spurs linking it to the Great Western Main Line and the Port of Southampton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Southern progresses with the procurement, these 116 new vehicles, and potentially 140 more, could initially be used on the Thameslink routes. Once the expected new Thameslink trains are operational these carriages will be moved to the newly electrified routes, which could include the Midland Main Line to Corby and North Transpennine Routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60272</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T17:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T17:04:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/princess-royal-attends-naval-cadets-passing-out-parade"/>
    <title>Princess Royal attends naval cadets' passing out parade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Her Royal Highness The Princess Royal has attended a parade performed by cadets passing out from Britannia Royal Naval College (BRNC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royal.gov.uk/thecurrentroyalfamily/theprincessroyal/theprincessroyal.aspx" title="The Princess Royal"&gt;The Princess Royal&lt;/a&gt;, accompanied by her husband, Vice Admiral Sir Tim Laurence, was the guest of honour at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s final passing-out-parade of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rain eased off, and with the Royal Marines band playing festive tunes, the Princess Royal was invited to inspect the cadets and take the salute during the march past. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parade signified the end of 30 weeks intensive training for the 67 Officer Cadets who can now enjoy Christmas with their families before embarking on the next stage of their Royal Navy careers. Among those passing-out were cadets from 10 overseas nations, who regularly send their personnel to &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; for training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Captain Jerry Kyd, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were very honoured to have Her Royal Highness visit us for our final parade of the year. These Cadets have been given a thorough induction into the Royal Navy and worked hard to earn their place on the parade ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Princess Royal chats to cadets" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5796/DSC_0146.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Princess Royal chats to one of the cadets during the parade [Picture: Copyright Craig Keating]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They spent the last nine weeks of their training at sea. Some were assigned to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Illustrious&lt;/a&gt;, while others were on board the fleet flagship, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/the-fleet/ships/assault-ships/hms-bulwark" title="HMS Bulwark"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Bulwark&lt;/a&gt;. Both warships were involved in the Royal Navy’s Cougar 12 deployment working as part of the UK’s Response Force Task Group, exercising with a multitude of other nations in the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was an excellent opportunity for the cadets to see at first hand the Royal Navy in operation, working in partnership with our allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Princess Royal has a long association with the Royal Navy. She holds the rank of Rear Admiral as Chief Commandant for Women in the Royal Navy and has special relationships with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class/HMS-Talent" title="HMS Talent"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Talent&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Albion" title="HMS Albion"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Albion&lt;/a&gt;. The Princess Royal is also Commodore-in-Chief for Portsmouth and last attended a parade at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2002, when she represented Her Majesty The Queen at Lord High Admiral’s Divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total 237 &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and cadets at varying stages of their training were on parade with music provided by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalmarinesbands.co.uk/reference/band_ply.htm" title="The Band of Her Majesty's Royal Marines Plymouth"&gt;Band of Her Majesty’s Royal Marines Plymouth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a period of leave, the College will re-open in January 2013 for what will be the 150th year of Royal Navy officer training in Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60282</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T16:02:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T16:02:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-launches-new-skynet-satellite"/>
    <title>MOD launches new Skynet satellite</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new satellite which will provide secure military communications for UK Armed Forces has been successfully launched into space.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The extra lines of communication will benefit personnel deployed in Afghanistan and other parts of the world, including the Falklands, Cyprus and on ships at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; pictures show the moment that Skynet 5D was launched from French Guiana, South America. It is the fourth satellite of the Skynet 5 project to be put into space since 2007 under a £4bn Private Finance Initiative (&lt;abbr title="Private Finance Initiative"&gt;PFI&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.astrium.eads.net/" title="Astrium website"&gt;Astrium&lt;/a&gt;, who built the satellite and service providers &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.astriumservices.com/" title="Astrium Services"&gt;Astrium Services&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Skynet project sustains approximately 800 jobs between the company’s sites in Stevenage, Portsmouth and Corsham, Wiltshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in space, Skynet 5D will travel at speeds of around 10,000 kilometres per hour and is expected to cover around 1.2 billion kilometres during its time in orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Skynet 5D satellite is launched from French Guiana" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5790/Decollage_Toucan_010.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Skynet 5D satellite is launched from French Guiana in South America [Picture: S Martin. © ESA-CNES-ARIANESPACE / Optique vidéo du CSG]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colonel Mike Griffiths, Head of Networks for the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/defence-equipment-and-support" title="Defence Equipment and Support page on GOV.UK"&gt;Defence Equipment and Support&lt;/a&gt; organisation, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Skynet programme provides vital support to the Armed Forces. The launch of this latest satellite will deliver additional global communications capacity to support our operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/philip-hammond" title="Read about Defence Secretary Philip Hammond"&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The launch of Skynet 5D marks another milestone in this very successful programme. These satellites provide essential secure communication channels for our Armed Forces in Afghanistan and allow all three Services to communicate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of the satellites, Skynet 5A, was launched in March 2007, followed by Skynet 5B in November 2007, and Skynet 5C in June 2008.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60215</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:45:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens"/>
    <title>Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has reaffirmed UK support for imprisoned Human Rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mark the United Nations vote on the human right situation in Iran, the Foreign Secretary has released a video. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic freedoms of ordinary Iranians are being denied. Many citizens live in constant fear of arbitrary arrest, false imprisonment and, in some cases, death. There is undeniable evidence of abuse: the recent death in custody of blogger Sattar Beheshti is one tragic example. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary also spoke about Nasrin Sotoudeh, who recently ended a 49-day hunger strike in protest against the harassment of her family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have sacrificed your own freedom, family life and health in order to help others. I want you to know that we are following your case closely. And that I echo the many calls upon Iran for your immediate release. Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regime hopes to silence those who call for basic human rights in Iran. I want to make clear that the promotion and protection of human rights is at the heart of UK foreign policy. And we are committed to supporting and protecting those who defend human rights and work tirelessly to advance personal freedoms, often at great personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OHQkieCYSZg"&gt;Watch the Foreign Secretary’s video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/ukiniran/punishing-a-human-rights-defender-nasrin-sotoudehs" title="Nasrin Sotoudehs story"&gt;Nasrin Sotoudeh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family" title="UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60204</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:16:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria"/>
    <title>UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria  </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt: The UK will continue to support work of UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria to ensure accountability. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the publication of a new UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today the UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria published its latest report on the human rights situation in Syria. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. The Commission concludes that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commission has received credible accounts of Government soldiers executing captives. Incidents of direct targeting of civilians by aerial bombardment, including “barrel bombs,” rocket attacks and machine gun fire have risen significantly over recent months. There is testimony of systematic patterns of torture in detention centres, including of children. This report is a stark reminder of the horrific situation in Syria. I call upon all sides to put an end to the violence and pursue a process of genuine political transition which reflects the will of the Syrian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work undertaken by the UN Commission of inquiry, in difficult circumstances, is vital to ensure that human rights violations and abuses committed by all parties are documented. We will continue to do all we can to support their work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Countries/SY/ColSyriaDecember2012.pdf" title="UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry report on Syria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Countries/MENARegion/Pages/SYIndex.aspx" title="UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports"&gt;UN Commission of Inquiry’s previous reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60117</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-everyone-a-happy-christmas"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish everyone a happy Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for Christmas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the year draws to a close and families up and down the country get ready to celebrate Christmas, we should all be immensely proud of the vital role that churches play in our neighbourhoods and the special place the Christian faith holds in our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our Christian communities have a strong tradition of giving back and improving the lives of those around them, as I saw for myself at a harvest festival service at London’s Borough Market where food and clothing was donated to the homeless, regardless of faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to those who will be selflessly helping others this year, whether through volunteering in a soup-kitchen or collecting and donating gifts - these generous acts make a real difference within our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The upcoming holiday is a strong reminder of the Christian ethos within our country and I wish a very merry Christmas to one and all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith and Communities Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Minister for Faith and Communities I would like to send my warmest wishes to everyone this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Christmas is an extremely special time for Britain, a country where the majority of people identify themselves as Christian. None of us should forget that, amid the turkeys, the tinsel and all the traditions that accompany this festival, lies the true meaning of Christmas: the birth of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a time for goodwill and generosity, reflection and redemption. These are themes we can all celebrate - people of all faiths and of none, who break their busy routines to come together with families and friends in the spirit of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Christmas let’s also remember the positive impact of faith on society and think about those who face persecution for holding a belief. Let’s also be confident in Britain’s Christianity, as I said when I led the largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See earlier this year. We cannot erase this faith from our history any more than we can erase the spires from our landscapes - or, indeed, the stars from the tops of our trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wishing everyone a very merry Christmas and a happy, peaceful New Year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60181</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T14:56:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-court-of-human-rights-decision-on-chagossian-case"/>
    <title>European Court of Human Rights’ decision on Chagossian Case</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary has commented on the European Court of Human Rights’ decision on the Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom case. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case concerns complaints made by the Chagos Islanders arising from the evacuation of the British Indian Ocean Territory between 1967 and 1973.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome the end of this legal process, which has taken many years. We have made clear our regret for the wrongs done to the Chagossian people over forty years ago. Nevertheless, it was right for the Government to defend itself against this action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that this litigation is concluded, the Government will take stock of our policy towards the resettlement of the British Indian Ocean Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;), as we have always said we would. There are fundamental difficulties with resettlement in &lt;abbr title="British Indian Ocean Territory"&gt;BIOT&lt;/abbr&gt;, but we will be as positive as possible in our engagement with Chagossian groups and all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Court of Human Rights decision on application 35622/04: Chagos Islanders v. the United Kingdom can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.echr.coe.int/ECHR/Homepage_EN" title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60653</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T14:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:16:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/chair-appointed-to-advise-government-on-setting-up-business-bank"/>
    <title>Chair appointed to advise government on setting up business bank</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sir Peter Burt confirmed as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, former Chief Executive of Bank of Scotland, has been confirmed today as the chair of a group that will advise the Government on the establishment and direction of the business bank.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business bank is being set up to address the long term problems affecting the provision of finance to small and medium sized enterprises (SMEs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Small and medium sized business are the lifeblood of the British economy but they are currently struggling to accrue the long term capital they need to grow. This is an important gap in their growth cycle which the business bank will plug by offering new sources of finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help deliver this, the Government will be advised by a talented panel of experts, led by Sir Peter Burt. It is important we get the development of the bank right. This is a long term, durable institution, not a quick-fix gimmick, and I’m confident that we are on track to deliver this help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Peter Burt, Chair of the business bank advisory group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been a significant long-standing gap in SME finance, so it is welcome news that the Government is taking action to tackle this problem and help provide long term finance solutions for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to have been asked to help the Government in their work to create this institution and recognise the potential this institution has in changing the finance landscape. I look forward to working with the advisory group and putting our collective experience to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future institution will support the development of a greater diversity of non-bank business finance sources and tackle other long-standing market gaps by deploying £1 billion of new funding. The impact and reach of this funding will be maximised by exploring joint investment opportunities with the private sector and the use of Government guarantees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was confirmed at the Autumn Statement, we propose to use £300 million of the new funding by investing alongside the private sector in sources of finance that will help diversify the business finance market. Further detail on how this funding will be made available will be provided at Budget 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s own business finance schemes will be brought together within the new institution so that they are managed as a single portfolio. It will also seek to bring Government-backed business advice services closer together, harmonise their engagement with customers and co-ordinate them closely with finance interventions, to improve accessibility for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected the institution will operate on a commercial basis within a strategic framework set by ministers. Discussions will begin in January with the European Commission to ensure the proposals for the creation of the bank and the support Government would like the institution to offer are in line with state aid rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Morgan has also been appointed to aid the Government in setting up the business bank. Starting in the new year, he will lead the team in Whitehall that will develop proposals for the design of the future bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The statement the Business Secretary made in the House is available on the parliament website: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/"&gt;www.parliament.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt will not receive remuneration for his role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Peter Burt has extensive experience in business banking. He started his career at the Bank of Scotland in 1975, working in the international and oil and energy department. He rose to become head of the international division in 1985, treasurer and chief general manager in 1988 and eventually Chief Executive Officer in 1996. Following the merger with Halifax, he served as Deputy Chairman of HBOS and Governor of the Bank of Scotland, (a largely ceremonial role) from 2001 to 2003.  In 2004, he was appointed Chairman of ITV plc. He also served as a non-executive director of Royal Dutch Shell until 2006, Chairman of Dyslexia Scotland and on the boards of a number of charities. He is now the Chairman of Promethean, which is an advisory and investment firm that focuses on UK lower mid-market companies facing financial or other constraints in their businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Morgan was a Director and Head of Wholly-Owned Investments at UKFI, responsible for managing the Government’s shareholdings in Northern Rock, Bradford &amp;amp; Bingley and UK Asset Resolution, until August 2012. He was a Non-Executive Director of Northern Rock plc until its sale to Virgin Money in January 2012. Keith joined UKFI from Banco Santander where he was a Director of Sovereign Bancorp in the USA, focusing on the integration of Sovereign into Santander. He was previously Director of Strategy &amp;amp; Planning at Abbey National, where he was a member of the Executive Committee, and was also Chairman of Santander’s Asset Management and Credit Card businesses in the UK. Before joining Abbey in 2004, Keith spent 18 years at L.E.K. Consulting, where he was a partner specialising in financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members of the advisory group will be announced in the new year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
