<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-09T20:35:57+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16641</id>
    <published>2012-12-09T20:35:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-09T20:35:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rafs-ii-ac-squadron-returns-from-afghanistan"/>
    <title>RAF's II (AC) Squadron returns from Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The personnel flew directly into the Norfolk base where they were greeted by RAF Marham’s Station Commander, Group Captain David Cooper, before being transported across to where their families eagerly awaited their arrival. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personnel are now looking forward to spending some time with their families after what has been an extremely eventful year for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/2squadron.cfm" title="II(Army Cooperation) Squadron"&gt;II(AC) Squadron&lt;/a&gt; or ‘Shiny Two’, as it is known. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The squadron has taken part in a major exercise in North America, and participated in a number of ceremonies to mark the squadron’s centenary, before turning their attention to the Operation HERRICK work-up and their subsequent deployment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, after four-and-a-half months, II (AC) Squadron’s deployment on Operation HERRICK has come to a close and it was fitting that the squadron, whose initial role was supporting ground troops back in 1912, has continued to do precisely that, 100 years after its formation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday 17 November II(AC) Squadron formally handed over to its sister squadron &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/9squadron.cfm" title="IX (Bomber) Squadron"&gt;IX (Bomber)&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/" title="RAF Marham"&gt;RAF Marham&lt;/a&gt;. This is familiar territory for both squadrons as it was only last year that the squadrons handed over to one another on Operation ELLAMY over Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="II (Army Cooperation) Squadron personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1140/MAR-UNCLASS-20121120-1366-0081.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;II (Army Cooperation) Squadron personnel returning to RAF Marham from their Afghanistan deployment [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Simon Armstrong, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;IX (Bomber) Squadron, under the leadership of Wing Commander Andy Turk, will be in residence at Kandahar Airfield in Afghanistan over Christmas and the New Year before handing over to the third RAF Marham-based squadron, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/31squadron.cfm" title="31 Squadron"&gt;31 Squadron&lt;/a&gt;, next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deploying at the height of summer, II (AC) Squadron can reflect and take pride in a job extremely well done. It has been a highly successful four-and-a-half month detachment, with the squadron flying over 2,000 hours in support of UK and coalition forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engineering challenge has also been significant, particularly with the high temperatures. However, the pragmatism, enthusiasm and dedication of the engineers ensured continued aircraft availability for daily and ground close air support taskings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Commanding II (AC) Squadron, Wing Commander Nick Tucker-Lowe, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has been a tremendously successful deployment for ‘Shiny Two’. With an operational pedigree that is ‘second-to-none’ the squadron always strives for operational excellence and, due to the consistent diligence and determination of all of the squadron’s personnel, that is exactly what we have achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39676</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities Ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish Community have made, and continue to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39721</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39686</id>
    <published>2012-09-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/success-for-british-teams-in-world-helicopter-championship"/>
    <title>Success for British teams in World Helicopter Championship</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The competition, in its 14th year, was held outside the Russian capital with two teams from the British Services taking part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Helicopter Club of Great Britain invited the crews to compete as part of the British team following their successes at the British and German Championships in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Championship requires the crews to exercise their skills through a number of flying tests including an obstacle course which involves dangling a bucket of water below the helicopter whilst negotiating a slalom course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two teams comprised instructors from the Defence Helicopter Flying School (DHFS), whose day job is to teach all UK military helicopter pilots and crews for all three Services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main team, comprising Squadron Leader Craig Finch and Mr John ‘JJ’ Jackson, an ex-RAF airman, are the current British champions, and were successful at both the UK and European competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also taking part in the competition was the second team, which paired Flight Lieutenant Mark Lazenby with Lieutenant Jim Fraser of the Royal Navy and was managed by Flying Officer Ryan Stowe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two Squirrel helicopters flown by the British teams were provided by FBHeliservices who own and operate the aircraft flown at RAF Shawbury. Mr Gareth Mayfield from FBHeliservices travelled with the aircraft to provide engineering support throughout the Championship. The company has been instrumental in ensuring that the teams have been able to compete at the highest level.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Championship ran from 22 to 26 August at Drakino Airfield in Russia, with 50 teams taking part from across the world. Twenty-five of those teams were made up of Russian or Belarusian crews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six teams competed for the team prize with the UK pairing of Finch and Jackson taking the silver medal having finished a creditable second behind Russia. In the overall competition the pair finished 13th out of 50 whilst the pairing of Lazenby/Fraser finished in 30th place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The medal presentation took place on Sunday 26 August and was attended by the Moscow Defence Attache. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Lazenby said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The DHFS crews’ attendance at the WHC reflected their pre-eminence at the National Helicopter Championships and their long-standing success at these and other international events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful performance of the DHFS crews ably demonstrated the professionalism and skill of UK military aircrew and the success of the military/civil partnership at DHFS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lead DHFS team was the highest-ranked team outside of Russia/Belarus, beating all military and civilian crews from Germany, Austria, Switzerland, China, Poland, France and Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28520</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T16:05:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T16:05:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/autumn-statement-huge-boost-for-transport"/>
    <title>Autumn statement: huge boost for transport</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor announced funding for the following transport projects as part of the Autumn statement 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scheme-a1-leeming-to-barton-improvements"&gt;Scheme: A1 Leeming to Barton improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £314 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upgrading the A1 between Leeming to Barton to motorway standard by upgrading a dual carriageway to a three lane road&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will create a continuous motorway standard route from Leeds to Newcastle and London to Newcastle (via M1/A1M)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will also improve journey times between Leeming and Barton and over 60 years is predicted to save around 100 lives and prevent around 650 serious casualties as well as helping speed up the time it takes to clear up traffic incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;during construction it is estimated that at its peak up to 750 new jobs will be created in the construction industry over the three year construction period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;completion of the scheme will support the economic competitiveness of the north-east and improve access to regional employment areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the reduction in journey times of some 20% will directly benefit business users, improving the attractiveness of these areas for future development and growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;works are planned to start in 2013/14 with the scheme open for traffic by 2016/17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a5-m1-link-dunstable-northern-bypass"&gt;Scheme: A5-M1 link (Dunstable northern bypass)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £126.6 million (Department for Transport (DfT) contribution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new dual two-lane road between the A5 (western end) and the M1 (eastern end) north of Dunstable and Houghton Regis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will remove through traffic between Dunstable and the M1 speeding up longer distance north south trips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will also unlock the development of 7,000 houses and 40 hectares of employment land – potentially providing 4,000 jobs – at Houghton Regis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work will start in 2014/15 with the scheme open for traffic in 2015/16.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a1-lobley-hill-improvement"&gt;Scheme: A1 Lobley Hill improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £64 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new roads in both directions parallel to the existing A1 between Lobley Hill and A184 in Gateshead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will provide an alternative route for local traffic improving congestion and accident rates on one of the most congested sections of the network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the government made a commitment through the Newcastle ‘City Deal’ process to work with local partners on considering proposals to address congestion on the A1 Newcastle/Gateshead western bypass – including proposals to deliver the Lobley Hill improvements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it also helps support local regeneration and development, including the creation of up to 22,000 new jobs, as the congestion is considered as a major constraint to expansion of regional employment and housing &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work is planned to start in 2014/15 with the scheme open for traffic by 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-highways-maintenance"&gt;Scheme: Highways maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £333 million &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated fund for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend life of road network in England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges, or repair damage caused by weather events, like recent floods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the money will be split between Highways Agency and local authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;details of how each area will benefit from this additional investment will be announced shortly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-strategic-road-pinch-point-fund"&gt;Scheme: Strategic road pinch point fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £100 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;additional funding for the Highways Agency’s pinch point fund to improve congestion and safety at bottlenecks on the strategic road network and facilitate local economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it will be used for improvements such as road widening and junction improvements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes delivered as part of this programme will facilitate the creation of jobs and housing, improve access to enterprise zones and transport gateways that are within the vicinity of the scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Highways Agency will now work on identifying the specific projects that will benefit and make an announcement shortly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;Scheme: Local pinch point fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £170 million &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fund to remove bottlenecks and support development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes delivered as part of this programme will facilitate the creation of jobs and housing development, improve access to enterprise zones and transport gateways - this could include new access roads, junction improvements or bridge strengthening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is open to local transport authorities in England - guidance on how to apply for funding and timescales will be published shortly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schemes considered will be ones that can be delivered quickly delivering an immediate impact on growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-a30-temple-to-carblake"&gt;Scheme: A30 Temple to Carblake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £60 million (£30 million DfT contribution and £30 million Cornwall Council contribution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 2.6 mile dualling of the existing single carriageway section of the A30 between Temple and Higher Carblake including changes to existing junctions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme will relieve congestion and improve journey times - it will also attract business growth and inward investment to Cornwall by improving links the rest of England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cornwall Council is proposing to deliver and part-fund the scheme on behalf of the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work will start in 2014/2015 (subject to the completion of planning processes and funding agreements between Cornwall Council) with the scheme open for traffic in 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-accelerated-national-road-projects"&gt;Scheme: Accelerated national road projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £95 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the acceleration of three major motorway upgrades for M3 J2 to 4a, Surrey, M6 J10a to 13, West Midlands and M1 J28 to 31, Derbyshire to deliver the improvement schemes by spring 2015&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will result in increased capacity of 73 miles and reduced congestion through use of the hard shoulder as an extra lane&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vital improvements to the A160/A180 route to the port of Immingham will also be brought forward to start construction in the summer of 2015 (subject to the completion of statutory processes), with completion in autumn 2016 - cutting 18 months off the original construction timetable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-development-of-future-national-road-projects"&gt;Scheme: Development of future national road projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £42 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continuing the development (detailed design, modelling and preparatory work) of future major road projects to maintain a pipeline of major road infrastructure proposals for delivery in the next spending review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development work will put in place the necessary preparatory work and analysis to ensure the Department for Transport can plan its future investments and ensure it is in a position to deliver vital future infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the development funding provides a contribution to UK job creation as it will be delivered in part through the transport supply chain &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department has previously identified a number of future national road proposals and will announce in due course which schemes will have their development work funded, following a process of prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-cycling-infrastructure-improvements"&gt;Scheme: Cycling infrastructure improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £42 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this funding will support infrastructure improvements that make it easier and safer for people get around their local areas by bicycle  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this could include more cycle lanes or tracks, improvements to junctions and signals, and cycle parking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local authorities will design solutions best for their areas while keeping a strong focus on economic growth and carbon reduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="scheme-m25-junction-30-improvements"&gt;Scheme: M25 junction 30 improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £150 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improved interface between M25 junction 30 and the A13 making the Thames Gateway more attractive to prospective developers, and improving access to the Lakeside shopping centre and the Port of Tilbury &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Highways Agency will now work up detailed plans for the scheme but options being considered are widening of the A13 and increased capacity at the junction roundabout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this will need to take account of the location of an additional crossing over the Lower Thames&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following scheme was also announced but will be funded from existing Highways Agency budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scheme-m40-j12-improvement"&gt;Scheme: M40 J12 improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: £10 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the layout at J12 of the M40 near Jaguar Land Rover’s (JLR) facility which includes their Research and Development Centre and the Aston Martin Lagonda site &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme includes realignment of the slip roads and a local side road and the installation of traffic signals at the top of the slip roads -it will assist traffic using the M40 which includes over 6,000 vehicles travelling to and from the JLR site and improve safety at the junction by alleviating traffic queuing back onto the M40 at peak times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme supports local economic growth and will benefit the national economy by reducing localised congestion on this strategic route between the Midlands and the south-east - it will also improve safety &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the scheme is being funded from existing Highways Agency budgets &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18821</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T11:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-coast-main-line-final-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"/>
    <title>West Coast Main Line: Final report of the Laidlaw inquiry</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the cancelled West Coast Main Line franchise competition has concluded that the project failed because of an accumulation of significant errors related to inadequate planning and preparation, complex organisational structure, and a weak governance framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Sam Laidlaw, the chief executive of Centrica and a non-executive &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; board member, to conduct an urgent investigation following the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the procurement process that led to the competition being cancelled on October 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;final report&lt;/a&gt;, published today by the Department for Transport, finds that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; used flawed and inconsistent methodology when guiding bidders on the amount of risk capital (known as the Subordinated Loan Facility) they would need to offer to guarantee their franchise against default (Inquiry report paragraph 4.31, p22)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Subordinated Loan Facility figures resulting from the flawed methodology were then varied in a way that contravened franchise competition rules (3.4, p11)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ministers made the original August 14 provisional contract award without being told about the critical flaws (2.12, p8) and having been given “inaccurate reports” (3.8, p12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the Laidlaw Inquiry also concluded that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the report’s recommendations to strengthen accountability and governance structures “if acted upon quickly and effectively, will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement” (paragraph 8.6, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;while there were inconsistencies in the way First Group and Virgin Trains Ltd were treated during the franchise process, the report finds that there is no evidence of a culture of bias against Virgin at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; (paragraph 2.6, p7)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is nothing in the report to suggest that the flaws discovered in this franchise competition exist in any other &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; procurements (paragraph 8.3, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; is today publishing its formal response to the report which commits the department to implementing swiftly a series of actions that will enable it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring future franchise competitions are delivered at a good pace based on sound planning, a clear timeline, rigorous management, and the right quality assurance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a simpler and clearer structure and governance process for rail franchise competitions, including the appointment of a single director general with responsibility for all rail policy and franchising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring we have the right mix of professional skills, in-house, and where necessary from professional external advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Building upon and confirming the conclusions from my initial findings, the final report provides an in-depth analysis of the events that led to the flaws whereby the InterCity West Coast competition was cancelled. Alongside this I have also made a series of recommendations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have explained in detail the technical nature of certain errors, specifically around modelling flaws and the Subordinated Loan Facility sizing process. In addition, the report outlines an accumulation of contributory causes including a lack of transparency, inadequate planning and preparation, as well as a complex and confusing organisational structure with weak quality assurance and insufficient governance oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While it is clear that a number of serious and regrettable errors have occurred, I believe that if acted upon quickly and effectively, my recommendations will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The final report from the Laidlaw inquiry makes extremely uncomfortable reading for the department. It has identified precisely what went wrong, revealing serious failures, as well as offering us a number of sensible recommendations to put things right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will not allow these mistakes to be made again and the department is determined to ensure all future franchise competitions are conducted on the basis of sound planning, the rigorous identification and oversight of risk, and the right quality assurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw has delivered an uncompromising report that offers us a way to face up to a number of shortcomings and I would like to thank him and his team for producing these findings with such diligence and speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; Permanent Secretary Philip Rutnam said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no question that this has been a serious blow for the department and I am determined that we learn everything we can from this episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will implement all of Mr Laidlaw’s recommendations, and go further, to ensure we have the right set of skills, support and training to ensure failures like this do not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Laidlaw inquiry final report to the Transport Secretary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;department’s response to the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report&lt;/a&gt;, setting out the actions being taken immediately to resolve the report recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laidlaw-inquiry-final-report"&gt;Transport Secretary’s oral statement to the House of Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report is only part of the work the department is doing to review its rail franchising policy. It will also take into account the forthcoming &lt;abbr title="National Audit Office"&gt;NAO&lt;/abbr&gt; report into the lessons from the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise and the conclusions of Richard Brown’s review of the future of the rail franchising programme, due to be submitted to the Secretary of State by the end of December&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Laidlaw inquiry team: 020 7861 2410&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18811</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T11:38:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:38:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/permanent-secretary-concerning-west-coast-main-line"/>
    <title>Permanent Secretary concerning West Coast Main Line</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport Permanent Secretary Philip Rutnam yesterday received the report of the investigation into the role and conduct of officials in the award process for the ICWC franchise process conducted by Bill Stow (a former Director General at Defra). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is now considering the report and decisions on action following this investigation will be made shortly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Secretary decided yesterday to lift the suspensions of three DfT officials imposed on the 3 October. The decision to suspend a member of staff, or to lift that suspension, is separate from the disciplinary process and does not imply any conclusion on culpability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18802</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T10:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T10:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-investment-in-local-growth-to-continue"/>
    <title>Government investment in local growth to continue</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures will enable the country to build new homes, deliver key infrastructure and support vital jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new £474 million Local Infrastructure Fund that will support investment in key local projects will open up new development, including locally supported large housing sites and bring surplus public land back into use, delivering much needed new homes, businesses, infrastructure and local transport schemes. Plus a further £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures announced in the Autumn Statement and the September Housing and Planning package will support delivery of up to 120,000 homes. There will also be cash injections for local areas through a £1.5 billion borrowing arrangement for local enterprise partnerships and more money for the Regional Growth Fund. While small firms will continue to receive larger business rate tax breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-investment-in-local-infrastructure"&gt;New investment in local infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £225 million will be used to accelerate delivery of locally supported large housing sites, supporting around 50,000 homes. There are many locally supported large housing schemes in the development pipeline that can provide real benefits to local communities that are struggling to move forward because of the current economic circumstances. This fund will help unlock those stalled sites so they become shovel ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £190 million of the funding will be used to enable the quicker disposal of surplus public sector land for new homes. Alongside this, the Government will provide £100 million to bring forward public sector sites for development. Government has identified enough land for over 106,000 homes and has already sold around 33,000. The Home and Communities Agency will become a single ‘shop window’ for land disposal so much needed homes can be built on these sites sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £60 million of this will be made available to support infrastructure in a limited number of enterprise zones. Building work has already begun on 20 zones and the majority have put in place simplified planning arrangements and secured private sector investment. The fund will help accelerate the infrastructure preparations so that new businesses can open and more new jobs are created as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from Lord Heseltine’s report which recommended devolution of more economic powers, local enterprise partnerships will be able to borrow up to £1.5 billion at cheap rates for nominated infrastructure projects. This puts partnerships and councils in much greater control over the levers of growth. They are already putting the Growing Places Fund to good use supporting 169 projects in the first 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will also pump an additional £350 million into the Regional Growth Fund, including a new £210 million to support jobs and growth across England - bringing the total fund to £2.6 billion. In addition, a new £170 million Department for Transport local transport pinch point fund, to unlock new development, homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="extra-support-for-business-continues"&gt;Extra support for business continues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the need to tackle the deficit there continues to be no real terms increases in business rates and inflation has fallen easing pressure further. The government will provide a further one year extension of the temporary doubling of small business rate relief to an estimated half a million business properties. In addition councils can now offer extra discounts to support local business and the 24 enterprise zones offer special 100% rate discounts to new firms that create local jobs. Postponing a revaluation will avoid local firms and local shops facing unexpected hikes in their business-rates bills over the next 5 years. Early estimates suggest that 800,000 premises faced a real-terms rise in their bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chancellor also announced a new temporary measure to extend the time period for the exemption from empty property rates, for newly built property for 18 months which will support construction. This will help promote regeneration and support high street renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="efficiency-savings-to-continue"&gt;Efficiency savings to continue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the government’s fiscal plans the new investment in the economy will, in part, be funded by some government departments’ resource budgets being reduced. The Department for Communites and Local Government has already become a smaller, streamlined, more flexible organisation. Its administration spending will reduce in real terms by 44% having reduced headcount by 37%. Arms length bodies have been reduced from 26 to 13 and the government office regions have been closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has been exempt from the reduction in 2013-2014 in recognition that local authorities are holding down budgets by comparable amounts by keeping council tax low in that year. This important concession will allow local authorities time in 2013-2014 to continue to protect frontline services by delivering reforms that will drive through further savings through transforming service delivery as demonstrated by the whole-place community budget pilots. Full details of local government funding for next year will be announced in the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement due later this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18795</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T09:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T09:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-6-december-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 6 December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has published transport statistics on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/waterborne-freight-in-the-united-kingdom-2011"&gt;waterborne freight in the United Kingdom: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details on all &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18775</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/virgin-trains-to-run-improved-west-coast-services"/>
    <title>Virgin Trains to run improved west coast services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers will experience better services including 28,000 more seats a day under an agreement announced today for Virgin Trains to continue operating rail services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise agreement will run for up to 23 months after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It coincides with the early completion of a government-backed deal to roll out 106 new Pendolino carriages, providing passengers with four new 11-carriage trains and lengthening 31 existing trains from nine carriages to 11. A new hourly service between London and Glasgow will also be introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to ensure not only that passengers continue to experience the same levels of service they have in the past, but that services improve. There will be a new hourly service linking Glasgow and London and we will also work with Virgin Trains to explore other service improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also extremely pleased that passengers will benefit from up to 28,000 more seats daily thanks to the delivery of 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line which has happened on budget and ahead of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling on Virgin Trains will also find it easier to claim compensation if their train is severely delayed thanks to plans for Virgin Trains to introduce an improved passenger’s charter incorporating a delay repay scheme from 1 April 2013, subject to agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 23 month franchise will run from 9 December 2012 until 9 November 2014 after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise. The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be able to shorten this period by up to six months if a subsequent franchise can be let on a shorter timescale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The franchise will operate as a management contract with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. In return Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;) will receive a margin of 1% on revenue for operating services. The franchise also makes a provision for the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 106 Pendolino carriages project has been delivered on budget and ahead of schedule and has resulted from a successful collaboration between the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;, Virgin Trains, Alstom, Angel Trains and Network Rail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28769</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/campaign-to-reward-designated-drivers-launched-by-coca-cola-great-britain-and-think"/>
    <title>Campaign to reward designated drivers launched by Coca-Cola Great Britain and THINK!</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designated drivers will be rewarded with a ‘buy 1 get 1 free’ deal on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coca-Cola Zero, this Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the winter period designated drivers across the UK will give lifts to friends and family as they enjoy a festive night out at pubs and bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain and the Road Safety Minister, Stephen Hammond MP, will today celebrate and pledge to reward responsible drivers, at the launch of this year’s designated driver campaign at the Mason Arms pub in Central London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in its 5th year the nationwide designated driver campaign will reward drivers who choose not to drink alcohol with a ‘buy 1, get 1 free’ offer on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and CokeZero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will run for 3 weeks from 6 to 31 December and is part of an ongoing partnership with the THINK! driver friendly campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dedicated website has also been set up to encourage consumers to take advantage of the offer. From the 6 December designated drivers and their friends can visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/"&gt;the Coca-Cola website&lt;/a&gt; to find a participating pub in their area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hammond, Road Safety Minister, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our THINK! campaign makes it clear that drink drivers risk losing their licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased that THINK! will be teaming up with Coca-Cola and pub chains across the country to reward designated drivers as well as reminding people of the consequences of getting a drink drive conviction. No one wants to spend their Christmas in a police cell.  My message is clear: don’t drink and drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Woods, General Manager, Coca-Cola Great Britain and Ireland said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Designated drivers provide an amazing service to friends and family. They allow people to have a good night and also help keep roads safe, so everyone can enjoy the Christmas period. By rewarding drivers who choose not to drink with a free Coke, Diet Coke or Coke Zero, we hope even more people will be encouraged to do the right thing and become responsible drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kieron Murphy, Licensee, Masons Arms: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We see a lot of people come in over the Christmas period who are responsible for driving their friends and family home at the end of the night. That’s why we are delighted to be participating in Coca-Cola’s designated driver campaign this year.  It will reward our regulars and make sure they still have a good night out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information, images or interview requests please contact Tim Smith.&lt;br&gt;
Telephone: +44 (0)20 7822 01734&lt;br&gt;
Email: &lt;a href="mailto:tim.smith@portland-communications.com"&gt;tim.smith@portland-communications.com&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event will take place on 6 December (7.30-9am) at the Mason Arms, Maddox Street, London. The designated driver campaign forms part of Coca-Cola Great Britain’s pledge to promote the positive role in which soft drinks can play as credible alternatives to alcohol. The designated driver campaign is a key feature of Coca-Cola Great Britain’s overall commitment to responsible marketing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-the-research"&gt;About the research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research was conducted by Populus for Coca-Cola in November 2011 with 2000 adults. Key findings include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;79% of women have used a designated driver at the end of a night out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;men are more likely to abstain from alcohol with 63% having given it up to drive friends/family home before &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;62% of adults plan to go to a pub or bar over the Christmas and New Year period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two thirds of those aged 65+ have been a designated driver compared to just over half of 18 to 24 year olds &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however 18 to 24 year olds will give the most lifts over the Christmas and New Year period, on average taking 5 people &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the majority of those polled never drive home after drinking more than one alcoholic drink on a night out (83%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nearly half of respondents thought that the best thing about designated drivers is that they stop people drink driving, while 3 in 4 believe it is because they ensure people can get home safely at the end of a night out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="about-coca-cola-great-britain"&gt;About Coca-Cola Great Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain is responsible for marketing 21 brands and over 100 products to consumers across Great Britain, focusing upon developing new brands, extending existing brands and protecting trademarks including Coca-Cola (recognised as the world’s most valuable brand). Other Coca-Cola Great Britain brands include Diet Coke, Coke Zero, Fanta, Sprite, Dr Pepper, Oasis, Glaceauvitaminwater, Schweppes, 5 Alive, Lilt, Kia Ora, Relentless Energy Drink and Powerade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coca-Cola Great Britain portfolio is worth £1,998 million with value sales growth of 8.4% year on year.  Within this the My Coke trilogy (Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coke Zero) is worth £1,150 million, growing at 6.4% in value year on year (Neilsen, w/c 11/02/12).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coca-Cola Great Britain is committed to developing innovative, responsible and sustainable initiatives that help protect the environment.  Recently the company launched its PlantBottle™ plastic made from up to 22.5% plant-based materials and up to 25% recycled plastic as the latest step on its journey towards petroleum-free plastic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company is also dedicated to recycling, with 97% of site waste recycled or recovered. For more information about Coca-Cola in Great Britain, please visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk"&gt;Coca-Cola website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-the-think-drink-drive-campaign-and-driver-friendly-initiative"&gt;About the THINK! drink drive campaign and driver friendly initiative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of people killed in drink drive accidents has been reduced by over three-quarters since 1979 thanks to more than 30 years of government education campaigns and measures to improve enforcement. However, drink driving is still a problem and provisional statistics show that 280 people lost their lives in drink drive accidents on Britain’s road in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The THINK! campaign has had a long-standing and well supported partnership with the on-trade and soft drinks industry. In December 2009, this was developed into the ‘driver friendly’ campaign which aims to support the designated driver through the provision of promotional offers and ‘rewards’, linked to the purchase of soft drinks, on their night out. Coca-Cola GB is leading the way for Christmas 2012, and their designated driver promotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DfT press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18813</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laidlaw-inquiry-final-report"/>
    <title>Laidlaw inquiry final report </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, with permission I would like to make a statement on what went wrong with the West Coast franchise agreement and what we are doing to put things right.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will update the House on the Laidlaw inquiry and the decisive action that we are taking in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I will inform the House of the new deal with Virgin Trains, including an enhanced service, that will begin this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dealing with all this, from the start, my approach has been to come to the House to explain the situation openly, quickly and clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is in that spirit that I make my third statement on this subject today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I turn to the Laidlaw inquiry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 3 October I announced the cancellation of the competition to run the Inter-City West Coast franchise because of the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the process run by the Department for Transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained to the House on the 15 October, I launched 2 independent inquiries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the first inquiry, led by Sam Laidlaw, to look into what happened and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing his final report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the second review, led by the Eurostar chairman Richard Brown, to focus on any lessons to be learned for future of rail franchising. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is well advanced. I expect to receive his report by the end of the year. I will publish it after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am placing a copy of Mr Laidlaw’s final report in the Library alongside a copy of my department’s response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not hide from the seriousness of his findings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make extremely uncomfortable reading for the department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They caused serious problems for bidding firms including First Group who were in no way at fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They must – and will – be acted upon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me turn to the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Laidlaw confirms much of what he first touched on in his interim report. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He finds that the department wrongly calculated the amount of risk capital bidders would have to offer to guarantee their franchise proposals against default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he says that these incorrect figures vary in ways that were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significantly, he also states for the first time that ministers made the original 14 August provisional award without being told about the flaws and after being given “inaccurate reports”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Laidlaw also confirms that if his recommendations on strengthening the organisation are acted upon quickly the department will be able to do its job correctly in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing in the report to suggest that the flaws discovered in this franchise competition existed in other procurements in the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Mr Laidlaw confirms that he has seen no evidence of bias against Virgin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also offers a clear prescription which we are already acting upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will ensure that all future franchise competitions are delivered with a clear timeline, rigorous management and the right quality assurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also create a simpler and clearer structure and governance process for rail franchise competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include the appointment of a single director general with responsibility for all rail policy and franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will ensure that we have the right mix of professional skills inside the department and, where necessary, from professional external advisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank Mr Laidlaw for carrying out such a comprehensive review to such a tight timetable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any specific personnel issues resulting from what has gone on are, and must of course remain, an issue for the Permanent Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, let me turn to the future of the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my actions, I have put the service to the passenger first. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am pleased to tell the House that my department has negotiated terms with Virgin Rail Group to allow Virgin Trains to continue running the West Coast service for up to 23 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our intention is to run a full competition for the longer term franchise to follow on from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms we have negotiated with Virgin secure continued service for passengers at the same levels they enjoy today, and in some cases better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timetable that was already agreed for December 2012 will operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today, the last of the 106 government-funded Pendelino carriages comes into service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will allow more trains and longer trains on this vital route. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That timetable includes a new hourly service between London and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to see more improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among them, the introduction of new services from London to Blackpool and Shrewsbury. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to Virgin securing the track access rights to provide these, and to our completing a value for money assessment, I would hope that both of these new services will be introduced from December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, the Laidlaw inquiry has told us that changes to the department’s governance and structure are needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are and will carry them out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have a new deal for the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been extremely serious issue for my department.  But I am determined that we learn the lessons and get on with the job we are here to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with our commitment to High Speed Two and the increase in capital spending on roads announced by my &lt;abbr title="Right Honourable"&gt;RH&lt;/abbr&gt; Friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer this week, this government is committed to improving our transport network and backing our railways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18789</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/intercity-west-coast-franchise"/>
    <title>InterCity West Coast franchise</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 October 2012 I announced to the House that following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise competition the Department for Transport was commencing negotiations with Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that negotiations have concluded successfully and that Virgin Trains will continue to operate services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After careful consideration I believe taxpayers, rail passengers and the wider rail industry will be better served by moving directly from this agreement with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to a longer term franchise on the West Coast Main Line. Doing so will provide greater certainty for passengers, minimise disruption for all stakeholders and enable us to maximise the benefits for taxpayers and West Coast passengers. For this reason the new franchise with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will be for up to 23 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce that passengers will not only experience the same levels of service they have previously enjoyed but will also benefit from improvements to previous levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition this agreement coincides with the successful completion today, on budget and ahead of schedule, of a project to deliver 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new carriages, which will see up to 28,000 extra seats provided each day, are being introduced with £1.5 billion of government support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new franchise agreement, there will also be a new hourly service between London and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This franchise will operate as a management contract, with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the government. In return &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will receive a margin of 1% on revenue. The contract also makes a provision for the department and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18642</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T17:28:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-announces-150-000-to-boost-great-british-pubs"/>
    <title>Minister announces £150,000 to boost Great British pubs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement followed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pubisthehub.org.uk/"&gt;Pub is The Hub&lt;/a&gt; ‘10 Years On’ event on 5 December 2012 where the minister was a keynote speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke about the key role pubs play in the social and economic life of many communities, often as community hubs, local service providers and a place where community relationships are formed and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to say that pubs contribute, on average, £100,000 per pub to the local economy as well as being strong sources of local employment for younger people to get involved in an entrepreneurial and innovative industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community pubs minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to announce we are giving Pub is The Hub £150,000 for their project. The government is taking decisive action to support community pubs including doubling business rate relief, which gives up to 100% discounts for small firms including pubs and postponing revaluation will also avoid local pubs facing an 11% rise in their business rates bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is on top of abolishing the last government’s cider tax, cutting red tape on live music in pubs and stopping unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price by supermarkets. We have given councils powers to offer local business rate discounts and the Community Right to Bid lets communities protect their pubs and guard against their unnecessary loss.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to see community pubs thriving everywhere and has introduced a series of measures to support them including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enabling councils to introduce local business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/contents/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt;, the department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17306</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T11:42:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T11:42:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dsa-opening-hours-christmas-and-new-year--2"/>
    <title>DSA opening hours: Christmas and New Year</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s online services will be available throughout Christmas and the New Year. You’ll be able to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/driving/learning-to-drive" title="Book and manage your theory or practical driving test"&gt;book and manage your theory or practical driving test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/dsa-online-business-service" title="Use the DSA online business service"&gt;use the &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; online business service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/driving/teaching-people-to-drive" title="Use instructor services"&gt;use instructor services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="driving-test-centres-and-customer-service-centre"&gt;Driving test centres and customer service centre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will be operating a normal service up to and including Friday 21 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Driving test centres&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Customer service centre&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;England and Wales: closed - Scotland: most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tuesday 25 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 26 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tuesday 1 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Closed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Scotland: closed - England and Wales: most centres will be open&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="last-date-to-change-or-cancel-a-driving-test"&gt;Last date to change or cancel a driving test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must give at least 3 clear working days’ notice to change your test date or cancel it, or you’ll have to pay again. Sundays and public holidays don’t count as working days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tables show the last dates you can change or cancel your test. The date will depend on where you live, and whether you’re doing it online or by phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="england-and-wales"&gt;England and Wales&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Test date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel online&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel by phone&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 22 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 30 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 3 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 4 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 5 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 6 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 7 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="scotland"&gt;Scotland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Test date&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel online&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Last date to change or cancel by phone&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 20 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday 22 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 30 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 24 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 21 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wednesday 2 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thursday 3 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday 27 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Friday 4 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturday 5 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 29 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday 28 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sunday 6 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monday 7 January&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday 31 December&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17815</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-fleet-commander-appointed-to-royal-navy"/>
    <title>New Fleet Commander appointed to Royal Navy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Philip Jones takes up the role from outgoing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/About-the-Royal-Navy/Organisation/Senior-Naval-Staff/Fleet-Commander" title="Fleet Commander and Deputy Chief of Naval Staff"&gt;Fleet Commander&lt;/a&gt; Admiral Sir George Zambellas who will continue in his NATO role, Commander Maritime Command, at Northwood in North West London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing Royal Navy personnel Vice Admiral Jones said it was an immense privilege to be invited to take up the role and that it was a proud moment for himself, his wife and three children. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m lucky to find myself taking over the Fleet Commander role at a time when there are so very many professional, energetic and, above all, committed people on the Navy Command team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A team committed to generating and supporting maritime forces operating on a front line that stretches from the South Atlantic to the northern Gulf, from the Strait of Hormuz to the Caribbean, and from the coastline of Somalia to the vehicle checkpoints of Nad ‘Ali in Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Admiral Sir George Zambellas (left) with Vice Admiral Philip Jones" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1333/FX120528002.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Admiral Sir George Zambellas (left) with Vice Admiral Philip Jones [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Keith Morgan, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Jones said that he would continue to make the strongest possible case for future investment in the Royal Navy in order to ensure the nation’s security and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incoming Fleet Commander added that the Royal Navy was held in high regard by other navies and that few other nations were able to match the range of activities carried out by the Royal Navy. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are in that place because we - more than anyone else in Defence - understand our business and we understand our environment, where the land, sea and air all meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And while we understand the need to seek continuous improvement, we are smart enough to try and do it in manageable steps. That is key to our success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Jones also thanked Admiral Zambellas for leaving a powerful legacy which is operationally-focused and hungry to succeed in all areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18662</id>
    <published>2012-12-05T09:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-engineers-squadron-receives-firmin-sword-of-peace"/>
    <title>Royal Engineers squadron receives Firmin Sword of Peace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lord Mayor of Nottingham, Councillor Leon Unczur, hosted a civic reception at Nottingham Council House in the centre of the city to formally thank the soldiers for their work in the UK and Afghanistan and to present them with their Op HERRICK campaign medals. The squadron was also awarded the Firmin Sword of Peace for its work carried out in Cumbria in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based at Chetwynd Barracks in Chilwell, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/units/866.aspx" title="64 Works Group Royal Engineers"&gt;64 Works Group Royal Engineers&lt;/a&gt; (64 Wks Gp RE) is one of five groups that, together, form &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/units/12182.aspx" title="170 (Infrastructure Support) Engineer Group"&gt;170 (Infrastructure Support) Engineer Group&lt;/a&gt;. Comprising chartered engineers, garrison engineers and clerks of works, the soldiers returned home from Afghanistan in late November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in Camp Bastion and at forward operating bases across Helmand province, it has been a busy tour for 64 Wks Gp RE that saw them planning, developing and maintaining all infrastructure support to UK forces, including the airport, power networks and life support such as kitchens, hospitals and ablutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lieutenant Colonel Tony Tait holds the Firmin Sword of Peace" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1347/LAND-2012-211-03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Tony Tait holds the Firmin Sword of Peace, presented to 64 Works Group for work carried out during the Cumbria floods in 2009 [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another important part of the team’s work was to develop the Afghans’ own expertise so that they can plan, build and maintain their own infrastructure. A team from 64 Wks Gp RE also worked with the Provincial Reconstruction Team based at Lashkar Gah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team worked with the Afghanistan line ministries supporting and managing large and small infrastructure projects. Delivered by Afghan construction companies the work centred on highways, irrigation canals, government buildings, prisons and police training centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Tony Tait, the Commanding Officer of 64 Wks Gp RE, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can look back on our time in Afghanistan with an immense sense of pride and achievement; as an organisation we really have delivered a significant amount in a relatively short timeframe and made a difference not only to our soldiers, sailors and airmen, but also the people and institutions of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This latter aspect is particularly important, and through work with the Provincial Reconstruction Team we have delivered genuine lasting infrastructure and, more importantly, an embryonic and sustainable engineering capability for the Helmand regional government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A plate of special medals awarded to the children" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1348/LAND-2012-211-04.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A plate of special medals awarded to the children of 64 Works Group Royal Engineers for their good behaviour during the soldiers' deployment [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Nottingham reception also saw 64 Wks Gp RE awarded the prestigious humanitarian award the Firmin Sword of Peace in recognition of their work to provide a temporary footbridge across the River Derwent in Workington, Cumbria, following the floods of 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 19 November 2009, unprecedented rainfall in Cumbria resulted in the rivers Cocker and Derwent flooding much of central Cockermouth. The next day, 20 November, tragedy struck when PC Bill Barker was swept to his death as the bridge at which he was stationed collapsed beneath him. Workington’s other bridges also collapsed or were rendered unusable, leaving Workington a geographically-divided community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the request of the civilian authorities the military were mobilised in order to provide a rapid response. Coordinated by the regional brigade for North West England, 42 (North West) Brigade, it involved 64 Wks Gp RE who designed the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other Army units which deployed soldiers in various numbers included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Armoured Engineer Squadron, part of 22 Engineer Regiment, based in Tidworth &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;32 Signal Regiment, based in Glasgow &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;27 Transport Regiment RLC, based in Aldershot &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9 Supply Regiment RLC, based in Hullavington &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Military Police &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;63 Medical Squadron, based in Preston &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Headquarters 42 (North West) Brigade, based in Preston &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4th Battalion The Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment, North West England’s TA infantry battalion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In just under two weeks from the first Army engineer arriving on site, the bridge and its abutments had been designed, resourced and constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Children receive specially-commissioned medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1349/LAND-2012-211-06.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Children receive specially-commissioned medals in Royal Engineers colours from Lieutenant Colonel Tony Tait and Councillor Leon Unczur [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was no mean feat; a complex engineering task completed against the clock and in the full public glare of both the media and the local community. The design work, logistics and construction effort, plus the wider stakeholder coordination to achieve this, was significant and should not be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect that this bridge had on the community of Workington was profound. It did much more than reconnect a divided community; it lessened the economic impact on the town, enabled businesses and schools to function and negated an otherwise long car journey to get across the river. The bridge was named the Barker Crossing after PC Bill Barker and remained in use until February 2011 when, under the control of 64 Wks Gp RE, it was deconstructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Firmin Sword of Peace citation read: 64 Works Group Royal Engineers displayed the highest professional standards in adversity and upheld the finest traditions and values expected of the British Army. It endeavoured tirelessly to provide support where it was needed most to the community of Workington and, in doing so, contributed to humanitarian activities and established friendly relations within a home community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17743</id>
    <published>2012-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/420-million-to-support-local-infrastructure--2"/>
    <title>£420 million to support local infrastructure</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This news article has moved to a new location:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/420-million-to-support-local-infrastructure"&gt;£420 million to support local infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17669</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:21:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T14:21:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/full-speed-ahead-as-government-appoints-new-director-general-to-oversee-hs2--2"/>
    <title>Full speed ahead as government appoints new Director General to oversee HS2</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government’s commitment to delivering a new national high speed rail network has been underlined by the appointment of a new Director General to oversee the crucial project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/government/people/david-prout"&gt;David Prout&lt;/a&gt;, currently a Director General at the Department of Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;), will join the Department for Transport (DfT) in the New Year in a newly-created post taking charge of the delivery of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a national high speed rail network linking London, Birmingham, Manchester, Sheffield, Leeds, the East Midlands, with each other and cities beyond it, to drive regional growth, improve connectivity and create extra space and capacity on our railways and roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his current role, David Prout has been at &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; since 2009, with responsibility for localism, and additional responsibility as deputy for &lt;a href="/government/people/bob-kerslake"&gt;Sir Bob Kerslake&lt;/a&gt; given the latter’s role as Head of the Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/government/people/philip-rutnam"&gt;Philip Rutnam, DfT Permanent Secretary&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a hugely important programme for the future of the UK. I am very pleased that David Prout will be taking charge at such an exciting time. He will be leading a team which is already hard at work delivering this project, as well as liaising closely with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, as we work together to introduce the legislation into Parliament on time next year that will make &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Prout said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Making &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; a reality is absolutely crucial to our country’s future prosperity and I am very pleased to have been asked to take leadership of this much-needed programme at this time. I look forward to helping to take the project through Parliament and continuing to demonstrate the very real need for more capacity for people and freight on our railways, which will help make Britain a more prosperous and less congested country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prior to his current role at &lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;, David was Executive Director for Planning and Borough Development at the Royal Borough of Kensington and Chelsea. Before that he was Director of Local Government Policy in the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David has held a range of high profile civil service positions including Principal Private Secretary to the Deputy Prime Minister in the Department for the Environment, Transport and the Regions, Cabinet Office and Office of the Deputy Prime Minister.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From 1995 to 1998 David was environment attaché at the UK Permanent Representation to the European Union in Brussels. Prior to that he held a variety of posts in the Department of the Environment. He also worked in the planning department of Westminster City Council from 1990 to 1993 and for the Victorian Society from 1991 to 1993.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
