<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50188</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali"/>
    <title>UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister made his comments following the arrest late on 10 December of Malian Prime Minister Diarra in Bamako by armed men on behalf of the military junta and the subsequent forced resignation of the Prime Minister and his Cabinet earlier today. Mr Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the latest events in Bamako, and particularly by the intervention of the Malian military junta which has forced the resignation today of Prime Minister Diarra and his Cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The United Kingdom calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali. The rapid appointment of a new government of national unity to take forward the political roadmap towards democratic elections and the reunification of Mali is critical to further progress. These events underline the need for coordinated international action, particularly with the United Nations, the African Union and ECOWAS, to achieve stability in Mali.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17286</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T23:02:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T23:02:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hospital-leaders-get-taste-of-military-medicine"/>
    <title>Hospital leaders get taste of military medicine</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/10566.aspx" title="16 Medical Regiment"&gt;16 Medical Regiment&lt;/a&gt; has a close relationship with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.colchesterhospital.nhs.uk/" title="Colchester Hospital University NHS Foundation Trust"&gt;Colchester Hospital University &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; Foundation Trust&lt;/a&gt;, with soldiers carrying out work placements and training at the Trust’s hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A delegation from the Trust, including its chair, Dr Sally Irvine, recently visited Colchester’s Merville Barracks to get an insight into the operational skills and working environment of military medics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16 Medical Regiment provides the Airborne Surgical Group (&lt;abbr title="Airborne Surgical Group"&gt;ABSG&lt;/abbr&gt;) to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/12409.aspx" title="16 Air Assault Brigade"&gt;16 Air Assault Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, which maintains a force ready to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice to do anything from disaster relief to war-fighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Airborne Surgical Group"&gt;ABSG&lt;/abbr&gt; provides accident and emergency, X-ray, surgical and intensive treatment facilities and is manned by anaesthetists, surgeons and other specialist medics, many of whom are parachute-qualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also deploy with a primary healthcare node, which includes a &lt;abbr title="General Practitioner"&gt;GP&lt;/abbr&gt; and dentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Steven Tracey, Commanding Officer of 16 Medical Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We enjoy an excellent relationship with the Trust, which is of mutual benefit. Through clinical placements at Colchester hospitals our men and women are able to keep their skills sharp and stay up to date with &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; best practice while sharing their operational experience with hospital staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Staff Sergeant Dean Cullen briefs Sir John Ashworth, Julie Firth and Dr Sally Irvine" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1254/HQ49EX20120450063g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Staff Sergeant Dean Cullen briefs Sir John Ashworth, Julie Firth and Dr Sally Irvine on the operational skills and working environment of military medics [Picture: Corporal Gabriel Moreno, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From recent deployments to Afghanistan and preparing for the rapid response role, our medics are trained and experienced at operating - in all senses of the word - in austere and hostile conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope that showing the Trust the facilities we are used to will give a better idea of the skills and quality of the soldiers working at their hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Irvine said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Trust and the Garrison are probably the two biggest employers in Colchester and we - and our patients - both benefit from the close working relationship we continue to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Trust has developed a number of collaborative arrangements to provide services to soldiers and their families and to integrate garrison medical staff into service provision at our organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trust delegation also visited the barrack’s medical facilities, which include a reception station with a 10-bed ward, dental surgery and primary healthcare facilities, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/NHSEngland/Militaryhealthcare/rehabilitationservices/Pages/Rehabilitation.aspx" title="NHS Rehabilitation Services"&gt;Regional Rehabilitation Unit&lt;/a&gt;, which provides physiotherapy and rehabilitation courses to help soldiers overcome injuries, and the regional headquarters of the Army Primary Healthcare Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit also took in Chavasse &lt;abbr title="Victoria Cross"&gt;VC&lt;/abbr&gt; House which gives wounded, injured and sick soldiers additional care and support to help them successfully return to duties or transition into civilian life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17281</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T23:01:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T23:01:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-naval-survey-ship-discovers-sunken-dhows"/>
    <title>Royal Naval survey ship discovers sunken dhows</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Making use of its new hi-tech, smaller motor launch, the Plymouth-based ship discovered two sunken dhows in one of the world’s busiest ports at the beginning of a nine-month deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spitfire, the new survey motor boat, can be sent off independently to gather data at the same time as the mother ship - effectively doubling the ship’s capacity to chart the seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After trials in the UK and around Souda Bay in Crete, the first real test of Spitfire came off Dubai with two days of surveying work in tandem with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Ice-Patrol-and-Survey-Ships/HMS-Enterprise" title="HMS Enterprise"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A three-dimensional graphical representation of a sunken dhow" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1251/Enterprise_3D_Dhow_Wreck_2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A three-dimensional graphical representation of a sunken dhow created by the computer systems and software on board &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The net result from the duo’s scanning using their multibeam sonars were the two previously undiscovered wrecks, each about 20 metres long and rising about five metres from the seabed of the harbour, produced in impressive &lt;abbr title="two-dimensional"&gt;2D&lt;/abbr&gt;/&lt;abbr title="three-dimensional"&gt;3D&lt;/abbr&gt; graphic representations courtesy of the powerful computer systems and software aboard &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the wrecks now surveyed, the data has been passed on to the Dubai Ports Authority and other mariners have been alerted to the dhows’ presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise, Commander Derek Rae, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A three-dimensional graphical representation of a sunken dhow" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1252/Enterprise_3D_Dhow_Wreckg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A three-dimensional graphical representation of a sunken dhow discovered by &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise in Port Rashid Harbour [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The level of detail visible on the wrecks shows the impressive capability of the new survey motor boat, and the opportunity afforded to us by the local authorities in Dubai to conduct this survey training has been invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The outcome of the training has been mutually beneficial and we are delighted to have been of assistance to other mariners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship will be carrying out survey work in the Middle East until May next year, building on the successes of sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Ice-Patrol-and-Survey-Ships/HMS-Echo" title="HMS Echo"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Echo&lt;/a&gt; which discovered numerous wrecks and obstacles during a 19-month deployment to the same region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as helping to update some of the 3,300-plus &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukho.gov.uk/onlinecatalogue/" title="Admiralty Digital Catalogue"&gt;Admiralty Charts&lt;/a&gt; which are used by many of the world’s seafarers (including the Royal Navy), &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Enterprise will also support the wider international naval effort to prevent piracy and other criminal activities in the Indian Ocean and its environs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50187</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:55:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reservists-take-centre-stage"/>
    <title>Reservists take centre stage</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event, which for the first time had Regular and Reserves Army personnel competing side by side, was hosted by reservist unit the Royal Yeomanry, and took place at Ash Ranges in Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, competitions such as this would be organised by a regular unit but with reservists playing an ever-increasing role in military activity, the task was allocated to the Royal Yeomanry to demonstrate their organisational skills and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 teams of 8 soldiers from across the Greater London area competed in several shooting events over the 2 days. Each of the events required the competitors to display skills essential in operational shooting: fitness, accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall winners of the competition were 106 (Yeomanry) Regiment Royal Artillery, London’s reservist gunners, based in Grove Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Rob Hewitt, their team leader, was thrilled with the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the culmination of hard work and training. It’s required dedication from all the team members, with a mix of old and new soldiers, and I’m thrilled to be returning home with the trophy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reservists are clearly in the limelight at the moment, as last week Foreign Secretary William Hague publicly praised an exercise which took place at Catterick Garrison which aimed to show employers the benefits of recruiting reservists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held by the MOD and support services provider Carillion. The exercise saw more than 120 of Carillion’s staff, including existing reservists, former members of the Armed Forces and those considering signing up with the Army Reserves for the first time, take part in a series of focus group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK Armed Forces are the envy of the world and the Government is fully committed to supporting them as they adapt to more complex and demanding needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reservists will play an increasingly important role in this and it is therefore vital that employers with reservists realise this and play their part to the full by offering the necessary flexibility and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A reservist alongside a Regular Army colleague" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/4393/120302LtPatStartandCplKelly2RIFLESonoperations.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Rifles reservist serves alongside a Regular Army colleague on operations in Helmand province (library image) 
[Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD launched a consultation last month inviting employers like Carillion to give their opinions on how the MOD and employers of reservists can work together to benefit from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD has committed to changing the way the Reserves work and is looking to increase the strength of the Reserve Forces by 50 per cent. Events like this will also help companies like Carillion understand how they can support their reservists and whether employment terms are flexible enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a reservist, regular or family member of a reservist? Then we want to hear from you. The MOD is considering what changes are required to the Reserve Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the right offer to attract and retain individuals in the Reserves?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right relationship with the civilian employers of reservists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right support for reservists and their families across our communities?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/FutureReserves2020Consultation.htm"&gt;Read up on the proposals in the FR20 Consultation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those wishing to join the Army Reserves as soldiers, the eligible joining age is 17-and-a-half  to 43. To find out more, telephone 0845 600 8080 or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.armyjobs.mod.uk/"&gt;www.armyjobs.mod.uk&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48782</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T22:40:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T22:40:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/light-dragoons-receive-afghanistan-medals"/>
    <title>Light Dragoons receive Afghanistan medals</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The medal parade was the last in a series of events marking the end off the Regiment’s deployment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Colonel of the Regiment, Major General Andrew Stewart, presented the campaign medals to the soldiers who have conducted homecoming parades in recent weeks in Barnsley, Newcastle and Dereham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicknamed ‘England’s Northern Cavalry’ this was the Regiment’s fourth tour of Afghanistan, having had Squadrons deployed in 2006, 2007 and 2009. Although a very successful tour, it was not without sacrifice and The Light Dragoons will always remember all those who died including Sergeant Lee Davidson who was Killed in Action on 9 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/26876.aspx" title="The Light Dragoons"&gt;The Light Dragoons&lt;/a&gt; have undertaken a number of different roles in Afghanistan. The soldiers from A Squadron acted as the eyes and ears of the Brigade. They also provided route security for convoys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D Squadron delivered training and mentoring support to the Afghan National Police Force and were later augmented by members of A Squadron. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Light Dragoons march through Dereham" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2654/16x-2012-119-0070g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The streets of Dereham came to a standstill on Wednesday 5 December as residents and businesses welcomed members of The Light Dragoons home from Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their fellow Light Dragoons sister unit, B Squadron, were The Brigade Reconnaissance Force (&lt;abbr title="Brigade Reconnaissance Force"&gt;BRF&lt;/abbr&gt;) who acted on military intelligence to remove key insurgency equipment and personnel from the area of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trooper Phil Burt and Sergeant Richardson who were part of the &lt;abbr title="Brigade Reconnaissance Force"&gt;BRF&lt;/abbr&gt; discovered a 50 calibre machine gun during one of their operations. Sgt Richardson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were preparing to clear a series of compounds when we saw a disturbance on the ground. The machine gun, nicknamed a Sushka, was covered with a sheet in a trench. It had been well maintained and had a box of ammo with it, so for us it was a great find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their six-month tour The Light Dragoons carried out some 248 operations, searched 1,700 Afghan compounds and discovered over three tonnes of Homemade Explosives and significant quantities of other bomb making equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the UK, C Squadron was the Rear Operations Group, ensuring that the families remaining behind were given the very best welfare support and ensuring that individual soldiers were fully prepared to deploy if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Large crowds in Derehm welcome The Light Dragoons " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2655/16x-2012-119-0013g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Large crowds, including family and friends of many of those marching, lined the route [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week the Regiment brought Central Norfolk to a standstill when thousands of people gathered on the streets of Dereham to welcome them home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shops closed and business came to a stand still as crowds, six people deep in places, waved flags and cheered as the proud soldiers marched through the streets. The Light Dragoons have been based in Swanton Morley near Dereham for the past 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the parade the Regiment attended a thanksgiving service at St Nicholas Church. Trooper Craig Hoe from Hull said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have had wonderful support at all of our homecoming parades. It’s great to know we have such support from the local community here where we are based and also back home in our recruiting areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The medal parade was also great; it has to the next best thing after my Pass Off Parade. I’m now looking forward to having some time off and enjoying some of my mam’s cooking. I’ve really missed that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17012</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T19:05:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T19:05:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/york-sends-christmas-wishes-to-troops-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>York sends Christmas wishes to troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The greetings card, produced by the Lord Mayor and the civic party, offers the public the chance to show their support for local soldiers who are on duty in Afghanistan, and to wish them a Merry Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be available for people to sign on Wednesday, 28 November, from 1000hrs to 1200hrs in the Mansion House. It will also be available for signatures in the reception area of the Guildhall on Wednesday afternoon, Thursday afternoon, and on Friday, 30 November, from 0900hrs to 1700hrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lord Mayor of York, Councillor Keith Hyman, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am glad that the residents of York have the chance to show their support and gratitude for the Armed Forces that are currently stationed in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;York has been home to the Army since AD 71, when the first garrison was established in the city, so the city has always held a strong bond with the Army. The card will be sent to Afghanistan to the soldiers from 2 Signal Regiment based in York, and other local regiments. I am delighted we can help them celebrate Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Officer Commanding 2nd Signal Regiment Rear Operations Group, Major Tony Barry, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are all really proud of how soldiers are performing on Operation HERRICK in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a caring initiative by the City of York and its people, and it will boost morale for the soldiers during the festive season when they will be missing their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2nd Signal Regiment is deployed in Afghanistan as part of 4th Mechanized Brigade who took over control of Task Force Helmand in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signallers are providing secure communications, computers, video-conferencing and telephones to military units throughout Helmand province, as well as having a force protection role in the country’s capital, Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-news"&gt;Related News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/EquipmentAndLogistics/ServiceCharitiesTheBestWayToSupportHmForcesThisChristmas.htm" title="Read the full story"&gt;Service charities the best way to support HM Forces this Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/EquipmentAndLogistics/GenerousPublicUrgedThinkTwiceBeforeSendingUnsolicitedChristmasGiftsToTroops.htm" title="Read the full story"&gt;Generous public urged: think twice before sending unsolicited Christmas gifts to troops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/PeopleInDefence/ModBrewsUpForSsafaForcesHelp.htm" title="Read the full story"&gt;MOD brews up for SSAFA Forces Help&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16671</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-defence-secretary-on-delivering-value-for-money-and-innovation-in-defence"/>
    <title>The Defence Secretary on delivering value for money and innovation in Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking yesterday, Mr Hammond used his speech to talk about how, over the last two-and-a-half years, the Department has set about reforming the way Defence is managed in order to deliver improved efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began by recapping the scale of the reform challenge faced by Defence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overheated equipment programme this government inherited was a symptom of a much deeper malaise that was fundamentally about the way in which the Department operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without fundamental reform in the way the budget is managed, the way decisions are taken, and how Defence is run, the same problems will rematerialise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two-and-a-half years of the transformation project, the Defence Secretary said we have started to see the benefits of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if we want them to be sustained, we need to ensure that the changes we are making in how Defence is managed become engrained in its culture so that budgetary discipline becomes the supporting foundation of everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Hammond said that while Defence needed a solid financial foundation, it was the people that really mattered and made the difference, and therefore an attractive employment package to attract and keep the best was needed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have to ensure that we can compete to attract them. And it has been 40 years since the current package of terms and conditions was last fully updated. In the meantime it has been adapted and modified on an ad-hoc basis. So that now, it is costly, complex, impenetrable and inflexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In many ways, it fails to meet the requirements of today’s Service personnel, or to reflect the needs of modern family life. So we need to modernise the offer we make to our people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that a new employment model was needed and this would need to be flexible to meet the varying and individual needs of Service personnel: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no identikit soldier, sailor or airman. Each one is an individual, with different needs at different points in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added that the package needs to be affordable and sustainable in the long-term and attractive to Service personnel and fair to the taxpayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we look at the structure of pay and allowances it will be to make it more flexible and more responsive to individual needs as well as to better reflect the priorities of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But, within an envelope that is broadly cost-neutral overall, designed to deliver better value to the individual at the same broad cost to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that this ‘New Employment Model’, or NEM, isn’t a single project at all but a number of distinct workstrands addressing different challenges, and it is not about overnight transformation but will be a process out to 2020 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the NEM will be a measured shift in the nature of the offer: towards a greater emphasis on individual value, personal choice and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring greater value to the individual through more flexible tailoring of the complex package that makes up Armed Forces remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And more stability to Service families through fewer moves, more opportunities for employment of the partners, and greater opportunities for home ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On housing, Mr Hammond said that, in a 22-year career, as currently structured, a typical Service person could expect to be asked to move 10 or more times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want this to change. As we bring the British Army back from Germany we want to offer more stability and in doing so make it possible for families to set down roots as civilian families do. Greatly reducing the need for family moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, the Defence Secretary said we should not underestimate the scale of what is still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real, long-term challenge is to change behaviours, align incentives and shift the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So that the resource discipline that we have imposed feeds through into sustainable, bottom-up efficiency gain, not reduction in output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In other words, the challenge is now to improve the productivity of every part of the Defence organisation. Rejecting the notion that a given percentage cut in the Defence Budget must inevitably mean a similar percentage cut in our military capability. That is the key task for 2013 for the leadership of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;None of us is in any doubt about the scale of that task, but neither do we doubt its centrality to everything we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17293</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T16:10:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:10:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/thanksgiving-service-for-tankies-return-from-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Thanksgiving service for Tankies' return from Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the service in Bury St Edmunds Cathedral, the soldiers marched into the centre of the market town where they were awarded their Op HERRICK campaign medals by the Lord-Lieutenant of Suffolk, Lord Tollemache. He was joined by the Mayor of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.stedmundsbury.gov.uk/" title="St Edmundsbury Borough Council"&gt;St Edmundsbury&lt;/a&gt;, Councillor Tim Marks, and Brigadier Harry Nickerson, Commander of 49 (East) Brigade, who also presented medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Marks said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an honour to welcome 1st Royal Tank Regiment to the town and I am delighted to have the opportunity to express appreciation of their service to us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bury St Edmunds has a historic and close relationship with the Armed Forces, and I hope the troops recognise the warmth of our welcome and of our gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 230 soldiers from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/26877.aspx" title="The 1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1 RTR&lt;/a&gt;, known as the ‘Tankies’, based at RAF Honington, have deployed to Afghanistan over the last ten months in a variety of roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;G Squadron was split into four 20-man troops and provided protected mobility to the infantry including 1st Battalion The Royal Anglian Regiment. Using the well-armoured Mastiff the troops moved the infantry between defensive positions and provided fire support to soldiers fighting on foot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The service of thanksgiving in Bury St Edmunds Cathedral" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1258/20121129rtr03_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The service of thanksgiving in Bury St Edmunds Cathedral, led by the Very Reverend Dr Frances Ward [Picture: Corporal Gabriel Moreno, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The regimental headquarters and other soldiers filled a number of positions throughout Helmand province, from support roles in Camp Bastion to key staff roles in the Brigade Headquarters. Other roles included training the Afghan Local Police and counter-improvised explosive device dog handlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H Squadron spent three months in Afghanistan as part of the reception, staging, onward movement and integration (RSOI) team for Operation HERRICK 16. RSOI is mandatory training and the final stage of a six-month-long training package to ensure that soldiers have the most up-to-date tactics, techniques, procedures and intelligence at their disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also provides a time for initial acclimatisation to allow the body to adapt to the harsh climate of Afghanistan, reducing the impact of heat on the body’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H Squadron returned in early June 2012 and handed the RSOI role over to D Squadron who deployed in August to do the same thing for Operation HERRICK 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H Squadron HQ then redeployed for a three-month tour to Cyprus to head up the decompression team. All troops returning from theatre spend 24 hours in Cyprus - a period of ‘decompression’ which provides a pause to allow the important step-change from Afghanistan’s operational tempo to that of returning to home life in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lord Tollemache presents a soldier with a medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1259/20121129rtr02_960x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Lord-Lieutenant of Suffolk, Lord Tollemache, presents a soldier of the 1st Royal Tank Regiment with a medal [Picture: Corporal Gabriel Moreno, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Alex Holloway was joined on the parade by his brother, Captain Will Holloway. Captain Will Holloway was the second-in-command of H Squadron, whilst his brother was based in the Brigade Headquarters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was awesome to see so many people on parade,” said Captain Alex Holloway. “It was great to be on parade, not just as a regiment but also with my brother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first time the brothers had deployed at the same time and they are now looking forward to spending Christmas at home with their family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Corporal Tony Knowles, who served with G Squadron, said his first tour was an eye-opener and he was now looking forward to spending time with his family, including his five-month-old daughter, Amber:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The turnout for the parade has been great,” he said. “It’s good to see so many people come out and make an effort to support us, especially in this cold weather. All the guys appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 RTR’s Commanding Officer, Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Britton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud of what the regiment has achieved. The soldiers make many sacrifices to fulfil their role and recognition of that by those at home is deeply appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are extremely grateful for all the support that the local community has shown us over this period and very much appreciate St Edmundsbury Cathedral and St Edmunds Borough Council marking our return with this event. It means a great deal to the soldiers and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-news"&gt;Related News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/HistoryAndHonour/1stRoyalTankRegimentTakesPartInHomecomingParadeInGlasgow.htm" title="Read the full story"&gt;1st Royal Tank Regiment takes part in homecoming parade in Glasgow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/HistoryAndHonour/TankiesHomeFromHelmand.htm" title="Read the full story"&gt;Tankies home from Helmand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50138</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:07:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:07:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region"/>
    <title>FCO Minister shows continued UK support to Libyan people on trip to region</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whilst in Libya the Minister will offer continued support to the Libyan people as they build a new future after Qadhafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tripoli, Mr Burt said:          &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be back in Libya for the third time in twelve months. Since my last visit in April, Libya has held incredibly successful elections, convened a new General National Congress and formed a new Government. I congratulate President Magarief, Prime Minister Zeidan and the Libyan people on these significant achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Government faces many challenges: improving security across Libya, particularly taking steps to ensure that armed groups are reintegrated into society, respect government decisions and act within the law; strengthening the justice system to ensure the transfer of all detainees to the custody of the state, where they must be held in accordance with international standards; delivering improved public services to its people; and reforming and revitalising the economy to provide better jobs and opportunities for ordinary Libyans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These challenges are significant but the British Government will continue to support Libya throughout its transition. I am meeting the Deputy Prime Ministers and Ministers for Justice and Finance to discuss how the UK can build on its current work to offer even greater assistance to the Libyan Government. I am also meeting a delegation of politicians, business leaders and civil society activists from Benghazi to reiterate our ongoing commitment to the East of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During these meetings I will emphasise the importance of securing justice for the victims of the Qadhafi regime in the UK, and I look forward to the continued cooperation of the Libyan authorities in resolving these outstanding legacy cases.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the Minister &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/alistairburtfco" title="@AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinlibya.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Libya"&gt;British Embassy in Libya website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50142</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:05:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:05:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk"/>
    <title>Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;From this Thursday the Foreign Office is publishing its news, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new web address is www.gov.uk/fco. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="topics-and-policies"&gt;Topics and policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FCO information will be in the “Inside Government” section on GOV.UK, alongside information from other government departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An advantage of being on gov.uk is that you can now see information from multiple government departments grouped by topics or polices. The FCO’s policies are listed under foreign affairs and Europe but we’ve also contributed policies to topics like ‘Establishing stability in Afghanistan’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each policy you can see a list of all the related announcements, consultations and publications in one list, called ‘activity’. This makes it easy for you to track what is happening on the policies that interest you, for example all government activity that relates to, ‘Working for peace and long-term stability in the Middle East and North Africa’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="news-and-speeches"&gt;News and Speeches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our news and speeches will appear under Announcements. You can search by department or by topic. You can subscribe to email alerts or set up your own RSS feed. Our embassies and high commissions will continue to publish their own local news on their websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our move to GOV.UK is only part of what we’re doing to improve our presence online. Later this month we will also be publishing the FCO’s Digital Strategy setting out how we plan to use digital in our service delivery and broader diplomatic work. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17072</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T13:12:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T13:12:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navys-847-squadron-returns-from-usa-trained-and-ready-to-fight"/>
    <title>Royal Navy's 847 Squadron returns from USA trained and ready to fight</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why did &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/847" title="847 Naval Air Squadron"&gt;847 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; go all the way to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cnic.navy.mil/elcentro/index.htm" title="US Naval Air Facility El Centro"&gt;US Naval Air Facility at El Centro&lt;/a&gt; in California? Well, it replicates many of the climatic and geographical features that the squadron will encounter in Helmand province, Afghanistan, and provides excellent value in terms of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like El Centro, the base at Camp Bastion is high above sea level and the air can be extremely hot and dusty in the summer and also extremely cold when operating in the mountainous regions in the winter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The locality in which the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk9" title="Lynx Mk9A"&gt;Lynx Mk9A helicopter&lt;/a&gt; will be operating will no doubt challenge both aircrew and ground crew alike, from the battle-hardened helicopter instructors to, in particular, the inexperienced aviators and engineers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Centro also provided easy access to a number of outstanding firing ranges, unlike anything available in the UK, where the air door gunners were able to hone their airborne gunnery skills with the 0.5-inch (12.7mm) M3M Browning machine gun, a weapon that has a long range, very good accuracy, and uses a variety of multi-role ammunition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Corporal Rob Hughes" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1222/CH120060033g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Corporal Rob Hughes mans a 12.7mm M3M Browning machine gun fitted to a Lynx Mk9A helicopter from 847 Naval Air Squadron during a gunnery shoot on the ranges surrounding the US Naval Air Facility at El Centro [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The squadron also managed to squeeze in some mutual training with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/45-Commando" title="45 Commando Royal Marines"&gt;45 Commando Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; who were also conducting pre-deployment training at the base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was not all about work. A very welcome fringe benefit of operating at El Centro is its close proximity to San Diego which proved to be an excellent run ashore and enabled all to recharge some very weary batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning the aircraft and support equipment to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Air-Stations/RNAS-Yeovilton" title="Royal Naval Air Station Yeovilton"&gt;Royal Naval Air Station Yeovilton&lt;/a&gt; proved to be a challenge for the squadron engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fitting all four aircraft into the hold of the Antonov 124 looked to be an extremely difficult and daunting task, but with considerable precision and skill they managed to gently manoeuvre their treasured aircraft into the available space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lynx Mk9A helicopters being loaded onto a Russian Antonov 124 cargo plane" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1223/CH1200630177g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Navy Lynx Mk9A helicopters from 847 Naval Air Squadron being loaded onto a Russian Antonov 124 cargo plane for transportation back to the United Kingdom [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Mez Merrill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Spence, a Senior Pilot in 847 Naval Air Squadron, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The training in the USA has now provided the squadron with the essential fighting skills required when they deploy to Afghanistan in January 2013 and we have all appreciated the quality of the training that El Centro provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The challenging conditions at the base tested many of the Junglies’ skills and, from an aircrew perspective, were able to understand how they and their aircraft performed in the intense hot and dusty environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/49050</id>
    <published>2010-06-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-06-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-are-first-to-use-new-sharpshooter-rifle-in-helmand"/>
    <title>Royal Marines are first to use new Sharpshooter rifle in Helmand</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Sharpshooter rifle fires a 7.62mm round and enhances accuracy of engagement during longer-range firefights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sharpshooter’s considerable range takes it into the realm of sniper territory, but it requires far less training, being more similar to the standard service rifle than the highly-specialised weapons used by those in the sniper profession:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Marine Sergeant Baz Evans of 40 Commando said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have fired over 1,000 rounds on the rifle in training; accurately hitting targets over 800 metres away. The new Sharpshooter rifle provides quick and accurate fire, with the flexibility of using it in the assault rifle role as well. It’s hoofing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 400 of the semi-automatic L129A1 Sharpshooter rifles have been bought as an Urgent Operational Requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sharpshooter complements the already potent range of weapons used by our forces in Afghanistan, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA80 A2 assault rifles, which fire 5.56mm rounds; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light Machine Guns, which fire 5.56mm rounds; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General Purpose Machine Guns, which fire 7.62mm bullets; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Combat Shotgun, which fires 12-gauge shells; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Sniper System, which fires 8.59mm bullets; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Javelin Weapons System - the integrated fire-and-forget missile system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colonel Peter Warden, Light Weapons, Photographic and Batteries Team Leader at Defence Equipment and Support, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Sharpshooter rifle is very capable and has been bought to fulfil a specific role on the front line in Afghanistan. It is a versatile weapon which will give our units a new dimension to their armoury. It will complement the SA80 A2 by adding to the weapons available to commanders on the ground. The Sharpshooter’s capabilities are also complementary to the current Sniper System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/49044</id>
    <published>2010-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rafs-reaper-logs-10-000-hours-over-afghanistan"/>
    <title>RAF's Reaper logs 10,000 hours over Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK Reaper Remotely Piloted Air System (RPAS) has been deployed to Afghanistan since October 2007 and provides a persistent, armed intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance (ISR) capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since November 2009, Reaper has been supporting operations 24-hours-a-day and more Reaper Remotely Piloted Aircraft are planned to be delivered later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RPAS is an integral part of the UK’s air power capability. Procured to meet an urgent operational requirement, Reaper is the only RPAS currently in service with the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Baz North, Assistant Chief of the Air Staff, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;10,000 hours in direct support of operations is a significant milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our experience of operating RPAS has confirmed that they have unique capabilities that complement those of traditional combat and ISR platforms; maximum effect is achieved by employing them in a mixed grouping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This network-enabled force has delivered a comprehensive combat ISTAR [Intelligence, Surveillance, Target Acquisition and Reconnaissance] capability that provides assured intelligence and situational awareness across the full range of operating environments, through the employment and integration of air, space and cyber systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaper is flown by 39 Squadron via satellite from a UK operations facility at Creech Air Force Base in the Nevada desert, and provides a range of ISR products to troops on the ground and operational headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its primary role is ISR but from May 2008 the system has been armed with Hellfire missiles and laser-guided bombs to enable it to better meet the requirements of ground commanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of engagement used for Reaper weapon releases are no different to those used for manned combat aircraft; the weapons are all precision-guided, and every effort is made to ensure the risk of collateral damage and civilian casualties is minimised, including deciding not to release a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Jules Ball, Officer Commanding 39 Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The squadron’s personnel, from pilots to imagery analysts and support teams, are motivated and dedicated to supporting all our coalition forces and the people of Afghanistan; everyone has played a significant part in the delivery of this landmark achievement. It’s absolutely clear that the Reaper plays a vital role in delivering Air’s contribution to operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our involvement has increased steadily since the MQ-9 Reaper’s introduction into the RAF inventory. In fact, in the last 12 months alone, 39 Squadron has more than doubled its operational flying output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By supporting coalition forces every minute of every day, there’s no doubt that this cutting-edge capability is saving lives and making a difference to those in danger in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was first published in RAF News, Voice of the Royal Air Force, on 7 May 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48339</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:29:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:29:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-backs-new-rough-sleeping-helpline"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk backs new rough sleeping helpline</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone looking to help rough sleepers this winter should contact a new service to get them long-term support, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke at the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt;, a new national hotline and website service that connects rough sleepers with the local help and advice they need to get off the streets and get their lives back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="StreetLink poster" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2025/streetlink_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said that while many want to help the people they see sleeping rough, they don’t know what to do. So the government has supported homelessness charities Homeless Link and Broadway to develop this new service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that StreetLink offers concerned members of the public a better option than handing out money or food, by directing rough sleepers to the help they need, and providing them with a “hand up, not a hand out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this service, the public can now turn their concern into practical action and take a direct step to help rough sleepers change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister urged people across the country to get behind StreetLink and call if they see someone in need this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the nights getting colder, many people will be wondering how they can help when they see someone facing a night on the streets. StreetLink will give them the chance to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new service will help rough sleepers across the country to connect with their local services, offering the help and advice they need to get back on track. So save the StreetLink number, 0300 500 0914, onto your phone, download the app or bookmark the webpage today. Your action could help a rough sleeper get out of the cold and into long-term support.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48346</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/podcast-marks-international-human-rights-day--2"/>
    <title>Podcast marks International Human Rights Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fight against torture has been a priority for the British Government for many years. We make clear time and time again that torture is an abhorrent, unjustifiable violation of human rights and human dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This audio download is introduced by the Louise de Sousa, head of the Foreign Office Human Rights and Democracy Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the podcast, we hear from Kolbassia Haoussou, a survivor of torture and Coordinator of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.freedomfromtorture.org/feature/survivors_speak_out/5993" title="Survivor Speak OUT.com"&gt;Survivor Speak OUT.com&lt;/a&gt;, Alex Wilks Senior Programme Lawyer at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ibanet.org/IBAHRI.aspx" title="International Bar Association Human Rights Institute"&gt;International Bar Association Human Rights Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and Nick Hardwick CBE, who has been Her Majesty’s Chief Inspector of Prisons since 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The podcast is available to download via &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/social-media/podcasts" title="FCO website"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a rel="external" href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/podcast/human-rights/id462779772" title="iTunes"&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/social-media/podcasts/" title="human rights podcasts"&gt;Listen or subscribe to human rights podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/ameliabate/2012/12/10/16-days-with-a-difference/" title="human rights and communications blog"&gt;Read our human rights and communications blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/FCOHumanRights" title="@FCOHumanRights"&gt;@FCOHumanRights&lt;/a&gt; on twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/foreign-commonwealth-office/id392006693" title="FCO on iTunes"&gt;FCO on iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://fcohrdreport.readandcomment.com/" title="FCO Human Rights and Democracy Report"&gt;FCO Human Rights and Democracy Report: read and comment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice on Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office on Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office on Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/4030</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:55:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:55:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/army-and-navy-bomb-specialists-tackle-v2-rocket"/>
    <title>Army and Navy bomb specialists tackle V2 rocket</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 4-foot-long (1.2-metre) section of the German Second World War missile was pulled from mudflats at low tide on the River Stour between Harwich and Felixstowe on Saturday, 31 March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6-man Navy team from &lt;a href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport/Southern-Diving-Group%20Southern%20Diving%20Group%20(SDG)"&gt;Southern Diving Unit 2&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Southern Diving Unit 2"&gt;SDU 2&lt;/abbr&gt;) in &lt;a href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth%20Portsmouth%20Naval%20Base"&gt;Portsmouth&lt;/a&gt; worked with the &lt;a href="http://www.army.mod.uk/%20British%20Army"&gt;British Army&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/units/852.aspx%20101%20(City%20of%20London)%20Engineer%20Regiment%20(Explosive%20Ordnance%20Disposal)"&gt;101 Engineer Regiment&lt;/a&gt; bomb disposal team to lift the section of weapon from the mud onto a barge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had first excavated around the lowest part of the V2 to discover that the warhead section was not there - meaning there was no safety risk to the local population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Venturi section of the rocket, named after a scientific reaction that happens when fluid passes through a narrow pipe, could now be donated to the nearby sailing club who have passed it in the mud for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Servicemen retrieving the V2 rocket section" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/864/FN120004_14.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British servicemen at work retrieving the V2 rocket section at Harwich [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Gaz Armes, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Dan Herridge, Officer-in-Command of &lt;abbr title="Southern Diving Unit 2"&gt;SDU 2&lt;/abbr&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was a successful result to the operation and means people using the waterways and living locally can have confidence that this was not a dangerous piece of ordnance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are grateful for the support of our colleagues from 101 Engineer Regiment for helping remove this section of the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first the Royal Navy team was sceptical it was a V2 rocket because the missiles plunged to earth at more than twice the speed of sound having reached heights of up to 128 miles (206 kilometres) above the earth’s surface – so normally there was nothing left of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On closer inspection the rocket was indeed identified as a V2. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The retrieved Venturi section of the V2 rocket" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/865/FN120004_15.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The retrieved Venturi section of the V2 rocket [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Gaz Armes, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rocket was submerged nose down and was projecting about 2 feet (60 centimetres) out of the mud, around 300 feet (90 metres) from the Harwich shoreline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V2 rocket was developed by pioneering scientist Werner von Braun - who went on to be a key figure behind the American effort to put a man on the moon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Built by concentration camp prisoners, more than 3,000 V2s were launched from the continent at London, south-east England and the Belgian port of Antwerp - with the aim of demoralising the civilian populace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The missile attacks resulted in the death of an estimated 7,250 people, mostly civilians. Of these, more than 2,750 were killed in London - and another 6,523 injured. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16964</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:50:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:50:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1st-royal-tank-regiment-takes-part-in-homecoming-parade-in-glasgow"/>
    <title>1st Royal Tank Regiment takes part in homecoming parade in Glasgow</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The soldiers of D Squadron took part in the homecoming parade in Glasgow on Saturday 24 November 2012 to mark their recent return from operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1 RTR&lt;/abbr&gt; deployed to Afghanistan throughout 2012 and took on a variety of roles during the deployments. The Regimental Headquarters filled a number of positions throughout Helmand province, from support roles in Camp Bastion to key staff roles in the Brigade Headquarters. Other roles included training the Afghan Local Police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1 RTR&lt;/abbr&gt;, Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Britton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud of what the regiment achieved in Afghanistan. The soldiers make many sacrifices to fulfil their role, and recognition of that by those at home is deeply appreciated. It means a great deal to the soldiers and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glasgow’s Lord Provost, Sadie Docherty, in her capacity as Lord-Lieutenant, took the salute at the parade in George Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the honours I have as Lord-Lieutenant is taking the salute at homecoming parades. It is always a privilege to welcome our brave men and women serving in conflicts across the globe. I am delighted that all of D Squadron have made it home safe and sound in time for Christmas with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/26877.aspx" title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1st Royal Tank Regiment&lt;/a&gt;  is based at RAF Honington in Suffolk and recruits from Scotland and the North West of England. The majority of soldiers come from Liverpool and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50172</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-philippines-partners-for-prosperity"/>
    <title>Britain and the Philippines: Partners for Prosperity</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here today, and especially pleased that we are in the company of Foreign Secretary del Rosario. I would like to thank the Makati Business Club, the Management Association of the Philippines and the British Chamber of Commerce for inviting me to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real thrill to be in the Philippines, on my first official visit to this beautiful country. It is almost 30 years since I was last here, in a personal capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a busy two days ahead and have just come from a very productive meeting with President Aquino, during which we discussed how Britain and the Philippines can work together to tackle today’s global challenges and support each other’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on the latter that I will focus today. I will talk first about the United Kingdom’s role in today’s changing world, before setting out why I think Britain and the Philippines can be powerful partners for prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom, like the Philippines, is an island nation – a characteristic which, unsurprisingly, has shaped how we view ourselves and the world around us. Britain is a relatively small place. We had enough but not bountiful natural resources. Combine that with a predisposition towards adventure and discovery, and it led us to build truly global networks and trade links. One thinks of names like Drake, Raleigh and Shackleton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No market was too far or too difficult; no peak too high. Indeed, the globalisation that people tend to view today as a very modern phenomenon has roots that go much deeper. The world in which the Victorians lived was far more integrated in some ways, with Britain sitting at the heart of a global economic system, including a de facto single currency – the Gold Standard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this brought us to South-East Asia. Our ties to countries like Malaysia and Singapore are perhaps best known and are still extremely strong. However, Britain’s links to the Philippines stretch back just as far. The first British Consul arrived as early as 1844. And I am reminded of one of your most famous national heroes, José Rizal, who lived in London’s Primrose Hill in the 1880s. Visitors today will find a blue plaque on the house in which he lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, and particularly in the last couple of decades, I have heard some say that Britain lost sight of the importance of South-East Asia; that our attention was diverted elsewhere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that relationships changed. But while it may have felt to some as if Britain had lost focus, we never went away. The commercial figures alone bear this out. UK trade and investment with South-East Asia today is still far higher than it is with China, despite the exceptional levels of growth and development that China has seen over the past 15 years. That said, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office has under the current Government significantly strengthened this focus, placing an even greater emphasis on our engagement with South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have rebalanced our foreign policy and diplomatic network. On a practical level, that means opening new missions, sending more diplomats to places like the Philippines. We are creating around 50 new jobs across the region. And I am sure many of you will have taken note of last month’s visit to Laos by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, to reopen the British Embassy there. The UK is now represented in all ten ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking this new approach because we see the emergence and re-emergence of economies across the world – not least the growth and development in Asia – as an opportunity. I believe there is much that we can achieve if we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is a key element of my Government’s efforts to deliver sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from an unbalanced growth model, reliant on government spending, to one based on expanding trade, encouraging inward investment, increasing the share of our economy that comes from exports, and manufacturing the goods that today’s consumers want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to meet our ambitious target to double exports to £1 trillion a year by 2020, we need to grow our exports by eight percent a year. Some of these will go to traditional markets like the European Union, but we are looking increasingly to fast-growing economies in places like South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Europe, the UK is leading the efforts to open up the EU market to trade with other nations. Growth may be slow in Europe – the forecasts suggest we can expect only 0.4 per cent next year – but it is still the biggest marketplace in the world, doing £11 trillion of business every year and encompassing 500 million consumers and 21 million companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our prosperity agenda forward won’t be easy – the global economic environment clearly remains a challenge. But it is a challenge I am confident Britain can respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we are doing within the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to embed commercial thinking should help. We are now training our diplomats in commercial as well as foreign affairs, and deploying new commercial staff across our diplomatic network. Our Ambassadors increasingly undertake secondments to companies before taking up their postings to gain firsthand commercial experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the often bleak commentary from elements of the media, the British economy has real strengths. Just think of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games held earlier this year. The Games followed hot on the heels of Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, and showcased to the world Britain’s diversity, openness, creativity and dynamism – politically, culturally and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is renowned for its excellence in financial services, the creative industries and, of course, in education. But as anyone who visited the British Business Embassy at Lancaster House in London during the Olympics would have noticed, we also remain one of the world’s most important manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s car industry, currently undergoing a renaissance, is one such example. We are home to seven global car manufacturers.  Ford, General Motors, Jaguar Land Rover and Mini you will know, but we also have big investments from Honda, Toyota and Nissan too, who produced over 480,000 vehicles in Britain last year. In total, more than one million vehicles and two million engines are produced in the UK each year, and over three-quarters of the vehicles we manufacture are exported. And enthusiasts of faster cars will know that eight Formula One teams have their headquarters in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the UK’s expertise across this and many other sectors makes us a highly compatible partner for the Philippines. I would point, for instance, to finance, where our ICT specialists are helping the Philippine Stock Exchange expand their optic fibre network across the ASEAN region; and to healthcare, where our extensive experience in Public-Private Partnerships is helping the Philippines in their plans to develop a centre of excellence in orthopaedic medicine, modelled on the Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our sectoral expertise is certainly not the only reason. What makes Britain a particularly attractive partner is, I think, the openness of our economy, our transparency and adherence to the rule of law and our firm belief in the rules-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of economic uncertainty, some are inevitably tempted to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. But protectionism is a short-term measure with long-term consequences, and in Britain we are taking the opposite approach. History has taught us that more trade, more competitiveness and making the UK open for business and open for investment are what will steer us towards sustainable economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines is heading down the same path, and I would highlight four areas that point towards this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is corruption, which remains a scourge on the global economy. It adds as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries. Those who are hardest hit are often the poorest and most vulnerable in society. That is why we are proud to have introduced the Bribery Act in the UK to address this all-too-common problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Aquino’s anti-corruption efforts and business-friendly policies such as the Integrity Initiative and the decision to join the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative are exactly the right thing to be doing – particularly now, during this period of global economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area is building the infrastructure needed to provide the foundations for long-term prosperity. Modern economies need roads, digital and cellular communications, public transport, schools and hospitals. Without them, we cannot deliver the skilled and trained workforce required to compete in the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third area is ensuring peace and stability. This is perhaps the most crucial platform for prosperity. I am proud that the UK played a small but important role in the framework agreement in Mindanao as a member of the international contact group.  And I would like to take this opportunity to repeat our deepest condolences for the terrible devastation caused there by Typhoon Pablo. Successful implementation of the framework agreement will unlock the economic potential of that area. We are also working closely with Secretary del Rosario and his team to bring about a peaceful resolution of the claims in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connected to international peace and stability is the fourth area: shunning protectionism and embracing free trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ future will not be shaped by growth in the archipelago alone. Whether it is through its overseas workers, the foreign investment that can create jobs, or its export markets abroad, it is clear that future prosperity here will be based on partnerships. This agenda is moving in the right direction.  But I think we can go further and faster. Agreeing a free trade agreement between the EU and the Philippines would be a valuable step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this policy prescription is good for your economy. But it is also vital for your broader development. International trade and investment is not just the best route to development; history tells us it is the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am speaking to you here today because I think – in fact I am certain – that the relationship between Britain and the Philippines can play an important part in promoting our mutual prosperity. We have much in common, and economies that rely on a strong and open global economy. We are democracies, with a strong attachment to human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today Secretary del Rosario marked this growth by signing a joint plan of action that will take our relationship to a new level. This is a genuinely exciting proposition. Our partnership will help to shape the business environment – working together on issues like anti-corruption, competitiveness, economic reform, a low-carbon economy and building awareness about the opportunities for trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade between our countries currently stands at around £1.1 billion. That is impressive, but is I think a fraction of what it can be, particularly when you consider just how fast your country is growing. In this year’s third quarter, growth in the Philippines reached 7.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joint action plan should help us to realise this potential. But we as governments can only do so much. Ultimately, it is businesses that will drive growth. We need your help to generate interest, build awareness and deliver projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore pleased that we have with us today some excellent examples of successful companies operating here –like Standard Chartered Bank, Marks and Spencer and Debenhams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On visas – not always an easy subject – I know that we have a fast, fair and efficient service here, and that we are opening new services to facilitate quick and easy travel for business via Saturday openings, a premium service and a new visa application centre in Cebu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sign that we are indeed open to business is the large number of Filipino overseas workers that are employed in the UK, who are making a valuable contribution to our economy but also sending back remittances to family in the Philippines. Their contribution cuts across many sectors, but is particularly evident in health and care work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that our new visa services will lead to many more visitors travelling between our countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help bring this about, I will sign a new air services agreement later today with Secretary Abaya, and meet Ramon Ang and Philippines Airlines, who hope to start direct flights to London soon. And, incidentally, their passengers will probably be arriving on new aircraft made partly in Britain, following the announcement by Philippines Airlines in August of a $7 billion order from Airbus for over 50 new aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to share our policy experience in infrastructure development, energy and Public-Private Partnerships so you can learn from our experiences, our successes and, occasionally, our mistakes. When President Aquino visited London in the summer, he went to St Pancras Station, a successful example of how well Public-Private Partnerships can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope what you have heard today is a clear indication of the UK’s role in today’s global economy, of what is happening here in the Philippines and, most importantly, a compelling vision for how Britain and the Philippines can be partners for prosperity, looking to the future with confidence and optimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit is just one of what I am confident will be many high-level visits in the coming months. I know that my colleague, the Foreign Secretary William Hague, is keen to visit in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the rest of my programme, and – with your agreement – I will not leave it another 30 years before I return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48079</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa hails Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’ following successful elections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the National Electoral Committee announced the Presidential election results, Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I congratulate John Dramani Mahama on his election as President of Ghana and on elections that were widely recognised to be free, fair and transparent. Ghana has now seen six successful elections since military government ended in 1992 and it is rightly seen as a beacon of democracy in the region. I commend the Ghanaian people, political parties and civil society on the peaceful environment in which the elections were held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The relationship between the UK and Ghana is strong and vibrant. It is rooted in our long-standing economic, political and cultural connections, our shared values, and the deep links between our peoples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to continuing a constructive and productive working relationship with President Mahama and his government, one that continues to bring our countries closer together.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
