<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60873</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-this-new-years-eve-try-a-mocktail"/>
    <title>Driving this New Year's Eve? Try a mocktail</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Department for Transport has produced a number of non-alcoholic cocktail recipes to help designated drivers celebrate in style.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is encouraging drivers to opt for non alcoholic ‘mocktails’ in a bid to cut down on drink driving this New Year’s Eve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has produced a number of recipes – from a Berry Breezer to a Piña Banana – to appeal to those who are designated drivers on nights out.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is also warning party-goers to plan their way home in advance so they can celebrate the New Year in style, not in the cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting television advert highlighting the consequences of drink driving has been shown throughout December as part of the Department for Transport’s THINK! drink drive campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our message is clear: have a great New Year’s Eve, don’t risk the consequences of drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you get behind the wheel after drinking you risk losing your licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2011, 280 people were killed in accidents where the driver was over the limit. Do not let 1 selfish and foolish decision ruin your or another family’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, drivers aged between 20 and 24 failed more breath tests than any other age group. This year’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign is aimed at young people who are shown to be consistently over-represented in drink drive casualty figures. THINK! advises planning your journey home well in advance and treating your designated driver to a non-alcoholic Christmas cocktail. The recipes are easy to make at home and provide a festive alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is currently consulting on a package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers. This includes removing drink drivers’ rights to demand a blood or urine test. This is because evidence shows it is used as a delaying tactic by drivers caught over the limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also supported Coke’s designated driver scheme, which offered buy 1 get 1 free soft drinks in pubs around the country throughout December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACPO lead for roads policing, Deputy Chief Constable Suzette Davenport, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millions of people will be heading out for New Year’s Eve celebrations and we would ask the public to play their part in remaining safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen hundreds of people die from drink driving this year and it has to stop. Innocent people are needlessly dying on our roads and people who make the decision to drive after taking alcohol or drugs are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are someone who drinks and drives, by making a decision to stop in 2013 could save someone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is provisionally estimated that 2011 saw 280 deaths, 1,290 serious injuries and 9,990 total casualties directly related to drink driving incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign budget totals £783,925&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for a high-resolution copy of the advert the THINK! ‘moment of doubt’ TV advert, contact the Department for Transport’s press office on 020 7944 6898&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK! campaign posters can be downloaded directly from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/drink-driving.html"&gt;campaign site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for more information about the Department for Transport’s consultation into the removal of a driver’s right to a blood test, visit &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"&gt;the GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;read table RAS51004 to see drink drivers by age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="non-alcoholic-christmas-cocktail-recipes"&gt;Non-alcoholic Christmas Cocktail Recipes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="berry-breezer"&gt;Berry Breezer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half a fresh lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the lime and sugar together, add the juices, shake and strain over ice. Top with tonic and garnish with a lime wedge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="elderflower-spritzer"&gt;Elderflower Spritzer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of elderflower cordial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 lemon wedges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;half a teaspoon of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soda water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mint to garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the sugar and lemon wedges together, add the elderflower cordial, shake, top with soda, stir and add more ice as required. Garnish with a lemon wedge and a sprig of mint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="winter-warmer"&gt;Winter Warmer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of apple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lemon and cloves for garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heat the apple and cranberry juice together for 1 minute in the microwave, stir in the honey and serve immediately in a heated mug or handled glass. Garnish with a clove-studded lemon wheel. For an extra twist replace the honey with spiced sugar syrup. To make this, mix some sugar gomme, vanilla pods, a cinnamon stick, a handful of cloves and some cardamom and allow to infuse for 3 days. Sieve
the sugar and mix with the heated apple and cranberry juices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="citrus-mock-tini"&gt;Citrus Mock-tini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 fresh kumquats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons of lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marmalade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 millilitres of clementine juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the kumquats with the marmalade, add the clementine juice, shake, pour over ice and top with tonic. Garnish with spent kumquat shells. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pia-banana"&gt;Piña Banana&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 banana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon of almond syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres single cream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dash of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blend all the ingredients together with some ice until frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16543</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/armys-airborne-engineers-build-french-connection"/>
    <title>Army's airborne engineers build French connection</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An exercise has seen British airborne engineers build a bridge over a large man-made lake and train with their French counterparts.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/role/834.aspx" title="23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)"&gt;23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)&lt;/a&gt; has been working in the harsh climate and unforgiving landscape of Northumbria with French troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/genie/17e-regiment-du-genie-parachutiste" title="17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste"&gt;17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (17e RGP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper tested troops in a humanitarian relief operation in a country facing famine and struggling to recover from damage caused by a tsunami, with government control undermined by insurgents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After deploying from their base at Woodbridge in Suffolk, the exercise started in earnest with the use of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/equipment/705.aspx" title="Air Portable Ferry Bridge"&gt;Air Portable Ferry Bridge&lt;/a&gt; (APFB) equipment to move vehicles and personnel across the two-mile-wide (3.2km) expanse of Kielder Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APFB specialist equipment is designed to be parachuted or moved by helicopter and set up either as a conventional bridge or a self-propelled ferry to cross wider obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sappers preparing the bridge" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1134/16x-2012-115-0114.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sappers preparing the bridge to go over Kielder Water during Exercise Eagle Sapper [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sappers then moved to Otterburn, where they were challenged to build water supply points capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day, cross rivers using bridging equipment and improvised materials, demolish obstacles, and construct defensive positions which were then attacked by enemy forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training was intended to test the unit in their role providing combat engineering support to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/12409.aspx" title="16 Air Assault Brigade"&gt;16 Air Assault Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, which is ready to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice for operations ranging from disaster relief to war-fighting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jason Hones, Commanding Officer of 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper has seen our soldiers working for up to 22-hours-a-day on demanding tasks that test both their combat engineering and infantry skills in very harsh terrain and weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1135/16x-2012-115-0631.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The sappers and their French counterparts built a water supply point capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges  [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that we test the mettle of the soldier we are going to send on operations in arduous and unknown conditions so that we know he can cope with anything that is thrown at him. If a soldier can survive in Northumbria in winter he can survive anywhere in the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The French troops joined the exercise as part of the developing partnership between 16 Air Assault Brigade and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/brigades/11e-brigade-parachutiste" title="11e Brigade Parachutiste"&gt;11e Brigade Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (11e BP), which have been tasked to develop a Combined Joint Expeditionary Force for contingency operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lt Col Hones said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really lucky to have soldiers from our French partner regiment with us, having recently sent troops over to train in France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1136/16x-2012-115-0667.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A water supply point constructed during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working together on this exercise is developing our integration at the section level, to learn how we each operate and our particular strengths and weaknesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will take this to the next level up in the coming months, working towards the aim of being able to work seamlessly together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Matthieu Le Puloc’h commanded the ten-strong 17e RGP contingent, who lived and worked with their British counterparts throughout the two-week exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is our first joint training and our presence is about learning how 23 Engineer Regiment works so that, if we do go on operations together, we know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defends his position" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1137/16x-2012-115-0804.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defending his position during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are a lot of similarities in our basic role as airborne engineers, but our equipment and working practices are different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Otterburn is a cold and hard environment but we have quickly adapted to it and the exercise has been a great experience to broaden the minds of our soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Steve McCann said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s been a tough exercise in difficult conditions that has been made more challenging by working with our French counterparts. Their kit is slightly different and the language barrier makes everything go a little bit slower, but we’re showing them how we work and it’s rewarding to complete engineering tasks together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17217</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/military-urge-generous-public-not-to-swamp-postal-system-at-christmas"/>
    <title>Military urge generous public not to swamp postal system at Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Service personnel are urging members of the public to avoid sending unsolicited Christmas gifts and packages to operational theatres.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Christmas post deadline of 3 December approaches for Armed Forces personnel serving overseas, servicemen and women are urging members of the public not to send unsolicited gifts and packages to operational theatres such as Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these kind sentiments are appreciated, such generosity has often resulted in delaying important mail from family and friends reaching their destination at this special time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceFor/ServiceCommunity/BFPO/BritishForcesPostOffice.htm" title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;British Forces Post Office&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) is overwhelmed by the generosity of the public who send individuals, and groups, in operational theatres boxes of treats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although well-intentioned, the message is very clear: if people wish to show their support for those serving in Afghanistan, there are far more effective ways of doing so such as donations to Service charities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; spokesperson Lieutenant Colonel Brett Duxbury said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with every year, the Christmas post period is by far our busiest. Just this week we dispatched more than 10,500 bags of mail to operational theatres, which will arrive in time for Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unsolicited mail can seriously impact on our ability to deliver post from loved ones to personnel serving on operations at Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not underestimate the impact that mail from friends and family can have on morale and it is for that reason we make it our priority each year to ensure it arrives on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parcels are coming in thick and fast to the military’s premier transport hub of &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, via the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, and have been loaded onto aircraft ready for dispatch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Service personnel are working hard to ensure that this mail is delivered alongside other vital supplies such as helicopters, armoured vehicles and lifesaving equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Danny Smith, from No 1 Air Mobility Wing at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last two days over 23 tonnes of mail has arrived at Brize Norton from the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, which has been loaded onto aircraft and is now en route to various operational theatres including Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a challenging but important task ensuring it is all dispatched quickly. Having served in Afghanistan at Christmas last year, I understand how much value our boys and girls place on receiving post from people closest to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1242/Mail1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas mail for the troops, sorted, bagged and packaged, awaits final transportation to Afghanistan in the air cargo hangar at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The volume of mail arriving at Camp Bastion for onward distribution to other locations in Afghanistan can cause other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The onward delivery of goodwill parcels to forward operating bases necessitates additional resupply flights and convoys, which places Service personnel at additional risk in what is already a difficult and dangerous operating environment. Every time an additional convoy is laid on, more troops are put at risk of enemy attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of items included in many welfare parcels are either already readily available in theatre or are simply not appropriate for the Afghan environment. Not only does this mean that the items go to waste, but time and resources have to be diverted from crucial operations to organise their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government is dedicated to the care and welfare of the men and women of our Armed Forces, particularly those deployed on operations. This is reflected in the Deployed Welfare Package, a key part of which is the safe and timely delivery of free personal mail from family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past this mechanism has been used by the general public to show their support and resulted in huge volumes of unsolicited goodwill parcels being sent, which have overwhelmed the in-theatre postal and logistics capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst unsolicited mail is well-intentioned, mail sent by families and friends is the most important to deployed personnel and is our absolute priority. Moreover, unsolicited mail strains the logistics supply and prevents mail from families getting through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason the MOD will be repeating its unsolicited mail campaign. Rather than sending their own letter or parcel, I would encourage people to make a donation to one of Britain’s excellent Service charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They might also consider &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;‘uk4u Thanks!’&lt;/a&gt; - a charity that provides Christmas gifts to deployed Service personnel. Once again I would like to say thank you to the British public, on behalf of the MOD and Armed Forces, for their incredible support of our serving personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1243/Mail2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mail for troops in places such as Afghanistan awaiting loading onto aircraft at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the charity uk4u Thanks! will, for the ninth year, deliver a Christmas Box of practical gifts and treats to every soldier, sailor and airman deployed overseas - in Afghanistan and elsewhere - and to those in hospital and recovery centres in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its parcels are delivered via the supply chain, meaning there is no impact on the mail network. Although the charity benefits from corporate sponsorship, it also needs donations from the public to continue its work bringing Christmas cheer to thousands of personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD provides a comprehensive Deployed Welfare Package which includes a free mail service for families and friends, 30 minutes of telephone calls a week and internet access, there are still areas where life in an operational theatre can be improved over and above that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and in order to enable members of the public to make a contribution to the welfare of personnel in an appropriate way, the MOD Operations Welfare Fund was established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priority for spending from the fund is set by commanders in theatre for those items which have the most impact on enhancing the morale of their personnel, and any money donated to this fund enables commanding officers on the ground to bid for items which their men and women have asked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of items purchased through the fund are Wii handsets, portable DVD players, games and table tennis tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make a donation can send a cheque to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations Welfare Fund, J1 Operation HERRICK, PJHQ, Sandy Lane, Northwood, Middlesex HA6 3HP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recommended Christmas posting date for personnel on Her Majesty’s ships is Friday 30 November 2012, and for Operation HERRICK and Operation KIPION is Monday 3 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60904</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:20:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:20:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"/>
    <title>Honours awarded to Brits for exceptional international achievement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list recognises outstanding work for the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FCO today announces the honours awarded on the Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list to British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The List has 99 awards to Brits or nationals of HM The Queen’s Realms in a range of fields such as for peace and security, stabilisation and development, education, science, British business and community/voluntary work plus exceptional contributions to London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some candidates are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain LOBBAN CB
Director, Government Communications Headquarters (GCHQ). For services to UK national security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain Lobban receives a KCMG.  Iain joined GCHQ in 1983 and has been the Director since 2008. He has made an outstanding personal contribution to the security of Britain and her allies bringing recognition as a world-class cyber organisation. His leadership of GCHQ has been transformational, adapting the organisation to meet the challenges of the ‘cyber age’ and moving the organisation’s focus to be at the heart of the UK’s prosperity and national interest agenda.  He has also actively promoted volunteering, outreach and charity work among his staff, raising over £100,000 for charity last year and furthering links with higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Raymond Allen DWEK
Professor of Glycobiology, Oxford University.   For services to UK/Israel scientific collaboration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Dwek receives a CBE. One of the most distinguished biochemists in the UK, he has been a major force in furthering UK/Israel scientific collaboration for over a decade. A key element of his work is promoting peace through science.  He has made significant medical advances, invested enormous time and effort in sharing the UK’s science excellence with the international community, all of which has brought many benefits for the UK and Oxford University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alison SHALABY
Chief Executive Officer, Reunite. For services to the prevention and resolution of international parental child abduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alison Shalaby receives an OBE.  A pioneer in the field of international parental child abduction, Alison is a leading global authority on the legal, social and emotional aspects on this issue and helps thousands of families around the world every year.  She has been instrumental in the development of the charity Reunite since 1992, initially as a volunteer and now as CEO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/protocol/honours/dso-list"&gt;Read the full 2013 Diplomatic Service and Overseas list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/honours"&gt;The honours system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60888</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-years-honours-2013"/>
    <title>New Year's Honours 2013</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham congratulates all those recognised in the New Year Honours.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to all those working in the local government, housing, fire and voluntary and community sector who have been recognised in the New Year Honours list which acknowledges their extraordinary contribution to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to see colleagues in local government being honoured. It’s testament to their services to the local community that their hard work, dedication and achievements have been recognised in this way. Many congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-government"&gt;Local government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the local government sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Jones, Leader of East Sussex County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in the South East&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Tapster, lately Chief Executive of Hertfordshire County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ian Greenwood, lately Leader of Bradford City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Kelly, lately Chief Executive of Gateshead Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government and the community in Gateshead and the North East &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharon Taylor, Leader of Stevenage Borough Council and Deputy Chair of the Local Government Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jane Todd, Chief Executive of Nottingham City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Nottingham &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clare Whelan, Member, London Borough of Lambeth receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brian Beale, Councillor in Southminster receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linda Green, Member, Gateshead Metropolitan Borough Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tyne &amp;amp; Wear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raymond Puddifoot, Leader of Hillingdon Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Hillingdon, Middlesex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katherine Gilcreest, Anti-Social Behaviour Manager, Brentwood Borough Council receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Brentwood, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="housing"&gt;Housing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the housing sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthony Pidgeley, Chairman of the Berkeley Group receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the housing sector and the community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Ruback, Deputy Director, Housing Revenue Account and Decent Homes Programe, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sue Chalkley, Chief Executive of the Hastoe Housing Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to housing and tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Downie, Deputy Director, Affordable Housing Management and Standards, Department for Communities and Local Government receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="fire-and-rescue"&gt;Fire and rescue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the fire and rescue sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Beardsall, Retained Watch Manager in Charge, Nottinghamshire and City of Nottingham Fire and Rescue Authority receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Mottram, Equipment Officer, South Yorkshire Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Richard Stanton, firefighter in West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Cole, Retained Firefighter, Isle of Wight receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the communities of Shanklin and the Isle of Wight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Boulton, Senior Adviser to the Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glynis Lomax, Head of the Operational Intelligence Unit receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gary Reason, Director of Operational Resilience and Training for services to the Olympics receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colin Rockey, Group Manager, Devon and Somerset Fire and Rescue Service receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="voluntary-and-community-sector"&gt;Voluntary and community sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the voluntary and community sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herschel Gluck, founder of the Muslim Jewish Forum receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to interfaith understanding &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Denys Shortt, founder of DCS Europe PLC and Chair, Coventry and Warwickshire Local Enterprise Partnership receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the economy in the West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruth Abrahams receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the voluntary and community sector in Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margaret Barker, founder of the Dorset Poverty Action Group receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to homeless and underprivileged people in Dorchester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Barker receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community of the Mixenden Social Housing Estate, Halifax &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Blower receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement in Fleetwood &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anita Halliday, Chief Executive of St Pauls Community Development Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Balsall Heath, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Highton, founder of the Brian Shields Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to personal finance and community support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mary Jones receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenants and the community in Saffron and Neston, Leicester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter McNestry, Chair of the Coalfields Regeneration Trust, Waith upon Dearne, Rotherham, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to coalfield communities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggarwal-Singh Neelam receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to community cohesion, health and welfare through the Indian Hindu Welfare Organisation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gerry Proctor receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Liverpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emdadur Rahman, journalist and community volunteer, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tower Hamlets and to the Bangladeshi Media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Sheehy receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Ahern, Chair of the Templar’s Estate Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment in Witham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eileen Alldritt receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment and the community in Liverpool &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christine Allen, Chief Executive of the Forum Housing Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Merseyside &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rose Cooke-Coton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Masefield, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heather Didwell, volunteer at Catton Grove Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John Filby receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Abridge, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Muriel Healey, board member, Havebury Housing Partnership receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to Tenants in Suffolk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Highton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in West Ealing, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asim Iftikhar receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Poplar &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Betty Koppa receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community and residents of North Curry, Taunton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shaun Lansfield receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement and to the community in Edmonton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jacqueline McGrew, Chair of the Whitebirk Tenants and Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Blackburn, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew Milnes, founder of the Scholemoor Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Bradford&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Riaz Ravat, Development Manager, St Philip’s Centre, Leicester receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to inter-faith understanding in Leicester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Smith receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Leyland, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56695</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-year-honours-for-service-personnel-and-defence-civilians"/>
    <title>New Year Honours for Service personnel and Defence civilians</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>120 UK Service personnel have been granted state honours by Her Majesty The Queen in the annual New Year Honours list.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;42 civilians have also been honoured either for work in the Ministry of Defence or in other aspects of UK Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 162 Defence personnel named in the New Year Honours list for 2013 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="royal-navy-awards"&gt;ROYAL NAVY AWARDS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h3 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath"&gt;PROMOTIONS IN AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST HONOURABLE ORDER OF THE BATH&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-knight-commander"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew David Hugh MATHEWS CB &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-companions"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Charles Anthony JOHNSTONE-BURT OBE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Robert LISTER OBE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;PROMOTIONS IN AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST EXCELLENT ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-commanders"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Boyce CHARLIER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Matthew Edward PORTER OBE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-officers"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew BETTON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nicholas Geoffrey DUNN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Nicholas John GRACE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Timothy Mark HULME &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surgeon Commander Anthony Wayne LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore Richard William MASON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore James Mark SLAWSON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-members"&gt;As Members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1(Abovewater Warfare Weapons) Paul Michael Stewart BARKER Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nigel David BOND &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Christopher Paul CANNING &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Damian Andrew Giles EXWORTHY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Terence GILLARD Royal Naval Reserve (Sea Cadet Corps)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Abovewater Warfare Tactical) James Edward HALL Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Thomas Maxwell Philip HENDERSON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Rodney Leslie LESTER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Brian MEADOWS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Annette Eileen PENFOLD Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 David John ROACH Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Air Engineering Technician) David Alun ROWLANDS &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Simon TOTTLE Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="appointments-to-the-civil-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;APPOINTMENTS TO THE CIVIL DIVISION OF THE MOST EXCELLENT ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-commander"&gt;As Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore William Michael WALWORTH OBE Royal Fleet Auxiliary  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal"&gt;QUEEN’S VOLUNTEER RESERVES MEDAL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting Commander Simon Roscoe COTTAM Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="army-awards"&gt;ARMY AWARDS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h3 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-1"&gt;PROMOTIONS IN AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST HONOURABLE ORDER OF THE BATH&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-knight-commander-1"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant General James Jeffrey Corfield BUCKNALL CBE late Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-companions-1"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Shaun Alex BURLEY MBE late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Ian Martin COPELAND late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Gregory Stephen SMITH QVRM TD DL late The Royal Green Jackets Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-1"&gt;PROMOTIONS IN AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST EXCELLENT ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-commanders-1"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Gareth Paul COLLETT late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Peter Andrew FOX late Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Edward Oliver FORSTER–KNIGHT OBE late Adjutant General’s Corps (Royal Military Police&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier John Craig LAWRENCE MBE late The Royal Gurkha Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-officers-1"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Barry William BENNETT MBE Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Ian Miles COMERFORD Corps of Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robert James HEALEY Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Garry HEARN late Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Peter Michael LITTLE The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Nicholas Charles Tristram MILLEN late The Royal Dragoon Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Timothy Marc Piers MOUNTFORD Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robin Charles SMITH The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Roger John Nathaniel STEWART late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Simon Philip STOCKLEY Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Neil UNSWORTH The Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Murray Courtenay WHITESIDE MBE late Army Air Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-members-1"&gt;As Members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Christopher Charles ATTRILL The Royal Irish Regiment Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kenneth Harry BAKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Joanna Jane BRAIN Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bombardier Alexander Robert BUCHANAN Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Robert James COLLINS The Parachute Regiment &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Jonathan DEANS Adjutant General’s Corps (Educational and Training Services Branch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Leigh James DRUMMOND The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Paul John EDWARDS The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Alastair Neil FIELD The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Darren John FISHER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal (Acting Sergeant) Terry John FITZGERALD Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James FLETCHER Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 James Alexander FORD Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch) Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Christopher James FULLER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Frederick William GREENHOW Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Rowena Charlotte GRIFFITHS Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Charles Edward Digby GRIST The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Barry HEAP Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Cameron Arthur HILL The Royal Logistic Corps Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Steven Robin HOOK The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Leslie John HUNT Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Christian Glyndwr LAMB The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Guy William John LOCK Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Matthew John Frederick MIDDLEDITCH QGM The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Stephen John MORGAN Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Stuart Andrew NASH Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Andrew James PARKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Bombardier Benjamin James PARKINSON Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Hemchandra RAI BEM Adjutant General’s Corps (Gurkha Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Fabian Andrew David Lechmere ROBERTS MVO Irish Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Brian Mackenzie ROSS The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Robert SADLER Royal Mercian and Lancastrian Yeomanry Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James SANGER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mathew Timothy James SHORT Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martyn Jonathan THOMPSON Royal Army Veterinary Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mark Lloyd WELHAM The Royal Welsh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Nicholas Simon WILSON The Yorkshire Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kevin YOUNG Royal Regiment of Artillery Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-1"&gt;QUEEN’S VOLUNTEER RESERVES MEDAL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major (Local Lieutenant Colonel) Stephen Wyatt BARTLETT TD The Rifles Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Simon Michael John BELL TD late The Cheshire Regiment Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Philip Guy DAVIS Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaplain to the Forces 3rd Class Reverend Louis KINSEY TD Royal Army Chaplains’ Department Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Sonja McCOY Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="royal-air-force"&gt;ROYAL AIR FORCE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h3 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-2"&gt;PROMOTIONS IN AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST HONOURABLE ORDER OF THE BATH&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-knight-commander-2"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Timothy Michael ANDERSON CB DSO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Andrew Douglas PULFORD CBE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-companions-2"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Raymond Jackson PENTLAND&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Julian Alexander YOUNG OBE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="promotions-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;PROMOTIONS AND APPOINTMENTS TO THE MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MOST EXCELLENT ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-commanders-2"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Nigel Philip BEET OBE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Margaret Elaine WEST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Domonic Anthony STAMP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-officers-2"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick Alexander BOUNDY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick John DENNIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Christopher John FISHER RAF Volunteer Reserve (Training)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain James Cameron McGregor JOHNSTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Michael Dawson LAVENDER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Justine Elizabeth MORTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stephen Michael Robert WARD MBE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="as-members-2"&gt;As Members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Timothy Alexander BARLOW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician David Jeremy BRIGGS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Benjamin John CLARK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Benjamin David CROSSLEY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Glynis Mary DEAN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Kevin John Patrick FOXWELL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Phillip Leslie JONES&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Tal Thomas Adam LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Martin Alan PURVIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Simon Edward READE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Derek Charles SMITH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician Barry John STRINGER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Paul WHEABLE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer David John WOODHEAD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Dale Edward Spencer WOOLMAN-LANE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-2"&gt;QUEEN’S VOLUNTEER RESERVES MEDAL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Maureen KENDALL Royal Auxiliary Air Force&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="civilians-in-defence"&gt;CIVILIANS IN DEFENCE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h3 id="knight-bachelor-kt"&gt;KNIGHT BACHELOR (Kt)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Hew Francis Anthony
For services to the Ministry of Defence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commanders-of-the-order-of-the-british-empire-cbe"&gt;COMMANDERS OF THE ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE (CBE)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Michael Thomas COCHRANE
For services to Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="officers-of-the-order-of-the-british-empire-obe"&gt;OFFICERS OF THE ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE (OBE)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Anthea DOLMAN GAIR
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Diana DONOVAN
For voluntary service to The Gurkha Welfare Trust&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James HEPBURN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher HURRAN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vincent MIFSUD, TD
For services to Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Charles PENLINGTON
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cynthia Kit Man SHAW
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Sylvia Nina QUAYLE, TD
For voluntary service to SSAFA Forces Help &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="members-of-the-order-of-the-british-empire-mbe"&gt;MEMBERS OF THE ORDER OF THE BRITISH EMPIRE (MBE)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Ann Elizabeth CABLE
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Andrew CAMBRIDGE
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Gail CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Stamford James CARTWRIGHT, TD
For voluntary service to the West Midland Reserve Forces &amp;amp; Cadets Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horace MacDonald CROSS
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Barrie DAVIES
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm DYER
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy JOBSON
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Graham John LAWRENCE
Ministry of Defence, Andover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Albert MABEY
For voluntary service to the RAF Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel John Robert MacKENZIE, TD
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel MAIN
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Rachel McLAUGHLIN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Rossiter NEWSOME, JP
For voluntary service to SSAFA Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher PAGE
Ministry of Defence, Yeovil&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken PAYNE
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry PITCHFORTH
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Mary Elizabeth PLUME
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David REES
For services to Defence Capability &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William John SCOTT
For voluntary service in the Air Training Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Hannah SEAKINS
Ministry of Defence, Hitchin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John UNDERHILL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE BRITISH EMPIRE MEDAL (BEM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Arnold BURCHELL
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Janet Stewart CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the British Red Cross Society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Paulin CLINTON
For services to Veterans Aid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian CLOUGH
Ministry of Defence, Mid Glamorgan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Ellis GRINNALL
Ministry of Defence, Monmouthshire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Carole Jean HILLMAN
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter William SKELLON
For voluntary service to the RAF Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Jean SLATER
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Alan Ronald TAPP
For voluntary service to SSAFA Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60903</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T19:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T19:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/general-normal-schwarzkopf-tribute"/>
    <title>General Norman Schwarzkopf tribute </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Chief of the Defence Staff has paid tribute to the retired US General Norman Schwarzkopf, who died yesterday, 27 December 2012, aged 78.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Schwarzkopf was commander of coalition forces in the first Gulf War from 1990-91.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, &lt;a href="/government/people/david-richards" title="General Sir David Richards"&gt;General Sir David Richards&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General Norman Schwarzkopf’s command in the Gulf was an example of the finest qualities of American leadership: decisive, inclusive and measured. At the head of a coalition of forces from around the world, including many from the region, he played a pivotal role in the liberation of Kuwait. The operation was not only a UN act but marked the transition from a Cold War doctrine of dissuasion and balance to a new world where force could be used for good. As its first practitioner General Schwarzkopf accomplished what so few can: he shaped his times. He was the first of what are now many US generals to lead British forces in this kind of conflict, rather than in Cold War stasis of the previous decades. For that, and his inspirational command in war, he will be remembered on this side of the Atlantic with respect. The Anglo-American alliance has gone from strength to strength since his time, but it started with him. My thoughts are with his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16790</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-illustrious-visits-malta"/>
    <title>HMS Illustrious visits Malta</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Illustrious has arrived at the Mediterranean island of Malta for a five-day visit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 1,500 sailors and marines lined the deck of the Portsmouth-based helicopter carrier as she entered the port of Valletta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an onboard reception for the Earl and Countess of Wessex, the ship will be holding an affiliation event for representatives from the Maltese cities of Senglea, Vittoriosa and L’Isla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helicopter carrier is twinned with the three cities due to a previous HMS Illustrious which was bombed during the Second World War and underwent extensive repair at the Grand Harbour in Malta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martin Connell, Commanding Officer of HMS Illustrious, said it was a proud moment for him to be sailing HMS Illustrious into Valletta. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very much aware of not just the history of this ship but also the previous Illustrious and what the people of Malta did to help save her in 1941.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1157/IL120467045.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious as she enters the port of Valletta [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gov.mt/" title="Government of Malta"&gt;Maltese Government&lt;/a&gt; also allowed the Grand Harbour in Valletta to be used for berthing by HMS Cumberland and HMS York following their evacuation of British nationals from Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time in Grand Harbour, sailors and marines from HMS Illustrious will be helping out with a variety of worthy causes including a clean-up of outdoor spaces in collaboration with the Nature Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the week &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;HMS Illustrious&lt;/a&gt; will be joined by the Royal Navy fleet flagship, HMS Bulwark, and Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship Mounts Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Illustrious is part of the Cougar 12 deployment - a three-month work-up of the Royal Navy’s Response Force Task Group (RFTG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1158/IL120467008.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deployment is a test of the RFTG’s capability should it be called into action at short notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The force is designed to respond to rapidly unfolding world events - the last time being Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of Cougar 12, the ships have been working with Royal Marines commando units and the Fleet Air Arm to put their amphibious capability to the test - the power to transfer marines from ships onto the beaches of hostile nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as exercising the 3,000 British sailors, marines and airmen, the task force has worked alongside French and Albanian forces to ensure the nations could co-operate on a military level in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-news"&gt;Related News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/BritishAndAlbanianNaviesWorkTogetherInTheAdriatic.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;British and Albanian navies work together in the Adriatic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/HmsIllustriousTrainsWithFrenchNavy.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious trains with French Navy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/EquipmentAndLogistics/HmsIllustriousReturnsToPortsmouthAfterUpgrade.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious returns to Portsmouth after upgrade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17291</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:34:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:34:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-personnel-attend-funeral-of-sir-rex-hunt"/>
    <title>RAF personnel attend funeral of Sir Rex Hunt</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Air Force personnel have attended the funeral of Sir Rex Hunt, former Governor of the Falkland Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personnel from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/34squadron.cfm" title="34 Squadron RAF Regiment"&gt;34 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/609squadron.cfm" title="609 (West Riding) Squadron"&gt;No 609 (West Riding) Squadron Royal Auxiliary Air Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) have attended the funeral of Sir Rex Hunt, former Governor of the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others attending included Air Commodore (Ret’d) Dempster Anderson representing &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment veterans and Group Captain Gary Bunkell, Inspector &lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, representing the Honorary Inspector General.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment formed part of the coffin-bearing party and assisted both in the church and at the graveside. Falklands veterans, ex-&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; and members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23304.aspx" title="The Parachute Regiment"&gt;Parachute Regiment&lt;/a&gt; donned their green and maroon berets to form a guard of honour for the coffin as it entered the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coffin left the church to the tune of the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; March and Sir Rex was buried with the Falkland Islands flag on his coffin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Jeff Metcalfe, Officer Commanding No 609 (West Riding) Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafleeming/aboutus/2fphome.cfm%202%20Force%20Protection%20Wing%20Headquarters"&gt;No 2 Force Protection Wing&lt;/a&gt; were honoured to be asked to perform this solemn duty for Sir Rex Hunt and his family. The personnel were drawn from 34 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment and 609 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Auxiliary Air Force"&gt;RAuxAF&lt;/abbr&gt; and were proud to support this sad occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I served on 2729 Squadron 20 years ago when Sir Rex was my Honorary Air Commodore. I had met him personally and I am proud that I have been involved in laying him to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF personnel in formation " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1256/rexhunt2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; personnel in formation at the church where Sir Rex Hunt was laid to rest [Picture: Ian McIntyre, gazettelive.co.uk, 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many within the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment, still serving or associated with the Corps, who remember Sir Rex with some affection from the earliest days of the Falklands conflict in 1982 when &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/squadrons/63_sqn_history.cfm" title="63   Squadron RAF Regiment"&gt;63 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment&lt;/a&gt; deployed with 5 Brigade and manned the Rapier air defence systems around San Carlos Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within days of the Argentinean surrender, 63 Squadron &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment redeployed from there to defend the new air base established at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Stanley, which was to be their home - and for those of the other &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Germany-based Rapier roulement squadrons involved - for another five years before the resident Rapier squadrons redeployed to the new Mount Pleasant Airbase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at Stanley, Sir Rex visited the remote Rapier site on many an occasion and he always took an intense interest in the men and what they were doing in defence of the Islands. The &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Regiment was to be deployed permanently in the Falklands until 2006, a total of 24 unbroken years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the news of the death of Sir Rex Hunt, Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was very sorry to hear of the death of Sir Rex Hunt. As Governor of the Falkland Islands he served his country and the Falkland Islanders with great distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16512</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:07:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:07:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/surviving-sandy"/>
    <title>Surviving Sandy</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Defence Attache in Washington, Major General Buster Howes, recalls his role in helping to manage the crisis that was Hurricane Sandy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the aftermath of Hurricane Sandy continues to affect the US East Coast, Major General Howes, the British Defence Attache in the USA and one of the Embassy’s designated crisis managers, described his role as the situation unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hurricane Sandy didn’t exactly take the US by surprise as for several days the US media were warning of a storm of biblical proportions shunting its way in from the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provoked a practical response from many - boarding up windows and evacuating homes along the coastal regions, but in places like Washington DC it generated a subdued sense of apprehension and expectation. The streets were empty and people braced themselves for ‘The Storm of a Lifetime’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Howes explained that the Embassy prepares for a range of civil emergencies, including natural disasters, with the specific aim of being able to assist British nationals who may be affected by such events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assistance focuses on passing information between the US and the UK and particularly helping to locate people in difficulties; assisting with travel arrangements when they have been disrupted as well as accommodation problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are about eight million British visitors to the US each year, so there is a high probability that British nationals will be caught up in such events, much as they were when the World Trade Centre was attacked on 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the hurricane, the Embassy was due to run a crisis exercise, involving teams in London, DC and New York, to further develop procedures and staff competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Major General Buster Howes" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1128/busterhowes.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Major General Buster Howes [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Dean Nixon, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Howes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We chose New York for a whole raft of technical reasons. We were due to do the final planning conference on the Monday, to test all the systems on Tuesday, and run it on the Wednesday - just at the time when Sandy struck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Sandy approached, the British Embassy in Washington and the consulates in New York and Boston began contingency planning for a hurricane and prepared for a possible crisis. A strong storm hit DC, but minimal damage actually resulted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison, the coastal areas around New York were devastated, inundated by a powerful, storm-driven tidal surge which was compounded by the full moon state and spring tides. Federal buildings were shut down for two days in DC as a precautionary measure, which also affected the Embassy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving in metropolitan DC is pretty ‘wild’ at the best of times so this measure was designed to relieve traffic congestion in potentially bad conditions which would have compounded the risk of accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of the dramatic media reporting, there was a general run on supermarkets for food and batteries and lanterns, since electrical supplies are often compromised by storm damage, as well as petrol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describing the mood, Major General Howes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clearly the vast majority of people aren’t British but within the Embassy there was a sense of calm expectation. We have a good system for passing information amongst Embassy staff which we obviously utilised, so between that and the television our people remained well informed throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Log jam on the Potomac River" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1129/sandy03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A log jam on the Potomac River next to the Tidal Basin [Picture: Glyn Lowe Photoworks]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;He dismissed any notion of hysteria saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was pretty understated with considerable humour. We were all stuck at home so, as the responsibility to help manage some of the consequences of the hurricane developed, people were networked at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of being holed up in a crisis centre, General Howes worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One consequence was that his personal hotmail account crashed at one stage under the weight of e-mails. Asked if he worked closely with the consular office, General Howes described a ‘battle rhythm’ punctuated with daily early morning and late night calls to London, regular sit-reps and daily telephone conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, the media focus switched to New York as it became clear that the worst devastation had affected Maryland, New Jersey, Delaware and the whole eastern seaboard of the US leaving 2.5 million homes and businesses crippled by surging seawater and loss of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 140 Defence Staff work in the British Embassy, underpinned by a team of support staff stretching across 34 of the 50 states. General Howes is based in the British Embassy, although he travels widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He praised the way that military and civilians pulled together, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We weren’t acting in a military way, though the expertise, experience and brain power involved military people. That said, the ‘crisis’ meant that people were isolated so the whole Embassy didn’t spin into action the way it would for a more extensive crisis affecting British nationals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flood barriers up at Washington Harbour" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1130/sandy04.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flood barriers up at Washington Harbour [Picture: Glyn Lowe Photoworks]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hypothetically, if there was a terrorist attack in Massachussetts, the Embassy would swing into crisis mode, everyone would coalesce, and more people would get swept into the operation. However, because we were all at home until Wednesday morning, fewer people were engaged but there were still military people involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked if there was a sense of detachment given that the focus was in New York, General Howes said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well, we just happen to be in DC because it’s the capital but if there’s a problem in America, the Embassy has a lead in helping to resolve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fact that the storm impact was on and around New York made gaining situational awareness in DC a bit harder and our job was to support people struggling with the impact there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an estimated 50,000 Brits thought to be staying in New York, General Howes explained that the crisis team provided consular care to British nationals as necessary and kept London informed of developments, issuing emergency travel papers and providing assistance to 57 British nationals who contacted the New York Consulate looking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This included supporting 25 schoolchildren whose flight was cancelled and helping 20 British nationals who fled without their luggage following their evacuation from the Salisbury Hotel adjacent to a dangling crane on West 57th Street:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We didn’t send people into the field in such uncertain and potentially hazardous circumstances. They anyway would have struggled to get where they wanted to go, but if people called in to say ‘hey, I need help, I’m British’, we were in a position to advise, direct and assist where we could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Hurricane Sandy rages over Manhattan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1131/sandy02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hurricane Sandy rages over Manhattan [Picture: Michael Cairns]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asked for his abiding memory of Sandy, General Howes explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well - from DC’s perspective - if you imagine a very powerful storm with 60mph [97km/h] winds and torrential rain for two days, that’s what it felt like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Howes added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think the abiding memory is thinking how fortunate we were here and how powerful nature is when it gets angry. It was also slightly surreal watching the drama playing out around New York on TV at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is absolutely not a story of personal drama. It’s important to reinforce the fact that the story wasn’t in DC. In a modest way, we helped manage the unfolding mayhem as it affected UK nationals in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our ability to influence what was happening in Delaware, New Jersey and Ocean City was non-existent, but through the TV images we had a profound sense of ‘There but for the grace of God go we’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60884</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T10:35:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-graduate-apprenticeships-for-the-professions-introduced"/>
    <title>Press Release: Graduate apprenticeships for the professions introduced</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graduate and post-graduate level apprenticeships will soon be available in subjects including law, accountancy and advanced engineering, Skills Minister Matthew Hancock announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next year, changes to the Specification of Apprentices Standards for England (SASE) will mean that level six and seven apprenticeships – equivalent to bachelors and masters degree level – are available for the first time, making vocational learning an attractive alternative to the traditional higher education route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are already a number of these top-level schemes in development, including in accountancy, law and human resources. BPP Law School is looking to develop a Legal Apprenticeship pathway which could be an alternative route to the legal profession and qualification as a solicitor. It is in discussion with the relevant regulatory body and sector skills council, Skills for Justice, to progress its proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills Minister Matthew Hancock said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past, apprenticeships were restricted to only some trades, and some parts of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now we are introducing apprenticeships in all types of jobs, including a new route to the professions, to ensure everyone can reach their potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These new apprenticeships will help more young people to receive on-the-job training at top companies like BPP Law School, ensuring a vocational route to success in accounting, insurance, and the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director of BPP Professional Apprenticeships James Hammill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to improving social mobility and diversity in the work place by opening up some of the most prestigious professions and employers to school leavers as an alternative to the traditional route. Apprenticeships are an excellent way for employers to recruit talent early and design a structured training programme that incorporates technical learning as well as invaluable work based skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BPP Law School is based in eight UK cities: Birmingham, Bristol, Cambridge, Leeds, Liverpool, London, Manchester and Swindon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60881</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T15:03:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T15:03:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-know-your-shoppers-rights-before-you-hit-the-winter-sales"/>
    <title>Press Release: Know your shopper's rights before you hit the winter sales</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Boxing Day sales begin and January sales loom, Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson is urging consumers to shop responsibly and be aware of their rights to a refund or exchange. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent figures show that more shoppers are choosing to buy their festive treats online, but with internet shopping and many other methods of buying, it can be difficult for consumers to know exactly what the rules are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The festive period is the one time we happily push away scrooge-like thoughts and shop for gifts for our loved ones or to take advantage of the wide range of sales. We are increasingly being spoilt for choice with a wide range of goods, services and shops to choose from, but the variety of choice can mean that consumers forget to take note of the different shoppers’ rights that apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would urge consumers to take note of when they are entitled to a refund or exchange, and to bear in mind any restrictions on certain purchases. When shoppers do buy something, and later change their mind or have a problem with the purchase, I want them to be aware of their rights and obligations to make sure they can get their money back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The current laws that apply to buying goods and services need to be clearer, as do the rules on shopping online or buying digital content. The proposed Consumer Bill of Rights aims to clarify and modernise the law, ensuring consumers are confident about their rights across all areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="general-rules"&gt;General rules&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a consumer buys goods, they must be of satisfactory quality, fit for purpose, last a reasonable time and match any description given. If they don’t the consumer can usually get either a repair, replacement, refund or partial refund. The consumer has the right to any claim for 6 years from purchase, or 5 years in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to be aware that sometimes these rights won’t apply. For example if a consumer just changes their mind they will not have the same rights unless the shop they bought from offers them under its own store policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="return-deadlines"&gt;Return deadlines&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers have a “reasonable time”, often around 4 weeks (although it may be less, depending on the goods in question), to return faulty goods and get a full refund. After this, they may only be entitled to an exchange or partial refund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="faulty-goods"&gt;Faulty goods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If goods are faulty, consumers don’t need to have a receipt to return the item, just proof of purchase. However they may not be entitled to a refund if the fault is due to normal wear and tear, or if the consumer damages the item themselves. This will also be the case where the consumer was aware of the fault before they bought the item. If a consumer keeps the goods for too long before telling the shop or trying to fix the problem themselves, they might not be entitled to get all of their money back. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sale-items"&gt;Sale items&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers have the same rights for sale items as they do for full price items. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="gifts"&gt;Gifts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most shops offer gift receipts, legally only the person who paid has a right to return faulty goods.  To avoid any hassle it’s best to use gift receipts where available, or get the trader to write ‘‘this is a gift for —’’ on any receipt or invoice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="dangerous-or-unsafe-goods"&gt;Dangerous or unsafe goods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an item is suspected to be dangerous or unsafe, the individual should stop using it immediately. Dangerous or unsafe goods should be reported to Trading Standards on 08454 04 05 06.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="private-purchases"&gt;Private purchases&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a shopper buys directly from a private seller, they cannot get their money back if the goods are not satisfactory or fit for purpose. They do however have the right to get their money back if the item doesn’t match the description, e.g. if the seller says the item works and it doesn’t. Consumers should always ask for a receipt and contact details from sellers where they can, and keep copies of any relevant adverts or website pages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="online-auction-sites"&gt;Online auction sites&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general shopper’s rights apply when buying from a seller who makes some or all of their income from selling through online auction sites. If the seller is just an occasional private seller, the more limited rules of private purchases apply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="online-mail-order-and-telephone-shopping"&gt;Online, mail order and telephone shopping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers who opt for these buying methods have extra rights in addition to the general rights. If they buy a service they can cancel their order up to 7 working days after making it, and if they buy goods they can cancel 7 working days after receiving the item. Consumers can claim a refund if they don’t receive their item within 30 days. However, consumers can’t return certain goods that they have changed their mind about, including opened CDs or DVDs, food, personalised goods, newspapers and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When buying online consumers should be able to see certain information about the seller, the goods, and the seller’s terms and conditions on the seller’s website. To see exactly what information required visit Citizen’s Advice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="future-proposals"&gt;Future proposals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, BIS consulted on proposals for a new Consumer Bill of Rights, which will set out a clear code of shopping rights with workable remedies when things go wrong.  It will empower consumers, making it easier for them to understand their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clarify the nature of consumers’ rights and remedies in relation to the supply of goods, which is currently an area where the law is unnecessarily complex.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bring the services regime more in line with the regime for goods, by strengthening consumer rights and remedies in relation to faulty services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modernise the law on digital content to protect consumers, by establishing a clear digital content regime with its own tailored set of rights and associated remedies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There will also be one clear set of rules governing public investigations of breaches of consumer law.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Bill of Rights consultation closed in October, and the government will respond in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-advice"&gt;Further advice:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information on shoppers’ rights visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.adviceguide.org.uk/england/consumer_e.htm"&gt;Citizens Advice Bureau webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For advice on money or debt contact the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.moneyadviceservice.org.uk/"&gt;Money Advice Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information on the Consumer Bill of Rights can be found at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-proposals-for-consumer-rights"&gt;Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further information on the Consumer Bill of Rights can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/consumer-bill-of-rights/"&gt;http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/consumer-bill-of-rights/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60865</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-new-settlement"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister condemns new settlement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister Alistair Burt statement: the approval of new units is a 'provocative action' contrary to Fourth Geneva Convention.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the announcements on 24 December that the Jerusalem District Planning Board issued approval for 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South, and that Ariel College is to be upgraded to university status thereby creating the first university in a settlement illegal under international law, Alistair Burt, Minister for the Middle East said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last week Foreign Secretary William Hague made clear our condemnation and deep disappointment at the approval of the East Jerusalem Ramat Shlomo plan. We also condemn the Jerusalem District Planning Board’s approvals for over 3150 units in Givaat Hamatos and 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South. These are further profoundly provocative actions that run contrary to the Fourth Geneva Convention. By taking these steps, despite the international community repeatedly raising our profound concerns, the Israeli Government is damaging Israel’s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also deeply disappointed in the decision to upgrade Ariel’s university centre. Ariel is beyond the Green Line in a settlement that is illegal according to international law. This decision will deepen the presence of the settlements in the Palestinian territories and will create another obstacle to peace. We reiterate our call on Israel urgently to reverse these decisions and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I spoke with President Abbas last week I expressed our appreciation for the measured response the Palestinian Leadership had been taking in response to Israel’s recent settlement announcements.  We utterly and unreservedly condemn the recent call for a third intifada and a suicide campaign by a Hamas official. Incitements to violence and terror are unacceptable. We welcome that President Abbas has publicly rejected the recent inflammatory statements by Hamas leaders, and that he has stated clearly the position of the legitimate Palestinian Leadership which has accepted the State of Israel in 1967 borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taken together, these further settlement announcements and comments deepen our worry for the region at such a crucial time, and demonstrate why we are convinced of the urgency for more positive indicators of change. Accordingly we continue to call on President Abbas and Prime Minister Netanyahu to show the strong leadership needed to achieve a return to negotiations for a two-state solution, which will bring a just and permanent solution to this conflict.  We repeat our hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60311</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/clear-up-initiative-saving-economy-millions-by-reopening-roads-quicker"/>
    <title>Clear-up initiative saving economy millions by reopening roads quicker</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An initiative to improve incident clear-up times is saving the economy tens of millions of pounds annually.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and the economy are seeing huge benefits from a government-led initiative to reopen motorways and roads quickly following major incidents, Roads Minister Stephen Hammond announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;’ (collision, lead, evaluate, act and reopen) initiative - launched by the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) last year to improve incident clear-up times – is helping to save the economy tens of millions of pounds annually, with even more savings to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key achievement has been the success of 38 &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;/police-funded 3D laser scanners which allow police forces to capture evidence quickly following collisions - helping to reopen major roads and motorways more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show an average time saving of 44 minutes per investigation – a 5 minute improvement on test estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other initiatives include the launch of a new hands-free smart phone app that notifies users of incidents and congestion, as well as the planned roll out of incident screens to shield collisions and prevent rubber necking. Time savings associated with screens alone can be up to several hundred thousand pounds per incident.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is confident these measures will help reduce the estimated £750 million cost to the economy that incidents cause on the strategic road network in England annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more frustrating than being stuck in a traffic jam for hours on end.  There is also the shocking cost of those lost hours for our economy. That is why we are improving the clear-up of incidents so we can get our motorways and major roads re-opened as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now witnessing even greater than expected time savings as a result of the roll out of laser scanning programme. This and other elements of the initiative, such as the use of incident screens, will help to keep traffic moving and save the economy tens of millions of pounds a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very encouraged by the cooperation shown by the Highways Agency, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Police and other emergency services, and fully expect these initiatives to result in further time and cost savings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief Constable Sean White, lead on collision investigations for the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This equipment allows police to manage critical events in a more efficient way and present the most accurate and detailed evidence to criminal, civil and coroners’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The time saved by using this technology is more economically friendly and reduces disruption on the roads, while allowing for thorough investigations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the success of this equipment, which has reduced delays for road users and proved extremely important in police investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Highways Agency signing a memorandum of understanding to facilitate data sharing about heavy goods vehicles. Studies have shown this type of vehicle is involved in a high proportion of the longest incidents. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working closely with operators to make sure problems are addressed   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the roll out by the Highways Agency of new towing equipment (load cells) to remove heavier vehicles obstructing live lanes and spill kits to clear spillages from motorway lanes. Time savings associated with the use of load cells have been estimated at several million pounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the production and distribution of a &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet to emergency responders outlining the roles and responsibilities of key organisations involved in managing incidents on the strategic road network. The Highways Agency has also produced a film reinforcing the booklet’s messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of emergency response guidance, training and learning to take on board &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of the 2007 Road Death Investigation Manual (RDIM) – the guiding doctrine of &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the 43 police forces of England and Wales to investigate and report on collisions that have resulted in a death. This is expected to be published in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report which sets out the next steps of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; is currently being finalised for publication next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laser-scanners"&gt;Laser scanners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laser Scanning Technology (LST) saves time by quickly making a 3D image of the whole incident scene, rather than investigators painstakingly surveying multiple sections of a scene. This digital image of the site can then be viewed on a computer screen remotely allowing investigators to take measurements of where vehicles are in relation to each other and examine other important evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009, the Highways Agency carried out an independent trial of 3D laser scanning technology using results from separate trials conducted by the Metropolitan Police Service and Humberside Police. The trials found that on average using laser scanners saved a total of 39 minutes on investigation time per incident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;38 laser scanners were funded by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Police for use by 27 police authorities at a cost of £4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest figures relate to information compiled from incidents over 4 months from forces using them on the strategic road network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clear"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2010 the Police, Highways Agency, Ambulance and Fire Services, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and related sponsoring departments came together to review evidence and knowledge about the handling of motorway incidents, and to make recommendations for improvement  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/review-of-investigation-and-closure-procedures-for-motorway-incidents-preliminary-report/review-of-investigation-closure-procedures-motorway-incidents.pdf"&gt;resultant report, published in May 2011 as the ‘Review of investigation and closure procedures for motorways incidents’ (PDF, 345KB)&lt;/a&gt;, made 10 recommendations and came together as the &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; initiative. The recommendations included further analytical work and some more immediate actions around, for example, supporting the wider roll out of laser scanning technology for the police to assist in speeding up incident investigation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congestion on the strategic road network is estimated to cost the economy £3 billion each year, 25% of which is caused by incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single incident that closes a 3 lane motorway for 4 hours can cost several million pounds in lost time, and there are some 80,000 incidents that impact at least one motorway lane each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; makes just 5% difference to the cost of congestion on the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Road Network"&gt;SRN&lt;/abbr&gt; it could save over £30 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="incident-screens"&gt;Incident screens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 105 sets of incident screens which will be made available for use by the Highways Agency next year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each set has 30 screens which are loaded onto purpose-built trailers and can screen up to 75 metres if used end-to-end (the individual screens are approximately 2.1 by two metres high)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They cost £2.3 million with each set costing £22,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="smart-phone-app"&gt;Smart phone app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	The Highways Agency app received 5,000 hits within the first 2 months of its launch. Further &lt;a rel="external" href="http://press.highways.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Hands-free-traffic-app-makes-Highways-Agency-data-available-to-road-users-ready-for-summer-67e24.aspx"&gt;information is available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spill-kits"&gt;Spill kits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Highways Agency"&gt;HA&lt;/abbr&gt; traffic officers will be equipped with spill kits to clear up small spillages such as fuel or other fluids which leak onto the carriageways from vehicles. The spill kits will absorb small spills and will allow the road to be safely re-opened while reducing damage to the carriageway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="load-cells"&gt;Load Cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load cells will be fitted to the tow straps used by traffic officers and will allow them to clear live lanes - moving heavier or damaged vehicles to the nearest place of safety.  The load cell acts as a strain gauge and will ensure that the safe towing load is not exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60863</id>
    <published>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-forces-mark-christmas-in-helmand"/>
    <title>British Forces mark Christmas in Helmand </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British forces in southern Afghanistan mark Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;British forces serving in southern Afghanistan have been marking Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province today (25 December).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities took place as the troops completed a full day of operational duties.  Many soldiers from the UK-led Task Force Helmand spent the day on patrol in support of the Afghan security forces, yet still most found time to open presents and ring home – and enjoy a freshly-prepared Christmas lunch with all the trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-post"&gt;Christmas post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last-minute festive cheer was provided by the Post and Courier Squadron as tonnes of mail arrived at a number of forward locations, delivered by Chinook helicopter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing last minute festive cheer on Christmas morning, 78 sacks of post (1 tonne) arrived by helicopter in Main Operating Base (&lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) Lashkar Gah – home to the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; (‘Black Rats’) headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5819/Xmas_post_delivery_helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province, Afghanistan&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a chilly Christmas morning, in &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; over 100 soldiers and civilians took part in the ‘Lash Dash’ 5km run around the base.  Many completed the course in fancy dress, with proceeds from the event split between two charities: the Lashkar Gah Orphanage and The Black Rat Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the male and female winners were Danish soldiers. The Brits fared better in the fancy dress competition with Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant’s General Corps, Royal Military Police) winning by running dressed as a well-wrapped Christmas present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5818/LashDash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant General Corps, Royal Military Police) won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="working-day"&gt;Working day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, is another working day for all military here in Helmand. As the sun rose on Christmas morning, troops from the Royal Dragoon Guards and the Royal Military Police set off on patrol to the Provincial Police Headquarters to train Afghan Police. The ‘train the trainer’ course sees Afghan Police qualifying to teach police skills. This will allow British troops to step back as the Afghan Security Forces take the lead in training their own forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-lunches-and-all-the-trimmings"&gt;Christmas lunches and all the trimmings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full Christmas lunch, including all the trimmings, was served in the cookhouses of Camp Bastion, &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; Lashkar Gah and patrol bases across Helmand. Even the troops manning the security towers or sangars surrounding Camp Bastion were not forgotten and enjoyed personal deliveries of hot food.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5820/Xmas_dinner_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Baldwin kitchen manager from KBR in Camp Bastion said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is the full Christmas celebration for the troops in Bastion.  This includes a traditional Christmas lunch consisting of roast beef, pork, turkey, sprouts, roast potatoes and pudding and mince pies. We are cooking for roughly about 4,000 people - ranging from 140 joints of beef, 200 turkeys, 120 gammons – that’s what it take to feed these guys.  Also using 40 boxes of brussel spouts, 150 bags of potatoes, it’s on a massive scale.  It also includes litres of gravy, tomato soup – it’s a big operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="presents-for-all-serving-personnel"&gt;Presents for all serving personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5821/Xmas_presents_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing a little Christmas cheer to forces overseas every year is the UK based charity called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4uThanks!"&gt;uk4uThanks!&lt;/a&gt;  This is an organisation funded by money donated by members of the public. The presents (affectionately known as the ‘square stocking’) act as a gift from the nation to all those serving in the UK Armed Forces overseas away from their families and loved ones on Christmas Day.  The boxes, containing a host of goodies from business sponsors and bought with money donated from members of the public, were delivered in time to be opened on Christmas Day.  Much speculation abounds as to the contents of the boxes and it is never a disappointment as much thought is put into providing amusing and useful gifts away from home at Christmas time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60858</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>"Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New style local settlement to reward striving councils with more income.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles spelled out 50 sensible savings, a Council Tax freeze and a fair funding deal as the “right road” for councils to protect residents and local services, as a major shake up of local finance was initiated today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister signalled the watershed moment for councils as he unveiled a new look local government finance settlement that will reward councils that strive to improve their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dramatic shift in spending power from Whitehall to the town hall means an estimated 70% of council income will now be raised locally compared to 56% under the centrally distributed ‘begging-bowl’ formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013 councils can channel this greater local control into encouraging local jobs and local firms via a new business rate retention incentive that rewards them for growth. It could potentially add £10 billion to the economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, councils account for a quarter of all public spending - with English councils still spending £114 billion - so it is vital they continue to play their part tackling the inherited budget deficit by making sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help councils in that regard a document containing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;50 practical ways to make sensible savings&lt;/a&gt; was published today. It shows how a culture change by councils can unearth significantly more taxpayer savings and help make services more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must keep doing their bit to tackle the inherited budget deficit because they account for a quarter of all public spending and still get through over £114 billion of taxpayers money each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement is a fair funding deal that will reward councils ready to strive for their communities and gives them another year to get their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must do 3 things to get on the right road for their residents: put our fair funding deal to work; do every single one of our 50 ways to save; and accept our Council Tax freeze offer. Councils that cry wolf without having done all of this are letting their residents down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils that put their thinking caps on now can save precious taxpayer pennies next year by cutting out waste and transforming frontline services that vulnerable people rely on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s fair funding deal arms councils with an average spending power of £2,240 per household. Local authorities have been protected from further spending reductions for 2013 to 2014. Overall the average spending power reduction for councils in 2013 to 2014 is expected to be limited to just 1.7% per household, less than last year’s comparable figure of 3.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe this important concession gives councils the time they need to transform service delivery, build up their local business rate income, improve procurement and comprehensively complete the suggested 50 savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total start-up funding assessment for councils 2013 to 2014 apportions £26 billion in a fair and sustainable way that ensures the smallest reductions for the councils most reliant on government support. More weighting has been given to areas with the highest levels of assessed need. For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is setting aside an extra £450 million over the next 2 years to help local government in England to freeze their Council Tax, equivalent to a 1% rise. A third year’s combined Council Tax freeze is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government confirmed today that where a council rejects the freeze, the majority will have to secure electoral agreement through a ‘local tax lock’ referendum to hike band D bills by more than 2%. Smaller authorities with a track record of low Council Tax will be given slightly more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘50 ways to save’ include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing back offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting Community Budgets to bring staff and money together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using transparency to cut waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clamping down on corporate charge cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting special spending controls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling the £2 billion of local fraud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising £16 billion of non-school reserves creatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve collection rates to reduce the £2.4 billion of uncollected Council Tax across England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage direct debit and e-billing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve property management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close subsidised council canteens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing senior pay and posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut spending on consultants and agency staff which had risen to £4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stop translating documents into foreign languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut expensive travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce printing costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hire out the town hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; for the full list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 20 December 2012, the day after the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement, Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis MP hosted a teleconference call for local authorities and fire &amp;amp; rescue services, fielding more than 25 questions from 200 callers. You can listen to the call &lt;a rel="external" href="http://bit.ly/Ul5u6X"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 to 2014 spending power calculation includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£26.07 billion start up funding assessment (which includes £10.9 billion of locally retained business rates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£23.9 billion in Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£859 million for NHS funding to support social care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£661 million via New Homes Bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£240 million for 2013 to 2014 Council Tax freeze grant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition local authorities will also benefit from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£112 million via the Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£33.5 million via New Burdens for Council Tax Support in 2013 to 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/spending-power-by-local-authority"&gt;Spending power data by local authority for 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;No authority will see a spending power reduction of more than 8.8% because of decisions taken by ministers to make an efficiency support grant available. The ‘per household’ figures are calculated using total spending power a combination of the new start up funding assessment and Council Tax, and the number of dwellings by Council Tax band for each administrative area in England. The counts are calculated from data for England extracted from the Valuation Office Agency’s database on 12 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;plain English guide&lt;/a&gt; to cut through Whitehall jargon and explain the new settlement system is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a period of statutory consultation on the settlement which runs to 15 January 2013. Ministers will then finalise their proposals and the settlement for 2013 to 2014 will be debated in Parliament in February in time for councils to set their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement committed the government to relinquishing control over excessive Council Tax increases and giving that democratic power directly to local communities. This was legislated for through the Localism Act. The government has today published the Council Tax principles it is proposing for 2013 to 2014. Council Tax increases would trigger a referendum, if they exceed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2% for most principal authorities; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 (which ever is higher) in the case of shire district councils, police and crime commissioners and fire and rescue authorities that set the lowest quartile of Council Tax in their class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final principles for 2013 to 2014 will be set out in a report for the approval of the House of Commons early next year, at the same time as the final report on the local government finance settlement. No equivalent principles are being proposed for town and parish councils for 2013 to 2014, although they may in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical data for the 2013-14 Local Government Finance Settlement can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;Local Government Finance site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have been protected with savings back loaded to allow time for sensible savings; they have also benefited from the protection to local government in 2013 to 2014. In addition the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, has been asked to carry out a review to pinpoint ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money. The government intends to announce the breakdown of £140 million of capital grant money to fire and rescue authorities. The money for 2013 to 2015 will be distributed by a combination of formula and for projects to fire and rescue authorities that have been successful through bidding. All fire and rescue authorities will receive some capital funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60315</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-warship-spends-christmas-on-operations"/>
    <title>Royal Navy warship spends Christmas on operations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sailors of HMS Monmouth keeping the oceans safe from criminals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While their families celebrate Christmas at home, the crew of  the Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate, will be spending Christmas engaged in countering piracy, smuggling and similar illegal activity. The ship, also known as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="the Black Duke"&gt;the Black Duke&lt;/a&gt; after its traitor namesake, is part of a coalition naval force policing the Gulf and keeping crucial trade routes safe for the UK’s imports and exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of the busy programme, members of the crew have found some time to prepare for the festivities with both the chaplain and the chefs limbering-up for the seasonal cheer and religious service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Chef Paul Gough said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve stocked the freezers in anticipation that we’ll be getting through more than two hundred pounds of turkey, beef and gammon for Christmas lunch; and yes, we’ve also made sure we’ve got plenty of sprouts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5807/Xmas_operations_room__HMS_Monmouth_2012.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It's beginning to look at lot like Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reverend Andrew Allcock, the ship’s chaplain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas is often a time for both celebration and reflection – the latter probably more so this year as we are away from home. It’s my hope that most people on board will have an opportunity to do both with our Christmas services including a traditional midnight communion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship will be patrolling the Gulf region until her return to the UK in the spring. While principal tasks on this deployment involve intercepting and boarding suspect vessels, HMS Monmouth is also ready and equipped to provide humanitarian aid or mount an evacuation in the case of war or natural disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60856</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T09:14:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T09:14:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-baroness-warsi-statement-on-the-murder-of-bashir-ahmed-bilour"/>
    <title>FCO Minister Baroness Warsi statement on the murder of Bashir Ahmed Bilour</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior Minister of State Baroness Warsi expresses her sadness at the murder of Pakistani minister Bashir Ahmed Bilour on Saturday.
 </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was deeply saddened to hear of the death of Bashir Ahmed Bilour and my thoughts are with his family and friends and those of the others killed and wounded in this vicious attack, an attack which I and the UK Government utterly condemns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr Bilour was a courageous and vocal opponent of extremism and refused to be silenced by those who threatened him.  His absence will be felt keenly in Pakistani politics. His enduring legacy will be the many people he inspired to speak out against terror and work to build a peaceful, democratic society for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
