<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-08T14:33:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9720</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:33:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:33:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-taskforce-to-end-the-problem-of-beds-in-sheds--3"/>
    <title>National taskforce to end the problem of 'beds in sheds'</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new national taskforce has been set up to tackle the issue of “beds in sheds” by taking action against criminal landlords and removing illegal immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Housing Minister Grant Shapps and Immigration Minister Damian Green held the first in a series of cross-Whitehall summits with representatives from the police, the UK Border Agency and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meetings will find ways to close down thousands of sheds and outbuildings being rented out illegally to migrants, including some with no right to be in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘tenants’ are being exploited by ruthless landlords who charge them extortionate rents to live in cramped conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These modern day shanty towns, often visible on websites such as Google Earth, can be plagued with rats and cockroaches - and are potential death traps with dodgy wiring and poor sanitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some foreign ‘tenants’ wish to return home but, after destroying their passports to avoid removal, find it difficult to do so quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Mr Shapps and Mr Green discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encouraging councils to make greater use of legal powers across planning, fire safety, housing and environmental health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to better measure the extent and nature of the problem, drawing on information collected by Whitehall and Town Halls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how best to ensure councils and the police share the intelligence available and enforcement activity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closer working with organisations such as the Indian High Commission to help those wanting to return home; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;steps to prevent more “beds in sheds” from being created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a scandal that these back garden slums exist to exploit people, many of whom are prepared to return voluntarily to their home country but instead find themselves trapped into paying extortionate rents to live in these cramped conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I want to see a crackdown on these criminal landlords. So today we are launching a national taskforce, made up of the police, local councils, the UK Border Agency and HM Revenue and Customs to close down these ‘beds in sheds’, help those living there to be reunited with their families and ensure their so-called landlords feel the full force of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immigration Minister Damian Green said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those with no right to be in the UK must leave the country. If they volunteer to leave, we will help. If they refuse, we will enforce their removal.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The UK Border Agency will do whatever is necessary, working with local authorities and the police, to clear up this problem and enforce our laws against those who are in the UK illegally and the employers who exploit them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This work is well under way - many individuals have already been removed from the UK and further enforcement visits will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some councils have argued that they need to have a new legal power of entry into premises without notice. However, councils already have this ability provided they obtain a magistrates’ warrant - which provides a proportionate check and balance on the use of such powers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64247</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:20:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-geraint-jones-appointed-as-reviewer-for-the-office-for-fair-access"/>
    <title>Press Release: Geraint Jones appointed as reviewer for the Office For Fair Access</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, announced today that he is appointing Geraint Jones as the statutory reviewer for OFFA. Should a university or college object to a provisional decision by the Director of Fair Access, the reviewer can be asked to assess the case impartially. He may recommend that there are grounds for the Director to reconsider his decision.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geraint Jones QC was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge before going to the Bar in 1976. He took silk in 2001 and is now recognised as a leading commercial and Chancery practitioner with extensive experience of judicial review work. He has an undoubted reputation for fearless independence and impartiality in upholding the rule of law. He sits as a Recorder and as a part-time Judge of the Tax Tribunal. He is also an arbitrator at the International Court of Arbitration for Sport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that Geraint Jones will be the reviewer for OFFA, his skills and experience, if called upon, will be of great value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The position of statutory reviewer for OFFA has been in place since OFFA was established in 2004. So far there has been no need to call upon the services of the statutory reviewer. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the ‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB), published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64262</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:10:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-new-proposals-to-stand-up-for-british-pubs-and-prevent-unfair-practices"/>
    <title>Press Release: New proposals to stand up for British pubs and prevent unfair practices</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans for pub industry adjudicator to help tackle unfair practices, including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling pub landlords were promised help today with Business Secretary Vince Cable announcing plans for an independent Adjudicator to address unfair practices in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the new Adjudicator Dr Cable also wants to establish a new statutory Code to look at the relationship between large pub companies and publicans, which will be enforced by the Adjudicator. This new Code will ensure fair practices for a number of issues including rents and the prices publicans pay for beer. It would also have the power to investigate and deal with disputes between pub companies (pubcos) and publicans, and in some cases have the power to fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the proposed Code would prevent abuses of the beer tie, which oblige publicans to sell particular types of beer. It would enshrine the fundamental principle that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’ which will ensure a level playing field is maintained in the pub sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some real hardship in the pubs sector, with many pubs going to the wall as publicans struggling to survive on tiny margins.  Some of this is due to pubcos exploiting and squeezing their publicans by unfair practices and a focus on short-term profits. Four Select Committee reviews since 2004 have highlighted these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we gave the pubcos one last chance to change their behaviour but it is clear that the self-regulatory approach was not enough and in October I wrote to the industry to seek their views. A change in the law is now needed to shift behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hope these measures mean publicans are given a fairer chance at running their pub, which in turn will help them grow their businesses instead of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal consultation on these proposed measures will be launched in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposed Code will be based on the existing Industry Framework Code but will be strengthened to include an overarching ‘fair dealing’ provision, and also the principle referring to the beer tie which states that ‘a tied licensee should be no worse off than a free-of-tie-licensee’. This will be particularly important for rents, as the consultation will propose that guidance issued by the Royal Institute of Chartered Surveyors be interpreted in light of this principle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proposed Adjudicator will be based on the model of the widely-welcomed Groceries Code Adjudicator, and will have the power and function to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arbitrate individual disputes between large pub companies and publicans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry out investigations based on complaints that have been received, during which they could require information from pub companies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;impose sanctions where an investigation finds that a pub company has breached the Code – including, in the case of severe breaches, financial penalties&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;publish guidance on when and how investigations will proceed and how these enforcement powers will be used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise pub companies and publicans on the Code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;report annually on his or her work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recommend changes to the Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Code is expected to apply to all pub companies which own more than 500 tied leases, exempting smaller companies so that only those with the greatest market power are targeted. This is due to evidence indicating that smaller companies have been behaving responsibly, although this will be explored further during the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about the relationship between pubcos and publicans have been raised by the pub industry for many years, with BIS Select Committee Reports highlighting the issue continuously since 2009. In 2011 the Committee recommended that the Government implement a binding industry Code and establish a Code Adjudicator. In November 2011 the Government announced a self regulatory approach, with the Code being brought into legal contracts and the industry establishing an independent arbitrator and advisory services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent arbitration service appears to be working well, with two of the three cases heard so far finding against the pubcos. Version 5 of the Industry Framework Code was incorporated into contracts by the end of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following further concerns raised by the BIS Select Committee the Secretary of State wrote to the industry to ask for evidence on how well the self-regulatory approach was working. Many responses showed some improvements had been made, but that much more was needed and that the necessary culture change had not taken place. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64214</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T11:41:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T11:41:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-chief-executive-designate-appointed-to-the-competition-and-markets-authority"/>
    <title>Press Release: Chief Executive Designate appointed to the Competition and Markets Authority</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alex Chisholm was today appointed the new Chief Executive of the Competition and Markets Authority by the Business Secretary Vince Cable.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a single, streamlined authority, the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) will drive competition policy. There are substantial economic benefits from a tough regime cracking down hard and quickly on cartels and monopolies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very pleased that Mr Chisholm is joining the CMA as Chief Executive, to lead the organisation alongside the Chair, Lord Currie. His expertise in economic regulation and wider experience in business and the public sector will play a crucial role strengthening the UK’s world class competition regime, building on the excellent record of the Office of Fair Trading and Competition Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMA Chair, Lord David Currie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I greatly look forward to working with Alex Chisholm to make the Competition and Markets Authority a world class competition and consumer protection body, that will generate major benefits for the British economy and for consumers and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMA Chief Executive Designate Alex Chisholm said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have the opportunity to lead the establishment of the Competition and Markets Authority, which has a vital part to play in helping competition and markets to thrive during this time of significant economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I look forward to working with the Office of Fair Trading and the Competition Commission, and with the wider government, business and consumer communities, to ensure the new authority is dynamic, efficient and accountable”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Chisholm will take up his five year appointment on 25 March 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="biography"&gt;Biography&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since October 2007 Alex Chisholm has been Commissioner at the Commission for Communications Regulation (ComReg) Ireland, and Chairperson of the Commission since February 2010. Since April 2011, Mr Chisholm has also served as Chair of the Economic Regulators Network in Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining ComReg, Mr Chisholm held a number of executive positions in the media, IT and communications industries, including Chief Executive of Ecceleration Ltd, Ecommerce Director at eCountries Inc, Publisher and General Manager in the Financial Times Group, and Development Manager at Pearson plc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also served for six years in the UK’s Department of Trade &amp;amp; Industry and Office of Fair Trading, specialising in competition policy and the media, communications and financial services sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm holds an MBA from INSEAD Business School (1997) and an MA from Oxford University (1989). In August 2012 he completed the Senior Managers in Government programme at the Harvard Kennedy School. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm is also currently involved in charitable work as Trustee and Deputy Chairman of the international charity Breadline Africa. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive will be the Accounting Officer for the CMA and a member of the CMA Board. He will lead the organisational design of the CMA and shaping of its competition processes. The Chief Executive will take ownership of the shadow organisation and along with the Chair Designate, will drive forward the creation of the CMA in bringing together the Office of Fair Trading (OFT) and the Competition Commission (CC) as a single, unified body by April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive’s appointment will be subject to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill receiving Royal Assent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chief Executive’s remuneration will be £190k per annum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The appointment was made on merit in accordance with the Civil Service Commissioner’s Recruitment Principles.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr Chisholm has no current conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government announced its plans for the creation of the CMA in March 2012. It will bring together the CC and the competition, markets and some consumer protection functions of the OFT to become a world-leading unitary authority, advocating competition both at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government recognises and values the close relationship between competition problems and consumer activities.  The CMA will therefore have the OFT and Competition Commission’s full competition toolkit and consumer protection enforcement powers.  It will have the power to tackle practices and market conditions that make it difficult for consumers to exercise choice in an otherwise competitive market.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unified CMA will bring about significant benefits to business and consumers, including greater coherence, flexibility, speed and transparency in the operation of the competition regime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64184</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T08:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-driving-tests-at-halfords"/>
    <title>Green light for driving tests at Halfords</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Plans to offer practical driving tests from branches of Halfords have been given the go ahead by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving tests will be available from the Halfords store in Wellingborough from Tuesday 5 February. Other branches of Halfords across the country are expected to start offering tests in coming months. All tests will be conducted by Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) examiners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move is part of an initiative to offer a more local service for driving test candidates. As well as using conventional test centres, &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working with public and private sector partners to provide driving tests in areas that don’t have a local test centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very pleased to be working with Halfords to provide a more local service for driving test candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great example of working with private sector partners to provide an important local service that is convenient as well as being cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfords Commercial Director, Paul McClenaghan, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Halfords is already a local destination for motorists, who come to us for a diverse range of automotive products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re always seeking new ways in which to enhance our offer, so working with the Driving Standards Agency is a natural fit for the business and extends the help we are able to provide to motorists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is currently consulting on proposals to improve the way all motoring services are delivered. The &lt;a href="/government/consultations/motoring-services-strategy" title="Motoring Services Strategy"&gt;Motoring Services Strategy&lt;/a&gt; consultation outlines long term proposals to put customers firmly at the heart of the way motoring services are delivered, so that they best serve the consumer while getting the best possible deal for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64193</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T06:42:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T06:42:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/fatalities/soldier-from-28-engineer-regiment-killed-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Soldier from 28 Engineer Regiment killed in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>Fatality notice</category>
    <summary>It is with great sadness that the Ministry of Defence must announce that a soldier from 28 Engineer Regiment, attached to 21 Engineer Regiment, was killed in Afghanistan on Monday 7 January 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The soldier was killed by small arms fire from a suspected member of the Afghan National Army (ANA) who turned his weapon on ANA and ISAF (International Security Assistance Force) soldiers at Patrol Base Hazrat in the Nahr-e Saraj district of Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spokesman for Task Force Helmand, Major Laurence Roche, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is my painful duty to report the death of a soldier from 28 Engineer Regiment who was shot and killed by a suspected member of the Afghan National Army at a patrol base in the Nahr-e Saraj district of Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is an extremely sad day for the Corps of Royal Engineers and everyone serving with Task Force Helmand. Our thoughts are with the soldier’s family and friends at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soldier’s family have been informed and have asked for a period of grace before further details are released.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64191</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:59:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:59:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"/>
    <title>2013 should be ‘year of peace’ for people in the Middle East</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary says 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, he reaffirms UK’s support for a political transition in Syria. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today met Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States. Following the meeting the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to welcome Mr Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States, to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We discussed the Middle East Peace Process and agreed that 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation.  We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.  We agreed that Arab League and EU member states needed to assist the Palestinian Authority to overcome its current financial difficulties and that  Israel should fulfil its obligations to transfer customs revenues due to the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also discussed the situation in Syria, and efforts to achieve a political transition and an end to the violence. We reiterated our support for UN and Arab League Special Representative Brahimi’s efforts to advance a credible political solution to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK believes that President Assad can never recover legitimacy in the eyes of the Syrian people.  His latest promises of token reforms demonstrate his increasingly desperate attempts to hold on to power. As well as supporting a political transition the UK will continue our humanitarian assistance, our work to support those documenting human rights violations in Syria, and our non-lethal support for the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64188</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"/>
    <title>Minister “dismayed” at verdict in Bahraini activists’ appeal </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt, has called on Bahrain to guarantee its citizens’ fundamental liberties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court today upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. Commenting earlier, Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am deeply dismayed at the decision of the Bahraini Cassation Court to uphold the sentences of 13 political activists in today’s appeal hearing. At the time these individuals were sentenced, reports which were acknowledged by the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry suggested that some had been abused in detention, denied access to legal counsel and were coerced into confessing. I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bahrain-independent-commission-of-inquiry-bici"&gt;Minister comments on Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64090</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-social-tenants-to-have-their-say-on-local-services"/>
    <title>Support for social tenants to have their say on local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk today launched a new training programme designed to put power firmly in the hands of social tenants.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He launched the £1.2 million Tenant Training and Support Programme to give residents the skills they need to hold their landlord to account, whether on their own, by setting up a tenant panel, or by taking over the management and maintenance of their homes and neighbourhoods themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boost in funding will offer a way for residents to ensure they get the service they deserve and that landlords offer the best possible value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said this new training programme would empower residents to take the first crucial step to having the necessary know-how to use their powers and take control in their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="empowering-tenants"&gt;Empowering tenants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/"&gt;Tenant Participation Advisory Service&lt;/a&gt;, the programme offers advice, training and support to tenants by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing tenants together from different neighbourhoods to discuss their experiences and inspire new tenant panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping individual tenants to engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offering face-to-face training with expert advisors for around 5,000 tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a tenant training programme to help them make the most of the powers they have, from accredited courses to local training systems and e-learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By doing this, new and existing social tenants will be equipped with the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be able to sign up to Community Cashback, which enables tenants to take over the management of their neighbourhood, from overseeing maintenance and minor repairs to signing up new contractors to run cleaning services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country want to use the powers they have to ensure their needs are reflected in the services they receive. But many simply lack the confidence to challenge the people in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why we’ve put this new tenant training scheme in place, helping make their voices heard and giving people the skills they need to ensure the changes that matter to them are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by playing this enhanced role tenants can help landlords improve the efficiency of local services and their work will help inspire even more communities to take control.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Meakin, Tenant Participation Advisory Service chair said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is exactly the programme we’ve all been waiting for. I urge any tenant who wants to be involved and make a difference in their community to get in touch and take advantage of the free support and training on offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples-of-effective-tenant-involvement"&gt;Examples of effective tenant involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helena Partnerships&lt;/em&gt; has set up the tenant-led customer excellence panel to challenge their landlord on performance and service delivery. It sets its own review programme, commissions mystery shoppers and has unfettered access to Helena’s performance and complaints information, customer surveys, activity-based costing and customer insight data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel carries out tenant-led peer reviews and hosts a series of webinars to engage with other organisations involved in scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works closely with Helena’s young inspectors - a group of under 25’s who play an active role in testing and challenging services while gaining transferable skills for employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel’s work has been responsible for a number of practical changes to Helena services to reflect the needs of tenants and delivered value for money savings, including tailored rent statements, extended repairs appointment times and changes to the complaints service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tower Hamlets, &lt;em&gt;Poplar HARCA&lt;/em&gt; (8,500 homes) is committed to helping social tenants to play a key role in their local housing. Recognising the benefits of tenant empowerment, the association enables democratically elected residents to monitor services on each of the association’s 12 estates, where they have delegated budgets enabling them to make community improvements. Additionally, tenant board members scrutinise the association’s policies and initiatives, challenging senior managers and making recommendations for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents can also use their local knowledge to try to resolve complaints about the association’s services. A youth empowerment board has been set up, comprising 30 young people drawn from across the estates, to ensure that the views of young people are heard. In total, over 300 residents are directly involved in decision making, performance monitoring and complaints handling at the association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding of almost £1.2 million will be made to the Tenant Participation Advisory Service to deliver a training and support programme. For further information on the programme visit their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/tenantcentral"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow DCLG’s Tenant Empowerment Team on Twitter (&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/TenantPower"&gt;@TenantPower&lt;/a&gt;) for all the latest news and updates on this programme and other activities to empower the lives of social tenants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64086</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T10:28:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-7-january-2013"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 7 January 2013</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Stephen Hammond MP provides an overview of the last EU Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the last Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council agreed a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. Following widespread criticism of the commission’s proposal at the October Transport Council, the UK has been an active and leading negotiator at the working group meetings chaired by the presidency. The presidency subsequently presented a compromise text that reflected the reality of member states’ road safety testing practices. We supported the change of the legal form of the proposal from a (directly applicable) regulation to a directive (which gives member states some flexibility in transposition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcomed the many improvements in the presidency’s text which had substantially reduced the cost implications to a manageable level, and indicated that the UK could accept the presidency’s text.  I made clear that as negotiations begin with the European Parliament, we would seek to provide members of the European Parliament with as much information as possible to explain why the changes to the original proposal were both justified, and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presidency provided progress reports on 2 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council establishing the Connecting Europe Facility. This regulation will provide the legal basis for funding of trans-European transport, energy and telecoms networks for 2014 to 2020. The text will not be finalised until the budget figures for 2014 to 2020 have been agreed in discussions on the Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The council’s position on this regulation, which will provide the legal basis for taking forward the Galileo satellite navigation programme from 2014, was agreed earlier in the year. However, technical discussions with the European Parliament since then have not led to much progress. The dossier will be passed to the Irish Presidency to conclude negotiations with the European Parliament once the budget for Galileo under the &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; has been confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The commission welcomed the conclusions, highlighting in particular the worsening aviation relationship with Russia, especially Russia’s ongoing refusal to implement its commitments on Siberian overflight charges. The commissioner called for collective action at EU level and said he would be producing a roadmap in the new year with a view to pursuing an EU/Russia comprehensive agreement in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council also adopted a proposal for a decision on the comprehensive aviation agreement between the EU and its member states and Israel. The original plan had been for the agreement to be signed in the margins of the council, but due to internal political reasons, Israel was not able to sign at this time. The commission hoped that Israel would be in a position to sign this agreement shortly after national elections in the Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high level cooperation agreement with Eurocontrol (European Organisation for the Safety of Air Navigation) was signed in the margins of the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the commission provided an update on recent discussions at the International Civil Aviation Organisation to agree a global approach to tackling emissions from aviation. The commission clarified that it was proposing a temporary derogation on enforcement of the Aviation Emissions Trading System (ETS) relating to international flights and hoped the European Parliament and the council would approve this through a decision in the first quarter of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under any other business, France tabled a room document which called for a discussion to be held in the International Maritime Organization on the 2015 deadline for implementing the new requirements on the sulphur content of marine fuels. A number of member states intervened and stressed that they would be keen to discuss practical issues, such as the cost of low sulphur fuels to businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cleaner Power for Transport Package which was due to be discussed as an &lt;abbr title="any other business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt; item was taken off the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Brown &lt;abbr title="Member of the Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSP&lt;/abbr&gt;, Scottish Minister for Transport and Veterans also attended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64224</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T12:52:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/why-we-must-continue-to-tackle-far-right-extremism-head-on"/>
    <title>Why we must continue to tackle far right extremism head on</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Don Foster to council leaders at the first meeting of the national special interest group on the far right.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all - thank you for inviting me here today and thank you for the work you are doing for each of your councils. I would have loved to have stayed for the whole day but I am told that you have a lot of work to do and so I am looking forward to hearing how the day went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremism is an affront to our society in every form, including the far right and the English Defence League (&lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt;) - they are divisive and create fear in our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right does not belong in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially following a year when the Olympics changed the way we see ourselves - gave us real confidence as a society with shared values. The Olympics showed how brilliantly our communities can come together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We basked in the glory of our country’s sporting success stories, whatever their background, skin colour or religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the Secretary of State is passionate about tackling extremism - his commitment is shared by the Prime Minster, the Deputy Prime Minister and across government - everyone is sickened by the messages and activities of the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; and their ilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us share a personal commitment to tackling them. In fact one of the reasons I came into politics was because many years ago the National Front were allowed to hire my children’s school to use as a meeting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their ugly messages and actions could not go ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I campaigned against them to get them out of my children’s school and back into the wilderness where they belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we have the English Defence League marching up and down our streets on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causing local shops and businesses to lose money just when they are struggling with the downturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And causing fear across our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/creating-the-conditions-for-a-more-integrated-society"&gt;Creating the conditions for integration&lt;/a&gt;’ published last February, the government set out its approach to creating and sustaining strong communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major part of the approach is to tackle extremism and intolerance head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right must be isolated, undermined, outflanked and subject to the ridicule they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we are working in schools with 10,000 students across the country to give them the tools to reject the far-right’s messages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we are working with communities in Dudley, Croydon, Barking and Luton, training volunteers to produce community newspapers for 14,000 families that provide an alternative voice to the far right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the government is supporting over 30 projects as part of our integration strategy - you have copies today. We need to invest now to reduce the costs and impacts generated by the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that it is only at local level that we can really address the conditions the far right feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we were so pleased when Blackburn with Darwen and Luton came to us and asked for our help to set up and run this national special interest group on the far right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is through the leadership of councils like Luton, Blackburn and many others that we will ultimately succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already know that there is a lot of good work going on in places up and down the country:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in Luton they have the ‘Luton in Harmony’ campaign involving nearly 70,000 Luton residents saying loud and clear that they do not want the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; in their towns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Blackburn they have the ‘hundred voice’ campaign, which puts people at extreme ends of the spectrum of opinions in the same room as each other to thrash it out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are fantastic innovative responses to the challenges we face by the far right but even more is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is critical if we are to succeed in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you that the far right has taken a battering but is still on the move - they haven’t managed to attract the numbers of supporters on marches that they did in their heyday in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to this year, we expect that the &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue to decline in numbers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they will still manage to get enough supporters out for marches in towns and cities across 2013 - enough to cause disruption and fear.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know that there are splinter groups appearing across the country threatening flash demonstrations and direct action - the Infidels and the English Volunteer Force are just two examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the good work that local authorities and the police have done in minimising the impacts of these people has had an effect but clearly as I said there is more to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local leadership is absolutely critical in succeeding in smashing the far right in our local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this leadership look like? What does it do? How does it keep its head above the parapet at all times, not just in the run up to &lt;abbr title="English Defence League"&gt;EDL&lt;/abbr&gt; demonstrations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is what we are here for today. I would encourage you all to look at the 30 or so projects the government is supporting. These projects include everything from music projects bringing different communities together for a common purpose, to looking at getting scouts and cadets groups in more areas, particularly areas where they may not have existed before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As leaders in your communities you will know this better than us. We look forward to hearing the ideas you come up with and to you sharing them with those leaders who couldn’t make it here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am interested in hearing proposals for innovative projects for undermining extremists of all stripes, so please share your ideas with me and we will see what we can do to support you. There may even be some money for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64021</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:57:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wwii-airman-celebrates-100th-birthday"/>
    <title>WWII airman celebrates 100th birthday</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A former Second World War Spitfire pilot celebrated his 100th birthday on New Year's Day.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On New Year’s Day, family, staff and residents at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.veterans-uk.info/new_ipph/ipph.html" title="Ilford Park Polish Home pages on the Veterans UK website"&gt;Ilford Park Polish Home&lt;/a&gt; in Devon joined their oldest resident, former Spitfire pilot Mieczyslaw Juny &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;, for his 100th birthday celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny was born in Lwow, Poland, on 1 January 1913. At the age of 26, he took part in the Polish Campaign of 1939. After Poland fell to German forces, he escaped to Hungary and was taken as a prisoner of war. He escaped again and eventually found himself aboard the ship ‘Empress of Canada’ in March 1943 as she sailed from Durban with 1,800 passengers. On 13 March, 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometres) off the coast of Africa, she was torpedoed and sank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surviving the waters of the Atlantic, Mr Juny found his way to the UK. He transferred to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/online-exhibitions/the-polish-air-force-in-world-war-2.aspx" title="The Polish Air Force in WWII - information from the RAF Museum"&gt;Polish Air Force&lt;/a&gt; as a flight lieutenant and served alongside his British RAF colleagues as a Spitfire pilot for 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny during the Second World War" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5856/Mr_Juny_in_1940s.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny during the Second World War [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the war, Mr Juny worked for the National Assistance Board, rehoming Polish people who had been decommissioned from the armed forces but could not return to Poland because of the political changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years as a civil servant working at Ilford Park, he was awarded an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for his service to Polish people in the UK in 1975 before retiring as Deputy Manager in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny continues to reside at Ilford Park, now managed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.veterans-uk.info/" title="Veterans UK website"&gt;Service Personnel and Veterans Agency&lt;/a&gt;, and has been the longstanding chair of the residents’ committee. In 2003, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pcmew.org/" title="The Polish Catholic Mission in England and Wales website"&gt;Polish Catholic Mission&lt;/a&gt; awarded him the Cross of Merit. He was further decorated in 2005, when the outgoing president of the Republic of Poland, Aleksander Kwasniewski, awarded Mr Juny the Knight’s Cross of the Order of Polonia Restituta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny wearing his medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5857/Mr_Juny_with_Medals.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny wearing his medals at Polish Independence Day celebrations [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being 100 years old is a funny feeling; it is not normal for human beings to live this long. It is exciting to tell people that I am 100 years old, and people are excited to hear this. I don’t know why I have been chosen to live so long, but I notice more and more beauty in the world as I get older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilford Park Manager Clare Thomas said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr Juny is an inspiration to us all and is a role model of grace and humanity. He has been so determined to reach this birthday. He desperately wanted to live long enough to see the London 2012 Olympics and since then his focus has been on his birthday. It has given him a new lease of life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny with his birthday card from Her Majesty The Queen" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5858/Mr_Juny_with_card_from_HM_The_Queen.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny with his birthday card from Her Majesty The Queen [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two more of the Polish Home residents will reach their 100th birthdays this year, and Mr Juny says he wants to join them when they have their parties. And his birthday wish? To live another 50 years!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61168</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:09:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-invites-tenders-for-uk-construction-projects"/>
    <title>MOD invites tenders for UK construction projects</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Ten private sector companies have been invited to tender for a new framework agreement to deliver construction projects across the UK Defence estate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The companies shortlisted for the framework by the Defence Infrastructure Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;) are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.balfourbeatty.com/" title="Balfour Beatty website"&gt;Balfour Beatty Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bam.co.uk/Construction/Construction-Overview.aspx" title="BAM Construction website"&gt;BAM Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.carillionplc.com/our-capabilities/construction-services.aspx" title="Carillion Construction website"&gt;Carillion Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.interserve.com/" title="Interserve website"&gt;Interserve Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kier.co.uk/" title="Kier Group website"&gt;Kier Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lendlease.com/worldwide/capabilities/project-management-and-construction.aspx" title="Lend Lease Construction website"&gt;Lend Lease Construction (EMEA) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millerconstruction.co.uk/" title="Miller Construction website"&gt;Miller Construction (UK) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://construction.morgansindall.com/" title="Morgan Sindall Construction website"&gt;Morgan Sindall plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.skanska.co.uk/" title="Skanska website"&gt;Skanska UK plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wates.co.uk/" title="Wates website"&gt;Wates Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Capital Works Framework will be used for the design and build of construction projects up to a value of £50 million. It will include up to 5 companies who will participate in ‘mini-competitions’ for individual projects. It is due to be awarded before the end of 2013 and will run for an initial 4-year period, with the potential to extend for up to 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework forms part of the &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; Next Generation Estate Contracts (&lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme, and will operate alongside 6 regional capital works frameworks for projects valued below £12 million. It has an estimated value of between £250 million and £400 million over the 4-year period and could be used at any site across the UK estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, the shortlisted companies attended a bidders’ conference at the Defence Academy in Shrivenham focused on the tendering process and on the proposed operating model for the framework. Delegates were also taken step-by-step through a typical Defence construction project, looking at the processes involved, legislative influences, sustainability and other requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tender will be rigorously evaluated based on the company’s approach to commercial and technical matters such as supply chain management, quality assurance, sustainable development, health and safety, and issues relating to the Government Construction Strategy. The tenderers have also been provided with a demonstration construction project and will be evaluated on their proposed approach to its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Rice, Head of the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changes to UK military basing arrangements are expected to generate requirements for new capital works in the years ahead, and it is vital these are met flexibly and cost-effectively, enabling us to provide a Defence estate which meets military needs and supports our Armed Forces. Early in the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme our research determined that framework arrangements were the best mechanism to achieve this, and I am delighted that we have such a strong field of companies in the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Wooden, &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks project manager, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This national framework is designed to deliver a range of potential major construction projects to support the Defence front line. We are determined to ensure firstly that all companies involved in the tendering process have a full and robust understanding of the potential demand, and secondly that we use the evaluation process to identify the best providers to meet that demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks are designed to support the Government Construction Strategy by reducing costs, improving value for money, and incorporating measures such as the ‘&lt;abbr title="New Engineering Contract 3"&gt;NEC3&lt;/abbr&gt;’ form of procurement, more focused performance management, and continuous improvement mechanisms. For all projects contractors will be required to use systems that meet UK Government requirements for Building Information Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework contractors will also be required to observe fair payment practices and - where decided appropriate on a project-by-project basis - project bank accounts will be set up to ensure prompt payment for all supply chain companies involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tenders are due to be returned by mid-February 2013 and it is expected that the National Capital Works Framework agreements will be awarded before the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61173</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Ministers urge progress between Sudan and South Sudan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK, US and Norway say that Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan must seize the opportunity for peace now.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January. In a joint statement, Foreign Ministers from the ‘Sudan Troika’ are calling for the two countries to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint statement by Norwegian Foreign Minister Espen Barth Eide, United Kingdom Foreign Secretary William Hague and U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the news that the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January in a further effort to resolve outstanding issues between the two countries. We applaud the progress made at their Presidential Summit held in Addis Ababa at the end of September 2012, which demonstrated that a durable and equitable settlement is within reach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We commend the continuing valuable role of the African Union High-Level Implementation Panel led by former President Thabo Mbeki and the efforts of Ethiopian Prime Minister Hailemariam Desalegn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We regret that progress in implementing the Agreements signed on 27 September has stalled and in particular that the agreed security arrangements at the border are not yet in place. We call on the two leaders now to address concretely all outstanding issues and ensure that the armed forces of the two countries immediately withdraw from the demilitarised zone and deploy the Joint Border and Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM), in line with what has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We stress the importance of making progress in parallel on other parts of the relationship between the two countries. Full implementation of all agreements on their own terms and without preconditions or linkages between them, will help build confidence and benefit the people of the two countries. The restart of oil production and export will be particularly valuable for both economies and should not be held up by negotiation on other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We underline our support for the approach taken by the African Union to the question of Abyei. The proposal made by former President Mbeki is based on the Comprehensive Peace Agreement, including the Abyei Protocol. The proposal, adopted by AUPSC on October 24, sets out a clear path towards determining Abyei’s final status in accordance with agreements already signed by both parties, while protecting the rights of all communities and ensuring Abyei can become a model for cross-border cooperation and coexistence. We note in particular that the proposal provides for Abyei’s continuing special status as a bridge between the two countries with guaranteed political and economic rights for both the Ngok Dinka and Misseriya, whatever the outcome of the referendum. We urge the two countries to meet to elaborate on these rights and to move toward agreement on Abyei’s final status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision. We strongly urge them to seize the opportunity of the Summit meeting on 4 January to demonstrate their commitment to implement what they have agreed and make peaceful co-existence a reality.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61178</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T15:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:09:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/keeping-the-uk-military-on-the-map"/>
    <title>Keeping the UK military on the map</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The experts at the Defence Geographic Centre near London are keeping UK Armed Forces worldwide on the right track.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Australian scientists went to have a look at Sandy Island in the South Pacific recently, they discovered that, despite having featured on maps and on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en_uk/earth/index.html" title="Google Earth UK homepage"&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; for years, it doesn’t actually exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts working at the Defence Geographic Centre (&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;) may well have smiled wryly on hearing this. There is no room in their world for such errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; provides geographic information to Defence, predominantly to the Army and the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, but also to other government departments, and works in a world of international collaboration, sharing and co-producing geographical information where a reputation for accuracy matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s geographers, or geospatial analysts as they prefer to be called, know that, if you rely on a map which hasn’t been created from entirely dependable source data, the result can get you into trouble. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A large printer at the Defence Geographic Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5847/Replication.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Defence Geographic Centre has a full range of modern print and production equipment [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even the best maps are the result of compromise and estimate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unless you are on the ground looking at something, geographical information is always an approximation,” said Ian Spencer, Head of Geo Research. “We know how accurate our sources are, and the technical parameters of our sensors, so we know how accurate our products are. We have to work within a defined margin of error for each military product. If it’s outside that margin it’s considered unfit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; augments some of their products with open source material, such as Google Earth pictures, to provide pop-up images of features, but they do it knowing where the risks lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; produces more than just maps, whether on paper or on a screen. After all, a map is just one way of presenting geographical information, and it might not be the best solution for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you might need a database of geographic data to put in a weapons system, or a 3D simulation created from stereoscopic photographs to prepare yourself for the environment through which you may have to fly and control a missile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; specialises in making sense of a huge mass of data and presenting it to the customer in a way that is going to help them make sense of the world, spot relationships, and make informed plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We get 2 types of request,” said Operations Officer Major Jim Danks. “These are ad hoc for a single event or operation, such as disaster relief or support to the Arab Spring operations. And longer term planned work which can include Afghanistan tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5848/Workstation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery to produce simulations [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A request may start as a one-off and then develop into a long-term requirement. When Camp Bastion was established more than a decade ago it started as an ad hoc request. Now, as a home for thousands of troops, it is a standard request requiring the provision of many different types of data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for Lionel Fewson, Head of Collection, are 5 Collection Officers who could be described as the geographic equivalent of Indiana Jones. They scour the globe in search of useful, creditable data, visiting countries of interest gathering information and making new contacts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making maps from scratch is time consuming and very expensive, so international collaboration and data-sharing is very cost effective. Lionel said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have memorandums of understanding with 50 countries and links with many trusted commercial suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the digital side, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is part of a 29-nation programme to capture digital data from various places of interest around the world. In return for their contribution, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; has access to the entire output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of the benefit of co-operation is the award-winning work producing image-based mapping of compounds in Helmand province to improve battlefield and situational awareness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the US Marine Corps Intelligence Activity, the project has to date captured and referenced more than 200,000 compounds and produced more than 1,100 large-scale maps covering more than 11,000 square kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Defence Geographic Centre personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5849/Research.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Defence Geographic Centre personnel meet to identify sources for new products [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to future products, there is a revolution taking place, and the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is leading the way. The move is towards making more use of human geography in an ordered way. Ian Spencer said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to develop standards with our overseas partners to define database structures so that we can start capturing information like ethnicity demographics, economics, religion and water control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you go on the internet you will see lots of people doing things in different disciplines, but at the moment it isn’t connected. We want to pull all this information together in a systematic way so that decision makers and analysts have a better understanding of what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we have the basic geographic foundation we can overlay that with all kinds of human activities. Once data is organised then you can share it and exploit it, and when it has a spatial element you can model these factors and see what effect their interaction has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian believes that marrying physical and social sciences will open up a new world of understanding, as long as you take into account the assumptions and approximations that have been made. Asking how does factor A affect element B is OK as long as you keep an eye out for any more fictitious islands on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="this-report-by-ian-carr-appears-in-the-december-2012january-2013-issue-of-defence-focus---the-magazine-for-everyone-in-defence"&gt;This report by Ian Carr appears in the December 2012/January 2013 issue of Defence Focus - the magazine for everyone in Defence.&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61122</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-commenting-on-the-latest-ucas-2013-cycle-applicant-figures"/>
    <title>Press Release: Commenting on the latest UCAS 2013 cycle applicant figures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Department for Business, Innovation and Skills spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is too early to form a definitive picture about university applications for the 2013/14 academic year. Traditionally fewer than 50 per cent of applicants have submitted their applications by this point in the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that no one is put off applying to university because they do not have information about the student support available to them. Most new students will not pay upfront, there will be more financial support for those from poorer families and everyone will make lower loan repayments than they do now once they are in well paid jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
