<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T19:53:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65761</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T19:53:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T19:53:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-deeply-concerned-by-move-to-impeach-sri-lankan-chief-justice"/>
    <title>UK deeply concerned by move to impeach Sri Lankan Chief Justice</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>United Kingdom calls on Sri Lankan government to respect democratic principles and safeguard Chief Justice and legal profession.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the Sri Lankan Parliament’s vote today to impeach the Chief Justice, a Foreign Office spokesperson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The British Government is deeply concerned by the impeachment proceedings against Sri Lanka’s Chief Justice Shirani Bandaranayake. We share the concerns already expressed by many people in Sri Lanka over both the process and related reports of the intimidation of members of the Sri Lankan Bar Association. The motion to impeach the Chief Justice runs contrary to the clear rulings of Sri Lanka’s highest courts and the proceedings appear to contravene basic principles of fairness, due process and respect for the independence of the judiciary and the Commonwealth Latimer House Principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Together with our international partners, we call on the Sri Lankan Government to respect democratic principles and the right to peaceful protest and to ensure the continued safety of Chief Justice Shirani Bandaranayake.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65733</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:50:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-ministers-visit-personnel-overseas"/>
    <title>UK Defence ministers visit Armed Forces overseas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Two UK Defence ministers have travelled to Afghanistan and the Middle East to visit British Service personnel on operations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/people/andrew-robathan" title="Minister of State for the Armed Forces web page"&gt;Minister of State for the Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Robathan, and the &lt;a href="/government/people/philip-dunne" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, visited personnel in Afghanistan to witness first-hand the progress being made in mentoring Afghan forces to take on their own security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their visit, they also met with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force website"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Afghan military commanders as well as Afghanistan’s Ministers for Defence and Interior in the capital Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan and Mr Dunne also saw the site of the Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy which is currently under construction but will play a major role in the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; military’s post-2014 non-combat commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Helmand, where the majority of British personnel in Afghanistan are located, they held a meeting with Naeem Baloch, the provincial governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan meets soldiers at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6037/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-349.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan meets with soldiers of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment at Main Operating Base Lashkar Gah [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive fact-finding mission saw the ministers briefed on the developing capabilities of the Afghan National Security Forces as well as on local governance and on future plans as &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; forces prepare to finish their combat role by the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their busy programme saw them visit the major &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; bases at Camp Bastion and Lashkar Gah as well as a smaller base in Nahr-e Saraj district &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also spent time at Camp Shorabak, the headquarters of the 3rd Kandak of 215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army. The ministers met Afghan officers there alongside officers and troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/26339.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland web page"&gt;1st Battalion The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; who are stationed there in an advisory role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers were met by Colonel Amin Jhan, the Afghan Brigade Executive Officer, who expressed his appreciation of &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; support and the sacrifices made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major James Christie, Chief of Staff for the Brigade Advisory Group, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This visit has highlighted the operational strength and ambition of 3/215 Brigade of the Afghan National Army as we progress towards an important stage of security transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my fourth visit to Afghanistan and I have to say that the change is remarkable. We are here to help the Afghans to secure their own country and the transition is going extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are drawing down gradually and handing over to the Afghans. What I have seen is that they are better and better prepared to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6038/TFH-4MechBde-2013-009-130.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Philip Dunne is shown a Foxhound vehicle stripped down during his visit to Afghanistan [Picture: Corporal Mike O'Neill, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was appointed to my new role in September so this is my first trip to Afghanistan. I’ve been extraordinarily impressed by both the scale of activity here and the quality of operations being conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Dunne saw mechanics in action as he visited both the Equipment Support Battalion and the Equipment Sustainability System at Camp Bastion where vehicles undergo ‘deep maintenance’ before being returned to operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ability of our own personnel and contractors to get vehicles back onto the ground - whether they have been disrupted on operations or require routine maintenance - is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also joined Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach, Commander Joint Forces Command, in a visit to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/UK-Maritime-Component-Commander" title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Commander web page"&gt;United Kingdom Maritime Component Command&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;) headquarters in Bahrain on 10 January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was made to provide a better understanding of the area in which the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; has provided an enduring naval commitment for more than 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their time at the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom Maritime Component Command"&gt;UKMCC&lt;/abbr&gt;, the visitors heard first-hand how the Royal Navy’s presence in the Middle East reassures our allies and protects both &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; interests and those of the wider international community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, they called upon the ship’s companies of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Sandown-Class/HMS-Ramsey" title="HMS Ramsey web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey&lt;/a&gt;, one of the Royal Navy’s mine countermeasures vessels located in the region, and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;, a frigate currently deployed to the region for maritime security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6039/FG130008021.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew Robathan and Philip Dunne are briefed on board a Royal Navy warship in the Gulf [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Will Haigh, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the Royal Navy’s contribution in the Gulf, Mr Robathan stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to meet the commanding officers and ships’ companies of &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Ramsey and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth and to see for myself the excellent work they are doing in the region, protecting not only the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt;’s interests but also those of the global maritime community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; is committed to a standing presence in the Gulf to ensure freedom of navigation in international waters. The Royal Navy has constantly operated, trained and exercised a number of its mine countermeasures vessels in the Gulf region for 6 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are currently supported by a Bay Class Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which, combined, make the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; one of the few nations that can truly demonstrate an integrated and expeditionary mine countermeasures capability.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65670</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--107"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"&gt;updated parliament on the crisis in Syria&lt;/a&gt; and outlined further UK action for the coming weeks. He said: “Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;meeting organised by the UK this week,&lt;/a&gt; the Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt will &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"&gt;answer questions about the UK’s policy on Syria&lt;/a&gt; via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"&gt;Foreign Secretary met the Secretary General of the League of Arab States&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the Middle East Peace Process and Syria. Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Secretary said: “We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bahrain"&gt;Bahrain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt expressed dismay at the decision&lt;/a&gt;, saying: “I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pakistan"&gt;Pakistan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"&gt;condemned the brutal terrorist attacks in Quetta and Swat this week.&lt;/a&gt; He said: “The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="saudi-arabia"&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemned the beheading&lt;/a&gt; of a Sri Lankan national Rizana Nafeek and reiterated the UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"&gt;urged the Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of respected community leader Sombath Somphone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Baugh the British Ambassador to Somalia &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/mattbaugh/2013/01/09/somalia-a-new-years-resolution-together-into-2013/"&gt;blogged about how the changes of 2012 offer better prospects for improved stability in Somalia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We advised British nationals travelling in Australia to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"&gt;check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65619</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T14:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T15:05:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/raf-typhoon-aircraft-exercise-in-uae"/>
    <title>RAF Typhoon aircraft exercise in UAE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Typhoon aircraft of 6 Squadron have been exercising with a multinational contingent at Al Dhafra Air Base in the United Arab Emirates.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has been the first time that aircraft, engineers and pilots from the squadron, normally based at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars, have deployed together on the Advanced Tactical Leadership Course (&lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;), which runs each year at Al Dhafra Air Base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Mike Baulkwill, Officer Commanding  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/6squadron.cfm" title="6 Squadron RAF web page"&gt;6 Squadron&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been sent out here to conduct this multinational exercise that looks at large scale air operations involving many aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been run over a number of weeks, giving the pilots, ground crew and support staff an opportunity to work alongside other nations. The squadron have been running air interdiction missions, self-escort missions and offensive and defensive counter air missions as part of the exercise. This has required the pilots and aircraft to be quick and reactive in a multi-role platform in all types of operational scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise has been conducted in 2 parts - one wave of flying per day in support of the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt; missions and one following wave each day where the pilots can fly alongside multinational aircraft to conduct further training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Baulkwill added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen the ground crew and pilots from 6 Squadron lead and operate in a very different environment. Everybody at every rank is learning something from this exercise. We are learning to operate fully combat capable aircraft in a hot and dry environment which is very different to conditions at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Leuchars in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senior Aircraftman Sam Norry, an Aircraft Maintenance Mechanic on 6 Squadron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my first detachment and it has been much harder work out here. There are a lot more elements to contend with - temperatures alone are incredible, you have to drink a lot more water. Not only that, on the engineering side of things, you don’t have that instant support that you have in the UK - there are fewer people to work on the aircraft so you really have to work together and work hard to get the jobs done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An RAF Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6026/AUAB_UNC_20121210_239_026.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Typhoon from 6 Squadron at Al Dhafra Air Base [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;To summarise the squadron’s support to the &lt;abbr title="Advanced Tactical Leadership Course"&gt;ATLC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Wing Commander Baulkwill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been operating huge missions with other nations, sometimes operating an air picture involving 60 aircraft with simulated high threat missions. It has been incredibly hard work for all of the pilots and the ground crew to support this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have found ourselves pushed hard, and the  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon FGR4 web page"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; aircraft has performed exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The systems that it has on board are second-to-none and we have seen the benefit of that - it has been impressive to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65623</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T13:37:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary condemns terrorist attacks in Pakistan </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague has condemned yesterday’s terrorist attacks in Pakistan and sent his condolences to those affected. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking today the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was extremely saddened to hear of the brutal terrorist and sectarian attacks in Quetta and Swat yesterday. My thoughts are with the families of those who have been killed. I wish all those injured in the attacks a swift recovery. The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65618</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T12:21:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T12:21:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretary-william-hague-met-the-ethiopian-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>The Foreign Secretary William Hague meets the Ethiopian Foreign Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary discusses human rights with the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary met the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, Dr Tedros on 10 January. Dr Tedros also met the Minister of Africa, Mark Simmonds, and the Secretary of State for International Development, Justine Greening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary discussed a range of issues including the UK’s bilateral relationship with Ethiopia, regional security, commercial relations and counter-terrorism. The Foreign Secretary also underlined the importance the UK attaches to human rights and raised concerns over the sentences handed down under Ethiopia’s anti-terrorism laws.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office officials also attended a business roundtable chaired by Dr Tedros in the Ethiopian Embassy for existing and potential investors.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65653</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T12:05:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T12:05:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"/>
    <title>UK urge’s Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of community leader</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has expressed concern about the disappearance of community leader Sombath Somphone in Vientiane, Laos.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sombath Somphone founded the Participatory Development Training Center (PADETC) a non-profit private school in Vientiane and was awarded the Ramon Magsaysay award for his work promoting sustainable development in Laos. Sombath also worked with the UK to organise the Asia-Europe People’s Forum in October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on his recent disappearance Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely concerned by the disappearance of the respected NGO worker Sombath Somphone in Vientiane, who went missing on 15 December 2012. Sombath has played a crucial role, over many years, in  helping some of the poorest communities in Laos develop a stable means of income. He has proved a crucial partner in preparing and delivering with the UK a forum for young people in Laos last year. The UK Government strongly urges the Lao authorities to ensure a prompt, thorough and impartial investigation into Sombath’s disappearance, and to do all they can to ensure that Sombath is reunited with his family as matter of urgency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rmaf.org.ph/" title="http://www.rmaf.org.ph/"&gt;Ramon Magsaysay Award Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.padetc.org/" title="http://www.padetc.org/"&gt;Participatory Development Training Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.aepf.info/" title="http://www.aepf.info/"&gt;Asia-Europe People’s Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65592</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"/>
    <title>FCO Minister to answer questions on Syria via Twitter</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions on Syria live via Twitter on 14 January 11:15am-12:00pm GMT.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his statement to Parliament on 10 January, the Foreign Secretary set out further UK action on Syria in the coming weeks. On 9-10 January, the UK organised a successful meeting at Wilton Park as part of our efforts in stepping up support for Syrian-led political transition and planning for the day after Assad. The meeting was an important step in taking forward this support. The Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives from 14 countries and international organisations agreed, alongside the Syrian National Coalition, that transition should build towards a Syria which offers equal opportunities for all, through which all Syrians can help determine the shape of a future Syria. This was an important milestone in Syria’s journey towards a lasting and peaceful democracy and we hope that our contributions play an important role in shaping it. The UK stands ready to support transition in Syria. But it will be a collective international effort to assist the Syrian National Coalition to bring about the changes the Syrian people so truly deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions about the UK’s policy towards Syria live via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm GMT. Questions can be submitted to Mr Burt &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt; using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt;. He will answer questions in English and as many as time allows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can follow the Q&amp;amp;A using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65593</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T10:38:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-pistols-for-uk-armed-forces"/>
    <title>New pistols for UK Armed Forces</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Armed Forces are to be supplied with more than 25,000 new Glock sidearms to replace the ageing Browning pistols currently in service.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://us.glock.com/products/model/g17gen4" title="Glock 17 Gen4 pistol web page"&gt;Glock 17 Gen4 pistol&lt;/a&gt; is not only much lighter than the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafregiment/forceprotection/browning9mmpistol.cfm" title="Browning 9mm pistol web page"&gt;Browning L9A1&lt;/a&gt;, it is also more accurate and its magazines can carry more bullets. It has an increased magazine capacity of 17 rounds, compared to 13 rounds for the Browning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnel across all 3 Services will begin to receive the new 9-millimetre (mm) calibre Glock 17s in the coming weeks and troops deployed to Afghanistan will be among the first to use the new weapon. The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.vikingarms.com/" title="Viking Arms Ltd website"&gt;Viking Arms &lt;abbr title="Limited"&gt;Ltd&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Harrogate, Yorkshire, also includes more than 25,000 holsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Glock 17 pistol (left) and a Browning 9mm pistol" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6012/ArmyHQ-2013-003-052_aGlock_17_pistol_EMBARG_00.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Glock 17 pistol (left) and the Browning the new pistols will replace [Picture: Richard Watt, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Mark Anderson, Royal Marines, who trialled the new weapon before the contract was awarded, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pistols are vital in close combat and are a key part of a soldier’s armoury. Reliable, light and easy to carry, the Glock inspires confidence and performs exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/ministers/parliamentary-under-secretary-of-state-defence-equipment-support-and-technology" title="Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology web page"&gt;Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Philip Dunne, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide our troops with the best possible personal kit available and these new Glock 17s will give them greater firepower and accuracy on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Glock pistol is fired on a range" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6013/Emb_DES-2013-003-0250.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines firearms instructor Sergeant Steve Lord demonstrates the new Glock pistol on the range at Woolwich Barracks in London [Picture: Andrew Linnett, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sidearms are a valuable weapon for servicemen and women on the battlefield, and the new Glock, manufactured in Austria, will complement the wide range of weapons already available to our forces, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA80A2 assault rifles, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light machine guns, which fire 5.56mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharpshooter rifles, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;general purpose machine guns, which fire 7.62mm rounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;combat shotguns, which fire 12-gauge cartridges; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sniper systems, which fire 8.59mm rounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Glock pistols will replace the Browning which after being used by the Armed Forces for more than 40 years has become increasingly expensive to maintain. The contract for a replacement pistol was put out to tender 2 years ago and is not in response to any specific or increased threat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65367</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-lynx-aids-capture-of-suspected-pirates"/>
    <title>Royal Navy Lynx aids capture of suspected pirates</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A Lynx helicopter and a crew from the Royal Navy have helped arrest 12 armed suspected pirates off the coast of Somalia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flight 217 of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; is currently deployed on board the French frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/News-and-Events/Latest-News/2013/January/03/121220-Blog-Surcouf" title="Read the blog from 815 Lynx Squadron on board the French frigate Surcouf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf&lt;/a&gt; as part of Operation Atalanta, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s counter-piracy mission off the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lynx was sent ahead by the French warship to find the suspected pirates after the &lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Halyburton, operating as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.manw.nato.int/page_operation_ocean_shield.aspx" title="Operation Ocean Shield web page"&gt;Operation Ocean Shield&lt;/a&gt;, received a distress call from a merchant vessel reporting she was under attack from 6 men armed with rocket-propelled grenades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6008/20130110surcouf3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel as Flight 217's Lynx helicopter hovers above [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;abbr title="Merchant Ship Characteristic"&gt;MSC&lt;/abbr&gt; Jasmine, sailing 260 miles off the Somali coast, managed to repel the attack themselves, a German &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; maritime patrol aircraft was scrambled to track the suspect vessel, which was by then towing another boat with several more men on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy Lynx sped to the scene and ordered the vessels to stop while French commandos from Surcouf arrived alongside in a fast boat and quickly boarded, resulting in the suspected pirates swiftly surrendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon searching the pirates’ boats, the commandos also discovered containers of diesel and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 12 suspects are now being held on board &lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf for evidence collection in order to fully assess the possibility of prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="French frigate Sucouf seen from Lynx helicopter cockpit" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6009/20130110surcouf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of the French frigate Sucouf from the Lynx helicopter cockpit of Flight 217 from 815 Naval Air Squadron [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commander of Flight 217, Lieutenant Mike Curd, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The whole operation was an excellent exercise in teamwork, with the US ship and Surcouf co-ordinating their efforts, including both units’ helicopters, to successfully track the 2 suspect vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our Lynx actually performed the ‘stop’ and support to boarding of both the suspect vessels and provided airborne support to the subsequent boarding operations. It was a long and tiring day that began before dawn, but by the end of it we were proud of a job well done; the procedures and routines we’d practised so many times worked extremely efficiently and by nightfall we knew we had played a large part in the successful apprehension of a dozen suspected pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of the Royal Navy’s Lynx on board the Surcouf is the first of its kind as part of the terms of the Lancaster House Treaty. Under this the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; and France agreed military co-operation to assure their international commitments and strengthen their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65345</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-health-partnership-awards-launched"/>
    <title>2013 Health Partnership Awards launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nominations are now open for this year's Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards which were launched today in Cardiff and Edinburgh.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ceremony honours the people, projects and initiatives that provide serving military personnel, including reservists, and their families and veterans with the very best in healthcare and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awards are open to civilian health staff and military medics working within the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-medical-services" title="Defence Medical Services website"&gt;Defence Medical Services&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/" title="NHS website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and private or voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 awards ceremony, to be held on 21 May, is being hosted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/" title="Welsh Government website"&gt;Welsh Government&lt;/a&gt; and, from today, people can nominate individuals or teams who provide care and support to Service personnel. Nominations close on 21 February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two launch ceremonies took place today - one at the Army’s Dreghorn Barracks in Edinburgh and one at the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/11018.aspx" title="203 Field Hospital web page"&gt;203 (Welsh) Field Hospital&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards provide a great opportunity to pay tribute to the dedication and fantastic results that our military and civilian colleagues achieve by working together to improve military health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to encourage people to visit the website to nominate all those who have provided the very best health and social care to our Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the awards in Cardiff, Welsh Health Minister Lesley Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud Wales is hosting the 2013 awards. The awards celebrate the hard work, commitment and dedication shown by health professionals from across the public, private and voluntary sectors in caring for the men and women of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important we recognise the immense contribution the Armed Forces and veterans have made to our country. We owe them a huge debt of gratitude and a duty of care, particularly those who have developed health problems as a result of their military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Tri-Service healthcare specialists" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6006/hqscot-2013-001-4476.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The awards honour the people who provide military personnel with the best health and social care [Picture: Mark Owens, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also vital we acknowledge the role of those who care for and support Service personnel and veterans, especially in recent years when the Armed Forces have been heavily engaged overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would encourage people to consider nominating either themselves or others for these awards as it is important we recognise their contribution to improving the lives of Service personnel and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Health Minister Dr Dan Poulter said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These awards will shine a light on the efforts of the military, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Service charities to make sure members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans have the best care possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such important work should not go unnoticed. I urge people to put themselves or their colleagues forward to have their efforts and achievements in caring for our Armed Forces, their families and veterans recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;203 Field Hospital was founded in 1914 and consists of reservist volunteers made up of civilian, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and military medics. The unit has already begun preparations for its upcoming deployment to Afghanistan in support of the Regular Army on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event included a demonstration of the treatment of a casualty from ambulance to resuscitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Lesley Griffiths was accompanied by Surgeon Rear Admiral Calum McArthur, Brigadier Philip Napier, Commander of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/28224.aspx" title="160 (Wales) Brigade web page"&gt;160 (Wales) Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, and Colonel Tina Donnelly, Commanding Officer of 203 Field Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the awards, including how to apply or nominate, are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org/" title="Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards website"&gt;www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65329</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister condemns killing of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alistair Burt reiterates UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Sri Lankan national, Ms Rizana Nafeek, was executed yesterday in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn the execution of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia yesterday, despite the many appeals for her sentence to be commuted. The UK opposes all use of the death penalty as a matter of principle, whatever the crime committed. The beheading of Ms Nafeek is particularly concerning as reports suggest she may have been a child of 17 at the time the crime was committed. We also find the practice of beheading to be particularly cruel and inhuman. We continue to raise our concerns about human rights with the Saudi authorities, including its frequent use of the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65403</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/million-pound-boost-to-extend-homelessness-help-to-thousands"/>
    <title>Million pound boost to extend homelessness help to thousands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A cash injection of £1.2 million will help thousands of vulnerable people into the rented homes they need, Mark Prisk said today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting the London Crisis Skylight Centre, the minister said the cash will extend the charity’s work through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.privaterentedsector.org.uk/prs-funding.asp"&gt;Crisis Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme&lt;/a&gt; to provide housing help for single people at risk of homelessness, who are unable to find private accommodation on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk at the Crisis Skylight centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6010/mark_prisk_crisis.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk speaks to Steve Grant at Crisis Skylight to hear the problems faced by single homeless people&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="helping-vulnerable-people-into-rental-homes"&gt;Helping vulnerable people into rental homes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Private Rented Sector Access Scheme, run by Crisis with government support, has helped nearly 4,000 people find the rented homes they need in the last 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already established in 120 areas across England, the scheme offers single people the advice and support they need to find and sustain a private rented tenancy, helping them overcome hurdles like budgeting and paying a deposit and working with local landlords to ensure the homes provided are suitable, safe and secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s £1.2 million cash injection will extend the programme, creating a further 23 local schemes. By focussing on helping those most at risk of homelessness, including young people, it aims to help a further 1,300 people in the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government has a strong safety net in place to prevent homelessness and Crisis’s programme has been a vital part of this, helping nearly 4,000 vulnerable people in just two years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why today I’m providing 1.2 million to extend that support even further. With another 23 areas on board, the scheme is set to help many more single people at risk of homelessness to find and keep the long-term home they need, providing the safety and security to get their lives back on track.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leslie Morphy, chief executive of Crisis, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To have already helped 4,000 homeless people into decent homes is an incredible achievement for the Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme and the local organisations working hard to support tenants and landlords. Challenging conditions in the private rented sector make this work difficult but all the more important as people struggle to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement of funding is for a further 23 schemes that will focus on helping particularly vulnerable people with no home of their own including young people and those leaving prison - groups that too often struggle to find a home and have often not been a priority for assistance through other schemes and programmes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The department has provided £10.8 million to Crisis to run the private rented sector scheme. The £1.2 million funding announced today is part of that investment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organisations that will help deliver the extended programme include:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homeless Action Resource Project (HARP), Southend on Sea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Giles Trust,	London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadway, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hope Worldwide (HWW), London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAYSH, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Mungo Community Housing Association Ltd, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DePaul UK, North Tyneside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton &amp;amp; District Advice &amp;amp; Information Service, Stockton on Tees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquila Way, Gateshead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hyndburn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crewe YMCA, Crewe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real Lettings South, Portsmouth and Southampton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Society of St James, Hampshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Southdown Housing Association, West Sussex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leatherhead Start, Mole Valley and Epsom and Ewell &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next Steps, Tandridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelter The National Campaign for Homeless People Limited, Cornwall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Threshold Housing Link, Swindon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1625 Independent People, Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encompass, Torridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SIFA Fireside, Sandwell&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hambleton&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fusion Housing, Kirklees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos of the visit to the London Crisis Skylight Centre are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632484931391/with/8368181276/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65312</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sailors-help-african-community"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sailors help African community</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During a break from anti-piracy and maritime security operations off the east coast of Africa, sailors from HMS Northumberland helped villagers to renovate their community centre.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;25 volunteers from the Plymouth-based frigate’s company headed to the village of Kigamboni while their ship was berthed in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. The sailors helped to install windows and doors in the community centre building, repaired fencing, and built ‘hugle beds’, which will be used to grow vegetables in dry conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Physical Trainer Andrew Davidson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All my shipmates were moved by the day at the &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt;. We felt a great sense of achievement knowing that we’d helped in every way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6001/N-land_sailor_2013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship’s captain Commander Paddy Dowsett said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our visit to Dar es Salaam has been a real success.  Not only has it reaffirmed and strengthened the commitment the United Kingdom has to Tanzania, it has also allowed my team to give something to the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community centre was set up in 2006 to offer shelter and education to children, but also runs a mobile library and promotes adult learning initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sign of their appreciation the community centre members performed an impressive musical and acrobatic dance – demonstrating just some of the skills they’re taught at Kigamboni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The centre’s founder, Festo Chengula, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The place looks great after all the hard work. The &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt; members love having guests and you are all welcome to visit again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A young boy squeezes a sailor's face" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6002/N-land_Tanzania_child_2013.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A young boy squeezes a sailor's face in a gesture of affection  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an exchange of gifts &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; donated 85 football shirts, courtesy of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavyfa.com/" title="Royal Navy Football Association website"&gt;Royal Navy Football Association&lt;/a&gt;, together with a rugby ball, football and Northumberland crest and commemorative coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship is still in the early stages of a patrol of the Indian Ocean and due home in Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65301</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sweet-deal-for-growth-in-birmingham"/>
    <title>Sweet deal for growth in Birmingham</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A raft of initiatives to boost economic growth in Birmingham will be on the agenda today as Business Minister Michael Fallon visits the city to champion government support for the area’s economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will be putting the seal of approval to a new deal to cut red tape for Mondelez International, owner of the Cadbury’s brand which will reduce duplication and costs whilst maintaining high safety standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal, known as a primary authority partnership, means Birmingham City Council will provide advice to all of Mondelez International’s UK sites on regulations including food safety and hygiene and has already lead to Mondelez International cutting £250,000 in packaging costs alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Fallon will then visit Quality Plated Products (QPP), a manufacturing company in Great Barr who have been awarded a loan of £245,000 from the government’s Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative. The company uses a unique technology to supply metal plated plastic to the automotive industry. Thanks to the government support it will be increasing capacity, creating an additional 11 jobs and starting a new apprenticeship scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Birmingham has long been an engine of the country’s economy, and my tour around the city has shown that’s certainly the case today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is doing all it can to support the West Midlands; whether that’s direct support through our Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative to companies like QPP, rolling out ultra fast broadband, or helping household names like Cadbury by reducing the amount of red tape they have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By taking clear and decisive action and giving direct help to companies and regions they can realise their growth potential and compete in the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister’s tour will also see him visiting Aero Engine Controls, a leading aerospace and defence manufacturing company. This is part of a series visits today by Business Ministers to discuss how business and government can work more effectively together to tackle barriers to growth, boost exports and grow high value jobs in the UK. The Minister will also meet members of the Greater Birmingham and Solihull Local Enterprise Partnership to discuss their ‘Strategy for Growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships can be formed to cover key aspects of environmental health, trading standards and fire safety services, including health and safety, fair trading, food standards and product safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are now more than 600 businesses and 97 local authorities operating one or more of the 2,016 primary authority partnerships. The scheme covers more than 58,500 premises. 37% of businesses involved are SMEs. It was introduced in 2009 and is administered by the Better Regulation Delivery Office (BRDO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative is a national fund of up to £125m to create more competitive supply chains, sustain or create new employment opportunities, and create better synergies and sustained collaborative relationships throughout supply chains that participate in this initiative. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx"&gt;http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s industrial strategy is about looking to the future, presenting a long-term, whole of government approach to supporting British business, giving them the confidence they need to invest, hire staff and grow. Long-term strategies are being developed in partnership with industry in key sectors including aerospace, nuclear, and the information economy - the aerospace strategy will be published in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65304</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"/>
    <title>Government's rail strategy receives independent endorsement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent review of the government’s rail franchising strategy, following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition, has backed the overall policy while delivering advice for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Richard Brown, Chairman of Eurostar, to conduct a thorough investigation into how the government should manage its franchising programme following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key conclusions from the Brown review stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the rail industry works, and that there is no credible case for major structural change (paragraph 1.4, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;passenger numbers have grown by 92% since privatisation… punctuality and passenger satisfaction are running at much improved levels… it is highly unlikely that these successes could have been delivered if franchising was fundamentally flawed (paragraph 1.5, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have now had nearly two decades’ experience of franchising and therefore a good idea as to what has worked and what still needs to be addressed (paragraph 1.6, p4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown’s report, published by the department today, recommends that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the department’s capability should be strengthened to manage future franchising programmes (paragraph 1.12, p8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise should be strengthened and simplified (paragraph 3.13, p23)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans should be put in place to devolve more English franchises to the relevant authorities (paragraph 5.5, p37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Brown said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In carrying out this review I have come to the conclusion that the franchising system is not broken, but rather it has made a major contribution to Britain’s increasingly successful rail network. It is therefore essential for both passengers and the wider rail market that the franchising programme is restarted as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To achieve this goal, my review has identified a series of practical proposals and recommendations which, if implemented, will result in a stronger and more effective approach to franchising. In addition, I have provided the department with three broad options for them to consider where a strengthened franchising organisation might be located. As set out in both my review and the Laidlaw Report, the department must look to strengthen its franchising capability as a top priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passengers cannot wait whilst theoretical discussions are held about the structure of railways. It is essential to get on with the franchising programme in order to maintain the momentum of investment in increasing capacity and improving services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The review has confirmed that government’s approach to rail franchising system is still the best way to secure the rail services for tax payers and fare payers alike. It has identified a number of detailed improvements, which I will carefully consider before publishing a further statement regarding the government’s franchising policy in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any delays to the franchising programme will not affect services for rail passengers and they will continue to receive the services they depend upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brown review was launched by the Department for Transport in October and follows work conducted by Sam Laidlaw, Chief Executive of Centrica and a non-executive DfT board member into what went wrong with the West Coast competition directly. His report was published in December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has recommended that by February the government should publish its plans for the Essex Thameside; Great Western; and the Thameslink, Southern and Great Northern franchise competitions which were put on hold last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government considers that, until those plans had been agreed, it would be inappropriate to publish the specific recommendations about these three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is planning to set out a programme for future franchise competitions in the spring alongside a further statement of franchising policy in light of the Brown Review and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"&gt;Rail franchising written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;br&gt;
Brown inquiry team press enquiries: 07584 115 270 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65589</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:38:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"/>
    <title>Travel advice: Bushfires in Australia </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British nationals in Australia should be aware of the risk of bushfires and check local state authorities for information.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Numerous bushfires have been burning across New South Wales, Tasmania, Victoria and southern Queensland in south east Australia this week, destroying over 120 houses, hundreds of thousands of hectares of land and triggering town evacuations. Areas near a holiday resort in central Australia were also affected by a bushfire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fires follow days of high temperatures and the extreme heatwave and dangerous fire conditions are expected to continue in coming days. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We advise British nationals travelling in Australia to check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cfa.vic.gov.au/"&gt;Victoria,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cfs.sa.gov.au/"&gt;South Australia,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rfs.nsw.gov.au/"&gt;New South Wales,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fire.tas.gov.au/"&gt;Tasmania,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfes.wa.gov.au/Pages/default.aspx"&gt;Western Australia,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pfes.nt.gov.au/Fire-and-Rescue.aspx"&gt;Northern Territory,&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://esa.act.gov.au/actfr/"&gt;Australian Capital Territory Fire &amp;amp; Rescue.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/asia-oceania/australia#natural" title="FCO travel advice"&gt;Foreign Office travel advice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the Foreign Office travel advice on twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/fcotravel" title="Foreign Office travel advice on twitter"&gt;@fcotravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinaustralia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="British High Commission in Canberra"&gt;British High Commission in Canberra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65293</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-to-receive-cash-boost-for-choosing-development"/>
    <title>Communities to receive cash boost for choosing development</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles announces new cash incentives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities that tackle the legacy of inadequate house-building and choose to accept new housing will benefit directly from new generous cash incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods that take a proactive approach by drawing up a neighbourhood development plan, and securing the consent of local people in a referendum, will receive 25% of the revenues from the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; arising from the development that they choose to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cash boost will be paid directly to parish and town councils and can be used to back the community’s priorities for example to re-roof a village hall, refurbish a municipal pool or take over a community pub. Neighbourhoods without a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood development plan&lt;/a&gt; but where the levy is still charged will still receive a capped 15% share of the levy revenue arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities without a parish or town council will still benefit from this incentive, with the local planning authority retaining it and spending it in accordance with the wishes of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of hectoring people and forcing development on communities, the government believes that we need to persuade communities that development is in everyone’s interest. Incentives are key to getting the homes built that we both need for today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital this country increases the number of homes it builds to meet the needs of its increasing population. The failure of previous administrations to build enough homes, latterly despite the credit boom, led to a severe housing shortage that has been made worse by the rapid increase in the number of households. The number of people living alone has rocketed, and immigration has led to an influx of 1.7 million people into England in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to tackle this housing shortage and make best use of what we already have the government has invested £160 million to deal with the 250,000 homes empty for more than 6 months - 50,000 fewer then in 2009. This money combined with a share of £300 million announced in September’s housing growth package, will help put more than 15,000 empty homes back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also made clear that planning should encourage the effective use of land, including brownfield land that is not of high environmental value. The majority of all new homes - 76% of those completed in 2010 - were built on brownfield land. But this will not be enough and some undeveloped land will need to be made available for house-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a simple choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. We can shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or we can accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land and resolve that we will make these decisions locally and build beautiful places like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is determined to persuade communities to accept more house-building by giving them a tangible share of the benefits it brings. By undertaking a neighbourhood plan that makes space for new development, communities can secure revenues to make the community more attractive for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is an important way to make sure that development has the backing of the community. It is right that the areas that have organised themselves to bring forward a neighbourhood plan and have taken the plan through all the stages of the neighbourhood planning (including a successful examination and referendum) should be rewarded for their positive, pro-active approach to delivering growth. This is why they are entitled to an extra 10% of the levy arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy amount passed to neighbourhoods reflects the rates the local planning authority set for the levy. These charge a rate or different rates for development in the local area in pounds per square metre. The neighbourhood funding element will be calculated based on the levy receipts from the relevant development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The levy’s charges will become due from the date that a chargeable development is commenced. The neighbourhood funding element will be passed to parish or community councils in accordance with a timetable agreed between the local planning authority and the local council.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the money is transferred to a parish council (in England) or a community council (in Wales) they will decide how the money will be spent - although they will be expected to work with the local planning authority. Where the money stays with the local planning authority (in areas without a parish or community council) the local planning authority will engage with the communities where the development has happened to agree how best to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In areas that have not been subject to neighbourhood planning there will be a cap of £100 per council tax dwelling on the neighbourhood funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We aim to have these incentives in place from Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We previously &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;consulted&lt;/a&gt; on allowing councils the choice whether to spend their levy receipts on affordable housing but given other ongoing policies to support housing, we are not proposing to make this change at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also going to enable a mayoral development corporation to impose a Community Infrastructure Levy charge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65616</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:17:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sails-into-london-boat-show"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sails into London Boat Show</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Royal Navy looks set to be a major draw at the London Boat Show, which opens at the ExCel Exhibition Centre this weekend.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an island nation, the UK’s prosperity and security are dependant on its ability to access the sea. That is why the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk" title="Royal Navy website"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; is globally deployed and has a range of versatile ships, submarines and aircraft operated by professional sailors, aviators and Royal Marines Commandos. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy will be at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonboatshow.com/2013/home.aspx" title="London Boat Show website"&gt;London Boat Show&lt;/a&gt; from 12 to 20 January, where visitors can learn more about naval life and how, every minute of every day, somewhere in the world they are protecting the nation’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cougar beach landing rehearsal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5921/offshoreraidingcraft.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from 45 Commando and HMS Bulwark carry out a beach assault in Plymouth [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as celebrating the Navy’s rich heritage, show visitors can learn how they operate across a variety of missions from anti-terrorism and counter-narcotics to disaster relief and peacekeeping operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy stand will include an opportunity to get up close to an advanced offshore raiding craft (&lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt;). Measuring 9 metres long and able to travel in excess of 35 knots, the craft were part of the Navy’s commitment to keeping the public safe during the Olympic Games. The &lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt; can also be equipped with general purpose machine guns, making them a highly-flexible and potent deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Boat Show, a Navy Search and Rescue Sea King Mark 5 will take to the skies beside ExCeL at 1400hrs on Saturday, 12 January, to illustrate what a rescue operation entails. The renowned Mark 5 is now the Navy’s workhorse of choice, operating in extreme conditions and ready to respond at a moment’s notice in an emergency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A four-man crew from 771 Naval Air Squadron in Cornwall will manoeuvre the helicopter with precision to make a simulated rescue from the dock. The helicopter will return on Sunday, 13 January, for a further demonstration at 1130hrs before heading back to its Cornish base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the show, the Search and Rescue crew will be at the C180 stand to meet the public and answer questions about the service, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/About-the-Royal-Navy/The-Navy-and-the-Environment/In-the-Air" title="Fleet Air Arm web page"&gt;Fleet Air Arm&lt;/a&gt; and the wider Royal Navy. There will also be the opportunity to attend a free daily presentation exploring the role of Search and Rescue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65346</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:27:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/housing-the-next-generation"/>
    <title>Housing the next generation</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Planning Minister Nick Boles at an event hosted by Policy Exchange.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;[This version of the speech excludes party political content].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last September, the Prime Minister declared that our mission is “to build an ‘aspiration nation’”, in which we “get behind people who want to get on in life.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s what’s always made our hearts beat faster,” he said. “It’s not just an economic mission” - but “a moral one” too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to that speech as one of David Cameron’s newest and most junior ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, though I find the Prime Minister’s message inspiring, implicit in it was a challenge that keeps me awake at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No aspiration is more deeply embedded in the British psyche than the desire to own your own home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the prospect of doing so has been slipping ever further out of the reach of millions of hard-working people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a result of our decades-long failure to build enough houses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the root cause of that is our decades-long refusal to release enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are other problems affecting the housing market in the short term: most of all, the lack of finance for buyers and developers since the credit crunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These the government is already tackling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers"&gt;FirstBuy&lt;/a&gt;, which helps reduce the deposit first-time buyers need to find to just 5% of the price of their new home, will invest £460 million, matched by housebuilders, to help 27,000 people by 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme"&gt;NewBuy&lt;/a&gt; enables other households to access 95% mortgages for new build homes, and the Prime Minister announced on Monday that we will bring forward further measures to increase the availability of affordable mortgages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my colleague, Mark Prisk, is deploying £570 million in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/get-britain-building"&gt;Get Britain Building fund&lt;/a&gt; to get building going on sites that already have planning permission, and using the £225 million fund that the Deputy Prime Minister announced to accelerate the delivery of housing on large sites like Cranbrook in Devon and Ebbsfleet in Kent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the long term, the original source of our housing crisis is the failure of past governments to provide enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As planning minister, it is my job to persuade local authorities to make more land available so that more homes can be built and the price of new homes comes down - and thereby reverse the trend that has been heading in the wrong direction for decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now can you understand why I sleep a little uneasily?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2011 census revealed that, in the ‘noughties’, home ownership in England fell, for the first time in 60 years: from 68% to 63%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because houses became too expensive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homelessness charity, Shelter, has shown that if the price of food had risen as fast as the price of housing in the last 30 years, a supermarket chicken would now cost £47 - and a jar of instant coffee would cost £20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, the average person setting aside 5% of their income each week could save up for a deposit on a house after 8 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it would take the same person 47 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some say that this trend is inevitable, given a growing population, rising incomes and a finite supply of land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Germany real house prices have remained constant since 2000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the Netherlands, which has shared the UK’s rapid growth in population, real house prices rose by a little bit more than a fifth in the same decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did they nearly double in the UK? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve built too few houses to keep up with the rapid increase in the number of households needing a place to live, especially the dizzying increase in the number of people living on their own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons for this growth in the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some we should celebrate - like the fact that people are living longer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others we should regret - like the high rate of divorce or the immigration policies that led to a net influx of 1.7 million people into England in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of these changes have happened and all of the people concerned have the right to a decent home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, Shelter estimated that we would need to build 240,000 new homes a year in England to cater for all of these new households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2012, Alan Holmans from the Cambridge Centre for Housing and Planning Research updated these estimates using my department’s publication of new projections of the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded, that, to keep pace with this trend, we now need to build 270,000 new homes a year, leading to a net increase of 250,000 a year as 20,000 of them would replace existing homes that have to be demolished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether Mr Holman’s projections will prove accurate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do know that the house-building that took place during the ‘noughties’ fell woefully short of what was necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a decade of easy credit and an explicit target to build 213,000 new homes a year in England, an annual average of only 147,000 new homes were completed between 2000 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period the population went up by 3.4 million and, from 1998 to 2008, the number of households went up by 1.7 million. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, in each year of the ‘noughties’, the Netherlands built over 4.4 new homes for every 1,000 inhabitants and the French built over 5.6 for every 1,000 inhabitants. In England, we built just 2.9. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in spite the fact that, between 2000 and 2010, total mortgage debt in the UK more than doubled - from £500 billion to £1.2 trillion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because this debt just fuelled a massive boom in prices - and did little to boost the supply of new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those homes that were built got smaller and smaller, as land prices went up and up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2001 to 2003 the new houses we built in England were smaller than the ones we’ve already got - and 30% smaller than the new houses being built in the Netherlands, a country that is more densely populated than ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For housing, as in so many areas of our national life, the ‘noughties’ were a wasted decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loads of money sloshing around, lots of top-down targets, but very little to show for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we have to build even more houses to make up the ground lost and to keep pace with future growth in the number of households needing homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s assuming we continue to tighten our grip on immigration so that net migration falls below 100,000 a year by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I do really understand why the idea of a lot more house-building makes people nervous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I certainly don’t want to see more open land developed than is absolutely necessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately there is no painless way to make homes affordable for working people earning ordinary wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the empty homes?” people ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are certainly right to suggest that we should make full use of our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes"&gt;existing housing stock&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most empty homes are only empty for short periods while they change hands or are renovated or are caught up in probate after the last owner’s death. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are around 259,000 houses that have been empty for more than 6 months, 50,000 fewer than in 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has already invested £160 million and that, together with a share of the £300 million additional spending announced in September’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;Housing Growth Package&lt;/a&gt;, should help put over 15,000 empty properties back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to see good homes standing empty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can’t make more than a marginal contribution to the hundreds of thousands of new homes that we need every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the brownfield land?” people then ask - and they point to the Campaign to Protect Rural England (&lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt;) estimate that England has enough brownfield land to support 1.5 million homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to maximise the number of homes we build on previously developed land - not least because such land tends to benefit from existing links to our road and rail networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; admitted that we would only get 450,000 new homes out of brownfield sites in those parts of the country where most of the new homes are needed - London, the South East and the South West. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And achieving that number would require us to build on every scrap of brownfield land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that we are already building most new homes on brownfield land: 76% of all the homes completed in 2010 as against 56% in 1997. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simply can’t squeeze much more out of brownfield sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To restrict new house-building to brownfield land would leave us a long way short of the number of new homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So “what about the developers’ land banks?” people then ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, I do understand why it riles people that their local councils have to find new sites for development, when the major house-builders are sitting on land with permission to build hundreds of thousands of new homes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m afraid this concern is also misplaced, resting on a misunderstanding about how the British house-building industry works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of September 2012, on sites of 10 or more units, there were 487,000 units with detailed planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 246,000 of them were on sites where no building has even started - and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; that I am taking through Parliament with colleagues will make it easier for developers to renegotiate the unaffordable Section 106 agreements that have made many of these schemes unviable and caused them to stall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most sites with planning permission are for schemes of 150 units or more which developers generally build out over 3 to 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are going to have any prospect of getting our current house-builders to build the number of new homes we need, we need them to have a pipeline of sites representing 3 to 5 years’ supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s over a million units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with developers’ land banks is not that they exist - but that they are currently much too small to feed the level of house-building that we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am afraid that we have a simple choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can turn a blind eye while the dream of a property-owning democracy shrivels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th Century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t believe that anyone really wants to go down that road. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we believe in anything, we believe in the power of home ownership to motivate people to work hard, raise strong families and build healthy communities, to put down roots, take responsibility for their surroundings and look out for their neighbours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron said, “We get behind people who want to get on in life, the young people who dream of their first pay-cheque, their first car, their first home - and are ready and willing to work hard to get those things.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to resolve that we will make these decisions locally, and that we will build beautiful places like we used to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way England can remain the green and pleasant land we all love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start from a good position. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, contrary to media myth, we’ve got plenty of undistinguished, undeveloped land to spare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By overlaying satellite imagery onto Ordnance Survey maps, the Centre for Ecology and Hydrology’s 2007 Land Cover Map shows that 8.9% of England is built up or developed as gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that over 90% is not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty together account for around 30% - more than 3 times the amount that is built on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we include the green belts that stop our cities sprawling without limit then that goes up to around 40% of England is protected from development - more than 4 times the area that is built on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are ancient woodlands and other irreplaceable habitats which are protected by the National Planning Policy Framework, and other important sites which lie outside the official designations, that are rightly championed by organisations like the &lt;abbr title="Royal Society for the Protection of Birds"&gt;RSPB&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Woodland Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is high quality agricultural land which all of us want to see used for the essential purpose of growing food. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are much loved open spaces in villages and towns, which local people understandably want to keep intact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done will undermine the protection of National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty and the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or stop good agricultural land being used for farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or prevent councils from identifying ancient woodland and green spaces that local people want them to protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done involves telling communities how many new houses they should accept or where they should be built. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional top-down housing targets caused enormous resentment and as we have seen failed to deliver the goods - house-building has fallen to its lowest peacetime level since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have already revoked the regional strategy for the East of England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, having considered the responses to the consultation on the environmental report, I can announce today that I have decided to revoke the equivalent edict for Yorkshire and the Humber while saving the policies to protect York’s green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making decisions about the other regional strategies in due course, once the consultations on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;other environmental reports&lt;/a&gt; have closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the localism that Eric Pickles has unleashed is not and never has been a one-way street. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has always said, with power comes responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; spells it out very clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they draw up their local plans, councils must assess their local housing need in an objective way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they must identify immediately developable sites sufficient to supply all of the new homes that are needed over the next 5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, many councils are embracing this duty with energy and imagination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some are dragging their feet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a few are looking for ways to evade their responsibilities - or slough them off onto their neighbours because the politics of house-building is just too difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is not acceptable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils which do not produce credible plans to meet local housing need will find that the presumption in favour of sustainable development will trump local decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will have to explain to local residents why their failure to produce a robust local plan exposed their communities to speculative development in places where it is not welcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not defend and the government will not support those local councils who abdicate their responsibility to meet their fair share of our common housing needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to pretend that it will be easy for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors will have to find a way to persuade the people who elect them that substantial further house-building is in the interest of the whole community, including those who are living there now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are giving them the tools they need to go about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that people want is input into the plans for development in their neighbourhood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not just perfunctory consultation that is acknowledged but then ignored. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But real involvement and a vote on the outcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve created the option of a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood plan&lt;/a&gt;, which is drawn up by representatives of a defined community and subject to a referendum of all their neighbours, before it can be adopted and form part of the statutory plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;300 localities are already pursuing a neighbourhood plan - from Thame in South Oxfordshire to St James’ ward in central Exeter to central Milton Keynes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailblazer is Upper Eden in Cumbria, where I was on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their neighbourhood plan will be the first to be put to the test in a local referendum in March of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing people want, aside from local input and local control, is a share in the benefits that new development can bring, whether that takes the form of a boost in the local authority’s tax revenues or an investment in new community facilities or better infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt; that gives local councils over £8,000 over 6 years for every new Council Tax Band D home that gets built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils received £430 million in New Homes Bonus in 2012 to 2013 and are provisionally set to receive £660 million in 2013 to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need incentives, as Policy Exchange has pointed out, that are even more local - so that the people who have to live with new housing developments get a direct benefit from them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I am pleased to be able to announce that in areas that charge the new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; neighbourhoods which accept new development will get 15% of the revenues from the Levy (up to a maximum of £100 per existing household).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because I believe, and this government believes, that neighbourhood plans are the key to unlocking more house-building, those communities that draw up a neighbourhood plan and have it approved by local people in a referendum will receive 25% of these revenues with no upper limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to re-roof your village hall, build a permanent home for your community shop, refurbish the municipal swimming pool, implement a new landscape design in your local park or save your local pub, look no further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jump on the bandwagon and get yourself a neighbourhood plan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government believes in localism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that if you give people power, they will use it responsibly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you explain to them what their community and their country needs, they will do their bit to make sure it is provided. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you give them a stake in a future in which beautifully designed homes with easy access to green space are, once again affordable for working people on ordinary wages, they will do what it takes to bring that future about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my perch on the lower branches at the Department for Communities and Local Government, I look around the great wood that is the British government and I see other ministers battering away at the barriers that hold people back with gusto and grit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain Duncan Smith reforming the benefits system to ensure that work always pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gove giving schools control over their own destinies while ramping up expectations of the standards that they will achieve for their students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are an inspiration and a goad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inspiration because they are ministers who have identified a shocking injustice in the way our society works and are fearless in their determination to “spread the privilege” of a good education and a decent job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A goad because we are more than half way through this Parliament, and it’s now up to me to make sure that our reformed planning system provides enough land to build the houses that England’s next generation so desperately needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does, I’m sure I will have no problem sleeping at nights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
