<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-30T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17230</id>
    <published>2012-11-30T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-30T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/think-don-t-drink-drive-this-christmas"/>
    <title>THINK! Don’t drink drive this Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;THINK! and the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) are joining forces to warn drivers that getting behind the wheel after a festive tipple could see them end up behind bars this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting television advert highlighting the consequences of drink driving will be shown throughout December as part of the Department for Transport’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; today also launched its anti-drink and drug driving enforcement campaign, warning that young drivers and people driving the morning after a night of drinking pose a huge risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Drivers should be in no doubt that if they get behind the wheel after drinking this Christmas, they risk losing their licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas should be a time for a celebration not a night in the cells. That is why our TV advert reminds drivers of the consequences of a drink drive conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2011, 280 people were killed in accidents where the driver was over the limit. Our message is clear: Do not let a selfish decision ruin your life or someone else’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; roads policing lead, Deputy Chief Constable Suzette Davenport, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you don’t drink and drive this Christmas you reduce the risk of killing an innocent person, or yourself. It is really that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an absolute scourge on our society and shameful that in 2012 some drivers fail to realise the impact of drink or drug driving. Next year’s figures could include them or one of their family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, drivers aged between 20 and 24 failed more breath tests than any other age group. This year’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign is aimed at young people who are shown to be consistently over-represented in drink drive casualty figures.* &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s enforcement campaign targets well-intentioned drivers who do not think they are breaking the law but may be over the legal limit by the time they get into their cars in the morning. Police forces will be taking to roads across the country to stop and check drivers. Those found to be over the limit will face prosecution, which can lead to a jail sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DCC Davenport added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are some drivers who think they are obeying the law but are in fact breaking it by getting into their cars the morning after a night of drinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People may be surprised to hear that last year between the hours of 6am and 11am more than 400 people failed breath tests (or refused to provide a specimen), which is more than those caught for the hour before or after midnight. **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Drivers need to be aware that regardless of the time of day they are caught, whether they are going to work or taking children to school, they will face the same penalties as someone who has chosen to drink heavily in a pub and driven at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Gifford, Executive Director of the Parliamentary Advisory Council for Transport Safety (PACTS), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is good to see the department re-launching the Christmas drink-drive campaign. This advert reminds drivers that the choice is theirs but the responsibility for the wrong choice will stay with them for years to come. If in doubt, do not try to mix two activities. Stay sober at Christmas and during the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the THINK! campaign, the Department for Transport is currently consulting on a package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers. This includes removing drink drivers’ rights to demand a blood or urine test. This is because evidence shows it is used as a delaying tactic by drivers caught over the limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="note-to-editors"&gt;Note to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is provisionally estimated that 2011 saw 280 deaths, 1290 serious injuries and 9,990 total casualties directly related to drink driving incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The THINK! Christmas Drink Drive campaign budget totals £783,925 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The THINK! TV advert - Moment of Doubt - will be aired 4 December to 23 December. For a high-resolution copy of the advert contact the Department for Transport’s press office on 020 7944 6898&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK! campaign posters can be downloaded directly from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/drink-driving.html"&gt;campaign site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Christmas campaign runs from 1 December 2012 to 1 January 2013 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more information about the Department for Transport’s consultation into the removal of a driver’s right to a blood test, read this &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"&gt;recent press release&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;View the table showing drink drivers by age - article RAS51004&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;View the table showing numbers of failed breath tests - article RAS51003&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17208</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The winning entry - 'There but for the Grace of God'&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and all the others that were entered in the competition can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.faiththroughalens.co.uk/category/gallery/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens gallery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17276</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T10:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T10:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-29-november-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 29 November 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport has today published the following transport statistics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/driver-and-rider-tests-and-instructor-statistics-quarter-2-2012-13"&gt;Driver and rider tests and instructor statistics: quarter 2 2012/13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/road-freight-statistics-quarter-1-2011"&gt;Road freight statistics: quarter 1 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;statistics at DFT&lt;/a&gt; for details on all recent transport statistics releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17247</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/institute-of-advanced-motorists"/>
    <title>Institute of Advanced Motorists </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank-you also for asking me along - it’s an absolute pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="not-complacent"&gt;Not complacent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I took up my post I inherited a road safety record second to none. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This country is a genuine world leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that doesn’t mean for a single minute that it’s ‘job done’ or ‘mission accomplished’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, the provisional figures for the year ending June 2012 show a reduction in fatalities compared to the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, it is very welcome news that, for all road users, the numbers killed and seriously injured are down 17% compared with the 2005-2009 average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s also worth remembering that, while the 2011 figures were slightly up on 2010, the 2010 figures were exceptionally low, and that 2011 was still lower than 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in spite of all we have achieved, we should never forget that road deaths are not statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are someone’s mother or father, brother or sister, son or daughter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are real lives cut short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as Simon (Simon Best – &lt;abbr title="Institute of Advanced Motorists"&gt;IAM&lt;/abbr&gt;) reminded us, road accidents also hit the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers and the graphs may change from year to year, but one thing stays constant - accidents carry a heavy human cost and a huge economic price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why this government is not complacent on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we will continue to do all we can to make our roads safer in our ambition to be the safest we can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in the short time I have today I don’t want to talk you through every last dot and comma of the government’s road safety agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I would like to do is give you an insight into my thinking around some of the key priority areas as I see them - a brief but broad overview if you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="localism"&gt;Localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let me touch on an issue Simon mentioned in his speech - the important road safety role of local authorities, especially in terms of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are testing economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recognise that local government, just like central government, faces tough spending choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also know that it is local communities, rather than Whitehall bureaucrats, who are best placed to design local road safety solutions to meet local road safety challenges&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that includes deciding where to focus their resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what localism is all about - the power to choose for yourself, backed by the funding to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are giving more than £1 billion to local councils enabling them to improve the transport infrastructure – including the design of better and safer roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re investing £600 million in local transport through the Local Sustainable Transport Fund – which again gives authorities greater power to deliver their own transport projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Transport for Manchester secured £32.5 million from the Fund for their ‘Let’s get to work project’ - a project designed to give people the kind of viable travel options that allow them to make their journey to work in way that is healthier and safer, cleaner and greener, whether it’s walking, cycling or hopping on the local bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the &lt;abbr title="Local Sustainable Transport Fund"&gt;LSTF&lt;/abbr&gt; projects contain a cycling element – not just providing better routes, but also making roads safer for cyclists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take the issue of cycle safety very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial at a time when thousands of people are taking up bike riding - inspired by the heroics of our Tour de France, Olympic and Paralympic cyclists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the department has recently launched a THINK! cycle safety campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve made £30 million available to tackle dangerous junctions for cyclists across the country&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have made it simpler for councils to put in place 20mph zones - and install Trixi mirrors to improve the visibility of cyclists at junctions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycle safety is about embracing technology and changing behaviour. So we will continue to develop new ideas and initiatives to build on the progress we’ve already made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="drug-driving"&gt;Drug driving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that one of the great successes of road safety over the last 40 years has been the extent to which drink driving has become socially unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the number of drink drive deaths has fallen by more than 75% since 1979. The culture has completely changed from social necessity to social pariah, such is the view of today’s drink drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sadly, people are still losing their lives because of drink drive collisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;280 were killed last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, through our award winning THINK Campaign, we continue to push home the message that people who drive while over the limit risk losing their licence, being fined or even going to prison. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more importantly, they have to be aware that they could injure, or worse kill someone – including someone they love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve also just launched a drink-drive consultation which includes proposals to close down the legal loopholes where some drivers try to avoid prosecution by demanding to replace their breath test with blood or urine tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drink driving kills. Fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in my view, it is just as socially unacceptable and dangerous to drive while impaired by drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we tackled drink driving in the 1980s, now in the 2010s, it’s time to defeat drug driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I believe we have to make sure that drug drivers face the full force of the law, just like drink drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the government is taking three major steps to do just that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type approval will shortly be given to drug testing devices for police stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we expect to introduce road-side drug screeners during 2014&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and the new law to prosecute drug-drivers will also come into come into effect by the summer of 2014 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This government is on the side of the motoring majority who abide by the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to the reckless minority of drivers who think they can take drugs, jump behind the wheel and get away with it, my message is clear and it’s simple - you will be caught and you will be punished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-hard-core-few-and-the-law-abiding-many"&gt;The hard core few and the law abiding many&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now say a few words about the hard core few and the law abiding many. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re targeting enforcement efforts against the dangerous behaviour of the hardcore few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drivers who commit serious, deliberate and repeated offences - the ones with a poor attitude rather than poor skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told you about cracking down on drink drivers. But there’s no hiding place for the uninsured either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, for example, we’re making full use of existing powers to seize an offender’s vehicle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The police seized around 140,000 vehicles for this offence last year, and the level of uninsured driving has decreased from around 2 million drivers in 2005 to 1.2 million drivers in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also introduced the continuous insurance enforcement scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insurance industry estimate that, with the introduction of this scheme - assuming that police enforcement continues at its current rate - the level of uninsured driving could be reduced by up to 40% in the next 5 years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the law abiding many that’s good news, both for road safety and, I hope, for future insurance premiums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I believe it’s absolutely vital to support the law abiding many.
The motorists who want to do the right thing and who just need a nudge in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, that means offering more educational options to drivers who make genuine mistakes, display poor skills or commit occasional low level offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means improving training and testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the reason we’ve made changes to the practical portion of the driving test so that, instead of being taught how to pass a test, people will actually learn how to drive safely on their own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we want to tackle careless driving with proportionate sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 14 June, the government consulted on proposals to make careless driving a fixed penalty offence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorists who commit less severe examples of the offence - such as driving too close to another vehicle - would be offered training to help them improve their safety skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if anyone knows the benefits of driver education and training, then it’s this Institution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You understand the positive impact it can have on road safety by preventing collisions and crashes from taking place in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="older-drivers"&gt;Older drivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also recognise the impact of changing demographics on motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so do I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Simon pointed out, with an ageing population the number of older drivers on our roads is set to increase over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the report you’ve just launched about older drivers is a welcome contribution to the on-going debate about what this might mean for road safety and road users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the overall aim must be to maintain a balance between freedom of movement for older drivers and road safety for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; is not considering compulsory testing for older drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned the crucial factor for road safety is not age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters is skills and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters is the physical and mental fitness of the driver to drive competently and safely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that applies to young drivers as well as older drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise that we have to do everything we can to make sure young motorists are as safe as they can be on our highways, whether they are driving on the motorway, through town or along country lanes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving the safety and ability of young drivers is a key priority for the government which is why we have adapted the driving test to reflect real conditions on the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of ongoing measures to reduce the risks of accidents, the department is working with young people, the insurance industry, and other partners to identify what more can be done - and we are considering several options to ensure that newly qualified drivers are properly prepared and able to drive safely &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the use of telematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In-car technology like this means insurers now have a real time data feed which allows them to see an individual’s driving behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some evidence suggests that young drivers could see their annual premiums fall by 20% more with a black box installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But research so far also shows that telematics can significantly reduce crash rates and levels of risky driving behaviours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome the increasing number of insurers who are making use of this technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are supportive of any measures that make driving safer and also want to see improvements in young driver safety reflected in their insurance premiums. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I was always taught that there isn’t much point in silent gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as well as thanking everyone here for your hospitality today, I’d also like to say a big ‘thank-you’ to the Institute itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you don’t just campaign for safer roads - you actively do something to make them a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more than half a century you have raised driving and riding standards and improved the skills of road users, both on two wheels and four wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the years you have helped to prevent accidents, save lives and make Britain’s highways some of the safest on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as the Road Safety Minister, I want to pay tribute to everyone at the Institute - your hard work and your expertise makes a real and lasting difference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17252</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-air-rail-conference"/>
    <title>UK Air-Rail Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along, it’s a genuine pleasure to be here this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-nation-was-ever-ruined-by-trade"&gt;No nation was ever ruined by trade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Benjamin Franklin, one of America’s founding fathers, who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No nation was ever ruined by trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That statement was spot on when Ben Franklin made it back in the 18th century and it is spot on today, in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade is Britain’s economic lifeblood. We’re an island nation that’s at our best when we’re a trading nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the very reason this government is re-balancing our economy - moving Britain from a ‘spend and borrow’ past to a ‘make and sell’ future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if they’re going to trade, then our entrepreneurs have to connect - connect with customers and markets, connect with other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the modern world that usually means a business trip and a seat on a plane - which also means a journey to an airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why air-rail links matter so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the theme of your conference rightly reminds us, these links are all about ‘connecting for growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now ‘growth’ is the word on everyone’s lips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s hardly surprising in these testing times of a Eurozone crisis, a fragile global economy and a record-breaking inherited debt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, while there is sill a long way to go, recent economic figures show we are moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do think there is a tendency in some quarters to talk about growth as though it’s an abstract concept - something that’s separate and stand-alone; something with a life-force all of its very own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s almost as though some commentators believe growth will magically appear of its own volition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that it’ll come about if you say the word often enough, or you want it badly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well actually, out there in the real world, you can’t talk or wish an economy into growing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t wave a wand and conjure up growth from thin air. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can’t sit back and wait for it to fall in your lap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth comes through hard slog: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the competitive company and the skilled workforce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the inventors and innovators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the risk takers and wealth creators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and yes… a supportive and empowering government &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is who and what drives growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s where transport can play such a massive part - by providing the vital connections that help to support and sustain growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the bottom line is - the government understands the overriding economic imperative of modernising our railways, our airports and the links between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="railways"&gt;Railways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take each of those areas in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First the railways, where we’re engaged in a massive effort to renew and rebuild Britain’s rail networks - and just this summer we announced a new rail investment programme worth more than £9 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re driving through landmark projects like Crossrail, Thameslink and the Northern Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to electrify more than 850 miles of track, compared to the 10 miles electrified by the last administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, right across the country, we’re making rail travel a whole lot better with new services and extra carriages, more seats and faster journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our focus doesn’t begin and end with the conventional railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also recognise the huge potential benefits of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that our country and our economy need more than a high speed line - they need a high speed network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s exactly what we’re going to build with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only links London and Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also speeds further north to Manchester and Leeds, and possibly to Edinburgh and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only opens up business opportunities at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also opens up business opportunities abroad by ensuring passengers have an opportunity to connect up with the Channel Tunnel rail link (HS1) and Heathrow airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will, of course, give people much quicker journey times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is so much more than simply a faster way to get from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; also means more capacity and better connected cities and regions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which, in turn, means that British businesses will be able to use it to exploit new markets, win new customers and attract new investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will create and support tens of thousands of jobs and so help to power up the recovery and put people back to work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also help to deliver better life chances for millions of people by opening up access to employment opportunities and essential services like education and health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s even a persuasive environmental case for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because it will offer people and businesses a high speed, low carbon alternative to short-haul flying and long-distance motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no exaggeration to say that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will transform the way we live and work every bit as much as it transforms the way we travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So make no mistake - the government’s commitment to this game-changing project is full on and flat out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="airports"&gt;Airports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now turn to the subject of airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the Wright Brothers defied gravity in a box-shaped biplane made of spruce and covered in cotton, air travel has shrunk our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in doing so, it has also broadened our horizons, personal and business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So airports have a front and centre role in keeping our country prosperous, as well as keeping it connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we’re working hard to make sure the aviation sector continues to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the Civil Aviation Bill, legislation that will improve the passenger experience by reforming the 25 year old set of regulations that currently govern our main airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve consulted on our draft Aviation Policy Framework - a framework that forms the basis for future sustainable aviation growth in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, to increase reliability and reduce delays, we’ve been trialling operational freedoms at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re thinking ahead too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that the future of aviation in Britain is one where our airports are globally competitive and where you can connect to places all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m not talking about the future as just the next 4 or 5 years, but in terms of the next 4 and 5 decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation faces long-term challenges that require long-term solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lots of people and lots of organisations have ideas about what those solutions should look like including, I’m sure, many of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve asked Sir Howard Davies to chair an independent Airports’ Commission to explore the evidence, consider the options and make recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Howard has now named the members of his commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its terms of reference have been published. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job of work is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so let me be clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is determined to build the consensus needed to deliver a lasting solution to this country’s aviation needs, and we believe that the Airports’ Commission is the way to do precisely that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="air-rail-links"&gt;Air-rail links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you take a look at this country’s major airports you will probably notice any number of things that mark them out and make them unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look again though and you’ll also see there are 2 things they have in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they act as global gateways to new markets and new customers - which means they are not just national transport assets, they are national economic assets too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But second, they’re set to become much easier places to get to and fly from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because we’re making real and lasting improvements to those crucial connections between the train and the plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me highlight some of the key investments and modernisations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;electrification of the Midland Mainline improves access to Luton, while Valleys electrification improves access to Cardiff Airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;electrification and capacity enhancements between Leamington and Coventry enables more Crosscountry trains to run via Birmingham Airport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extra platform capacity at Redhill means more opportunity for Gatwick services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in Greater Manchester the Metrolink tram extension is due to open in 2016 and will take passengers from the city centre into Manchester Airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as part of the Northern Hub improvements, there will be an extra platform at Manchester Airport, which will allow more and longer trains to serve the airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investment in the Ordsall Chord and additional platforms at Piccadilly station means that trains from Bradford, Halifax and Rochdale will be able to get to Manchester Airport for the first time &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new £500 million rail link will give direct western access to Heathrow Airport and is expected to cut passenger journey times from the Thames Valley, the south-west, Wales and the west Midlands by around half an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once it’s completed, Crossrail will provide new services linking Heathrow with the West End, the City of London and Canary Wharf.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thanks to Thameslink, Gatwick will get new direct services to destinations north of London, such as Cambridge, Stevenage and Welwyn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, not only will &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; make it much easier for passengers from London and the south-east to get to Birmingham Airport… &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will also mean that people and businesses in the Midlands and the north of England get improved access to Heathrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an impressive list of projects and programmes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if you add it all up, what you get are train services that work for rail passengers and air passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay - whenever I make a speech I’m always conscious of the words of President Bill Clinton who gave the following advice about public speaking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;if you can’t say what you want to say in 20 minutes or less, you should go away and write a book about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’m sure that lovers of literature everywhere will be greatly relieved to know that I have no plans whatsoever to be an author - which means it’s time for me to conclude my speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I finish up though there’s something I want you to know, and it’s this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting for growth isn’t just at the top of your priority list – it’s right at the heart of our transport policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seamless air-rail journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better, faster, closer links between the station platform and the check-in desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s our vision, that’s our ambition and, step by step, that’s what we’re delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17243</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/town-and-country-planning-association-conference-speech"/>
    <title>Town and Country Planning Association conference speech</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;England is famous for the beauty of its landscapes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Yorkshire Dales to the South Hams, from the Weald of Kent to the Cumbrian Lakes, England glories in countryside of which generations of man and nature are joint authors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes - together with the greater drama of their Celtic cousins - that draw visitors to these islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes that our most popular institution and your sister organisation, the National Trust, was set up to preserve in perpetuity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of England is its finest asset and, for each of us, our most precious inheritance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative in both name and spirit, as a West Country boy and a Lincolnshire MP, as the son of a former director general of the National Trust and the brother of 1 of its conservation managers, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that nothing would do more to improve the health and happiness of the British people than if more of them got to spend more of their lives surrounded by beauty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty lifts, calms, excites, inspires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more intoxicating than any narcotic, more soothing than any therapy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Britain becomes more prosperous, we must insist that it becomes more beautiful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the beauty we seek, and the landscapes we treasure, are not only to be found in our open spaces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the loveliest scenery in Britain is to be found in our villages, cities and towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take you on a journey, which starts in my constituency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, the river Welland has snaked its way through the low contours of Lincolnshire from its source in Northamptonshire’s Hothorpe Hills.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enters Lincolnshire at the point where 4 counties meet and passes through countryside that is pleasant but hardly memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wandering painter or poet would not give this stretch of the Welland valley a second look, were it not for the landscape of Lincolnshire limestone that is the town of Stamford.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is not just 1 of England’s most beautiful towns; it is 1 of its finest bits of scenery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man-made. Built from stone and timber frames and slate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the aesthetic equal of our most splendid hills, lakes and rivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did this landscape come from?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it spring fully formed from the mind of some 17th century master planner, the brainchild of a Lincolnshire Haussman?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is, as the Royal Commission for Historic Monuments pronounced, ‘a town of discrete buildings’, each 1 unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earls of Exeter from nearby Burghley House provided long leases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the local community of wool, leather, cloth and hemp merchants, apothecaries and solicitors indulged themselves with a great variety of stone window surrounds, doorways, eaves, corner and chimney details.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did so within a broad set of rules set out in the London manuals of Rome educated James Gibbs but almost always used local architects and builders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford was the spontaneous product of human initiative, haphazardly executed and totally unplanned, motivated by the desire for profit, the love of God and that age-old urge that keeps makeover shows in business, the desire to make your house nicer than your neighbours’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop is north of the border, in Great Britain’s first New Town.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by contrast, was an example of municipal town planning at its boldest and most inspired.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the economic stagnation into which Edinburgh had slipped after the Act of Union, in 1752 the Provost, George Drummond, launched an architectural competition to design a new cityscape of wide streets, crescents and squares, featuring symmetrical terraces of town-houses as well as purpose-built shops and public gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-six year old James Craig won the competition and, in 4 stages between the 1760s and the 1850s, he, Robert Adam, William Chambers and William Playfair all stayed loyal to the original vision and developed their own variations on a Greek revival theme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In building their New Town, Edinburgh’s town councillors not only restored commercial and cultural vigour to Scotland’s capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also created 1 of the most beautiful landscapes in the British Isles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who can resist the melancholy charm of a walk in the rain around Charlotte Square and through Ainslie Place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would wager that the Facebook pages of recent visitors to Scotland contain at least as many photographs of Bute House and Moray Place as they do of Loch Lomond or Glencoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Stamford in the early 1600s, and in Edinburgh 150 later, beauty came about as a result of the natural human urge to get together with one’s neighbours to build a place in which it would be a pleasure to live and work, to raise a family and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same generous set of instincts that, another hundred and fifty years later, inspired Ebenezer Howard to build Letchworth Garden City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I am skating on very thin ice telling members of the Town and Country Planning Association anything about the Garden City movement, when your association was founded to promote just that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do want take a moment, as a layman, lacking all planning qualifications, to say why, like the Prime Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister, I believe that we have so much to learn from Ebenezer Howard and his garden cities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genius of Letchworth, like so many of the most appealing towns and cities, lies as much in the spaces between the buildings as in the buildings themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By resisting the temptation to cram as many houses as possible onto the available land and adopting their golden rule of twelve houses to the acre, Letchworth’s architects, Barry Parker and Raymond Unwin allowed room for the organic intermingling of nature and architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings are buttressed by front and back gardens, the roads are lined with broad verges and trees, the town is criss-crossed with footpaths and patchworked with allotments and parks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ebenezer Howard himself put it, “Parks and gardens, orchards and woods, are being planted in the midst of the busy life of the people, so that they can be enjoyed in the fullest measure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letchworth and the other garden cities work as living, breathing urban communities because, as an Ebenezer Howard put it, they combine “the advantages of the most energetic and active town life, with all the beauty and delight of the country.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way most English people want to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find a way to build places like this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has been holding us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only been planning minister for a few months but I have observed the debate about housing and planning for over ten years and I think I know what is wrong.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trapped in a vicious circle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at the new housing estates that have been bolted on to their towns and villages in recent decades and observe that few of them are beautiful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not to put too fine a point on it, many of them are pig-ugly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Harrisons Wharf in Purfleet that I visited last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure the flats inside are nice enough but they occupy an overbearing and unbroken slab of dismal brickwork that is an insult to the community it borders, cutting it off from a stretch of the River Thames which, in Victorian times, attracted day-trippers from London keen to take a pleasant walk along banks of the river.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since new housing estates are all too often soulless and formulaic, and those who will inhabit them will add to the pressure on local roads, primary school places and doctor’s appointments, existing residents oppose any proposal to build new houses on green field sites, even when the land is of low environmental quality.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities respond to the wishes of local voters by putting too few sites into their local plans. And this drives the cost of development land up to stratospheric levels (roughly £3 million an hectare in the South East and East of England by 2010.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers respond by stuffing as many units as they can onto any site and, in an attempt to make the properties affordable, skimp on room size, architectural features, vernacular materials, communal spaces and landscape design.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, because we don’t build beautifully, people don’t let us build much. And because we don’t build much, we can’t afford to build beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the coalition, and my personal mission as planning minister, is to help us break out of this vicious circle once and for all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get back on to that confident, progressive path, which created Stamford, Edinburgh New Town and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to build beautiful and affordable places once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have we done to bring this about? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles’ first step, in June 2010, was to scrap John Prescott’s blanket density target of 30 dwellings per hectare and to stop the garden grabbing that was destroying the precious green spaces that make Britain’s cities so pleasant to live in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government then embarked on a root and branch reform of the planning system and the creation of the National Planning Policy Framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mammoth task which had to be masterminded by a minister with a mammoth brain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my predecessor, Greg Clark, is blessed with exactly that - as well as the unfailing patience and politeness required to bring the good ship Reform to dock with most of those interested in planning and development still on board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Framework establishes a few clear principles, which it is now my job to drive through.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That local councils should take charge of development in their areas by drawing up local plans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that alongside the power to plan comes the responsibility to provide new houses to meet people’s aspirations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their local plans, councils must bring forward enough land to meet the objectively assessed housing needs of their area over the next 5 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they do so, they will be able to protect precious open spaces against speculative development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Secretary of State and I will back them to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they fail to take their responsibilities seriously, the presumption in favour of sustainable development will fill the vacuum and make the vital decisions that they are ducking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Framework, Grant Shapps introduced the New Homes Bonus, which gives local councils additional money for every new home for which they give planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in what I believe will turn out to be our most revolutionary step, the government launched neighbourhood planning through which villages, parishes and other neighbourhoods can take control of their future and decide for themselves how and where development should take place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be talking more about our ambitions for neighbourhood plans after the Autumn Statement.
So the government has acted to ensure that more land is brought forward for development and that local communities have an incentive to welcome new housing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now for planners, architects and developers, large and small, to seize the opportunity we have created and start designing beautiful places, which local people will welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, on the edge of Bishops Castle in Shropshire, Bob Tomlinson and Carole Salmon set out to create a new, contemporary village, a friendly place that people would want to live.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was The Wintles, 1 of the most exciting and enchanting collection of new houses anywhere in England.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses are all different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are unashamedly contemporary but incorporate vernacular features in a bold and imaginative way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a wide range of both natural and manufactured materials and make a priority of the spaces between the buildings (both private and communal) and the planting of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wintles did not get everything right first time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which experiment ever does?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not as integrated into the rest of Bishops Castle as some long-standing residents would like. And, to replicate it on a large scale, one would need to find a way to build houses that are just as beautiful and just as sustainable but cost less to build.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Bishops Castle I believe that the Living Village Trust created a model for our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which Ebenezer Howard would be proud.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which, once again, we build beautiful new urban landscapes full of affordable houses surrounded by green spaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be our goal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17213</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets-conference"/>
    <title>Community budgets conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome. It’s great to see so many people from right across the local authority spectrum here today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues we’re discussing couldn’t be more pressing. In fact, they go to the very heart of why we entered public life in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="complex-issues-require-local-responses"&gt;Complex issues require local responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the one thing I have learned as a local councillor and as an MP is that in every local area you will find a complex cauldron of issues requiring a sophisticated local response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in my old patch of Essex, they’re wrestling with the increasing demands of an elderly population on overstretched hospitals and care homes. But they’re also wondering how to address the rise in re-offending and domestic violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, up the other end of the country, in West Cheshire, they are looking to deal with persistent pockets of long-term unemployment, and low-economic activity. And they too are having to face down the problems of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pilots"&gt;The pilots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots were set up precisely to address these entrenched, many sided issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know these are the sorts of things governments have been talking about tackling since the year dot. But the point is our pioneers are actually involved in something radically different from what’s gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, we grew used to the man from the ministry dipping into his ever diminishing bag of tricks and pulling out another quango. We got used to broad brush, one-size fits all solutions - which actually suited nobody. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we ended up with were ill-thought through, inefficient and unnecessarily expensive, public service silos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw cash funnelled to places that were most likely getting funds from another quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw, in Essex’s case, the proliferation of services - a staggering array of eighty agencies and over 116 phone numbers offering services to victims of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we witnessed inequality, lack of access - a society less free, less fair and less united. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no actuary but when I heard that some London boroughs spend more than £25,000 on an individual with serious health conditions and less than £300 on those with minor health conditions, I sense a problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="example-of-the-problem-west-cheshire"&gt;Example of the problem: West Cheshire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you only really get a sense of the problem when you start to consider the people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the experience of one woman from West Cheshire. For the sake of her privacy let’s call her Jane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane’s husband has been going through a difficult time since he lost his job and he’s started drinking. One day Jane calls the police and reports her husband for hitting her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as her GP knows, this isn’t the first time it’s happened. It’s the 30th. And, shockingly, that’s not untypical. Nationally it takes on average 34 incidents before domestic abuse is reported. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s no coincidence that (in West Cheshire) £1.2 million is spent by GPs on managing the consequences of domestic abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story. The police assess Jane’s husband as a standard risk and order him to stay away. But within days he’s back. Smashing down the front door, putting Jane in hospital and later finding himself in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="west-cheshire-the-solution"&gt;West Cheshire: the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now West Cheshire realised the tragedy of this situation, was that it could have been avoided. They found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thanks to a subtle rewiring of the system they will now make sure Jane doesn’t have to end up in a hospital bed before anyone raises the alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-will-they-be-doing-differently"&gt;What will they be doing differently?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they’ve recognised prevention is better than cure. So they’ve developed a volunteer outreach programme providing mentoring support. It’s made up of people who have been through what Jane’s been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they’ve understood that local people can easily get bewildered by the many different “front doors” agencies. So they are ensuring Jane has a single point of contact. Someone to work with her whole family to join up the dots. That way Jane will speak to the right people at the right time to get the support she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, West Cheshire have made sure all relevant local services are in on the act. The police, local authorities, GPs and voluntary services all working together. So Jane will get beefed up security. While her husband will be made to face up to his actions and helped with his broader drinking problems.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering in this way will make a real difference to the whole family and at the same time it will save the public purse £17 million over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-people-at-the-heart-of-the-system"&gt;Local people at the heart of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s key to West Cheshire, to its fellow pilots, to the whole of our open public service reform programme - of which these initiatives form an integral part - is that they put local people at the heart of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s lives are complicated enough. We don’t need to make things even more confusing. What we do need to do is reduce dependency and give individuals a greater sense of independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know our services would be better if they were more responsive to local peoples’ needs, better serving the people that pay for them and use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, different areas work best when you, our public sector leaders are unconstrained. What’s more, free people up to innovate and they come up with ingenious, inventive solutions to complex, previously unsolved problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the magic of this approach is that it will save money. Lots of it. Greater Manchester alone, for example, reckons that improving its early years service will save £215 million over the next couple of decades for each year-group of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical? Revolutionary? Perhaps. But isn’t it also plain common sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty more I could say about the pilots. About how they’ve got eight Whitehall departments working hand in glove with local authorities. About how we’ve taken civil servants out of their ivory tower and parachuted them into the places where the problems lie. About how we’ve managed to get people from all the relevant services, in a room, round a table, talking. But actually I hope you’ll use today to find out more for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-budgets"&gt;Community budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d like to turn to another group of pioneers. I’m talking, of course, about our neighbourhood community budgets. Now these are only part way through their work, yet the signs are already encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White City, has established that around £40 million is spent on services in their neighbourhood from housing and employment to welfare benefits and adult social care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it remains one of the most deprived areas of Hammersmith and Fulham with high levels of unemployment and crime, low educational attainment and high mortality rates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now local providers and residents are sitting down together to redesign local services. At long last we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ilfracombe, in Devon, is developing an innovative virtual bank that shows local people the annual public sector investment in the town and what they are getting for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What better way to encourage local people to take the big decisions that affect their area?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Whole-Place and neighbourhood pilots are showing us the way forward. Helping us rethink how we’ve always done things. Showing us the merit of going back to the drawing board, following the money and working together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect we will find all the answers here today. But this isn’t about looking for new panaceas or new wonder cures for every one of our country’s ills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about using innovation and imagination to make the most of what we’ve got. And if you’ve ideas and thoughts on what else we can do and where we can go next, I’m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17108</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"/>
    <title>Cash boost to get England cycling</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cities, towns and villages across England are set to benefit from an extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure.  The new funding was announced today by Transport Minister Norman Baker, at a conference in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new funding will help people take to two wheels.  Projects could include better cycle facilities at railway stations, improved cycle links, or projects to improve the layout of road junctions to make them more cycle-friendly. Previous investment has seen some great projects making a real difference in communities, including better cycle routes from residential areas to schools to encourage the next generation of cyclists to cycle more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference in Leicester, attended by Public Health Minister Anna Soubry and Norman Baker, explores how councils’ health and transport officials can work better together to deliver better options for cycling and walking in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is great for your health, the economy, and for the environment so we are determined to make it easier for people to cycle whether for leisure, getting to the shops or as part of their commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the success of the Olympics, there is a huge appetite for more cycling provision from the travelling public and we need to capitalise on this enthusiasm at local and national level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are investing £20 million in cycling infrastructure and getting councils to bring an end to silo working in their offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public Health Minister Anna Soubry said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being active helps us stay healthy and protects against life threatening conditions such as heart disease, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a great way for adults to get their recommended 150 minutes of physical activity each week and this funding will help encourage more people to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million announced today is in addition to £30 million already announced for similar projects this year which drew in an additional £15 million in matched funding from local sources.  The projects to be funded will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"&gt;written statement&lt;/a&gt; was laid in Parliament this morning &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence today also published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nice.org.uk/"&gt;guidance on public health for local authorities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17109</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Additional funding for cycling infrastructure</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has today made available an additional £20m for our existing infrastructure projects to support cycling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will increase the total available for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Community Linking Places Fund (in addition to the £15m announced on 7 February 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving cycle safety at junctions (in addition to the £15m announced on 26 June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Community Linking Places Fund is primarily for improvements to cycling and walking infrastructure, facilities and links. This includes improving access to the rail network by bicycle. In addition the fund aims to support jobs, enhance access to employment and encourage greater use of more environmentally friendly transport.   Projects currently being supported were announced on 6 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment in junctions - for use by English local authorities outside London - will help to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured, or are deemed to be at greater risk.  Local authorities are currently submitting bids for funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand from local authorities, Sustrans and train operating companies, who are delivering the infrastructure, has been high.  An increase of £20m to the total funding available will allow the Government to support more high quality proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the projects to be supported under the additional funding will be published early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"&gt;Cash boost to get England cycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17338</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-value-of-parishes"/>
    <title>The value of parishes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently JK Rowling’s new novel doesn’t paint parishes in a flattering light. It’s as fictional as the boy wizard himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we love our parish people. You are localism’s magic wand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Local Government Act of 1894, you’ve been providing unrivalled help, to the smallest of villages, the largest of towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the principles you embody are hardwired into the social DNA of every hometown, every village, in every era of our history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because you care about your areas, because you are rooted in the places you love, you are prepared to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="good-works---floods-and-jubilee"&gt;Good works - floods and Jubilee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent days, as floods have drenched our towns, we’ve seen parishes, from Oxford to Devon, coming to the rescue again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laying sandbags, battening down the hatches, working with police and fire crews, doing everything they can to save their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in this great year of the Jubilee, we’ve seen parishes, stepping into the spotlight, organising Big Lunches and street parties, helping the celebrations go with a swing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, wherever I find a new parish in a rural or urban area, like Queen’s Park in Westminster, I cheer it to the rafters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because our local services are at their best when they are run by local people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me say to &lt;abbr title="National Association of Local Councils"&gt;NALC&lt;/abbr&gt;, that the role you continue to play, championing local people, ensuring their voice resounds loud and clear in the corridors of power, is absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="putting-parishes-in-charge"&gt;Putting parishes in charge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we all know parishes, have the credibility to lead their communities. So we’ve made sure you’re calling the shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve cut through the jungle of red tape that tied you up in knots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve scrapped the Standards Board that summed up everything that was wrong with local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of wasting taxpayers money on petty squabbles, we’re letting the sunlight of transparency shine through. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Localism requires local accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some councillors are concerned about publishing their business interests. The names of their spouses. Pictures of their pet goldfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as our light-touch guidance explains, only one of the above has to be on record. I won’t tell you which one. That might spoil the surprise. But here’s a clue - it’s just common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for bullies and liars, they must expect the full force of the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, local people should trust the public. You put decent people in and if they get it wrong they don’t get elected next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call it minimalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-powers-new-rights"&gt;New powers, new rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standards Board apart, we’ve also got rid of the childish power of well being which died a death every 4 years. And we’ve given you the General Power of Competence instead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils can now do anything an individual can do unless it’s specifically ruled out. These days you don’t have to get things signed-off in triplicate, if you want to, for example, back community composting, or transform a village pub into a wi-fi hotspot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of competence means you’re only limited by your imagination and your ingenuity. And when it is combined with new community rights - that let you bid to control local services like street cleaning or step in to save a much love community asset like the local pub - the implications are far reaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, some parishes will need training in the art of power. But no need to dust down your copies of Sun Tzu’s ‘The Art of War’. Just log onto the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/"&gt;my community rights website&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I strongly suspect, the more power you grab, the more power you’re going to want. That’s why we’ve also introduced neighbourhood planning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of the slim-line National Planning Policy Framework, the days of wasting time on the amount of projection of a window are gone. So too the pettifogging bureaucracy and the master planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve put local people at the heart of the system. So they get to decide where new homes, new shops and new offices should go. And which green spaces to protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your chance to remould your area in your own image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="frontrunners"&gt;Frontrunners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our neighbourhood frontrunners are already blazing a trail in Upper Eden. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventeen parishes are beavering away in the most sparsely populated area of the country to provide housing for farmers and rural businesses. They’re hoping to hold the first ever neighbourhood plan referendum in March. I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also pretty excited about what’s going on in the City to Ripon - where they’re working out how to allocate land for 160 homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="over-to-you---the-precept"&gt;Over to you - the precept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve thrust genuine power into the hands of local people. Now it’s over to you to get your parish in order; to build proper neighbourhoods, to choose activism not nimbyism. And to make sure you’re not overburdening hard working folk with increased taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn’t escaped my noticed that, at a time when most districts are freezing their council tax, the average parish precept has gone up by 3%. And the trend is seeing parish increases outstripping the rest of local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made it clear. We would look at again at the council tax referendum principles. But, as a general rule of thumb what you really need to ask yourself is this; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can you square any rise with your electorate? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can you really look your local folk in the eye?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have you really done everything you can to manage your resources, work with others, make the most of what you’ve got…?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood-budgets"&gt;Neighbourhood budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last point is critical because if there is one thing neighbourhood budgets have shown it’s the advantage of looking beyond your borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in Ilfracombe in North Devon where they’re digitally mapping their resources. Or Haverhill in Suffolk where they are bringing local business and public agencies together to equip young people with the skills local businesses need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know where to begin my department is here to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re proud of our parishes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re out there in your communities revolutionising public services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing your civilising influence to bear on all around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve given you the power but now we’re looking for you to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So be vigorous, be innovative, be independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all never forget the people you serve and you won’t go far wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17099</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-sets-out-government-support-for-lifeline-shops"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk sets out government support for "lifeline shops"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the Association of Convenience Stores, Mr Prisk described them as a vital service for the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He warned against overlooking the crucial role the army of small shopkeepers across the country plays not only economically but also socially - offering a friendly face and social hub to local communities, and especially older people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister pointed to research suggesting that around a quarter of elderly people use their local shop, often a convenience store, every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convenience stores represent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;almost 40% of all rural shops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over a third of shops in urban areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a quarter of all shops in the suburbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the age of supermarkets and online retail it’s easy to forget that convenience stores make up more than quarter of all shops. Yet they are not just an important part of the economy. For many people their local shop is also a lifeline. Whether they’re used for daily supplies or the occasional pint of milk, they are an essential part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s why this government is introducing measures specifically designed to support convenience stores. That means reforming the planning system, easing the financial pressures with business rate support, and offering practical ways to attract new custom, all in order to keep this vital local resource intact.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-support-to-convenience-stores"&gt;Government support to convenience stores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk acknowledged the new economic challenges traditional shops now face, especially the changing way that people shop - whether online or in out-of-town retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he also highlighted some of the key actions the government is taking to help them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s work to cut the deficit by a quarter in 2 years, which has kept interest rates lower for longer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new changes to the planning system to ensure that existing town centres should be the first preference for new retail facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expert support and a multi-million pound fund for Portas Pilots and Town Team Partners will encourage strong and bold local leadership to create competitive high streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doubled small business rates relief and a 20% reduction of corporation tax are helping smaller firms manage their bills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a delayed business rate revaluation, providing a more stable business environment and preventing an increase in rates for around 800,000 premises &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to help town centres adapt to changing demands, making it easier to convert empty offices into homes and bringing people back into the town centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"&gt;speech to the Association of Convenience Stores&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17387</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/speed-limit-exemption-for-life-saving-services"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemption for life-saving services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proposals to allow drivers from a wider range of emergency services to break the speed limit in order to save lives, have been published today for consultation by Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance services are already allowed to exceed speed limits in the course of their emergency response duties and this is not changing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3 month consultation exercise will examine the possibility of extending the exemption to other services including those carrying organs for transplant, bomb disposal units and coastguard vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also look at amending road safety legislation so that emergency drivers would be required by law to complete high-speed training before exceeding the limit. But this will not place any additional burden on police, fire and ambulance services which already run an effective voluntary training scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Police, fire and ambulance service drivers are highly trained individuals who are at times required to exceed the speed limit in order to save lives. It is only right that we look at allowing other services whose duties can mean the difference between life and death to exceed the speed limit when responding to emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also time to look at the legal requirements of emergency vehicle training so we can build on the rigorous standards the police, fire and ambulance services have already applied through their code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While emergency service drivers are not exempt from the offences of dangerous and careless driving, the current legislation allows drivers in some circumstances to break speed limits legally as well as exempting them from certain traffic regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consultation document can be viewed on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/speed-limit-exemptions"&gt;DfT website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services currently exempt from speed limits include Police, the Fire Service, the Ambulance Service and the Serious Organised Crime Agency (shortly to be replaced by the National Crime Agency)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The full list of services who have expressed an interest in being exempt are listed within section 5 of the consultation document, they include Ministry of Defence bomb disposal units, fire (other than for fire and rescue authorities which are covered), conveyance of human tissue for transplant, blood transfusion, mountain rescue, mine rescue, radiation emergencies, coastguard and lifeboat launching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The emergency services set up a joint emergency services’ speed limit exemption driver training group to develop their procedures. It also includes representatives from the Driving Standards Agency, the Institute of Advanced Motoring and the Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents. It has developed a Code of Practice which is based around current best practice for each of the exempt organisations and reflects what is being taught there, recognising that there are organisation specific competencies. The consultation proposes using this Code of Practice as the basis for the regulated standards for the mandatory training courses to be used following the proposed legislative change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation includes a set of criteria designed to establish the rationale of each request, balancing the operational need for the exemption against any potential road safety risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The consultation proposes amending the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984 and make any legal exemption dependent on drivers attaining the core competencies identified in the Emergency Services’ Code of Practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"&gt;Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles&lt;/a&gt; written statement by Stephen Hammond MP, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16979</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/widespread-support-for-greater-rail-devolution"/>
    <title>Widespread support for greater rail devolution</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers and local communities could achieve better rail services and value for money for taxpayers if they have more say on how their railways are run, according to responses to a government consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback published today also reveals widespread support for rail devolution. The consultation asked individuals, regional groups and interested organisations to give their views on how devolution might work and what the benefits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide the best possible rail services for passengers and ensure that we reduce the cost of running our railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring decisions are taken by those best placed to make them – those who live and work in those areas – could make certain not only that services are planned to maximise value for money for taxpayers but that passengers get services they need and want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also revealed enthusiastic expressions of interest in helping to manage the railways from regional groups in London, the West Midlands and the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responses highlighted the success of regions where the operation of rail services has already been devolved, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merseyside, where Merseytravel has been responsible for the management of rail services since 2003&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London, where Transport for London has been responsible for the operation of London Overground services since 2007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland and Wales, where the operation of regional services is managed by the Scottish government and the Welsh Assembly government&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses also showed support for transport models specifically designed for particular regions on the basis of local geography and the structure of local networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A consultation document, ‘Rail decentralisation’, was published on 8 March 2012. Comments were invited by the end of June 2012. This is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport’s response to the rail decentralisation consultation is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government remains committed to seeking to implement an appropriate form of decentralisation in those parts of England where it is sensible to do so. Following the responses to the consultation, &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue informal discussions with those bodies who have submitted proposals or firm expressions of interest. It will consider further a number of issues that need to be resolved in order to proceed with any decentralisation agreement, subject to any changes to franchising policy which may emerge from the Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most train services are specified, procured and funded centrally by the Department for Transport in London. A public consultation has shown broad support for devolving greater responsibility for local rail services to local authorities, Passenger Transport Executives (PTEs) and Transport for London, where conditions are right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposals for decentralisation have been received from the Rail in the North consortium comprising Transport for Greater Manchester, West Yorkshire PTE with York City Council and South Yorkshire PTE; Centro and Transport for London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressions of interest have been received from West of England Partnership (the Greater Bristol area), Devon and Cornwall Councils, Merseytravel, the Association of North East Councils and Cumbria County Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is envisaged that interested bodies will be ready to submit formal proposals in the first half of next year. In the meantime, the Department for Transport will continue informal discussions with these bodies as they prepare and consult on their formal proposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 70% of respondents to the consultation said they supported devolution of powers to manage the railways to regional bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17271</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/transport-scotland-high-speed-rail-summit"/>
    <title>Transport Scotland high speed rail summit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2gEnT-LreI&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA"&gt;Transport Scotland high speed rail summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello and thank you for the opportunity to put on record coalition government’s commitment to high speed rail, and its determination that all parts of our country, including of course Scotland, should benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing demand for inter-city rail travel is putting increasing pressure on existing infrastructure. Without planning for additional capacity, passengers face the prospect of increasingly crowded and more unreliable services. To be clear, the primary, though not the only, justification for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a clear need for extra capacity north to south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plans for a high speed rail network from London to the West Midlands and on to Leeds and Manchester will be the backbone of a new transport system for the 21st century.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2026, Phase 1 of High Speed 2 will link London and Birmingham. Comfortable trains travelling at 225 miles per hour will cut the journey time to just 45 minutes, compared to the 84 minutes it currently takes. Importantly for Scotland, the first phase of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide connections to the existing network at Birmingham, and also link &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt;, opening up the opportunities for through trains to run from Scotland to Paris and Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completion of the Y network to Leeds and Manchester will further spread the benefits of high speed rail across the country, increasing capacity and enhancing connectivity all the way to Scotland by relieving pressure on the most congested southern end of the line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition agreement makes it clear that our ultimate goal is a genuinely national network, with high speed services from London to the Midlands and the north, including Scotland. We see phases one and two of the High Speed 2 project as the best way to make progress towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport ministerial team is very much engaged in the question of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; as it affects and, indeed, benefits Scotland. I visited Glasgow last year, the former Secretary of State went in March this year, and the current Secretary of State intends to visit later this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last month we announced the launch of a study on ways to get fast journeys further north and to Scotland, making sure that the north-east benefits too. The aim is to fully understand and articulate transport needs in Scotland and the north of England, setting out the remit for any future work, using completion of the ‘Y’ network as a starting point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study won’t start with any preconceptions but will be open to all options that offer good value for money to the taxpayer. This may include a full high speed solution, upgrades to existing infrastructure, or a combination of the two.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands today the network is expected to deliver up to £50 billion of business benefits alone and that will be felt very much in Scotland and the north of England as well as the South. The claim by some opponents of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; that better and faster transport links between north and south will see economic activity pulled into London and away from the UK’s other great cities is defeatist and misguided, and out of line with public opinion. The further north you go, the louder are the voices in support of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing Edinburgh and Glasgow closer to London as well as the cities of the midlands and the north of England will undoubtedly boost growth across all of our major conurbations. That confidence is based on the evidence from our European neighbours, who began their high speed rail journey a generation before we had even started arguing about our first 67 mile stretch of high speed track from the channel tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With passengers enjoying faster journeys, there has been more extensive modal shift between rail and air as the train becomes the mode of choice for more travellers. High speed rail is already greener than flying and the gap between the two modes will widen as we make progress in decarbonising the sources of our electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will benefit every type of traveller, not just on the new network, but on existing lines too, freeing up more space and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, not only will high speed rail help boost the Scottish economy and support thousands of jobs in Scotland and throughout the UK, it gives us a once-in-a-generation opportunity to reshape the economic geography of the whole country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever way you look at it, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a national scheme in the national interest driven by a national government. Realising the full benefits of high speed rail for Scotland is crucial to the economic wellbeing of the whole country, and I can assure you we will continue to work very closely with our partners in Scotland to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17189</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/inter-faith-week-and-a-year-of-service-speech"/>
    <title>Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service speech</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to thank you all for coming to this a wonderful event, marking both Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks also to the Faith-based Regeneration Network, Mitzvah Day, the Co-exist Foundation and others for their help in making the event a reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for the people here, it’s Inter Faith Week every week and it’s A Year of Service every year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because day in, day out, you are giving your time, your energy, your hearts and your souls to making your communities better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United by faith and driven by faith - whichever faith that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Sikh-run Nishkam Centre in Birmingham, which provides a whole range of training and educational opportunities for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Sewa Day, which inspires Hindus across the country to acts of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like the St Vincent de Paul Society, which provides gifts and hospitality to the needy in the run-up to Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These projects and many more prove that faith motivates good works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today you have a government that doesn’t deny that fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a government that supports, celebrates and - in my case - shares that motivation. A government that does God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know that people who ‘do God’ do good things up and down the country every single day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys show people of religious observance are more likely to become volunteers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see that fact in the 30,000 faith-based charities making a difference throughout Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="interfaith-action"&gt;Interfaith action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the interfaith movement officially started in 1893 with the ‘World’s Parliament of Religions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s major religions came together in Chicago for serious discussions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I don’t think they would have a parliament; they’d have a day of social action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because today interfaith dialogue has become much more about interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always argued that interfaith shouldn’t just be tea in a draughty church hall or a samosa in the local mosque between the imam and the vicar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t just be clergy to clergy: it should be congregation to congregation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I helped get a programme called Active Faith off the ground - which, of course, became Near Neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the wonderful projects we see here today are just a small selection of the 300 local projects that have been supported so far.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producing projects like the Departure Café, a drop-in centre and community hub for Tower Hamlets, which I hope to visit soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of local congregations coming together to ‘do their bit’ underpin our support for the A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’ll agree - there can be no better way of marking Her Majesty the Queen’s many years of service to our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Year of Service has produced some fantastic projects, like the wonderful Mitzvah Mummies, who I went to see yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers and their toddlers, meeting, talking to and sharing moments with residents of a retirement home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integenerational interaction - such a simple idea and so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Faith and Communities, every day I see the power and the potential of interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last Thursday as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a catch-up with the Chief Rabbi… A meeting with Christian groups… An introduction with the Buddhist Network… A speech at my department’s Eid event… And a House of Lords debate on the importance of religion in society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the common thread running through these events wasn’t the fact these people observed a faith. It was that they were inspired to do good things as a result of their belief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I’m so proud that we have so many local and national 300 inter faith organisations in the UK - more than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I’m so proud that 3 Faiths Forum, the Joseph Interfaith Foundation, the Christian-Muslim Forum are leading the way in the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I am so heartened to see the launch this week of advice to couples and families on interfaith marriages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-identities"&gt;Stronger identities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had my own theory on inter faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that if you are stronger in your identity then you are more tolerant of others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who don’t associate with people of other beliefs because they think it somehow weakens theirs - they have got it the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if you’re a person who unites with people of other faiths for a common goal - it doesn’t make you less of a Muslim, less of a Hindu, less of a Jew - it makes you more of one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is no more powerful demonstration of one’s security in one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I went to the Vatican earlier this year and argued that Europe should be stronger in its Christian identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Christian heritage of Britain is what has made me feel comfortable here in practising my faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending my daughter to an Anglican convent school made her feel stronger in her identity. When she would swap ‘Amen’ for ‘Ameen’ during the Lord’s Prayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain leads the world in its interfaith ethos. But I think we can build on the progress we’ve made since that conference in American back in 1893. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that if we - people of all faiths and none - pull together, we can defeat the intolerance and bigotry faced by people of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, an attack on a mosque is an attack on a church; an attack on a gudwara is an attack on a synagogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, an attack on one faith is an attack on all faiths. So let’s be inspired by the story of Siavosh Derakhi, who has recently been recognised for founding Young Muslims Against Anti-Semitism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by the words of President Obama, following the release of the abhorrent, gratuitously offensive ‘Innocence of Muslims’ film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he said: “to be credible, those who condemn that slander must also condemn the hate we see when the image of Jesus Christ is desecrated, churches are destroyed, or the Holocaust is denied. Let us condemn incitement against Sufi Muslims, and Shia pilgrims.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by all the good things that are done and can be done in the name of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the subject of inspiration I want to present this beautiful piece of artwork.
Doctor Fox, I know you’re accepting this on behalf of the Evelina Hospital, so thank you, and also to the extremely talented artist Sam Cowan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m off to see some more fantastic artwork now as I go and award the winner of the Faith Through a Lens competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me once again thank you for coming today and thank you for all you do. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17020</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speed-limit-exemptions-for-emergency-vehicles"/>
    <title>Speed limit exemptions for emergency vehicles</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department has today published a consultation paper on Speed Limit Exemptions for vehicles used for emergency purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper proposes that Section 19 of the Road Safety Act (2006) is brought into effect. Section 19 allows the Secretary of State for Transport to designate other vehicle purposes as being exempt from speed limits in certain circumstances and if drivers of said vehicles complete successfully a “high-speed training course”.  Section 19 replaces Section 87 of the Road Traffic Regulation Act (1984) in relation to exemptions from speed limits for certain vehicle purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department recognises that there are certain vehicle purposes that the wider public may well consider as having a speed limit exemptions but which do not currently.  These include, for example, vehicles used to carry human tissue for transplant, mountain rescue teams, bomb disposal squads and others listed in the consultation document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branches of the Emergency Services (Police, Fire Service &amp;amp; Ambulance Service) are currently exempt from speed limits and provide appropriate training to their staff.  No additional requirements will be placed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has worked with representatives of the police, fire and rescue, NHS ambulance services, the Serious Organised Crime Agency and road safety stakeholders on the development of standards for driver training.   This led to the creation of a code of practice based on the principles applied in each organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department seeks to identify the core competencies specified in the code of practice and include them in regulations. It also proposes that the Driving Standards Agency (DSA) will take responsibility for the accrediting and quality assuring training providers seeking to provide high speed driver training courses, against the competences identified in the code of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further consideration within the consultation document is to exempt paramedics and other medical personnel from the requirements to wear seatbelts in the back of ambulances, particularly when providing emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17100</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"/>
    <title> Heart of the Community conference 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be able to join you at this, my third Association of Convenience Stores conference, though I don’t think that earns me a Crackerjack pen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to pay tribute to James Lowman and the work of the Association. Whilst we have not always agreed, I have always found James to be both persistent and effective, in putting your case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it was following talks with James that I pressed for, and secured, a 3 year moratorium for small shops from the tobacco display ban, (much to the chagrin of the supermarket groups!). This was partly because of the points James made on how a convenience store is run, so his knowledge is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tough-times"&gt;Tough times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I recognise as someone who has been involved with business, and the government recognises, that these are tough times for retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer incomes are under continuing pressure. The uncertainty in the Eurozone has prolonged the credit crunch. And of course there is increasing competition, which only squeezes your already tight margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, alongside the established competition from the supermarkets and out of town centres, we are also seeing a long term shift in consumer habits, as the online market grows. In fact, I was looking at the numbers and online sales have doubled in the last decade, to make up 10% of UK retail sales. That trend is only going to continue, and begs real challenges for all of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in consumer habits is not wholly bad for smaller bricks and mortar retailers. Indeed it has been shown to actively help specialists or those with a particular offer to reach much wider markets. But it means that the question for all retailers is no longer whether you should adapt your business, but how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a very important shift which we in government must respond to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="value-of-convenience-sector"&gt;Value of convenience sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In government, we recognise the economic worth of the retail sector, both by turnover and measured by the number and type of jobs. Retailing is, for example, one of the most important ‘first’ employers, with a third of all retail employees, aged under 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a social value in small shops, (and particularly in the convenience sector) which we should not ignore, as indeed your research has shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A local convenience store is often one of the few places, where people meet and talk today. In villages and on many estates, it’s you and it’s your staff who know the local community, (and make time to talk to the elderly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representing 40% of all rural shops (and a third of shops in our towns), it’s the convenience sector which is usually there for a whole range of customers - perhaps those who don’t have a car, for young families, and for the elderly. It’s not to say that you aren’t economically important, but I also recognise the social benefit of a diverse, convenience sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, both as a constituency MP and as a member of Parliament, as well as a user of my local convenience store, and on behalf of the many customers who rely on the service and care you and your staff provide, let me say thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-can-be-done-to-help"&gt;What can be done to help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former businessman, I understand that of course empathy doesn’t pay your bills, or help you compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I would like to do if I can, is explain what we’re doing in government to help business generally, and retailing in particular, to weather the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think it’s important that we have been able to keep interest rates lower for substantially longer, by cutting the financial deficit by a quarter. The fact that we’ve been able to do this over the last 2 and a half years is vital. Clearly, there’s a difference between what we the government and you as retailers can borrow, but if we had continued to borrow, interest rates would have soared, crippling businesses and families alike. We can all see what that means, when we look abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So low interest rates have helped. But the government has also acted to cut your costs. We have cut corporation tax rates to 24 pence for larger firms, and to 20 pence for smaller businesses. And we have reversed plans to increase National Insurance contributions, which would have hit jobs hard. The Association of Convenience Stores were amongst those who helped to make that point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we came into office, we also acted to help cut business rate bills. It’s why we extended and doubled the small business rates relief that’s helped thousands of small shops pay their bills, and it’s why we have now given councils new powers to discount rates, (funded locally), to help those firms which are struggling. It’s a new power, only a few months old, and only a few councils have taken it up. I am sure the association will want to change that. In fact, your own submission to the Treasury says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s there, now all they need to do is use it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, our financial room for manoeuvre is very limited but we are listening carefully to your concerns and will try and help where we can. However, as I’d like to remain a minister, I won’t pre-empt the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently we have delayed the planned revaluation from 2015 to 2017. This is an important issue. Let me explain our thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we know that the last thing businesses needed right now, is the uncertainty which a revaluation would create. You get your valuation, there’s the counter valuation, appeals which leads to 18 months of uncertainty. It isn’t the right time to be doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we looked carefully at the independent evidence produced by the Valuation Office Agency as to who the likely winners and losers would be. We were and you might be surprised by the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Valuation Office Agency’s analysis shows that some 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates bill, with roughly 300,000 benefitting. Indeed many of the businesses represented here would have seen big hikes, in some cases up to 28%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems counter-intuitive, but the reason for this, is that because the revaluation must be revenue neutral, to compensate for lower rateable values, the tax rate would have to increase by approximately 20%. As a result, many businesses whose rents have fallen by less than the national average, which is how it is balanced, would have seen business rate bill goes up from 2015. We have asked business to come in so that we can explain how this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we felt, on balance, that now is not the time to be making this revaluation and in doing so we believe we can help many businesses in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that for many people, they think, ‘my rents have gone up’ but because there are 2 elements to business rates it doesn’t quite work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="town-centres-need-to-compete"&gt;Town centres need to compete&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s not just individual shops that need help. It’s also the traditional high street and many of our town centres. And our role should not be not to protect, but to enable. To ensure that our high streets are able to adapt to changing markets and consumer habits, so you can compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why last year the Prime Minister asked Mary Portas to review what needs to be done, by government, by local authorities and by business itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has produced an excellent report and brought her typical real energy and a keen consumer eye to the towns wanting to pilot this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s actually happening on the ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, our Town Centres First policy is an important and explicit part of our new National Planning Policy Framework. What it means in practice is that town centres should be the first preference for new retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we want to reform, planning to help town centres adapt. This means making it easier for the conversion of redundant first floors into homes, and secondly to enable empty offices that can often blight some high streets to also be converted into homes. Both these measures will bring people back into the town centre, increase footfall and so help existing retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we believe that strong local leadership is vital if towns are to be renewed. That is the clear lesson from both the Portas pilots and what we see regularly from successful shopping centres, who manage the whole customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If struggling high streets and town centres are to compete, they need the right people to deal with the promotion, management and coordination of their ‘centre’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we announced last month the creation of over 320 town team partners, who will get the expert advice, mentoring and support they need, to get an effective business plan in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went to Deptford, where I met the leaders of their town team, who are using one-stop shops and community cafés to make the most of what they feel is their unique selling point - its significant cluster of local artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UuacApa2aUE"&gt;Deptford visit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They plan to bring benefits to the entire high street, install art in the high street and set up shops as galleries under the ‘Made in Deptford’ banner to bring more people in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a really encouraging visit and just shows what together local civic and business leaders working as a partnership can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="physical-change"&gt;Physical change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course if towns are to compete, they need to address other issues than those I mentioned: from actively promoting local markets; through to being innovative, when managing and charging for local parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, lets be honest many need to change their appearance. And getting empty shops occupied is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why my predecessor Grant Shapps provided a £10 million High Street Innovation Fund, specifically to help those areas with the worst levels of empty shops. We’re already starting to see this helping to bring run down shops back into use, with other businesses kicking off as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think we can do more. The pop up shop movement, which helps new businesses set up and sell, is a great idea. Its something I want to impress on both landlords and tenants, and see expand right across the country, not least as it helps new firms start and will generate additional footfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am in talks with the Pop Up Britain team, led by Emma Jones, to see how we in government can help promote pop up shops across the country, and I hope to have something positive to say about it very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-next-step"&gt;The next step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope you can see, as a government we believe that much can be done to help retailers and our town centres compete. But it has to be a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government, councils, businesses and local people (especially) need to be engaged and feel that they can make a difference. This involves a long term shift and short term squeeze. This won’t be easy and many towns will struggle, especially where that sense of collaboration is missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can be done. As the people in Deptford have shown, if there’s the right imagination, will and support our high streets can have a great future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be different to what went before, but it’s vital that once again our town centres regain their role, at the heart of our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17358</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T13:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/serious-fraud-office-inspection-report-published"/>
    <title>Serious Fraud Office inspection report published </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General has today published HM Crown Prosecution Service Inspectorate’s report on the Serious Fraud Office (&lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspection found significant process failures and other weaknesses, which the agency needs to address to improve performance. The Inspectorate also identifies strengths, for example in analysis and presentation of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report makes eight recommendations, all of which the new &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; Director, David Green &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt;, has accepted. Changes instigated in the past few months have begun to address the issues of concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM Chief Inspector Michael Fuller &lt;abbr title="Queen's Police Medal"&gt;QPM&lt;/abbr&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The inspection found that there was a great will to see the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; succeed. But much needs to be addressed if the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is to become a respected crime fighting organisation which is the envy of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with all our inspections, this report represents a tool for improvement and I welcome the fact that David Green has already asked us to return within two years to see that progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our inspection team was tailored for this task, supported by specialist fraud investigators/prosecutors and two police fraud specialists. I would like to thank all the people, not least the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; staff, who gave us their views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the report, the Attorney General, Dominic Grieve &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt; MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would like to thank HM Chief Inspector and his team for this very helpful report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling economic crime and complex fraud must be a priority and I wanted to ensure from the outset that the work of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; should be subject to independent inspection to ensure that processes and practices are continually improved. I am grateful to the former Director, Richard Alderman, for inviting the Inspectorate in to the Department and for the current Director, David Green CB &lt;abbr title="Queen's Counsel"&gt;QC&lt;/abbr&gt;, for taking the majority of the review work forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While there are clearly problems to address, I am encouraged that the inspection team also found that the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; does many things well and that the direction in which the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is now headed is the right one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The report also makes clear the compelling case for investigators and prosecutors working together, as they do at the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;, as the model best suited to the kind of complex cases the agency was set up to take on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The report was published via Written Ministerial Statement with copies laid in the House libraries. It is also published on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hmscpsi.gov.uk"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty’s Crown Prosecution Service Inspectorate"&gt;HMCPSI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unlike the Crown Prosecution Service, there is no statutory basis for the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; to be subject to inspection. Therefore it was inspected by agreement with the Attorney General and at the invitation of the former Director. There is no formal requirement to publish; the report was made to the Attorney General, who confirmed to Parliament in July his intention to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The report does not refer to specific cases due to the operational sensitivities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inspection was carried out during March and April 2012. The report was passed to the Attorney General’s Office on 8 November.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
