<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59902</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK condemns the decision by the Jerusalem District Planning Board to give approval for a plan to build 1,500 housing units in the East Jerusalem neighbourhood of Ramat Shlomo, and is extremely concerned by reports that the Board is considering giving the approval to a further 5000 housing units in East Jerusalem this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on yesterday’s announcement the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Israeli settlements are illegal under international law, and I condemn this decision. It is deeply disappointing that despite the international community repeatedly raising our concerns, Israel continues to press ahead with plans to expand them.  Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties.  This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.  If implemented, it would make a negotiated two-state solution, with Jerusalem as a shared capital, very difficult to achieve.  We  urge Israel to reverse this decision and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity”
.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57535</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-pop-up-shop-to-showcase-high-street-entrepeneurs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens pop-up shop to showcase high street entrepreneurs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s efforts to regenerate high streets and encourage entrepreneurs, the shop is being opened in time for final Christmas present buying this week by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk, with the support of national enterprise campaign StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To directly support enterprise and showcase Britain’s best new retailers, ministers have set up the pop-up store inside their Victoria-based office building to act as a blueprint for high streets across the country to emulate through schemes such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cutting the ribbon on the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5697/ribbon-cutting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles cutting the ribbon with Mark Prisk and Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the first ever Whitehall pop-up shop with ‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell. Every fortnight six new British start-up businesses will move into the shop, sharing costs and trialling their exciting ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop will be open to the public for at least a year and will offer affordable retail space to over 150 small start-up businesses. The department is not seeking any financial return from the shop, which is being supported by sponsors Intuit, John Lewis, SNR Denton and StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5698/shop-floor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The first 6 pop-up tenants are NANUKK, Milla &amp;amp; Arti, Arthur &amp;amp; Henry, London Mummy, Morrow’s Outfitters and The English Tee Shop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe pop-ups are a great way to get empty spaces used and could be easily replicated in other town centres across the country. Mr Prisk has written to the British Property Federation to urge landlords to get on board. He said that, starting in January, all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Town Team partners will receive support to facilitate new pop-ups in their empty high street premises, which could support thousands of new businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to rejuvenating the high street. A multi-million pound strategy is backing local partnerships such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams to breathe new life into their town centres. This includes a doubling of small business rate relief; mentoring from retail experts; and workshops to address town centre challenges. A guide to opening a pop-up will be published soon and StartUp Britain has published a tool kit today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is providing over £80 million of start-up loans for young entrepreneurs, which could create over 30,000 new businesses. Ministers are also changing planning restrictions so that landlords can alter how an empty shop is used for up to two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these steps will make it easier for start-ups to find other low-cost stores to set up in. Last year 450,000 people set up new businesses and almost two thirds of new start-ups say they would benefit from trading on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are absolutely determined to support the high street and we know pop-ups are a great way to bring empty shops back to life and get new businesses going, so we thought ‘why not open one right here in the department?’. It will also showcase how we can unleash more of our best and brightest young entrepreneurs onto the country’s high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The PopUp Britain model gives retail entrepreneurs an affordable opportunity to scale up their businesses and become a part of their own high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing record numbers of people setting up businesses and they are starting out small and online. They are the driving force of the economy. This initiative offers them a chance to physically test out new markets as well as get their products in front of consumers and big buyers in a way that has never been available to them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By actively encouraging local authorities to give start-ups access to empty shops across Britain, we hope it will help accelerate British enterprise as well as providing a vibrant addition to the local British shopping experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real appetite in our town centres to get them revitalised so they remain attractive places to visit. And it’s not just talk: there are many extremely capable and serious people with some superb ideas; but they need a bit of help to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up shops are a superb way for all sorts of entrepreneurs to test their ideas. So I’m delighted that this department is opening the first pop-up shop in Whitehall and I look forward to inviting all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Towns Teams here to see how they could replicate this model across the country in the new year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a brilliant idea and it is great to see the government actively supporting business in this way. For many aspiring and growing enterprises, having access to a retail unit where new propositions and ideas can be tested directly with customers can be the catalyst to increase sales. I hope other landlords follow this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the Bright Ideas Trust, where we invest in businesses started by young unemployed people, we see many business struggle to secure retail space as they grow out of their bedrooms and away from their kitchen tables.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=neKNqnTu6qY"&gt;Pop-up shop event video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="startup-britain"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startupbritain.co/"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/a&gt; is a national campaign by entrepreneurs for entrepreneurs, harnessing the expertise and passion of Britain’s leading businesspeople to celebrate, inspire and accelerate enterprise in the UK. The campaign was founded by eight entrepreneurs and was launched in March 2011 by the Prime Minister. It has successfully run pop-up stores in Richmond, Surrey, which opened in July and which have already helped 42 businesses get access to the high street. Four in five of the tenants said the experience had been good for their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-six-pop-up-britain-victoria-tenants"&gt;First six pop-up Britain Victoria tenants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established 6 months ago by 27-year-old Shrewsbury-based designer Sarah McLeod, silk scarf company &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nanukk.com/"&gt;NANUKK&lt;/a&gt; features beautiful pieces of Art printed onto silk fabrics. All the scarves are made in England. Sarah has been labelled as one to watch, after she was awarded the River Island Graduate Fashion Week Award in 2008. 
Sarah said: “It will be great to have a physical presence in the marketplace at last! So far I’ve only been online. People will love the feel of my silk scarves and I hope it will make them buy. I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millaandarti.co.uk/"&gt;Milla &amp;amp; Arti&lt;/a&gt; was set up by product design consultant Deborah Reyner 18 months ago. Her British-made homeware collection includes bespoke lavender hearts for weddings, patchwork kits, gift ties and ribbons, collars and bows. 
Deborah said: “This is a wonderful opportunity for Milla &amp;amp; Arti and to talk about my products which are made by the British seaside and get people interested in making and doing themselves. I haven’t been able to sleep for a week before this, I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brother and sister Mark and Clare Lissaman named their ethical organic cotton men’s shirt company after their grafting grandfathers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.arthurandhenry.com/"&gt;Arthur &amp;amp; Henry&lt;/a&gt; was developed after ethical consultant Clare noticed there were no ethical formal shirts on the market. “I was at the World Congress on Organic Cotton a few years back and realised that although all the men attending were passionate about organic cotton - none were actually wearing any as they were all suited up and couldn’t find proper smart shirts in organic cotton,” Clare, from Islington, said. “So we thought we’d make some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re thrilled and delighted to have this opportunity. For a newly established, ethical menswear brand, this is an amazing opportunity to meet customers face-to-face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single mum and former interior designer Esther Gibbs, from Chiswick, created &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmummy.com/"&gt;London Mummy&lt;/a&gt; after people kept asking her where she bought the cushions and accessories she had made herself. All her products are now either made in England – some by Esther herself - or by women’s collectives in China. Her handpicked selection includes retro bed linen, colourful crochet animals, quirky kids’ stationery, classic toys and games, funky lunchboxes, wall art and more. Esther also makes beautiful children’s fabrics, which she sells in store too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther said: “I sell online but I’ll sell much more in the shop. Once people understand what the shop is about and what it’s doing for small British businesses, it will be a great asset for the high street and small businesses. I’m delighted to be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sock entrepreneur Philip Morrow, 25, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.morrowsoutfitters.com/"&gt;Morrow’s Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; last year as a way to re-establish his great-grandfather’s former gentlemen’s outfitters shop that operated in Liverpool between 1912 and 1987. His range of Loughborough-made cotton socks come in over 40 designs and colours. 
Phillip said: “Pop-up shops make a great deal of sense for small online businesses such as mine. I’m over the moon about getting the opportunity to come into PopUp Britain in Victoria.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-time English teacher and designer Alia Qadir, 30, from Ealing, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theenglishteeshop.com/"&gt;The English Tee Shop&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to combine her passion for fashion and love of grammar! All her cotton is English-made and printed. She sells online and runs her business part-time from home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia said: “Until now I have relied on my online presence to sell my brand. But my T-shirts are made from a really good quality, soft jersey, and that doesn’t come across online. I’m really delighted about this new pop-up adventure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-town-team-tool-kit"&gt;New Town team tool kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the prototype shopping concept comes a newly-developed pop-up-specific tool kit for Town Teams to implement, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a national pop-up lease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a central website with information about the initiative for town teams and new businesses interested in applying for a slot at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.popupbritain.com"&gt;www.popupbritain.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to free pop-up payment equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a step-by-step guide for setting up a PopUp Britain shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PopUp Britain branding to make the shop recognisable to the consumer as a place where they can support British enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review, the department is running a number of high street Town Team Portas Pilots in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs. Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams in May, and 15 more in July, with three from London, bringing the total to 27. They each receive up to £100,000 of funding plus support from Government and retail expert Mary Portas. More detail can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"&gt;Improving high streets and town centres pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-teams"&gt;Town Teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 330 Town Team Partners support includes: an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management; special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and support from industry experts and trade bodies including an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice; regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas; and ‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work. All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919132719/www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;List of Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="statistics"&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key statistics and evidence on start-ups in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 saw a record high for start-ups: over 450,000 people set up a company
 and became their own boss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a StartUp Britain poll revealed 82% of start-ups found the pop-up experience was valuable for their business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the UK, there are 4.8 million private sector companies employing an estimated 23.9 million people with a turnover of £3,100 billion. Small and medium-sized enterprises also account for almost half of the net growth in jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to the latest figures from the British Retail Consortium, 11.3% of shop premises in UK town centres are now vacant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to research from StartUp Britain, 63% of businesses not already on the high street think their business would benefit from a high street presence and, of these, 88% believe funding is the biggest barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="additional-quotes"&gt;Additional quotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Johnson, Chairman of StartUp Britain, former Pizza Express boss and Chairman and part-owner of Patisserie Valerie and Giraffe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new high street name that will become synonymous with buying British and supporting small British enterprise is a fantastic idea. I’m sure PopUp Britain will be embraced by town planners and local government as a way to offer tangible support to their own high streets and start-up communities.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Russell, Chief Executive of WeArePopUp, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-ups are ideal incubators for the next generation of entrepreneurs. It’s very encouraging to see the Government opening a national showcase in a high-profile location such as Cardinal Place in Victoria. Pop-ups can change the fortunes of local communities and we look forward to this support encouraging more landlords to open up their empty shops and become part of the solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosie Cann, Director at Popupspace, a property consultancy that specialises in pop ups, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find space for lots of established retailers, but the challenges for new businesses wanting to open shops are much wider. What we have here is a unique offering to smaller start-ups looking for affordable space to sell, but also for business support and a high profile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Little, UK Managing Director of Intuit, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up tenants need to be able to accept card payments but it can take weeks to get set up, the equipment and transactions can be expensive and require long-term contracts. Intuit is proud to support PopUp Britain with Intuit Pay, giving start-up retailers a way to get set up in minutes to securely take card payments on their smart phone or tablet – with no commitment and no contracts. With Intuit Pay anyone can now accept card payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the shop are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269606220/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57532</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-joy-for-old-soldier-who-finally-got-his-medal"/>
    <title>Christmas joy for old soldier who finally got his medal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Army veteran Joe McKenna, 72, who volunteers at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/" title="Duke of Lancaster's Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum"&gt;Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Preston, left the military in 1970 just months before his Northern Ireland service medal was minted and eventually decided to track down his medal after years of attending parades where he was the only veteran not wearing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Bob Dixon, from 2 Medical Regiment and a fellow volunteer at the museum, offered to help Joe claim his honour. Sergeant Major Dixon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had been helping some visitors at the museum with enquiries about their service medals and so I offered to help Joe too. I got all the paperwork together, went around to his house, and we filled in the documents before sending them off to the MOD Medal Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We got a reply within 2 months, the quickest I’ve ever known; I think the turnaround was so fast because he still lives at the same address that appeared on his service papers back in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe enlisted in the Loyal Regiment, a forebear to the North West’s current infantry regiment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/3477.aspx" title="The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;The Duke of Lancaster’s&lt;/a&gt;, almost exactly 51 years ago and served in Kenya, Swaziland, Cyprus and Malta as well as in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern Ireland service medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5711/Joe_smedal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Joe McKenna's Northern Ireland service medal [Picture: Sergeant Mark Garry, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After he left the Army as a Lance Corporal in 1970, Joe worked for more than 30 years as an &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; driver, married Josie, with whom he had his children Sandra and Peter, and is now a grandfather of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said until recently the distractions of day-to-day life meant he just never got around to claiming what was his: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was only when I was marching at the Armed Forces Day parade in Preston last summer when I thought ‘I’m getting on a bit now and I should really get my medal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think my son would like to have it when I’m gone; he and my daughter think that it is marvellous that it’s finally here. It’s the best Christmas present ever and it makes me very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe’s wife Josie added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It really was something special to see his face when he received the medal; it was as if all his Christmases had come at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe now plans to wear his medal at his regiment’s Kimberley Day service and parade in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57555</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-sutherland-returns-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Sutherland returns in time for Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship was greeted by cheering and waving families and friends wearing festive hats and holding banners with loving messages at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;HM Naval Base Devonport&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth on Saturday 15 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship’s Culdrose-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopter flight arrived back separately at the Helston air station on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Sutherland" title="HMS Sutherland"&gt;HMS Sutherland&lt;/a&gt; has been busy conducting anti-piracy and terrorism patrols as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/Combined-Maritime-Forces" title="Combined Maritime Forces"&gt;Combined Maritime Forces&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring the sea lanes and waters east of Suez and off the Horn of Africa are safe for seafarers to conduct their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship conducted boarding operations on suspect vessels and also reassurance visits to build relationships with mariners and obtain information on pattern of life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="AS(ME) Dale Plumpton kissing Terri Layden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5729/Sutherland5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Able Seaman (Marine Engineering) Dale Plumpton receives a welcome home kiss from Terri Layden [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crew also exercised with coalition and allied forces in the region to strengthen ties and improve methods of working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland’s Commanding Officer, Commander Al Wilson, said it was a ‘magic’ time to come home at Christmas. He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The huge variety and diversity of task that Sutherland has fulfilled whilst on operations illustrates the inherent flexibility of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; in protecting and promoting UK interests worldwide, whether it is preventing piracy or terrorism at sea or strengthening bonds with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, I could not have achieved this without an efficient, capable and highly motivated ship’s company and, as always, I am highly proud of what my team has achieved over the last 6 months whilst remaining cheerful and utterly professional throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My team and myself are now looking forward to spending Christmas at home with our loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Navy personnel on board HMS Sutherland" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5730/Sutherland4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Petty Officer on board HMS Sutherland waves to the waiting families on the dockside as the ship comes into port [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Able Rate (Communication Information Specialist) Peter Hodgkin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland is my first ship and I joined her 3 months prior to deploying on operations. With this being my first deployment and first time away from the UK I was nervous, but excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There have been some tough times, but overall I have really enjoyed it, especially the team spirit of the ship and all the good work that we have achieved on operations. My most memorable moment was helping out at an orphanage in Tanzania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having handed over duties to sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;HMS Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; at the end of November, the crew of HMS Sutherland is now looking forward to spending Christmas at home and time with families and friends before a busy 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57079</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (EFG) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The EFG scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving SMEs the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EFG scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for SMEs, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the EFG scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the EFG scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but EFG lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of EFG loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of EFG loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the EFG scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57510</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth Land </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen visited the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office for the second time today, as the last official engagement of her Diamond Jubilee year. Her Majesty’s previous visit was in 1982 to mark the department’s bicentenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of the building, Foreign Secretary William Hague announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory had been named ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’ in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a mark of this country’s gratitude to The Queen for Her service, we are naming a part of the British Antarctic Territory in her honour as ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fitting tribute at the end of Her Majesty’s Diamond Jubilee year, and I am very proud to be able to announce it as she visits the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Territory is a unique and important member of the network of fourteen UK Overseas Territories. To be able to recognise the UK’s commitment to Antarctica with a permanent association with Her Majesty is a great honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area now to be known as Queen Elizabeth Land, which was previously unnamed, is around 169,000 square miles (437,000 sq km), making up just under a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory. This is almost twice the size of the UK, which stands at 94,000 square miles (244,000 sq km).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land is bounded on the North side by the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves, to the North East by Coats Land, on the East by Dronning Maud Land and extending on the West side to a line between the South Pole and Rutford Ice Stream, east of Constellation Inlet.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen has been on the throne for 60 of the 104 years since the UK claimed territory in Antarctica in 1908. This includes the entire time it has been known as the British Antarctic Territory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Queen Elizabeth Land" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5726/QEL-Antarctica-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Antarctic Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt;) extends from 20⁰ to 80⁰ West. It was claimed by the UK in 1908 and was the first official claim in Antarctica. It was designated officially as a separate Overseas Territory in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All claims to territory within Antarctica are held in abeyance under Article IV of the Antarctic Treaty, 1959, which neither confirms nor denies competing claims, but prevents new claims being made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name Queen Elizabeth Land will now be used on all British maps. Because of the unique status of Antarctica, which is covered by an international Treaty that suspends territorial sovereignty, it is for other countries to decide whether or not they will officially recognise this name.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place naming in &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaken on the basis that a currently unnamed area requires a name for scientific or logistical purposes. This approach is fully in line with the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions on names are made by the Commissioner of the British Antarctic Territory, who is based in London. The Commissioner takes advice on new names from the Antarctic Place Names Committee, which meets twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has no permanent population. British presence is maintained via three research stations operated by the British Antarctic Survey. The Territory itself is self-financing, investing modest receipts from stamp sales and the income tax from overwintering British scientists in environmental projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is not the first time that land in Antarctica has been named after The Queen. Princess Elizabeth Land in East Antarctica, which was discovered in 1931 by the Australian Sir Douglas Mawson, was named by him after Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth (now Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II). And in 2006, an unnamed mountain range in the Antarctic Peninsula was named The Princess Royal Range, in recognition of Her Royal Highness’s work to support environmental and heritage protection work in Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Foreign Secretary's speech"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s speech&lt;/a&gt; welcoming Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on supporting the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories" title="Supporting the Overseas Territories"&gt;Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57049</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-boost-for-business-as-government-sets-out-plans-to-update-employment-legislation"/>
    <title>Press Release: Boost for business as government sets out plans to update employment legislation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to collective redundancies rules to help employees and businesses were announced by Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government announced it plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the current 90 day minimum period, before very large scale redundancies can take place, to 45 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legislate to make clear that fixed term contracts which have reached the end of their natural life are excluded from obligations for collective redundancies consultation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce new non-statutory Acas guidance to address a number of key issues affecting collective redundancies consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK has a labour market that is flexible, efficient and fair but some of our laws need reform to respond to an ever changing employment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to improve the quality of consultations by making sure that there are tools available to help employers manage this process fairly and successfully to deliver the best possible outcomes for all parties.  Acas will be working with stakeholders to produce non-statutory guidance that will be designed to help improve the quality of consultations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have listened to stakeholders and there is a strong argument for shortening the minimum period which is backed up by hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The process is usually completed well within the existing 90-day minimum period, which can cause unnecessary delays for restructuring, and make it difficult for those affected to get new jobs quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our reforms will strike an appropriate balance between making sure employees are engaged in decisions about their future and allowing employers greater certainty and flexibility to take necessary steps to restructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement responds to a consultation launched in June and to calls for improvements to the way collective redundancies rules operate and for the processes involved to be made easier to understand. It also forms part of the Government’s commitment to review employment law to support business and concentrate on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replacement of the current 90 day period to 45 days will still allow full employee engagement and offer employee representatives a statutory right to contribute to the process. The new 45 day period will be a minimum period, and businesses may consult for longer where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will be made through secondary legislation. Draft regulations will be laid in the New Year and the changes are expected to be made by 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition government started a systematic review of employment law in 2010. This Employment Law Review (ELR) is now half way through its work and aims to provide clarity, certainty and give businesses the confidence to manage their workforce effectively. The Review sits alongside the Employment Law-related Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulatory burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the government’s response to Collective
Redundancies can be found at
&lt;a href="/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill sets out a comprehensive series of reforms aimed at supporting businesses, developers, and first time buyers by slashing red tape that delays or discourages business investment, development or job creation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe
Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57066</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/defence-secretary-welcomes-defence-reform-annual-report"/>
    <title>Defence Secretary welcomes Defence Reform annual report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a letter to the Secretary of State, Lord Levene congratulated the Department on strong progress made against the 53 recommendations since the publication of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2" title="Defence Reform Report, June 2011"&gt;Defence Reform Report&lt;/a&gt; in June 2011 and said that he believes the programme is being run with genuine urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full report, with the new annex by Lord Levene, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-reform-an-independent-report-into-the-structure-and-management-of-the-ministry-of-defence--2"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome Lord Levene’s recognition of the strong progress made to date in implementing his recommendations, and his confidence that we can deliver transition to a new operating model for the Ministry of Defence in April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some of the key changes of Defence Reform are already complete, such as strengthened top-level decision-making and the focus on strategic direction from a newly-constituted Defence Board, which I chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-joint-forces-command-established--2" title="Read more about the establishment of the Joint Forces Command"&gt;The Joint Forces Command has been established&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14926288" title="Read more about the appointment of the first Commander of the UK's Joint Forces Command"&gt;first Commander appointed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many other recommendations are on track for delivery by April 2013, including the delegation of financial and military capability management to give the Service Chiefs greater accountability and freedom to manage their resources and plan for future capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A few recommendations will take longer to complete: I acknowledge that there is more to do in some areas, such as development of the Whole Force Concept and the delivery of improved Management Information, and I value Lord Levene’s continued interest and focus on these important changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am confident, though, that by April [2013] we will have gone a long way towards achieving the aim of the Defence Reform programme: a smaller more professional MOD that is better at supporting the Armed Forces now, and looking forward to Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57030</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-local-roads"/>
    <title>Cash boost for local roads</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils can plan how to spend their share of a £215 million fund for local road maintenance after funding allocations were published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £215 million is part of a £333 million fund announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend the life of roads in England.  This funding is in addition to the £3 billion the government is already providing for councils in England between 2011 and 2015 for highways maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This maintenance funding could be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges or repairing damage to highway infrastructure caused by severe weather events, such as the recent flooding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extra money will support economic growth and development by helping local authorities to get the best out of their local road networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding can be spent on measures to bring smoother, safer and more reliable journeys to the travelling public whether they are commuting to work or taking the children to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help local residents see where this money has been spent it will be a condition of the funding that local authorities commit to publishing a short statement on their websites at the end of each financial year setting out what and where this additional funding has been spent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities are also encouraged to look at the information published by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep"&gt;Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme&lt;/a&gt; which is leading the way by bringing together the public and private sectors to develop good practice and reduce costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne announced in the Autumn Statement on 5 December additional funding of £333 million for highways maintenance for both the motorway and trunk road and local road network. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£215 million additional capital funding will be provided to local highway authorities, including London, to help renew and repair the network in England. £140 million will come in 2013 to 2014, with the remaining £75 million following in 2014 to 2015. The funds will be distributed on the basis of the department’s existing highways maintenance capital funding formula. A &lt;a href="/government/publications/local-transport-capital-block-funding"&gt;full list of the allocations by region and local authority&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be eligible for this additional funding and to promote greater transparency and accountability, the department will require local highway authorities to publish a brief note on their website by the end of each financial year (end of April 2014 and end of April 2015) on where (in terms of location) and how this additional funding was spent on highways maintenance. This is so local communities are able to see how this extra funding has been spent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme (HMEP) is a sector-led programme designed to maximise returns from highways investment and deliver efficient and effective services.  HMEP provides practical guidance on highway maintenance efficiencies for local authorities, supplier organisations and representative bodies in the form of toolkits, case studies and good practice.  The most recent of these, launched on 29 November, are the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/standard-spec.php"&gt;standard specification&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/asset-management.php"&gt;asset management toolkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57040</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/video-hms-edinburgh-sends-home-festive-cheer"/>
    <title>VIDEO: HMS Edinburgh sends home festive cheer</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 260 sailors serving on board &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-42-Destroyers/HMS-Edinburgh" title="HMS Edinburgh"&gt;HMS Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; will spend the festive season on board the Portsmouth-based warship while she sails the South Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a bid to spread some Christmas cheer the personnel have donned their smartest Santa outfits and created a video for their loved ones set to The Darkness’ Christmas Time (Don’t Let The Bells End):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jEz0dfCrqaI" title="HMS Edinburgh Christmas Video"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video features scenes from around the ship with sailors wearing Santa hats, Christmas cracker outfits and elf costumes waving hello to family and friends from thousands of miles away at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the crew have also made videos to send back to their home towns - the full selection can be seen on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/royalnavyofficial" title="Royal Navy Official YouTube channel"&gt;Royal Navy’s official YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of HMS Edinburgh, Commander Nick Borbone, who will be away from wife Joanne and children Barney, 9, Eddie, 6, and Amy, 5, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will be strange not being there on Christmas Day and I will miss seeing them, but they have lots of friends and family to keep them entertained and I will call them to see how they are getting on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a tough time of year to be away, but I expect there will be a good festive spirit on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last of the Royal Navy’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-42-Destroyers" title="Type 42 destroyers"&gt;Type 42 destroyers&lt;/a&gt;, HMS Edinburgh is halfway through a six-month deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a historic milestone for both the ship and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; as it will be the last time a Type 42 destroyer deploys on operations as they make way for the new-generation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Edinburgh is undertaking a range of tasks across the length of the Atlantic in support of British interests. Her tasking will see her supporting counter-narcotics efforts in the West African region as well as providing reassurance to UK territories and dependencies worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Borbone will be the last commanding officer of a Type 42 destroyer. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a real privilege. HMS Edinburgh might be the last of the class but she remains a capable ship with a highly-trained and motivated ship’s company that is determined to preserve the fine tradition that the Type 42s have established in 30 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57046</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-affairs-council-and-general-affairs-council--2"/>
    <title>Foreign Affairs Council and General Affairs Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Europe Mr David Lidington said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Right Honourable Friend the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and I attended the Foreign Affairs Council (FAC) on 10 December, the Foreign Secretary attending the initial part before handing over to me.  I attended the General Affairs Council (GAC) on 11 December in Brussels. The Foreign Affairs Council was chaired by the High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Baroness Ashton of Upholland, and the General Affairs Council was chaired by the Cypriot Presidency, the Deputy Minister for European Affairs, Ambassador Andreas Mavroyiannis, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Dr. Erato Kozakou-Markoullis.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="foreign-affairs-council"&gt;Foreign Affairs Council&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commissioners Füle (Enlargement and European Neighbourhood Policy) and Georgieva (International Cooperation, Humanitarian Aid and Crisis Response) were also in attendance for some of the discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A provisional report of the meetings and all Conclusions adopted can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/EN/foraff/134152.pdf" title="Provisional report"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="eu-russia-summit"&gt;EU-Russia Summit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch, Ministers discussed the EU-Russia Summit which will be held in Brussels on 21 December. There was a widely shared view that  the EU should focus on human rights, including the role and freedom of NGOs; push Russia to end its restrictive trade practices in order to comply with its World Trade Organisation obligations; press for implementation of the agreement on Siberian overflight royalties; and reaffirm the importance of the Third Energy Package. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers considered the need for re-engagement by the international community on the Middle East Peace Process in 2013 over lunch.  Ministers agreed Conclusions calling for the parties to return to negotiations without precondition with international support; expressing deep dismay at and strong opposition to recent Israeli announcements on settlements; calling on Israel to avoid undermining the financial situation of the Palestinian Authority; and urging the Palestinians not to build on their change in UN status in a way that would undermine a return to talks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="southern-neighbourhood"&gt;Southern Neighbourhood&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council debated the latest developments in Syria, ahead of the next meeting of the Friends of Syria group in Marrakech on 12 December. During lunch, ministers exchanged views with Ahmed Moaz Al-Khatib, President of the National Coalition for Syrian Revolutionary and Opposition Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed Conclusions on Syria, expressing their concern at the deteriorating situation, and the need for greater protection of civilians.  The Conclusions state that ‘the EU accepts [the National Coalition for Syrian Revolutionary and Opposition Forces] as legitimate representatives of the Syrian people’.  The Conclusions reiterated that “if concerns about war crimes and crimes against humanity are not adequately addressed on a national level, the International Criminal Court should deal with the situation”, and called upon the United Nations Security Council “to urgently address the situation in Syria in all aspects”.
Ministers expressed their concern about the situation in Egypt, ahead of the planned referendum on 15 December.  They agreed that it was in the EU’s interest to see a democratic, inclusive, economically-sound Egypt, and noted the need for strong EU engagement with Egypt, based upon mutual accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers discussed the situation in Libya.  The High Representative stated that there had been a number of positive developments in Libya, politically and economically, and that the EU now needed to develop co-operation in border management and security.  Ministers welcomed the Fact Finding Mission, which had demonstrated significant Libyan political will to engage. Ministers noted that the EU needed to build on and sustain contacts with the Libyan authorities and UN so that international efforts were coordinated and met Libyan requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="western-balkans"&gt;Western Balkans&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers had a short discussion on Western Balkans issues. This was one of a series of Western Balkans related meetings building up to the General Affairs Council discussion of the Enlargement Conclusions.  The High Representative briefed ministers on the latest developments in the Belgrade-Pristina Dialogue, noting that the successful opening of two crossing points was a significant step in terms of Integrated Border Management implementation. Member States welcomed the leadership of Baroness Ashton on this issue.
The need to maintain a credible EU perspective for Macedonia was also raised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="council-conclusions"&gt;Council Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I anticipated in my pre-Council statement, Ministers agreed Conclusions without discussion on Ukraine and the Democratic Republic of Congo.  In addition, Ministers approved the Crisis Management Concept for a Common Security and Defence Policy military mission aimed at providing training and advice to the Malian Armed Forces; and the revised Crisis Management Concept for the EU Training Mission for Somalia.  In light of the DPRK’s recent announcement of its plan to launch a satellite, in breach of UN Security Council Resolutions, the Council agreed Conclusions expressing deep concern, urging the DPRK not to conduct the launch, and signalling the need for an international response, potentially including sanctions, were the launch to go ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers agreed without discussion a number of others measures, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Azerbaijan Cooperation Council, to take place on 17 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Georgia Cooperation Council, to take place on 18 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of the EU position and provisional agenda for the 13th meeting of the EU-Armenia Cooperation Council, to take place on 17 December in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adoption of a decision on the signing, on behalf of the European Union, of a protocol to the Partnership and Cooperation Agreement with the Republic of Armenia, which will allow the participation of Armenia in EU programmes. It forwarded the draft decision on conclusion of the protocol to the European Parliament for its consent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A review of the list of persons, groups and entities subject to EU restrictive measures with a view to combating terrorism, according to common position 2001/931/CFSP. No changes were made to the measures, which currently affect 11 persons and 25 groups and entities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approval of preparations for the annual review of EU restrictive measures against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adoption of the implementation plan for the EU advisory and assistance mission for security reform in the Democratic Republic of Congo (EUSEC RD Congo) for the period until 30 September 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="general-affairs-council"&gt;General Affairs Council&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A provisional report of the meeting and all Conclusions adopted can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/ueDocs/cms_Data/docs/pressData/EN/genaff/134235.pdf" title="Provisional report"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="statute-of-the-court-of-justice-of-the-european-union"&gt;Statute of the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC discussed the issue of the appointment of nine additional judges for the General Court of the Court of Justice of the European Union.  The Presidency presented their proposals, suggesting a rotating system between Member States with a weighted allocation.  I emphasised the importance of sufficient representation of judges from a common law background and stressed the need to ensure that the proposals were budget neutral.  There was no consensus on this issue which will be revisited next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="european-semester-and-the-annual-growth-survey"&gt;European Semester and the Annual Growth Survey&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission presented the main priorities for this year’s Annual Growth Survey, stressing that Member States must “stay the course” on fiscal consolidation and structural reforms if the EU is to achieve long-term, sustainable growth. The incoming Irish Presidency then outlined their roadmap for handling the process in Council, focussing on the importance of bilateral dialogue and multilateral surveillance to resolve Member States’ concerns relating to country specific recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="preparation-for-the-december-european-council-and-february-european-council"&gt;Preparation for the December European Council and February European Council&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency announced the agenda for the February European Council, which is due to focus on trade and external relations. The outcome of the December European Council will be covered in the Prime Minister’s statement to the House of Commons and the Leader of the House of Lords’ statement to the House of Lords.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-18-month-programme-for-the-presidencies-of-ireland-lithuania-and-greece"&gt;The 18-month programme for the Presidencies of Ireland, Lithuania and Greece&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC endorsed the programme of the incoming Trio of Presidencies; Ireland, Lithuania and Greece. The programme covers a broad range of priorities for the next 18-month period. For Ireland, the key was strengthening Economic and Monetary Union, implementing agreed reforms to economic governance, and securing financial stability including Banking Union. Ireland also looked for progress on the Multiannual Financial Framework and related dossiers.  They underlined the importance of measures which have the potential to improve competitiveness and create jobs and growth.  Finally they also want to see progress on third country trade agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="enlargement"&gt;Enlargement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAC discussion focussed on Macedonia, Serbia and Kosovo. The Council agreed a package of Conclusions on enlargement including important steps forward for several countries, which rightly recognise their progress so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council made its commitment to Macedonia’s EU path clear with the Council taking a possible decision on opening accession negotiations during the next Presidency, based on a report to be presented by the European Commission in spring 2013 on progress relating to good neighbourly relations and movement on the name issue. This is an important and valuable opportunity for Macedonia to move further forward next year, and we look forward to a positive decision to open accession negotiations soon. I welcome, in that regard, the Commission starting preparatory work. Likewise the government is pleased that the Commission will propose negotiating directives to take forward Kosovo’s EU path with a Stabilisation and Association Agreement, once Kosovo meets the short term conditions. This will be a significant step forward for Kosovo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The High Representative briefed again on the EU-led Dialogue between Serbia and Kosovo. I set out the UK government’s continued firm support for Serbia’s EU future. The Council undertook to review during the first half of next year progress on the conditions the Council has agreed for Serbia to open accession negotiations, including progress in the Dialogue and irreversible progress on the parallel structures in northern Kosovo, as reiterated by the High Representative. The Council was clear that it wanted to see Serbia moving to the next stage as soon as they have met the conditions to do so. The recent steps taken in the EU-led Dialogue between Serbia and Kosovo had shown that both countries can move forward and deal with difficult issues, enabling them to continue on their European paths. I welcomed the steps taken by the parties so far and I endorsed the Council’s commendation for Prime Ministers Dacic and Thaci: they had approached their recent discussions in a statesman like and courageous manner. The Council expected the two sides to continue and accelerate their work in addressing all aspects of the relations between them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusions on Bosnia and Herzegovina set out the Council’s concern about the slow progress being made in Bosnia and Herzegovina and stalled reforms there; and the risk that Bosnia and Herzegovina will lag further behind her neighbours unless the political leaders deliver on the actions they have agreed.  The GAC called on the Bosnian leaders to act, in the interests of their citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council Conclusions also covered Albania, reflecting recent progress and underlining the need to further intensify efforts as identified by the Commission. The successful conduct of Parliamentary elections in 2013 will be a crucial test for the smooth functioning of the country’s democratic institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council adopted forward-looking Conclusions on Turkey which will allow the accession process to be taken forward in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council looked forward to Croatia’s accession and welcomed progress made by Iceland and Montenegro. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to update Parliament on future Foreign Affairs Councils and General Affairs Councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57435</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office"/>
    <title>Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary announced that an area in the British Antarctic Territory has been named Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are all delighted to welcome you to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office for the final event of your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In a year in which millions of British people have been able to see you and cheer you, we are truly honoured here in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to have you here with us and to take our part in closing this magnificent period of celebration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is an opportunity for everyone here to show how proud they are to serve in your Majesty’s Diplomatic Service and in the Home Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And there are over 10,000 British and locally-engaged staff in our Embassies and High Commissions abroad who will be equally inspired by your visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You embody a life of service to our country, and a lifetime of diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have made over 260 official visits to 116 different countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Promoting reconciliation, as you did on your visit to West Germany in 1965, and to Japan in 1975;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving encouragement to nations after profound change, such as your visit to Russia in 1994 and to South Africa in 1995;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Helping to heal the wounds of history and to make peace irreversible, as I saw myself during your truly historic State Visit to Ireland last year;
And all the time steadfastly uniting the Commonwealth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are deeply grateful to you, and to the 11 members of the Royal Family who have travelled to 29 countries and territories for your Diamond Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, I am conscious that I am your twenty-second Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your wisdom and experience are an inspiration to all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are striving for excellence in all that we do in the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our goal is to be the best Diplomatic Service in the world: helping British people overseas, supporting our economy, keeping our country secure, and upholding freedom and human rights at all times. We do this with your example always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we are renaming in your honour the newly-restored old Home Office Library, which now houses our historians and the Knowledge and Information Management team, which will be called the Diamond Jubilee Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And I am delighted to announce that as a mark of our country’s gratitude to you, an area of the Antarctic 437,000 square kilometres in size, nearly twice the size of the United Kingdom and more than a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory, will be given a name for the very first time. From today, in your honour, it will be forever known as Queen Elizabeth Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your Majesty, we are proud to serve a Queen who has achieved so much for our nation and who embodies the ideals of public service that we cherish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we thank you for your visit; for this proud and happy occasion that we will all remember for the rest of our lives, and which will be recorded for our successors in the plaque you are unveiling today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I thank everyone here and all the staff of Foreign and Commonwealth Office, all over the world for all their hard work on behalf of our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And now your Majesty to commemorate your visit today I invite you to unveil the plaque marking your Diamond Jubilee Year.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5731/Queen_s-visit--final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title="Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57077</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"/>
    <title>Update on Enterprise Finance Guarantee lending  </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today announcing the publication of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures by individual bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to ensuring that viable small and medium-size enterprises can obtain the finance they need for working capital and investment. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; plays an important part in this, with over 9,900 &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; being offered loans with a value in excess of £1 billion since May 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has made a number of important changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme during the last twelve months. &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans are now available to an additional 3,800 businesses with an increase in the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million. The maximum £1 million lifetime scheme limit has been replaced by a rolling £1 million limit. We also raised by 7%, the level of lenders &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; annual loan portfolios to which the Government guarantee applies from 13% to 20%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was made to address the legitimate concern of lenders that they would breach their annual claim limit. In doing this, the Government committed to a more even share of the risk of default with the lenders, with the aim of removing that as a barrier to lending &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; is a demand led scheme, accounting for one to two per cent of overall &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; lending. While utilisation is directly linked to subdued demand for credit in the wider economy, overall &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending levels are disappointing. There have been some positive signs, with a number of the main banks increasing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending this financial year, albeit from a low level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that banks lend responsibly and make use of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; when it is appropriate to do so, but it is clear from the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures that a number of lenders could and should be doing more. The publication of individual bank &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures is intended to help achieve this. In parallel, we are exploring with the banks ways of flexing &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; to address debt serviceability, which is the principal reason behind loan declines. Further detail will be provided in the New Year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills, already publishes a wide range of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures, which are updated on a quarterly basis. Publication of individual &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending figures will further enhance this, allowing business customers to identify which banks are making most use of the scheme, and also enable participating lenders and new market entrants to identity new opportunities, thus increasing choice and competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks a further step towards greater transparency in bank lending, specifically to &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/number-of-enterprise-finance-guarantee-efg-scheme-loans-drawn"&gt;The full list of available &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn, by bank.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57028</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-18-december-2012"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 18 December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the last Transport Council of the Cypriot Presidency (the Presidency) taking place in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be asked to reach a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the Council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. I was very concerned when we first received the proposal from the Commission. The Commission’s impact assessment was inadequate and failed to make the required links between the costs and benefits of new requirements. It was also incomplete as it did not accurately assess costs in all member states. Our initial analysis was that it would cost over £1 billion pounds to implement while having an insignificant positive impact on road safety in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position we adopted during the negotiation of the draft periodic roadworthiness regulation at Council working group meetings has been to resist additional burdens where insignificant road safety benefit was identified. With the support of the UK and other member states in resisting excessive burdens, the Presidency has proposed moving from a regulation to a directive and has made substantial changes to the text that radically simplifies the implementation of the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has been positive and has resulted in a substantially improved and less expensive proposal and as such I hope the Presidency will be able to achieve a general approach on the dossier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency will provide a progress report on 2 other proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing the ‘connecting Europe’ facility. The UK abstained from the partial general approach agreed on this dossier at the June Transport Council. While we were broadly supportive of the text of the regulation we could not formally support agreement to the draft regulations in advance of an agreement on the overall Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;) negotiations as this could prejudge the overall &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The UK supports the thrust of the proposal in introducing a clearer, stable governance arrangement for the programme but has concerns that some of the European Parliament’s proposed amendments, such as the introduction of funding for applications to use the navigation systems, could have significant financial implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will adopt conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The UK welcomed this timely communication from the Commission and has been actively engaged in the drafting of Council conclusions. We support the broad aims of the communication – liberalisation of aviation and fair competition – and we are pushing to ensure that the Council’s conclusions reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will also adopt a proposal for a Council decision on the signature, on behalf of the EU, and provisional application of the Euro-Mediterranean aviation agreement between the EU and its member states, on the one part, and the State of Israel, on the other. The UK supports the signature and implementation of this agreement which forms a part of the EU’s external aviation policy to negotiate comprehensive air services agreements with neighbouring countries. This agreement will supersede the current bilateral agreements between individual member states and Israel. It aims at gradual market opening, promoting regulatory (e.g. safety) harmonisation and the promotion of open and fair competition between air carriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This agreement will integrate the Israeli aviation market into the European single market accompanied by convergence with EU aviation regulations. It will enhance opportunities for EU airlines and investors in Israel, provide consumer benefits as a result of increased competition and better access, and help to strengthen the economic links between the EU and Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the Commission will provide information on the cleaner power for transport package and aviation emissions trading scheme (&lt;abbr title="emissions trading scheme"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56983</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Seventy years ago the British Government, shocked by mounting evidence from Poland of Nazi extermination of the Jews, joined eleven other war-time allies in a sharp united condemnation of what was happening on the continent of Europe. Sir Anthony Eden’s Statement to Parliament on 17 December 1942 was followed by much public and Parliamentary discussion in the UK and among the United Nations about what could be done to stop the genocide and had a strong impact on subsequent allied planning for the post-war trials of Nazi leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The disastrous events of the Holocaust continue to reverberate through Western society, as the Stockholm Declaration in 2000 so eloquently reaffirmed. The British Government supports the work of the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research (&lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and looks forward to assuming the chairmanship of the &lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2014/15.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.holocausttaskforce.org/about-the-itf.html" title="Holocaust Task Force"&gt;Information on the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56976</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet"/>
    <title>UK has serious concerns about human rights in Tibet</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a European Union statement on self-immolations in Tibet, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We strongly support the recent statement from Baroness Ashton about the situation in Tibet. We continue to have serious concerns about the human rights situation there, including the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We urge the Chinese authorities to exercise restraint. At the same time, I join Baroness Ashton in calling on Tibetans not to resort to extreme forms of protest such as self-immolation, and urge their community and religious leaders to use their influence to stop this tragic loss of life. We strongly support the resumption of meaningful dialogue to resolve the underlying grievances of Tibetan communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I also urge the Chinese government to ensure unrestricted access to the Tibetan Autonomous Region and other Tibetan areas of China for diplomats, international media and other concerned parties. We believe a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/en/cfsp/134378.pdf" title="EU statement on Tibetan self-immolations"&gt;European Union statement on Tibetan self-immolations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56853</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/female-officer-cadet-wins-sandhursts-sword-of-honour"/>
    <title>Female Officer Cadet wins Sandhurst's Sword of Honour</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The top accolade from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/training_education/training/17057.aspx" title="Royal Military Academy Sandhurst"&gt;Royal Military Academy Sandhurst&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Officer Cadet Sarah Hunter-Choat, who received the award during her commissioning at the Sovereign’s Parade on Friday 14 December.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted Sword of Honour is presented to the best overall Officer Cadet out of 200 in the senior term and is personally chosen by the Academy’s Commandant, Major General Timothy Evans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 200 cadets have their performance rigorously monitored throughout the year. Then, going into the final phase of their training, the 3 top candidates, termed ‘blade runners’, are carefully scrutinised then brought before the Commandant for a final interview. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat received the Sword of Honour from Defence Secretary Philip Hammond, who represented Her Majesty The Queen at the Sovereign’s Parade. It has been 6 years since a female officer won, when Angela Laycock was commissioned into the Royal Engineers in December 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Cadet Hunter-Choat’s success follows in her parents’ footsteps. Her father Brigadier Tony Hunter-Choat had a long, distinguished military career, starting out in the French Foreign Legion before commissioning into the British Army, while her mother is a former RAF officer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
