<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T18:59:37+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64191</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:59:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:59:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"/>
    <title>2013 should be ‘year of peace’ for people in the Middle East</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary says 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, he reaffirms UK’s support for a political transition in Syria. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today met Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States. Following the meeting the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was pleased to welcome Mr Nabil El-Araby, Secretary General of the League of Arab States, to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We discussed the Middle East Peace Process and agreed that 2013 offers new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation.  We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.  We agreed that Arab League and EU member states needed to assist the Palestinian Authority to overcome its current financial difficulties and that  Israel should fulfil its obligations to transfer customs revenues due to the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also discussed the situation in Syria, and efforts to achieve a political transition and an end to the violence. We reiterated our support for UN and Arab League Special Representative Brahimi’s efforts to advance a credible political solution to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK believes that President Assad can never recover legitimacy in the eyes of the Syrian people.  His latest promises of token reforms demonstrate his increasingly desperate attempts to hold on to power. As well as supporting a political transition the UK will continue our humanitarian assistance, our work to support those documenting human rights violations in Syria, and our non-lethal support for the Syrian opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64188</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"/>
    <title>Minister “dismayed” at verdict in Bahraini activists’ appeal </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt, has called on Bahrain to guarantee its citizens’ fundamental liberties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court today upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. Commenting earlier, Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am deeply dismayed at the decision of the Bahraini Cassation Court to uphold the sentences of 13 political activists in today’s appeal hearing. At the time these individuals were sentenced, reports which were acknowledged by the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry suggested that some had been abused in detention, denied access to legal counsel and were coerced into confessing. I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bahrain-independent-commission-of-inquiry-bici"&gt;Minister comments on Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64090</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-social-tenants-to-have-their-say-on-local-services"/>
    <title>Support for social tenants to have their say on local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk today launched a new training programme designed to put power firmly in the hands of social tenants.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He launched the £1.2 million Tenant Training and Support Programme to give residents the skills they need to hold their landlord to account, whether on their own, by setting up a tenant panel, or by taking over the management and maintenance of their homes and neighbourhoods themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boost in funding will offer a way for residents to ensure they get the service they deserve and that landlords offer the best possible value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said this new training programme would empower residents to take the first crucial step to having the necessary know-how to use their powers and take control in their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="empowering-tenants"&gt;Empowering tenants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/"&gt;Tenant Participation Advisory Service&lt;/a&gt;, the programme offers advice, training and support to tenants by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing tenants together from different neighbourhoods to discuss their experiences and inspire new tenant panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping individual tenants to engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offering face-to-face training with expert advisors for around 5,000 tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a tenant training programme to help them make the most of the powers they have, from accredited courses to local training systems and e-learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By doing this, new and existing social tenants will be equipped with the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be able to sign up to Community Cashback, which enables tenants to take over the management of their neighbourhood, from overseeing maintenance and minor repairs to signing up new contractors to run cleaning services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country want to use the powers they have to ensure their needs are reflected in the services they receive. But many simply lack the confidence to challenge the people in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why we’ve put this new tenant training scheme in place, helping make their voices heard and giving people the skills they need to ensure the changes that matter to them are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by playing this enhanced role tenants can help landlords improve the efficiency of local services and their work will help inspire even more communities to take control.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Meakin, Tenant Participation Advisory Service chair said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is exactly the programme we’ve all been waiting for. I urge any tenant who wants to be involved and make a difference in their community to get in touch and take advantage of the free support and training on offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples-of-effective-tenant-involvement"&gt;Examples of effective tenant involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helena Partnerships&lt;/em&gt; has set up the tenant-led customer excellence panel to challenge their landlord on performance and service delivery. It sets its own review programme, commissions mystery shoppers and has unfettered access to Helena’s performance and complaints information, customer surveys, activity-based costing and customer insight data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel carries out tenant-led peer reviews and hosts a series of webinars to engage with other organisations involved in scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works closely with Helena’s young inspectors - a group of under 25’s who play an active role in testing and challenging services while gaining transferable skills for employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel’s work has been responsible for a number of practical changes to Helena services to reflect the needs of tenants and delivered value for money savings, including tailored rent statements, extended repairs appointment times and changes to the complaints service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tower Hamlets, &lt;em&gt;Poplar HARCA&lt;/em&gt; (8,500 homes) is committed to helping social tenants to play a key role in their local housing. Recognising the benefits of tenant empowerment, the association enables democratically elected residents to monitor services on each of the association’s 12 estates, where they have delegated budgets enabling them to make community improvements. Additionally, tenant board members scrutinise the association’s policies and initiatives, challenging senior managers and making recommendations for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents can also use their local knowledge to try to resolve complaints about the association’s services. A youth empowerment board has been set up, comprising 30 young people drawn from across the estates, to ensure that the views of young people are heard. In total, over 300 residents are directly involved in decision making, performance monitoring and complaints handling at the association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding of almost £1.2 million will be made to the Tenant Participation Advisory Service to deliver a training and support programme. For further information on the programme visit their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/tenantcentral"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow DCLG’s Tenant Empowerment Team on Twitter (&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/TenantPower"&gt;@TenantPower&lt;/a&gt;) for all the latest news and updates on this programme and other activities to empower the lives of social tenants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64086</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T10:28:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-7-january-2013"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 7 January 2013</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Stephen Hammond MP provides an overview of the last EU Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the last Transport Council of the Cypriot presidency in Brussels on Thursday 20 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council agreed a general approach on the proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and the council on periodic road worthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers and repealing Directive 2009/40/EC. Following widespread criticism of the commission’s proposal at the October Transport Council, the UK has been an active and leading negotiator at the working group meetings chaired by the presidency. The presidency subsequently presented a compromise text that reflected the reality of member states’ road safety testing practices. We supported the change of the legal form of the proposal from a (directly applicable) regulation to a directive (which gives member states some flexibility in transposition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcomed the many improvements in the presidency’s text which had substantially reduced the cost implications to a manageable level, and indicated that the UK could accept the presidency’s text.  I made clear that as negotiations begin with the European Parliament, we would seek to provide members of the European Parliament with as much information as possible to explain why the changes to the original proposal were both justified, and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presidency provided progress reports on 2 proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council establishing the Connecting Europe Facility. This regulation will provide the legal basis for funding of trans-European transport, energy and telecoms networks for 2014 to 2020. The text will not be finalised until the budget figures for 2014 to 2020 have been agreed in discussions on the Multi-Annual Financial Framework (&lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems. The council’s position on this regulation, which will provide the legal basis for taking forward the Galileo satellite navigation programme from 2014, was agreed earlier in the year. However, technical discussions with the European Parliament since then have not led to much progress. The dossier will be passed to the Irish Presidency to conclude negotiations with the European Parliament once the budget for Galileo under the &lt;abbr title="Multi-Annual Financial Framework"&gt;MFF&lt;/abbr&gt; has been confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted conclusions on the communication on ‘EU’s external aviation policy – addressing future challenges’. The commission welcomed the conclusions, highlighting in particular the worsening aviation relationship with Russia, especially Russia’s ongoing refusal to implement its commitments on Siberian overflight charges. The commissioner called for collective action at EU level and said he would be producing a roadmap in the new year with a view to pursuing an EU/Russia comprehensive agreement in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council also adopted a proposal for a decision on the comprehensive aviation agreement between the EU and its member states and Israel. The original plan had been for the agreement to be signed in the margins of the council, but due to internal political reasons, Israel was not able to sign at this time. The commission hoped that Israel would be in a position to sign this agreement shortly after national elections in the Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high level cooperation agreement with Eurocontrol (European Organisation for the Safety of Air Navigation) was signed in the margins of the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the commission provided an update on recent discussions at the International Civil Aviation Organisation to agree a global approach to tackling emissions from aviation. The commission clarified that it was proposing a temporary derogation on enforcement of the Aviation Emissions Trading System (ETS) relating to international flights and hoped the European Parliament and the council would approve this through a decision in the first quarter of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under any other business, France tabled a room document which called for a discussion to be held in the International Maritime Organization on the 2015 deadline for implementing the new requirements on the sulphur content of marine fuels. A number of member states intervened and stressed that they would be keen to discuss practical issues, such as the cost of low sulphur fuels to businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cleaner Power for Transport Package which was due to be discussed as an &lt;abbr title="any other business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt; item was taken off the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Brown &lt;abbr title="Member of the Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSP&lt;/abbr&gt;, Scottish Minister for Transport and Veterans also attended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64021</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:57:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wwii-airman-celebrates-100th-birthday"/>
    <title>WWII airman celebrates 100th birthday</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A former Second World War Spitfire pilot celebrated his 100th birthday on New Year's Day.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On New Year’s Day, family, staff and residents at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.veterans-uk.info/new_ipph/ipph.html" title="Ilford Park Polish Home pages on the Veterans UK website"&gt;Ilford Park Polish Home&lt;/a&gt; in Devon joined their oldest resident, former Spitfire pilot Mieczyslaw Juny &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;, for his 100th birthday celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny was born in Lwow, Poland, on 1 January 1913. At the age of 26, he took part in the Polish Campaign of 1939. After Poland fell to German forces, he escaped to Hungary and was taken as a prisoner of war. He escaped again and eventually found himself aboard the ship ‘Empress of Canada’ in March 1943 as she sailed from Durban with 1,800 passengers. On 13 March, 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometres) off the coast of Africa, she was torpedoed and sank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surviving the waters of the Atlantic, Mr Juny found his way to the UK. He transferred to the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/online-exhibitions/the-polish-air-force-in-world-war-2.aspx" title="The Polish Air Force in WWII - information from the RAF Museum"&gt;Polish Air Force&lt;/a&gt; as a flight lieutenant and served alongside his British RAF colleagues as a Spitfire pilot for 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny during the Second World War" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5856/Mr_Juny_in_1940s.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny during the Second World War [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the war, Mr Juny worked for the National Assistance Board, rehoming Polish people who had been decommissioned from the armed forces but could not return to Poland because of the political changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years as a civil servant working at Ilford Park, he was awarded an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for his service to Polish people in the UK in 1975 before retiring as Deputy Manager in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny continues to reside at Ilford Park, now managed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.veterans-uk.info/" title="Veterans UK website"&gt;Service Personnel and Veterans Agency&lt;/a&gt;, and has been the longstanding chair of the residents’ committee. In 2003, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.pcmew.org/" title="The Polish Catholic Mission in England and Wales website"&gt;Polish Catholic Mission&lt;/a&gt; awarded him the Cross of Merit. He was further decorated in 2005, when the outgoing president of the Republic of Poland, Aleksander Kwasniewski, awarded Mr Juny the Knight’s Cross of the Order of Polonia Restituta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny wearing his medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5857/Mr_Juny_with_Medals.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny wearing his medals at Polish Independence Day celebrations [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Juny said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being 100 years old is a funny feeling; it is not normal for human beings to live this long. It is exciting to tell people that I am 100 years old, and people are excited to hear this. I don’t know why I have been chosen to live so long, but I notice more and more beauty in the world as I get older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilford Park Manager Clare Thomas said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr Juny is an inspiration to us all and is a role model of grace and humanity. He has been so determined to reach this birthday. He desperately wanted to live long enough to see the London 2012 Olympics and since then his focus has been on his birthday. It has given him a new lease of life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mieczyslaw Juny with his birthday card from Her Majesty The Queen" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5858/Mr_Juny_with_card_from_HM_The_Queen.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mieczyslaw Juny with his birthday card from Her Majesty The Queen [Picture: via MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two more of the Polish Home residents will reach their 100th birthdays this year, and Mr Juny says he wants to join them when they have their parties. And his birthday wish? To live another 50 years!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61168</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T10:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T11:09:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-invites-tenders-for-uk-construction-projects"/>
    <title>MOD invites tenders for UK construction projects</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Ten private sector companies have been invited to tender for a new framework agreement to deliver construction projects across the UK Defence estate.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The companies shortlisted for the framework by the Defence Infrastructure Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;) are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.balfourbeatty.com/" title="Balfour Beatty website"&gt;Balfour Beatty Group Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bam.co.uk/Construction/Construction-Overview.aspx" title="BAM Construction website"&gt;BAM Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.carillionplc.com/our-capabilities/construction-services.aspx" title="Carillion Construction website"&gt;Carillion Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.interserve.com/" title="Interserve website"&gt;Interserve Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kier.co.uk/" title="Kier Group website"&gt;Kier Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lendlease.com/worldwide/capabilities/project-management-and-construction.aspx" title="Lend Lease Construction website"&gt;Lend Lease Construction (EMEA) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millerconstruction.co.uk/" title="Miller Construction website"&gt;Miller Construction (UK) Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://construction.morgansindall.com/" title="Morgan Sindall Construction website"&gt;Morgan Sindall plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.skanska.co.uk/" title="Skanska website"&gt;Skanska UK plc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wates.co.uk/" title="Wates website"&gt;Wates Construction Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Capital Works Framework will be used for the design and build of construction projects up to a value of £50 million. It will include up to 5 companies who will participate in ‘mini-competitions’ for individual projects. It is due to be awarded before the end of 2013 and will run for an initial 4-year period, with the potential to extend for up to 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework forms part of the &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; Next Generation Estate Contracts (&lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt;) programme, and will operate alongside 6 regional capital works frameworks for projects valued below £12 million. It has an estimated value of between £250 million and £400 million over the 4-year period and could be used at any site across the UK estate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, the shortlisted companies attended a bidders’ conference at the Defence Academy in Shrivenham focused on the tendering process and on the proposed operating model for the framework. Delegates were also taken step-by-step through a typical Defence construction project, looking at the processes involved, legislative influences, sustainability and other requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tender will be rigorously evaluated based on the company’s approach to commercial and technical matters such as supply chain management, quality assurance, sustainable development, health and safety, and issues relating to the Government Construction Strategy. The tenderers have also been provided with a demonstration construction project and will be evaluated on their proposed approach to its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Rice, Head of the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changes to UK military basing arrangements are expected to generate requirements for new capital works in the years ahead, and it is vital these are met flexibly and cost-effectively, enabling us to provide a Defence estate which meets military needs and supports our Armed Forces. Early in the &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; programme our research determined that framework arrangements were the best mechanism to achieve this, and I am delighted that we have such a strong field of companies in the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Wooden, &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks project manager, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This national framework is designed to deliver a range of potential major construction projects to support the Defence front line. We are determined to ensure firstly that all companies involved in the tendering process have a full and robust understanding of the potential demand, and secondly that we use the evaluation process to identify the best providers to meet that demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Next Generation Estate Contracts"&gt;NGEC&lt;/abbr&gt; Capital Works Frameworks are designed to support the Government Construction Strategy by reducing costs, improving value for money, and incorporating measures such as the ‘&lt;abbr title="New Engineering Contract 3"&gt;NEC3&lt;/abbr&gt;’ form of procurement, more focused performance management, and continuous improvement mechanisms. For all projects contractors will be required to use systems that meet UK Government requirements for Building Information Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework contractors will also be required to observe fair payment practices and - where decided appropriate on a project-by-project basis - project bank accounts will be set up to ensure prompt payment for all supply chain companies involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tenders are due to be returned by mid-February 2013 and it is expected that the National Capital Works Framework agreements will be awarded before the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61173</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:13:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"/>
    <title>Ministers urge progress between Sudan and South Sudan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK, US and Norway say that Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan must seize the opportunity for peace now.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January. In a joint statement, Foreign Ministers from the ‘Sudan Troika’ are calling for the two countries to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint statement by Norwegian Foreign Minister Espen Barth Eide, United Kingdom Foreign Secretary William Hague and U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the news that the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan are to meet in Addis Ababa on 4 January in a further effort to resolve outstanding issues between the two countries. We applaud the progress made at their Presidential Summit held in Addis Ababa at the end of September 2012, which demonstrated that a durable and equitable settlement is within reach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We commend the continuing valuable role of the African Union High-Level Implementation Panel led by former President Thabo Mbeki and the efforts of Ethiopian Prime Minister Hailemariam Desalegn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We regret that progress in implementing the Agreements signed on 27 September has stalled and in particular that the agreed security arrangements at the border are not yet in place. We call on the two leaders now to address concretely all outstanding issues and ensure that the armed forces of the two countries immediately withdraw from the demilitarised zone and deploy the Joint Border and Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM), in line with what has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We stress the importance of making progress in parallel on other parts of the relationship between the two countries. Full implementation of all agreements on their own terms and without preconditions or linkages between them, will help build confidence and benefit the people of the two countries. The restart of oil production and export will be particularly valuable for both economies and should not be held up by negotiation on other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We underline our support for the approach taken by the African Union to the question of Abyei. The proposal made by former President Mbeki is based on the Comprehensive Peace Agreement, including the Abyei Protocol. The proposal, adopted by AUPSC on October 24, sets out a clear path towards determining Abyei’s final status in accordance with agreements already signed by both parties, while protecting the rights of all communities and ensuring Abyei can become a model for cross-border cooperation and coexistence. We note in particular that the proposal provides for Abyei’s continuing special status as a bridge between the two countries with guaranteed political and economic rights for both the Ngok Dinka and Misseriya, whatever the outcome of the referendum. We urge the two countries to meet to elaborate on these rights and to move toward agreement on Abyei’s final status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision. We strongly urge them to seize the opportunity of the Summit meeting on 4 January to demonstrate their commitment to implement what they have agreed and make peaceful co-existence a reality.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61166</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T16:51:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:51:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary discusses progress in Somalia with Foreign Minister </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Foreign Secretary William Hague met the Somali Foreign Minister and Deputy Prime Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have met Foreign Minister Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam in her first visit to the UK in her new role. Somalia has made tangible progress in recent months, both politically following the end of the transitional period, and in improving security, with Al Shabab pushed from major towns. It is critical that this momentum continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Minister outlined the Somali government’s plans to tackle the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development. The UK is committed to working in partnership with the Somali government to support these priorities and to ensure coordinated international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Office for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinsomalia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61178</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T15:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T16:09:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/keeping-the-uk-military-on-the-map"/>
    <title>Keeping the UK military on the map</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The experts at the Defence Geographic Centre near London are keeping UK Armed Forces worldwide on the right track.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Australian scientists went to have a look at Sandy Island in the South Pacific recently, they discovered that, despite having featured on maps and on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en_uk/earth/index.html" title="Google Earth UK homepage"&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; for years, it doesn’t actually exist. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experts working at the Defence Geographic Centre (&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;) may well have smiled wryly on hearing this. There is no room in their world for such errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; provides geographic information to Defence, predominantly to the Army and the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt;, but also to other government departments, and works in a world of international collaboration, sharing and co-producing geographical information where a reputation for accuracy matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s geographers, or geospatial analysts as they prefer to be called, know that, if you rely on a map which hasn’t been created from entirely dependable source data, the result can get you into trouble. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A large printer at the Defence Geographic Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5847/Replication.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Defence Geographic Centre has a full range of modern print and production equipment [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even the best maps are the result of compromise and estimate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unless you are on the ground looking at something, geographical information is always an approximation,” said Ian Spencer, Head of Geo Research. “We know how accurate our sources are, and the technical parameters of our sensors, so we know how accurate our products are. We have to work within a defined margin of error for each military product. If it’s outside that margin it’s considered unfit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; augments some of their products with open source material, such as Google Earth pictures, to provide pop-up images of features, but they do it knowing where the risks lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; produces more than just maps, whether on paper or on a screen. After all, a map is just one way of presenting geographical information, and it might not be the best solution for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you might need a database of geographic data to put in a weapons system, or a 3D simulation created from stereoscopic photographs to prepare yourself for the environment through which you may have to fly and control a missile. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; specialises in making sense of a huge mass of data and presenting it to the customer in a way that is going to help them make sense of the world, spot relationships, and make informed plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We get 2 types of request,” said Operations Officer Major Jim Danks. “These are ad hoc for a single event or operation, such as disaster relief or support to the Arab Spring operations. And longer term planned work which can include Afghanistan tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5848/Workstation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A geospatial analyst using stereographic imagery to produce simulations [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A request may start as a one-off and then develop into a long-term requirement. When Camp Bastion was established more than a decade ago it started as an ad hoc request. Now, as a home for thousands of troops, it is a standard request requiring the provision of many different types of data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for Lionel Fewson, Head of Collection, are 5 Collection Officers who could be described as the geographic equivalent of Indiana Jones. They scour the globe in search of useful, creditable data, visiting countries of interest gathering information and making new contacts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making maps from scratch is time consuming and very expensive, so international collaboration and data-sharing is very cost effective. Lionel said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have memorandums of understanding with 50 countries and links with many trusted commercial suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the digital side, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is part of a 29-nation programme to capture digital data from various places of interest around the world. In return for their contribution, the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; has access to the entire output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of the benefit of co-operation is the award-winning work producing image-based mapping of compounds in Helmand province to improve battlefield and situational awareness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the US Marine Corps Intelligence Activity, the project has to date captured and referenced more than 200,000 compounds and produced more than 1,100 large-scale maps covering more than 11,000 square kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Defence Geographic Centre personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5849/Research.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Defence Geographic Centre personnel meet to identify sources for new products [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to future products, there is a revolution taking place, and the &lt;abbr title="Defence Geographic Centre"&gt;DGC&lt;/abbr&gt; is leading the way. The move is towards making more use of human geography in an ordered way. Ian Spencer said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to develop standards with our overseas partners to define database structures so that we can start capturing information like ethnicity demographics, economics, religion and water control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you go on the internet you will see lots of people doing things in different disciplines, but at the moment it isn’t connected. We want to pull all this information together in a systematic way so that decision makers and analysts have a better understanding of what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we have the basic geographic foundation we can overlay that with all kinds of human activities. Once data is organised then you can share it and exploit it, and when it has a spatial element you can model these factors and see what effect their interaction has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian believes that marrying physical and social sciences will open up a new world of understanding, as long as you take into account the assumptions and approximations that have been made. Asking how does factor A affect element B is OK as long as you keep an eye out for any more fictitious islands on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="this-report-by-ian-carr-appears-in-the-december-2012january-2013-issue-of-defence-focus---the-magazine-for-everyone-in-defence"&gt;This report by Ian Carr appears in the December 2012/January 2013 issue of Defence Focus - the magazine for everyone in Defence.&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61122</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:26:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-commenting-on-the-latest-ucas-2013-cycle-applicant-figures"/>
    <title>Press Release: Commenting on the latest UCAS 2013 cycle applicant figures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Department for Business, Innovation and Skills spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is too early to form a definitive picture about university applications for the 2013/14 academic year. Traditionally fewer than 50 per cent of applicants have submitted their applications by this point in the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that no one is put off applying to university because they do not have information about the student support available to them. Most new students will not pay upfront, there will be more financial support for those from poorer families and everyone will make lower loan repayments than they do now once they are in well paid jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60955</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:30:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/better-choices-better-deals"/>
    <title>Better choices, better deals</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A radical new approach to give more power to consumers in their relationships with business.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumer Minister Edward Davey has announced today new plans on how businesses will provide key information to their customers on how they use and buy goods and services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help people get the best deal possible, and make business more dynamic in response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new approach is published in &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/better-choices-better-deals-strategy-helping-consumers-make-better-choices"&gt;Better Choices, Better Deals: Consumers Powering Growth&lt;/a&gt; and marks a shift away from legislating to make change happen. Instead it announces new ways to help consumers help themselves and challenges business to innovate, which in turn will drive growth in the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="midata"&gt;Midata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the initiative published today will be a project called &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"&gt;midata&lt;/a&gt;, which will assess how to give people their personal data in a format that is safe to pass onto third parties, such as price comparison sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an application or website can pick out the one perfect deal based on your user information, this will help to make consumer choices simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Davey said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an important new initiative that will radically change how consumers relate to business. By giving you more power in your relationship with businesses you will be better placed to get the deal you want, and that deal may put a bit of money back in your pocket.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will in turn reward the most competitive and innovative businesses.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-people-are-saying-about-better-choices-better-deals"&gt;What people are saying about ‘Better Choices: Better Deals’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Professor Nigel Shadbolt, Chair of Midata: **   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Information about how we shop, travel, communicate and live our lives is a powerful source of insight, so it’s important that each of us should be able to access our own data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am very much looking forward to chairing the mydata group, which aims to make accessing this data much simpler, and should be a watershed on how we use data to get a better deal every day.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Gillian Guy, Citizens Advice Chief Executive: **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Citizens Advice is an active champion for consumers. We help people get a better deal and make it simpler and easier to get information and advice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are thrilled to be part of this new consumer empowerment strategy alongside Citizens Advice Scotland and Consumer Focus.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In particular we are really pleased to see recognition that in new technology is not good news for everyone. Some vulnerable groups can be excluded from best value deals and methods of redress.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our experience helping over 2 million clients a year shows that consumers have many varied needs. We look forward to helping ensure that provision for consumers really is inclusive and services and products are equally available to all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christine Farnish, Chair of Consumer Focus, said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘It’s good news that government is looking at how more powerful consumers can create more effective markets and public services. While there are companies who want to provide better value and service, the truth is that if you don’t have demanding consumers, then you won’t have responsive markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A challenge for the government strategy is how it removes the barriers and opens the field for consumers to take action. This also needs to go hand in hand with making the most effective use of regulation and tackling the wider problems exhibited by consumer markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since its creation Consumer Focus has campaigned for better customer information and complaints handling. Increasingly we have been pushing new ways to unlock the ability of consumers to band together and either discipline poor companies or reward good ones. The opportunity for coordinated consumer action through online and social media is growing all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The success of this approach will depend on whether it really helps consumers to mobilise their market power by coming together and showing companies the benefits of providing the value and customer service that people want.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Richard Thaler, co-author of Nudge: Improving Decisions About Health, Wealth, and Happiness: &lt;br&gt;
** &lt;br&gt;
“This is a very exciting initiative that shows how modern technology can create entirely new ways of thinking about the government’s role in business regulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is of course true that we cannot replace all laws and regulations with nudges. However, this approach will give honest, high quality firms an edge in their battle with competitors who use obfuscation as their chief marketing strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Simple electronic disclosure is not costly for large firms to provide, and can provide enormous benefits to consumers. Eventually, this approach has the potential for replacing much more intrusive and burdensome regulations that firms inevitably find ways to evade.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Mayo, Secretary General of Co-operatives UK:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We welcome the growing interest in collective purchasing, from both government and from consumers. We are pleased to be working with BIS to launch the Innovation Prize. The best way to empower consumers is to enable them to come together co-operatively.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chris Wermann, Director of Corporate Affairs - Home Retail Group, Argos:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Argos always puts the customer first. Being at the forefront of multi-channel retailing in the UK we believe any successful retailer will need to evolve their product range, services and accessibility to ensure the customers get the best choice and value most suited to their needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government’s consumer empowerment programme is a great way to enable this to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Chan, CEO, Barclaycard Consumer Europe:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Barclaycard believes that digital technology - through simple online tools such as mybarclaycard, its award winning online servicing site which enables customers to analyse their spending, has the potential to really empower consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just imagine if people could easily access and review all their financial transaction data from all their banks, in one place, using simple web-based tools. We believe that could make a real difference to people, and that’s why we support mydata.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419163&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-better-information-and-protection-for-consumers"&gt;Consumer issues at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/better-choices-better-deals-report-on-progress-on-the-consumer-empowerment-strategy"&gt;Better choices: better deals. Report on progress on the consumer empowerment strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61079</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/30-million-boost-as-start-up-loans-for-young-entrepreneurs-expanded"/>
    <title>£30 million boost as Start-Up Loans for young entrepreneurs expanded</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Thousands more young people have the opportunity to apply for government loans to turn their business ideas into reality.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron has today announced a boost to the government’s Start-Up loans scheme, with funding being increased by £30 million to £110 million over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also said that due to demand from those who had just missed out on the scheme, and the challenges faced to secure loans to start a business, the age limit for applying will now be extended from 24 to 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-Up Loans provide budding entrepreneurs a range of support to get their business idea off the ground, including access to a business mentor as well as funding in the region of £2,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 3000 people have applied or registered an interest in a Start-Up loan; when their business plan is robust and approved, applicants are able to access the financial support, with a repayment period of up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that the scheme has been live over £1.5 million worth of loans have been approved, helping over 460 new businesses get off the ground. Around 100 new businesses a week are expected to reach approval stage in January, with thousands more in the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Start-Up Loans scheme forms an integral part of the Business in You campaign, which encourages the start up and growth of new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startuploans.co.uk/"&gt;Visit the Start-Up Loans Company for more information and details on how to apply.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Business in You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/browse/business"&gt;Tools and guidance for businesses on Gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/start-up-loans-scheme-expanded/"&gt;Read the full story on the Number 10 website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61086</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:14:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/playful-pup-newest-recruit-to-irish-guards"/>
    <title>Playful pup newest recruit to Irish Guards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An Irish Wolfhound puppy called Domhnall is the new regimental mascot for the 1st Battalion Irish Guards.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To the untrained eye, he is just a rather large, playful puppy. But in a few months, Irish Wolfhound Domhnall will be leading the way as the new regimental mascot for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/23990.aspx" title="The Irish Guards website"&gt;1st Battalion Irish Guards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based at Mons Barracks in Aldershot, Hampshire, the five-month-old is already training for the moment he dons a special silver collar and a scarlet tunic to join the guardsmen in their ceremonial role at occasions such as the Queen’s Birthday Parade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domhnall, whose name means ‘World Leader’ in Gaelic, came to the regiment from Northern Ireland untrained. He and handler Drummer David Steed are on a steep learning curve to make sure they look the part when Domhnall first fulfills the role of mascot at the regiment’s grand St Patrick’s Day parade in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5843/LAND-2012-212-IRISH_GDS_MASCOT_-087_copy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Irish Guards' new mascot, Domhnall, in festive spirit [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In just 2 months, ‘blank canvas’ Domhnall has already been housetrained and obedience-trained, Drummer Steed said, with his ceremonial training in London due to start in the near future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This will involve being with the regimental band, taking him out on Queen’s Guard mounts to get him used to the noises and the sights and sounds of London, as well as taking him to Knightsbridge for his horse-friendly training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because ceremonial duties are with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/28071.aspx" title="Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment website"&gt;Household Cavalry Mounted Regiment&lt;/a&gt;, it’s making sure that the horses aren’t startled by him and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drummer Steed admitted that training the hyperactive puppy - whose favourite occupation is chasing cyclists - is hard work for both of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But this kind of training the two of us are undergoing is something slightly different - it’s different from marching down the road carrying a rifle to suddenly having a four-legged friend by your side that you’ve got to control as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Benjamin Irwin-Clark, Adjutant of the 1st Battalion Irish Guards, said an Irish Wolfhound has been the regimental mascot for over a century:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quite early in our regiment’s history, in 1902, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.iwcni.co.uk/" title="Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland website"&gt;Irish Wolfhound Club of Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; offered to provide an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot to the Irish Guards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The regiment accepted, and, ever since then, I think with a few gaps, there has been an Irish Wolfhound as the regimental mascot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5844/LAND-2012-212_Irish_Guards_Mascot_075.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Drummer David Steed walks Domhnall [Picture: Corporal Steve Blake, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mascots are traditionally named after Irish chieftains and have a ceremonial role in the regiment, parading with guardsmen during ceremonial duties and state occasions in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Irwin-Clark added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the moment we’re just putting him through a sort of inoculation of the bagpipes, among other things, and I think it’s going to take a little time for him to get comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61065</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:56:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:56:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-innovation-workshop"/>
    <title>Support for Innovation Workshop</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A series of one day workshops about government support for business R&amp;D and innovation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A series of one day workshops about government support for business &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; and innovation are being organised over the next few months for small and medium sized enterprises and their professional advisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas covered include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the world-class level of &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credit relief to invest more in your &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;planning for the reduced (10%) rate of corporation tax on profits attributable to patents  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; grants available  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;networking with your peers in &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising government procurement opportunities for your &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maximising the value of intellectual property for competitive advantage  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using design to add value and help your business grow &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each session will be led by a representative from the relevant delivery body, and will allow ample time for Q&amp;amp;As. The day is supported by manned stands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government hopes that one of the outcomes of the workshops will be to increase take-up of &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credits by companies in sectors in which claims are low such as agri-food and also the energy and water industries. The government would also like to increase awareness that &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credit claims can be made for design work where this involves &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops are organized by the Department for Business Innovation &amp;amp; Skills (BIS) and HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs (&lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dates-and-venues"&gt;Dates and venues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details, including a link to the booking site, are below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please Note: A light lunch will be provided. If you have any food allergies that you would like us to be aware of please forward this information separately to &lt;a href="mailto:andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disabled access: if you have any special requirements please forward this information separately to &lt;a href="mailto:andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;andrew.culley@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="midlands"&gt;MIDLANDS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January 16, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birmingham Science Park Aston Ltd, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FW 8a, Faraday Wharf, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holt Street Birmingham, B7 4BB &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://bsp-a.com/contact/"&gt;View map and Directions&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: basement car park, charges ₤5/car 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=birmingham&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;submit=Search+Events"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="north-east"&gt;NORTH EAST&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January 30 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle                                                &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bewick Hall &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle City Library &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;33 New Bridge St West &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newcastle upon Tyne, NE1 8AX &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetmap.co.uk/map.srf?x=425037&amp;amp;y=564547&amp;amp;z=0&amp;amp;sv=NE18AX&amp;amp;st=2&amp;amp;pc=NE1+8AX&amp;amp;mapp=map.srf&amp;amp;searchp=ids.srf"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt;: located in central Newcastle close to metro, national rail and bus links.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking: there are around 10,000 parking places within five minutes walk. 
Note: this workshop is presented as part of the Newcastle Business and IP Centre programme of activities. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Newcastle+Upon+Tyne&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;date_from=30%2F01%2F2013&amp;amp;date_to=30%2F01%2F2013&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;ds_business_stage=&amp;amp;price_min=&amp;amp;price_max=&amp;amp;organiser_name=&amp;amp;text=&amp;amp;sort=location_distance.asc"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="north-west"&gt;NORTH WEST&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February 13 
STFC Daresbury Laboratory                    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecture Theatre &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daresbury Science and Innovation Campus &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrington &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WA4 4AD &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.sci-techdaresbury.com/location/"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: Free, but names of all attendees have to be provided in advance 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Warrington&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;submit=Search+Events"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="solent-and-south"&gt;SOLENT and SOUTH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February 20 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coach House                                   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilworth Manor Hotel, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilworth Southampton SO16 7PT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places available: 120 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bestwestern.co.uk/Hotels/Chilworth-Manor-Hotel-Southampton-83920/Meetings/Default.aspx?ImageType=Meeting&amp;amp;Microsite=Business"&gt;View map&lt;/a&gt; 
Parking: ample, free parking. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.business-events.org.uk/eventsearch?location=Southampton&amp;amp;location_distance=50&amp;amp;date_from=20%2F02%2F2013&amp;amp;date_to=20%2F02%2F2013&amp;amp;ds_sector=&amp;amp;ds_topic=110&amp;amp;ds_type=14&amp;amp;ds_business_stage=&amp;amp;price_min=&amp;amp;price_max=&amp;amp;organiser_name=&amp;amp;text=&amp;amp;sort=location_distance.asc"&gt;book at Business Events Finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="wales"&gt;WALES&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 6 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zen Room &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ATRiuM &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardiff School of Creative &amp;amp; Cultural Industries &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Glamorgan &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Street &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardiff &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CF24 2FN &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places avaliable: 70&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: A representitive of the Welsh Government will discuss SMARTCymru RD&amp;amp;I Funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nearest rail station is Cardiff Queen Street however Cardiff Central Station is also within walking distance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking There is a large car park opposite ATRiuM Building on Adam Street 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://profile.glam.ac.uk/findus/"&gt;more information and driving directions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="booking"&gt;Booking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A link to the booking site will be made available shortly. 
This workshop is being organised by BIS and &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; together with the Welsh Government in partnership with the University of Glamorgan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="scotland"&gt;SCOTLAND&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 20 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eden Court &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bishop’s Road &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inverness IV3 5SA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information including a link to the booking site will be made available shortly. 
This workshop is being organised by BIS and &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; together with the Scottish Government&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agenda&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09.30 Registration and manned stalls open &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00 Welcome &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10.10 Introduction by BIS &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10.20 &lt;abbr title="HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs"&gt;HMRC&lt;/abbr&gt; Presentation - &lt;abbr title="research and development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; tax credits scheme / Patent box &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11.10 Coffee/ networking and chance to visit manned stands &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11.40 Technology Strategy Board Presentation - Supports available and 
how to access them including: Grants and net-working &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:20 Intellectual Property Office Presentation - Supports available to 
protect and maximise value from intellectual property &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:00 Design Council - Presentation - how design can add value / 
Designing Demand programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:40 Concluding comments &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:45 Lunch - plus opportunity to network and visit manned stands &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14:50 Close&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="business-in-you"&gt;Business in You&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops are part of the Business in You campaign – a partnership between private enterprise and government to highlight support for start-ups and growing businesses and encourage entrepreneurial spirit. 
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://businessinyou.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Further information at the Business in You website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61179</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T14:50:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/army-olympic-gold-medalist-awarded-mbe"/>
    <title>Army Olympic gold medallist awarded MBE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Captain Heather Stanning has been awarded an MBE by Her Majesty The Queen in the New Year Honours for her achievements at the 2012 Olympics.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Stanning, of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24677.aspx" title="32 Regiment website"&gt;32 Regiment Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, and her rowing partner, Helen Glover, were &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympic-gold-for-armys-heather-stanning" title="Read more at GOV.UK"&gt;the first British Olympians to win gold medals in the 2012 Olympic Games&lt;/a&gt;, and the first female pairing to win Olympic gold medals in a women’s rowing event at the Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about her award, Captain Stanning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud and honoured to be awarded an &lt;abbr title="Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;. After an amazing year this really is the perfect end. I can’t thank the public, the Army and my family enough for all the support they have given to me in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now I am looking forward to 2013 and my planned deployment to Afghanistan, which I know will be as challenging and rewarding as everything I achieved in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Stanning was commissioned from Sandhurst in 2008 before joining 32 Regiment Royal Artillery. Two years ago she was released from Army duties to allow her attempt to row into Olympic history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair had a number of successes leading up to the Olympics, notably winning all 3 World Cup regattas prior to the London Games. This level of form and confidence was carried into the Olympics, and through months of hard work, intense training and determination, the pair won Olympic gold in the women’s coxless pairs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Stanning has now returned her unit in the Army and is due to deploy to Afghanistan later this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
