<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-02T14:50:42+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61035</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T14:50:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/army-olympic-gold-medalist-awarded-mbe"/>
    <title>Army Olympic gold medalist awarded MBE</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Captain Heather Stanning has been awarded an MBE by Her Majesty The Queen in the New Year Honours for her achievements at the 2012 Olympics.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Stanning, of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24677.aspx" title="32 Regiment website"&gt;32 Regiment Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt;, and her rowing partner, Helen Glover, were &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympic-gold-for-armys-heather-stanning" title="Read more at GOV.UK"&gt;the first British Olympians to win gold medals in the 2012 Olympic Games&lt;/a&gt;, and the first female pairing to win Olympic gold medals in a women’s rowing event at the Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about her award, Capt Stanning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud and honoured to be awarded an &lt;abbr title="Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;. After an amazing year this really is the perfect end. I can’t thank the public, the Army and my family enough for all the support they have given to me in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now I am looking forward to 2013 and my planned deployment to Afghanistan, which I know will be as challenging and rewarding as everything I achieved in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capt Stanning was commissioned from Sandhurst in 2008 before joining 32 Regiment Royal Artillery. Two years ago she was released from Army duties to allow her attempt to row into Olympic history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair had a number of successes leading up to the Olympics, notably winning all three World Cup regattas prior to the London Games. This level of form and confidence was carried into the Olympics, and through months of hard work, intense training and determination, the pair won Olympic gold in the Women’s coxless pairs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capt Stanning has now returned her unit in the Army and is due to deploy to Afghanistan in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60988</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T11:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T11:25:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cutting-red-tape-will-save-homeowners-240-on-diy-electrical-jobs-says-don-foster"/>
    <title>Cutting red tape will save homeowners £240 on DIY electrical jobs, says Don Foster</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government moves to scrap the requirement to get simple and low risk electrical works approved will save money for householders. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government moves to scrap the requirement for householders to get simple and low risk electrical works approved by their local council will save ‘DIYers’ £240 each, and in some cases even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduced just before Christmas, these changes will come into force in April 2013 and will avoid the need for householders to seek council approval for simple jobs such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding a socket to a kitchen, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;installing a new security light or a lawnmower socket in the garden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under current rules obtaining council approval for such jobs costs around £240 each time, or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riskier jobs such as work near baths and showers, installing new circuits and house rewires will continue to require approval from councils’ building control departments or be carried out by an electrician registered to approve their own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lots of people will have made it a new year resolution to fix or improve their home’s electrics, but they are often put off by the bureaucratic costs. I am cutting red tape to allow people to get on with making simple and safe improvements without having to spend hundreds of pounds on getting the council’s approval. Safety is the number one concern though and riskier jobs will always need to be signed off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also urged people to stay safe and continue using common sense saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I urge anyone who is either inexperienced at DIY or in doubt as to what they are doing to always consult a professional. Using a competent electrician is the simplest way to ensure you and your family remain safe. That’s why I’ll be working with industry and others to see what more we can do to get this simple message across.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also acknowledged that many people - mainly married men like him - were going to lose an excuse for not getting on with their list of jobs around the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are part of a package of measures to clarify and update the building regulations that will also save businesses £50 million a year. Taking over 400,000 electrical jobs out of the system annually contributes to savings to electrical firms of around £14 million per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The changes to electrical safety were included in a package of deregulatory measures &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations" title="Written Ministerial Statement by Don Foster on changes to the building regulations regime in England"&gt;announced to Parliament&lt;/a&gt; on 18 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety" title="Consultation on building regulations -electrical safety"&gt;consultation in January 2012&lt;/a&gt; sought views on electrical safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The deregulation package also delivers other savings to business including:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;bringing together currently separate guidance on how to design stairs and ramps so they are both safe and accessible - saving £4.4 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;updating fire safety guidance for lighting diffusers - saving £26.3 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;making the building control system more efficient and to extending the scope of competent person schemes - saving £6 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60977</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T11:05:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T11:05:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-ministers-letter-to-g8-leaders"/>
    <title>Prime Minister's letter to G8 leaders.</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Prime Minister David Cameron has written to fellow G8 leaders to outline his plans for the G8 Presidency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“As the UK takes over the Presidency of the G8, I wanted to write myself to begin a discussion with you about what we can achieve together. We will be meeting at Lough Erne in Northern Ireland in June. Northern Ireland’s prospects have been transformed by the peace process of the last twenty years – and it is a mark of the progress made that we can hold a G8 Summit there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that in 2013 the world will continue to face grave economic uncertainty. Our first priority will be dealing with the challenges in our own countries. But as leaders of eight countries making up around half of the world’s entire GDP, the ambitious standards we set and the bold steps we take by working together through the G8 can make a tangible difference by firing up economies and driving prosperity, not just in our own countries, but all over the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that at Lough Erne we can seize this opportunity. At the heart of my agenda for the Summit are three issues – advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency. All of them are areas where I believe the G8 can play a distinctive role, using our commitment to open economies, open governments and open societies to support enterprise and deliver economic growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to achieve this will require strong political leadership and months of detailed policy work from our teams.  This G8 will not be the kind of Summit where we simply whip out a chequebook at the 11th hour, pledge some money and call it a success. What we are talking about are long-term changes in our countries and the rules that govern the relationships between them. With ambition on this scale, I am convinced that success depends on us starting a debate on these changes now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, on trade, there is a huge amount on the table in the coming year – including a possible deal between the EU and Canada, the opening of negotiations between the EU and Japan, and Russia deepening its integration into the global trading system as it enters its second year of WTO membership. Globally we can also hope to reduce paperwork and bureaucracy at borders including through an agreement on Trade Facilitation at the WTO Ministerial in December, which would also give extra impetus to our support for free-flowing trade across Africa. And, with Europe and America together accounting for a third of global trade, perhaps the single biggest prize of all would be the beginning of negotiations on an EU-US trade agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are vital opportunities for global growth, and I hope that we in the G8 can offer leadership – in particular by working with businesses in every sector of our economies to mobilise support for these deals and by using the openness of our direct engagement as leaders to address the sticking points frankly and to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, on tax, we know that in a globalised world, no one country can, on its own, effectively tackle tax evasion and aggressive avoidance. But as a group of eight major economies together we have an opportunity to galvanise collective international action.  We can lead the way in sharing the information to tackle abuses of the system, including in developing countries, so that Governments can collect the taxes due to them. We can work together to sign more countries up to the international standards. And we can examine the case for strengthening those standards themselves – whether by improving existing standards or looking at new ones. These are complex questions, and will involve honest and detailed discussion about the right approach. But I do believe that as leaders, we all have a common interest in being able to tell our taxpayers who work hard and pay their fair share of taxes, that we will make sure others do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, in our partnership with less developed and emerging economies, I believe we must put a new and practical emphasis on transparency, accountability and open government. Too many developing countries are held back by corruption – and this can be reinforced or even encouraged by poor business practice and a lack of transparency from those that trade with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our collective efforts on international development over the years give the G8 both the legitimacy and responsibility to move the international agenda forward to focus not just on aid, but also on the underlying drivers of growth and jobs which will lift people out of poverty for good.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like to see the G8 continue to increase transparency in our aid flows so people in developing countries can hold their governments to account for spending them effectively, and people at home can see the impact their generosity makes. This accountability is vital if we are to maintain a global coalition on development and to build on last year’s New Alliance for Food Security and Nutrition, stepping up the fight against hunger by encouraging the growth of more nutritious food and getting it to families at prices they can afford. 
The G8 can also support the underlying building blocks of growth, including the rule of law, the absence of conflict and corruption, and the presence of property rights and strong institutions – what I have called the “golden thread” that makes open economies and open societies the best foundation for growth.  I hope our work will demonstrate that this is not just about what developing countries do themselves. We in the developed world need to work together with them to prevent money laundering and stamp out bribery and corruption. And we need to look at how to enhance transparency – including through the Construction Sector Transparency Initiative and new ideas like a global land transparency partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, there will be questions about what we are each prepared to sign up to. I hope we can be ambitious. In that spirit I have already signalled some important changes in the UK’s positions. For example, while the US has agreed to sign up to the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative, Britain and all the other G8 countries have yet to subscribe to this global process which helps to ensure that people around the world benefit from the extraction of natural resources from the countries in which they live. We need to change that. We cannot call on other countries to live up to these high standards if we are not prepared to do so ourselves. That is why I have asked for an urgent review of the UK position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These decisions can not simply be left to our technical experts. They need our decisive leadership. The truth is that on all these issues, we know what the sticking points are and we need to find the political will to tackle them head on. By working together over the coming months, I believe that we can. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to discussing these issues with you and to welcoming you to Lough Erne this Summer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60963</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T20:15:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T20:15:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"/>
    <title>UK offers condolences to Ivory Coast following deadly stampede</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has expressed his sadness following the death and injury of people in a stampede in Ivory Coast.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on a stampede following a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan in Ivory Coast, Foreign Office Minister of State Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked and deeply saddened at the tragic loss of life in a stampede in Ivory Coast, which has also injured hundreds of people. During what should have been a happy and joyous celebration of the New Year, many families are now mourning their loved ones. The UK Government sends its sincere condolences to all the Ivorian people at this time.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60959</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"/>
    <title>The UK's G8 priorities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK's G8 Presidency will be an economic G8 that deals with big issues in the global economy and prioritises trade, tax and transparency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK takes over the one-year Presidency of the G8 today (1 January) and will hold the annual leaders’ summit in Northern Ireland on 17 and 18 June. As the chair of the G8, the UK has a unique opportunity to lead in shaping the outcomes of the summit and taking concrete action with other G8 countries to address some of the world’s most pressing challenges, including important economic and foreign policy issues of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has announced that he will focus the G8 in 2013 on 3 key areas: open economies, open governments and open societies to unleash the power of the private sector by advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="trade"&gt;Trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no greater stimulus for growth in the world economy than trade and no more important battle than the fight against protectionism. The G8 has collective responsibility to drive forward trade liberalisation. Among G8 countries work is already on going to prepare a free trade agreement between the EU and Canada and work will start next year to begin free trade negotiations between the EU and Japan and the EU and US. An EU-US free trade agreement would be particularly significant – the EU and US together make up nearly a third of all global trade and an ambitious deal between the two could provide an enormous boost to jobs and growth. The G8 leaders’ summit will be an opportunity to show the importance of this ongoing work and to agree how to accelerate progress across our common trade priorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tax"&gt;Tax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will focus on strengthening international tax standards and working on greater international tax information exchange to tackle tax havens.  This will build on work that is already underway in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) and maintain the momentum set by the G20. And we will work with developing countries to enable them to collect tax that is due to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transparency"&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 has a long history of advancing the development agenda - and the UK’s G8 Presidency will be no different. The UK is meeting its commitment to spend 0.7 per cent of its gross national income on aid from 2013 and will hold other countries to account for their promises too. With this track record on aid, the Prime Minister plans to use the G8 Presidency to support the ‘golden thread’ of conditions that he sees as critical to the growth and prosperity of countries across the world. These include the absence of conflict, clamping down on corruption and ensuring strong and accountable government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency and accountability are vitally important to achieve these conditions. Too often, development at the G8 has been about rich countries doing things to poor countries. But at Lough Erne the G8 will focus on getting its own house in order and helping developing countries to prosper in the process. An example of this is mineral wealth. It’s important that developing countries rich in minerals see this as a blessing not a curse. The UK is already leading efforts in the EU that will require oil, gas and mining companies to publish key financial information for each country and project they work on. The UK’s G8 Presidency will push for greater transparency all around the globe so that revenues from oil, gas and mining are transparent. This should encourage greater accountability and ensure money doesn’t fuel conflict and corruption, but instead is used to provide better public services for citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined action on trade, tax and transparency during the UK’s G8 Presidency could lay the foundations of long-term growth and prosperity for generations to come and will support the development of open economies, open governments and open societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will also make progress across a range of vital global issues, including foreign policy challenges and supporting Arab Spring countries. The UK’s Presidency will also build on the Olympic Hunger Summit and the US’s New Alliance for Food Security and Nutrition, leading the way in the battle against hunger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this year the UK will also produce a comprehensive accountability report (CAR) that will show progress against key commitments made by the G8. The report is a concrete example of transparency and accountability at work, a central theme of the UK’s G8 Presidency, and an opportunity to hold G8 leaders to account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.linkedin.com/today/post/article/20121121130535-146036479-eyes-of-the-world-on-uk-again-for-g8-summit"&gt;Read the Prime Minister’s recent article on the G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60960</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:17:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue"/>
    <title>Lough Erne: G8 venue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year's G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2013 the UK will hold the Presidency of the G8. As part of the year-long Presidency there will be a G8 Summit of the 8 global leaders in June. The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year’s G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, in Northern Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing the G8 to Lough Erne will showcase to the world a modern Northern Ireland with huge potential for investment and tourism, demonstrating the growing confidence that exists in this part of the UK. It will highlight what Northern Ireland, its people and its businesses have to offer the global community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The venue of Lough Erne 2013 was also chosen because it creates the right conditions to encourage open and frank discussions between the G8 leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to welcoming my fellow leaders to Lough Erne and to showcase Northern Ireland to the world as a modern and dynamic part of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Northern Ireland’s transformation over the last 2 decades was made possible by the courage of so many people across sections of the community. Their determination and leadership has inspired the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60958</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:16:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/what-is-the-g8"/>
    <title>What is the G8?</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The G8 is a forum that brings together 8 global leaders to address global issues and tackle the most pressing global challenges.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The G8 (Group of 8) is made up of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Russia, the USA and the UK. The EU is represented by Jose Manuel Barroso, the President of the European Commission, and Herman Van Rompuy, the President of the European Council. The Presidency of the G8 rotates each calendar year and the country holding the G8 Presidency is responsible for hosting and organising the annual summit, with a number of preparatory meetings leading up to it. The summit is an opportunity for G8 leaders to have frank and open discussions about the important global issues of the day. In 2013 it will be the UK’s turn to shape the G8’s approach to these discussions with G8 leaders holding each other to account and agreeing concrete steps to advance growth and prosperity across the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="history-of-the-g8"&gt;History of the G8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1973 the world experienced its worst economic crisis since the Great Depression. The finance ministers of the USA, UK, France and West Germany met informally to talk about how they could solve the economic problems linked with the oil price shock. In 1974 Japan was invited to the meetings and in 1975 the French President brought these informal discussions to the leaders. He also invited Italy to what was the first G6 in Rambouillet, France. There was no army of political advisers in tow, just the leaders in a relaxed and private setting. This low-key formula was very successful and the leaders agreed to meet annually. A year later Canada joined and after the collapse of the Soviet Union, Russia became a full member in 1998. The EU has been part of the group since 1977, but does not hold a Presidency. Almost 40 years on, the G8 countries can provide guidance and stability in an unpredictable world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-presidency-involve"&gt;What does the Presidency involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 Presidency runs for 1 calendar year and rotates among the 8 member countries. The country chairing the Presidency is responsible for shaping the issues that leaders discuss at the G8 Summit and hosts a number of preparatory meetings leading up to the summit. It also acts as the spokesperson for the G8. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Presidency is an opportunity for the UK to influence the international debate on our global priorities, which include tax, trade and transparency. At the end of this year, the UK will hand over the Presidency to Russia for 2014. The Presidency will continue in its rotation to Germany in 2015, Japan in 2016, Italy in 2017, Canada in 2018, France in 2019, and the USA in 2020 before it returns to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-g8-do"&gt;What does the G8 do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 is a forum that provides the opportunity for its members to co-operate in addressing global challenges. The standards it sets, commitments it makes and steps it takes aim to drive prosperity and economic growth all over the world. Prime Minister David Cameron has said that this year the G8 will return to its roots, creating the right environment for frank and open discussions to promote growth and address global economic problems. There will be a short declaration aimed at holding G8 leaders to account and ensuring that good intentions become vital actions to advance growth and prosperity across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60961</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:14:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"/>
    <title>G8 events</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During the UK G8 Presidency 2013 there will be events in addition to the leaders' summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="g8-foreign-ministers-meeting"&gt;G8 foreign ministers’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 and 11 April 2013, the Foreign Secretary William Hague will host his counterparts from the G8 countries. They will meet for the G8 foreign ministers’ meeting at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to the UK’s G8 Presidency making headway on the serious challenges facing our global community today. Today the Prime Minister explained that by supporting the development of open economies, open governments and open societies we can harness the power of the private sector for everyone’s benefit. Our G8 priorities of advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency can only take place in an environment of political stability and peaceful international relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With my G8 foreign minister partners, I look forward to discussing and taking decisions on some of the most pressing foreign and security policy issues that we face. In particular I will be focusing on the Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative, a personal priority for me during the UK’s G8 Presidency and beyond, and ensuring that the G8’s Deauville Partnership provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g7-finance-ministers-and-central-bank-governors-meeting"&gt;G7 finance ministers’ and Central Bank governors’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 to 11 May 2013, the Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne and the Governor of the Bank of England Sir Mervyn King will host a spring meeting of the G7 finance ministers and Central Bank governors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Chancellor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to hosting colleagues from the G7 to Britain in the spring. This group remains an important institution and a key forum in which to grapple with the challenges that face the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This meeting will be a significant opportunity for the UK and our partners to take on these challenges and to show leadership in the fight to tackle the ongoing ramifications of the global financial and debt crisis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g8-leaders-summit"&gt;G8 leaders’ summit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G8 leaders’ summit will take place on 17 to 18 June 2013 at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue" title="Lough Erne Venue"&gt;Lough Erne in County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60909</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/action-on-council-tax-a-helping-hand-to-residents-cost-of-living-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>Action on council tax a helping hand to residents cost of living, says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Communities Secretary hailed new rules for 2013 that mean taxpayers can now choose to pay their bill over 12 months rather than 10.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move will lower average band D council tax instalments by an average of £24 per month for 10 months and helps tax payers manage their finances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legislation passed by the government means that in 2013 council tax payers can now request to pay their bills over a longer period of time, lowering their monthly bills, and so easing the financial burden&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has already &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/third-year-of-council-tax-freeze-announced"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; support for local authorities in England to help them freeze council tax in 2014-15 for a third year and assist in keeping bills down. The government has set aside £450 million as part of the Autumn Statement package to help support local authorities. Taxpayers living in an average band D home in England could save up to £72 compared to a 5% increase, while the cumulative effect of the 3 freezes is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils will also be able to publish online the detailed supporting information that until now they have had to supply with council tax bills in hard copies. While residents still have the legal right to request hard-copy documents, the online versions will enable authorities to cut costs, improve efficiencies and help the environment through a decrease in the use of paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are also urging councils to follow the example of utility companies in offering discounts to those customers who pay online or through direct debit facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We know many people are worried about their cost of living expenses and we’ve already acted to freeze council tax in the past 2 years after bills doubled under the last administration. We have now offered councils a third freeze deal, which could have a combined effect potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have also changed the rules so hard working council residents can choose to pay their annual bills online or spread their payments over 12 months instead of 10. These sensible measures will make paying easier giving tax payers a little more room for manoeuvre and bring down their monthly outgoings by around £24 for most of the year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Billing authorities collect and enforce council tax as per the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/1992/613/contents/made"&gt;Council Tax (Administration and Enforcement) Regulations 1992&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/3038/contents/made"&gt;Council Tax (Demand Notices)(England) Regulations 2011&lt;/a&gt;. For each financial year, billing authorities must issue demand notices (the bill) setting out the amount that is due and how it is to be paid. From April 2013, the demand notice will inform bill payers of their right to pay in 12 instalments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government consulted on its technical reforms to council tax between 31 October and 29 December 2011. The government’s response can be found on the 
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-of-council-tax"&gt;consultation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has set aside £450 million over two years as part of the Autumn Statement package to help support local authorities in freezing their council tax in 2013-14.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60956</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T23:02:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"/>
    <title>Ministerial statement on UN sanctions against the M23, FDLR, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Legerero</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for Africa comments on vote agreeing sanctions against groups and individuals involved in the conflict in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds MP, the UK Minister for Africa, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome today’s agreement by the UN Security Council Sanctions Committee to add the Congolese rebel group, M23, to its list of sanctioned organisations and individuals. The Committee also agreed the listings of two M23 leaders, Eric Badege and Jean-Marie Runiga Lugerero, as well as of the militia group Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR). The UK supports these measures as part of the international community’s response to the crisis in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). We remain committed to finding long term solutions which will end the cycle of violence in the DRC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops, that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR. It is also important that the DRC Government shows leadership in addressing the underlying causes of conflict in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK, with its partners, will continue to seek ways to support the building of a sustainable peace in eastern DRC.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61041</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T10:01:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/make-it-your-new-year-s-resolution-to-help-get-rough-sleepers-off-the-streets"/>
    <title>Make it your New Year’s resolution to help get rough sleepers off the streets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>People setting their New Year’s resolutions can now pledge to offer practical help to rough sleepers in 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk urged anyone wanting to get help for someone sleeping rough to use the new StreetLink hotline and website to ensure they are put in touch with the local agencies offering it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that while people want to offer help to those facing homelessness, they often don’t know where to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But StreetLink, run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway with support from the government, offers a “valuable alternative” to a cash handout for people sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those looking to offer help can call 0300 500 0914 or go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk" title="StreetLink"&gt;www.streetlink.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; to put those facing sleeping rough in touch with local charities and councils who can them get them long-term support and safe accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued this new and innovative service helps support the No Second Night Out initiative as it is extended across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London, where No Second Night Out has been adopted, 70% of rough sleepers have not spent more than one night on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The New Year offers many of us an opportunity to make a new start - StreetLink offers that opportunity to those facing the prospect of living on our streets and a valuable alternative to simply a cash handout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge anyone looking to set themselves a New Year’s resolution to use this service to ensure people sleeping rough in their area get the support they need to get off the streets and into a stable home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;Mark Prisk on rough sleeping and Streetlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60873</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-this-new-years-eve-try-a-mocktail"/>
    <title>Driving this New Year's Eve? Try a mocktail</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Department for Transport has produced a number of non-alcoholic cocktail recipes to help designated drivers celebrate in style.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is encouraging drivers to opt for non alcoholic ‘mocktails’ in a bid to cut down on drink driving this New Year’s Eve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has produced a number of recipes – from a Berry Breezer to a Piña Banana – to appeal to those who are designated drivers on nights out.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is also warning party-goers to plan their way home in advance so they can celebrate the New Year in style, not in the cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hard-hitting television advert highlighting the consequences of drink driving has been shown throughout December as part of the Department for Transport’s THINK! drink drive campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Stephen Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our message is clear: have a great New Year’s Eve, don’t risk the consequences of drink driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you get behind the wheel after drinking you risk losing your licence as well as facing a fine and even a prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2011, 280 people were killed in accidents where the driver was over the limit. Do not let 1 selfish and foolish decision ruin your or another family’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, drivers aged between 20 and 24 failed more breath tests than any other age group. This year’s THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign is aimed at young people who are shown to be consistently over-represented in drink drive casualty figures. THINK! advises planning your journey home well in advance and treating your designated driver to a non-alcoholic Christmas cocktail. The recipes are easy to make at home and provide a festive alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is currently consulting on a package of tough measures to crack down on drink drivers. This includes removing drink drivers’ rights to demand a blood or urine test. This is because evidence shows it is used as a delaying tactic by drivers caught over the limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also supported Coke’s designated driver scheme, which offered buy 1 get 1 free soft drinks in pubs around the country throughout December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACPO lead for roads policing, Deputy Chief Constable Suzette Davenport, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millions of people will be heading out for New Year’s Eve celebrations and we would ask the public to play their part in remaining safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen hundreds of people die from drink driving this year and it has to stop. Innocent people are needlessly dying on our roads and people who make the decision to drive after taking alcohol or drugs are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are someone who drinks and drives, by making a decision to stop in 2013 could save someone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is provisionally estimated that 2011 saw 280 deaths, 1,290 serious injuries and 9,990 total casualties directly related to drink driving incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the THINK! Christmas drink drive campaign budget totals £783,925&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for a high-resolution copy of the advert the THINK! ‘moment of doubt’ TV advert, contact the Department for Transport’s press office on 020 7944 6898&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THINK! campaign posters can be downloaded directly from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/drink-driving.html"&gt;campaign site&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for more information about the Department for Transport’s consultation into the removal of a driver’s right to a blood test, visit &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tough-new-measures-to-tackle-drink-drivers"&gt;the GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/ras51-reported-drinking-and-driving"&gt;read table RAS51004 to see drink drivers by age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="non-alcoholic-christmas-cocktail-recipes"&gt;Non-alcoholic Christmas Cocktail Recipes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="berry-breezer"&gt;Berry Breezer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half a fresh lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the lime and sugar together, add the juices, shake and strain over ice. Top with tonic and garnish with a lime wedge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="elderflower-spritzer"&gt;Elderflower Spritzer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 millilitres of elderflower cordial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 lemon wedges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;half a teaspoon of brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soda water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mint to garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the sugar and lemon wedges together, add the elderflower cordial, shake, top with soda, stir and add more ice as required. Garnish with a lemon wedge and a sprig of mint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="winter-warmer"&gt;Winter Warmer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of apple juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75 millilitres of cranberry juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lemon and cloves for garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heat the apple and cranberry juice together for 1 minute in the microwave, stir in the honey and serve immediately in a heated mug or handled glass. Garnish with a clove-studded lemon wheel. For an extra twist replace the honey with spiced sugar syrup. To make this, mix some sugar gomme, vanilla pods, a cinnamon stick, a handful of cloves and some cardamom and allow to infuse for 3 days. Sieve
the sugar and mix with the heated apple and cranberry juices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="citrus-mock-tini"&gt;Citrus Mock-tini&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 fresh kumquats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons of lime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marmalade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 millilitres of clementine juice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonic water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crush the kumquats with the marmalade, add the clementine juice, shake, pour over ice and top with tonic. Garnish with spent kumquat shells. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pia-banana"&gt;Piña Banana&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 banana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon of almond syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons of honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 millilitres single cream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dash of pineapple juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blend all the ingredients together with some ice until frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16543</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:55:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/armys-airborne-engineers-build-french-connection"/>
    <title>Army's airborne engineers build French connection</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An exercise has seen British airborne engineers build a bridge over a large man-made lake and train with their French counterparts.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/role/834.aspx" title="23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)"&gt;23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault)&lt;/a&gt; has been working in the harsh climate and unforgiving landscape of Northumbria with French troops from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/genie/17e-regiment-du-genie-parachutiste" title="17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste"&gt;17e Regiment du Genie Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (17e RGP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper tested troops in a humanitarian relief operation in a country facing famine and struggling to recover from damage caused by a tsunami, with government control undermined by insurgents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After deploying from their base at Woodbridge in Suffolk, the exercise started in earnest with the use of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/equipment/705.aspx" title="Air Portable Ferry Bridge"&gt;Air Portable Ferry Bridge&lt;/a&gt; (APFB) equipment to move vehicles and personnel across the two-mile-wide (3.2km) expanse of Kielder Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APFB specialist equipment is designed to be parachuted or moved by helicopter and set up either as a conventional bridge or a self-propelled ferry to cross wider obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sappers preparing the bridge" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1134/16x-2012-115-0114.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sappers preparing the bridge to go over Kielder Water during Exercise Eagle Sapper [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sappers then moved to Otterburn, where they were challenged to build water supply points capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day, cross rivers using bridging equipment and improvised materials, demolish obstacles, and construct defensive positions which were then attacked by enemy forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training was intended to test the unit in their role providing combat engineering support to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/12409.aspx" title="16 Air Assault Brigade"&gt;16 Air Assault Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, which is ready to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice for operations ranging from disaster relief to war-fighting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jason Hones, Commanding Officer of 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Exercise Eagle Sapper has seen our soldiers working for up to 22-hours-a-day on demanding tasks that test both their combat engineering and infantry skills in very harsh terrain and weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1135/16x-2012-115-0631.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The sappers and their French counterparts built a water supply point capable of providing 40,000 litres of drinking water every day during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges  [Picture: Corporal Obi Igbo, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that we test the mettle of the soldier we are going to send on operations in arduous and unknown conditions so that we know he can cope with anything that is thrown at him. If a soldier can survive in Northumbria in winter he can survive anywhere in the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The French troops joined the exercise as part of the developing partnership between 16 Air Assault Brigade and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defense.gouv.fr/terre/presentation/organisation-des-forces/brigades/11e-brigade-parachutiste" title="11e Brigade Parachutiste"&gt;11e Brigade Parachutiste&lt;/a&gt; (11e BP), which have been tasked to develop a Combined Joint Expeditionary Force for contingency operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lt Col Hones said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really lucky to have soldiers from our French partner regiment with us, having recently sent troops over to train in France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Water supply point" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1136/16x-2012-115-0667.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A water supply point constructed during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working together on this exercise is developing our integration at the section level, to learn how we each operate and our particular strengths and weaknesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will take this to the next level up in the coming months, working towards the aim of being able to work seamlessly together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Matthieu Le Puloc’h commanded the ten-strong 17e RGP contingent, who lived and worked with their British counterparts throughout the two-week exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is our first joint training and our presence is about learning how 23 Engineer Regiment works so that, if we do go on operations together, we know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defends his position" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1137/16x-2012-115-0804.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sapper from 23 Engineer Regiment (Air Assault) defending his position during Exercise Eagle Sapper on Otterburn Ranges [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are a lot of similarities in our basic role as airborne engineers, but our equipment and working practices are different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Otterburn is a cold and hard environment but we have quickly adapted to it and the exercise has been a great experience to broaden the minds of our soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Steve McCann said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s been a tough exercise in difficult conditions that has been made more challenging by working with our French counterparts. Their kit is slightly different and the language barrier makes everything go a little bit slower, but we’re showing them how we work and it’s rewarding to complete engineering tasks together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17217</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/military-urge-generous-public-not-to-swamp-postal-system-at-christmas"/>
    <title>Military urge generous public not to swamp postal system at Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Service personnel are urging members of the public to avoid sending unsolicited Christmas gifts and packages to operational theatres.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Christmas post deadline of 3 December approaches for Armed Forces personnel serving overseas, servicemen and women are urging members of the public not to send unsolicited gifts and packages to operational theatres such as Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these kind sentiments are appreciated, such generosity has often resulted in delaying important mail from family and friends reaching their destination at this special time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceFor/ServiceCommunity/BFPO/BritishForcesPostOffice.htm" title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;British Forces Post Office&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) is overwhelmed by the generosity of the public who send individuals, and groups, in operational theatres boxes of treats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although well-intentioned, the message is very clear: if people wish to show their support for those serving in Afghanistan, there are far more effective ways of doing so such as donations to Service charities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; spokesperson Lieutenant Colonel Brett Duxbury said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with every year, the Christmas post period is by far our busiest. Just this week we dispatched more than 10,500 bags of mail to operational theatres, which will arrive in time for Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unsolicited mail can seriously impact on our ability to deliver post from loved ones to personnel serving on operations at Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not underestimate the impact that mail from friends and family can have on morale and it is for that reason we make it our priority each year to ensure it arrives on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parcels are coming in thick and fast to the military’s premier transport hub of &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, via the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, and have been loaded onto aircraft ready for dispatch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Service personnel are working hard to ensure that this mail is delivered alongside other vital supplies such as helicopters, armoured vehicles and lifesaving equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Danny Smith, from No 1 Air Mobility Wing at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last two days over 23 tonnes of mail has arrived at Brize Norton from the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, which has been loaded onto aircraft and is now en route to various operational theatres including Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a challenging but important task ensuring it is all dispatched quickly. Having served in Afghanistan at Christmas last year, I understand how much value our boys and girls place on receiving post from people closest to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1242/Mail1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas mail for the troops, sorted, bagged and packaged, awaits final transportation to Afghanistan in the air cargo hangar at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The volume of mail arriving at Camp Bastion for onward distribution to other locations in Afghanistan can cause other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The onward delivery of goodwill parcels to forward operating bases necessitates additional resupply flights and convoys, which places Service personnel at additional risk in what is already a difficult and dangerous operating environment. Every time an additional convoy is laid on, more troops are put at risk of enemy attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of items included in many welfare parcels are either already readily available in theatre or are simply not appropriate for the Afghan environment. Not only does this mean that the items go to waste, but time and resources have to be diverted from crucial operations to organise their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government is dedicated to the care and welfare of the men and women of our Armed Forces, particularly those deployed on operations. This is reflected in the Deployed Welfare Package, a key part of which is the safe and timely delivery of free personal mail from family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past this mechanism has been used by the general public to show their support and resulted in huge volumes of unsolicited goodwill parcels being sent, which have overwhelmed the in-theatre postal and logistics capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst unsolicited mail is well-intentioned, mail sent by families and friends is the most important to deployed personnel and is our absolute priority. Moreover, unsolicited mail strains the logistics supply and prevents mail from families getting through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason the MOD will be repeating its unsolicited mail campaign. Rather than sending their own letter or parcel, I would encourage people to make a donation to one of Britain’s excellent Service charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They might also consider &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;‘uk4u Thanks!’&lt;/a&gt; - a charity that provides Christmas gifts to deployed Service personnel. Once again I would like to say thank you to the British public, on behalf of the MOD and Armed Forces, for their incredible support of our serving personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1243/Mail2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mail for troops in places such as Afghanistan awaiting loading onto aircraft at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the charity uk4u Thanks! will, for the ninth year, deliver a Christmas Box of practical gifts and treats to every soldier, sailor and airman deployed overseas - in Afghanistan and elsewhere - and to those in hospital and recovery centres in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its parcels are delivered via the supply chain, meaning there is no impact on the mail network. Although the charity benefits from corporate sponsorship, it also needs donations from the public to continue its work bringing Christmas cheer to thousands of personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD provides a comprehensive Deployed Welfare Package which includes a free mail service for families and friends, 30 minutes of telephone calls a week and internet access, there are still areas where life in an operational theatre can be improved over and above that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and in order to enable members of the public to make a contribution to the welfare of personnel in an appropriate way, the MOD Operations Welfare Fund was established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priority for spending from the fund is set by commanders in theatre for those items which have the most impact on enhancing the morale of their personnel, and any money donated to this fund enables commanding officers on the ground to bid for items which their men and women have asked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of items purchased through the fund are Wii handsets, portable DVD players, games and table tennis tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make a donation can send a cheque to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations Welfare Fund, J1 Operation HERRICK, PJHQ, Sandy Lane, Northwood, Middlesex HA6 3HP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recommended Christmas posting date for personnel on Her Majesty’s ships is Friday 30 November 2012, and for Operation HERRICK and Operation KIPION is Monday 3 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17063</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T17:46:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/historic-signing-marks-victory-for-15-north-east-brigade"/>
    <title>Historic Signing Marks Victory for 15 (North East) Brigade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK’s largest regional brigade is the first to sign up every local authority in its area to the new Armed Forces Community Covenant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15 (North East) Brigade joined Barnsley Metropolitan Borough Council and its partners for the grand finale this week at the historic signing – just a week after thousands of people lined the town’s streets to welcome home the Light Dragoons from their tour in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Signing the covenant" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1210/signingup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Signing of the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall.
The last of the covenants to be signed in 15 Brigade (N&amp;amp;E) area. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Greville Bibby, Commander of 15 (North East) Brigade, added his signature to that of Barnsley council leader Stephen Houghton; Commander David Pickthall, Chief of Staff, Naval Regional Commander for Northern England, and RAF Squadron Leader Phil Todd, of Recruiting North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="signing-ceremony"&gt;Signing ceremony&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the signing ceremony in the town hall’s council chamber, Brig Bibby, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The signing of an Armed Forces Community Covenant by the people of Barnsley is the final ceremony that sees all local authorities in my brigade area – representing a population of 7.8 million – pledge their support for their Armed Forces’ communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Brigadier Greville Bibby." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1211/Brigadier_Bibby.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Commander 15 North East Brigade Brigadier Greville Bibby CBE singing  the Armed Forces Covenant in Barnsley town hall. Crown copyright. Corporal G. Moreno.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This achievement, along with the recent signing of the North East Armed Forces Community Charter by the Association of North East Councils, means that the people of Yorkshire, the Humber and the North East are leading the way with their support for the Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="forces-friendly"&gt;Forces friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brig Bibby added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley has always been a Forces-friendly town, with the local community supporting military personnel both past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The covenant will help cement that support at a local level and ensure that our Armed Forces, veterans and their families have the assistance they need and are treated with the dignity they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cllr Steve Houghton, Barnsley council leader, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Barnsley is delighted to add its signature to those of a growing number of local authorities across the county. The people of Barnsley have always been extremely grateful and proud of those men and women working in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our signing of the Armed Forces Community Covenant is an opportunity for us to recognise, formally, our ongoing commitment to support those involved with and leaving the Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Community Covenant was drawn up in May 2011. It is aimed at building closer ties between military families and the local community within the 11 regional brigades that span the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then just over half of the 430 local authorities that are eligible to sign have made that commitment, with 15 (North East) Brigade – the largest regional brigade in the UK - being the first to get all local authorities within its area to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60904</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:20:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:20:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"/>
    <title>Honours awarded to Brits for exceptional international achievement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list recognises outstanding work for the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FCO today announces the honours awarded on the Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list to British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The List has 99 awards to Brits or nationals of HM The Queen’s Realms in a range of fields such as for peace and security, stabilisation and development, education, science, British business and community/voluntary work plus exceptional contributions to London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some candidates are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain LOBBAN CB
Director, Government Communications Headquarters (GCHQ). For services to UK national security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain Lobban receives a KCMG.  Iain joined GCHQ in 1983 and has been the Director since 2008. He has made an outstanding personal contribution to the security of Britain and her allies bringing recognition as a world-class cyber organisation. His leadership of GCHQ has been transformational, adapting the organisation to meet the challenges of the ‘cyber age’ and moving the organisation’s focus to be at the heart of the UK’s prosperity and national interest agenda.  He has also actively promoted volunteering, outreach and charity work among his staff, raising over £100,000 for charity last year and furthering links with higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Raymond Allen DWEK
Professor of Glycobiology, Oxford University.   For services to UK/Israel scientific collaboration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Dwek receives a CBE. One of the most distinguished biochemists in the UK, he has been a major force in furthering UK/Israel scientific collaboration for over a decade. A key element of his work is promoting peace through science.  He has made significant medical advances, invested enormous time and effort in sharing the UK’s science excellence with the international community, all of which has brought many benefits for the UK and Oxford University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alison SHALABY
Chief Executive Officer, Reunite. For services to the prevention and resolution of international parental child abduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alison Shalaby receives an OBE.  A pioneer in the field of international parental child abduction, Alison is a leading global authority on the legal, social and emotional aspects on this issue and helps thousands of families around the world every year.  She has been instrumental in the development of the charity Reunite since 1992, initially as a volunteer and now as CEO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-us/what-we-do/protocol/honours/dso-list"&gt;Read the full 2013 Diplomatic Service and Overseas list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/honours"&gt;The honours system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61033</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-year-honours-for-service-personnel-and-defence-civilians"/>
    <title>New Year Honours for Service personnel and Defence civilians</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>120 UK Service personnel have been granted state honours by Her Majesty The Queen in the annual New Year Honours list.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;42 civilians have also been honoured either for work in the Ministry of Defence or in other aspects of UK Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 162 Defence personnel named in the New Year Honours list for 2013 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="royal-navy-awards"&gt;Royal Navy Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Andrew David Hugh MATHEWS &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vice Admiral Charles Anthony JOHNSTONE-BURT &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Robert LISTER &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Boyce CHARLIER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Matthew Edward PORTER &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew BETTON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nicholas Geoffrey DUNN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Nicholas John GRACE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Timothy Mark HULME &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surgeon Commander Anthony Wayne LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore Richard William MASON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore James Mark SLAWSON &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1(Abovewater Warfare Weapons) Paul Michael Stewart BARKER Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Nigel David BOND &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Christopher Paul CANNING &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Damian Andrew Giles EXWORTHY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Terence GILLARD Royal Naval Reserve (Sea Cadet Corps)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Abovewater Warfare Tactical) James Edward HALL Warfare Specialist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Thomas Maxwell Philip HENDERSON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Rodney Leslie LESTER &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Commander Brian MEADOWS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Annette Eileen PENFOLD Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 David John ROACH Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 (Air Engineering Technician) David Alun ROWLANDS &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer 1 Simon TOTTLE Royal Marines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="appointments-to-the-civil-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire"&gt;Appointments to the Civil Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commander"&gt;As Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore William Michael WALWORTH &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Fleet Auxiliary  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acting Commander Simon Roscoe COTTAM Royal Naval Reserve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="army-awards"&gt;Army Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-1"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander-1"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant General James Jeffrey Corfield BUCKNALL &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions-1"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Shaun Alex BURLEY &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Ian Martin COPELAND late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major General Gregory Stephen SMITH QVRM &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; DL late The Royal Green Jackets Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-1"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders-1"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Gareth Paul COLLETT late The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Peter Andrew FOX late Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Edward Oliver FORSTER–KNIGHT &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Adjutant General’s Corps (Royal Military Police&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier John Craig LAWRENCE &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late The Royal Gurkha Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers-1"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Barry William BENNETT &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Ian Miles COMERFORD Corps of Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robert James HEALEY Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Garry HEARN late Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Peter Michael LITTLE The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Nicholas Charles Tristram MILLEN late The Royal Dragoon Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Timothy Marc Piers MOUNTFORD Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Robin Charles SMITH The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Roger John Nathaniel STEWART late Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Simon Philip STOCKLEY Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Neil UNSWORTH The Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Murray Courtenay WHITESIDE &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; late Army Air Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members-1"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Christopher Charles ATTRILL The Royal Irish Regiment Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kenneth Harry BAKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Joanna Jane BRAIN Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bombardier Alexander Robert BUCHANAN Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 Robert James COLLINS The Parachute Regiment &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Jonathan DEANS Adjutant General’s Corps (Educational and Training Services Branch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Leigh James DRUMMOND The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Paul John EDWARDS The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Alastair Neil FIELD The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Darren John FISHER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal (Acting Sergeant) Terry John FITZGERALD Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James FLETCHER Intelligence Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 James Alexander FORD Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch) Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Christopher James FULLER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Frederick William GREENHOW Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Rowena Charlotte GRIFFITHS Adjutant General’s Corps (Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Charles Edward Digby GRIST The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Barry HEAP Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Cameron Arthur HILL The Royal Logistic Corps Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Steven Robin HOOK The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 2 Leslie John HUNT Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Christian Glyndwr LAMB The Rifles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain (Acting Major) Guy William John LOCK Coldstream Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Matthew John Frederick MIDDLEDITCH QGM The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Stephen John MORGAN Royal Corps of Signals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Stuart Andrew NASH Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Andrew James PARKER The Royal Logistic Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Bombardier Benjamin James PARKINSON Royal Regiment of Artillery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Hemchandra &lt;abbr title="Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland"&gt;RAI&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; Adjutant General’s Corps (Gurkha Staff and Personnel Support Branch)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Fabian Andrew David Lechmere ROBERTS &lt;abbr title="Member of the Royal Victorian Order"&gt;MVO&lt;/abbr&gt; Irish Guards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Brian Mackenzie ROSS The Royal Regiment of Scotland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Robert SADLER Royal Mercian and Lancastrian Yeomanry Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Andrew James SANGER Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mathew Timothy James SHORT Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martyn Jonathan THOMPSON Royal Army Veterinary Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Mark Lloyd WELHAM The Royal Welsh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Nicholas Simon WILSON The Yorkshire Regiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Kevin YOUNG Royal Regiment of Artillery Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-1"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major (Local Lieutenant Colonel) Stephen Wyatt BARTLETT &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; The Rifles Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Simon Michael John BELL &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; late The Cheshire Regiment Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Philip Guy DAVIS Corps of Royal Engineers Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaplain to the Forces 3rd Class Reverend Louis KINSEY &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt; Royal Army Chaplains’ Department Territorial Army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Sonja McCOY Royal Corps of Signals Territorial Army &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="royal-air-force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-honourable-order-of-the-bath-2"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Honourable Order Of The Bath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-knight-commander-2"&gt;As Knight Commander&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Timothy Michael ANDERSON &lt;abbr title="Companion of the Most Honourable Order of the Bath"&gt;CB&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Distinguished Service Order"&gt;DSO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Marshal Andrew Douglas PULFORD &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-companions-2"&gt;As Companions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Raymond Jackson PENTLAND&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Vice-Marshal Julian Alexander YOUNG &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="promotions-in-and-appointments-to-the-military-division-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-2"&gt;Promotions in and appointments to the Military Division of the Most Excellent Order Of The British Empire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-commanders-2"&gt;As Commanders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Nigel Philip BEET &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Commodore Margaret Elaine WEST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Domonic Anthony STAMP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-officers-2"&gt;As Officers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick Alexander BOUNDY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Roderick John DENNIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Christopher John FISHER &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Volunteer Reserve (Training)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain James Cameron McGregor JOHNSTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Michael Dawson LAVENDER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Justine Elizabeth MORTON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wing Commander Stephen Michael Robert WARD &lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="as-members-2"&gt;As Members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Timothy Alexander BARLOW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician David Jeremy BRIGGS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Benjamin John CLARK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Benjamin David CROSSLEY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Glynis Mary DEAN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Kevin John Patrick FOXWELL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Phillip Leslie JONES&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Tal Thomas Adam LAMBERT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Martin Alan PURVIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Simon Edward READE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Derek Charles SMITH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Technician Barry John STRINGER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Paul WHEABLE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer David John WOODHEAD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Sergeant Dale Edward Spencer WOOLMAN-LANE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="queens-volunteer-reserves-medal-2"&gt;Queen’s Volunteer Reserves Medal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Maureen KENDALL Royal Auxiliary Air Force&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="civilians-in-defence"&gt;Civilians in defence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="knight-bachelor-kt"&gt;Knight Bachelor (&lt;abbr title="Knight Bachelor"&gt;Kt&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Hew Francis Anthony Strachan
For services to the Ministry of Defence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="commanders-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-cbe"&gt;Commanders of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Michael Thomas COCHRANE
For services to Health&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="officers-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-obe"&gt;Officers of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Officer of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Anthea DOLMAN GAIR
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Diana DONOVAN
For voluntary service to The Gurkha Welfare Trust&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James HEPBURN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher HURRAN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vincent MIFSUD, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For services to Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Charles PENLINGTON
Ministry of Defence, Gloucestershire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cynthia Kit Man SHAW
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Sylvia Nina QUAYLE, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="members-of-the-most-excellent-order-of-the-british-empire-mbe"&gt;Members of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (&lt;abbr title="Member of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Ann Elizabeth CABLE
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Andrew CAMBRIDGE
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Gail CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Stamford James CARTWRIGHT, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to the West Midland Reserve Forces &amp;amp; Cadets Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horace MacDonald CROSS
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Barrie DAVIES
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm DYER
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy JOBSON
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Graham John LAWRENCE
Ministry of Defence, Andover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Albert MABEY
For voluntary service to the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel John Robert MacKENZIE, &lt;abbr title="Territorial Decoration"&gt;TD&lt;/abbr&gt;
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel MAIN
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Rachel McLAUGHLIN
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Rossiter NEWSOME, JP
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher PAGE
Ministry of Defence, Yeovil&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken PAYNE
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry PITCHFORTH
For services to the Defence Industry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Mary Elizabeth PLUME
Ministry of Defence, London&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David REES
For services to Defence Capability &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William John SCOTT
For voluntary service in the Air Training Corps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miss Hannah SEAKINS
Ministry of Defence, Hitchin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John UNDERHILL
For voluntary service to the Royal British Legion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-british-empire-medal-bem"&gt;The British Empire Medal (&lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Arnold BURCHELL
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Janet Stewart CAMPBELL
For voluntary service to the British Red Cross Society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Paulin CLINTON
For services to Veterans Aid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian CLOUGH
Ministry of Defence, Mid Glamorgan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Ellis GRINNALL
Ministry of Defence, Monmouthshire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Carole Jean HILLMAN
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter William SKELLON
For voluntary service to the &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Association&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs Jean SLATER
For voluntary service to St John Ambulance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel Alan Ronald TAPP
For voluntary service to &lt;abbr title="Soldiers, Sailors, Airmen and Families Association"&gt;SSAFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces Help&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60888</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-years-honours-2013"/>
    <title>New Year's Honours 2013</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham congratulates all those recognised in the New Year Honours.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to all those working in the local government, housing, fire and voluntary and community sector who have been recognised in the New Year Honours list which acknowledges their extraordinary contribution to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to see colleagues in local government being honoured. It’s testament to their services to the local community that their hard work, dedication and achievements have been recognised in this way. Many congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-government"&gt;Local government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the local government sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Jones, Leader of East Sussex County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in the South East&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Tapster, lately Chief Executive of Hertfordshire County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ian Greenwood, lately Leader of Bradford City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Kelly, lately Chief Executive of Gateshead Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government and the community in Gateshead and the North East &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharon Taylor, Leader of Stevenage Borough Council and Deputy Chair of the Local Government Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jane Todd, Chief Executive of Nottingham City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Nottingham &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clare Whelan, Member, London Borough of Lambeth receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brian Beale, Councillor in Southminster receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linda Green, Member, Gateshead Metropolitan Borough Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tyne &amp;amp; Wear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raymond Puddifoot, Leader of Hillingdon Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Hillingdon, Middlesex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katherine Gilcreest, Anti-Social Behaviour Manager, Brentwood Borough Council receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Brentwood, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="housing"&gt;Housing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the housing sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthony Pidgeley, Chairman of the Berkeley Group receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the housing sector and the community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Ruback, Deputy Director, Housing Revenue Account and Decent Homes Programe, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sue Chalkley, Chief Executive of the Hastoe Housing Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to housing and tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Downie, Deputy Director, Affordable Housing Management and Standards, Department for Communities and Local Government receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="fire-and-rescue"&gt;Fire and rescue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the fire and rescue sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Beardsall, Retained Watch Manager in Charge, Nottinghamshire and City of Nottingham Fire and Rescue Authority receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Mottram, Equipment Officer, South Yorkshire Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Richard Stanton, firefighter in West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Cole, Retained Firefighter, Isle of Wight receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the communities of Shanklin and the Isle of Wight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Boulton, Senior Adviser to the Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glynis Lomax, Head of the Operational Intelligence Unit receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gary Reason, Director of Operational Resilience and Training for services to the Olympics receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colin Rockey, Group Manager, Devon and Somerset Fire and Rescue Service receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="voluntary-and-community-sector"&gt;Voluntary and community sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the voluntary and community sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herschel Gluck, founder of the Muslim Jewish Forum receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to interfaith understanding &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Denys Shortt, founder of DCS Europe PLC and Chair, Coventry and Warwickshire Local Enterprise Partnership receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the economy in the West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruth Abrahams receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the voluntary and community sector in Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margaret Barker, founder of the Dorset Poverty Action Group receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to homeless and underprivileged people in Dorchester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Barker receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community of the Mixenden Social Housing Estate, Halifax &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Blower receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement in Fleetwood &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anita Halliday, Chief Executive of St Pauls Community Development Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Balsall Heath, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Highton, founder of the Brian Shields Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to personal finance and community support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mary Jones receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenants and the community in Saffron and Neston, Leicester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter McNestry, Chair of the Coalfields Regeneration Trust, Waith upon Dearne, Rotherham, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to coalfield communities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggarwal-Singh Neelam receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to community cohesion, health and welfare through the Indian Hindu Welfare Organisation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gerry Proctor receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Liverpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emdadur Rahman, journalist and community volunteer, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tower Hamlets and to the Bangladeshi Media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Sheehy receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Ahern, Chair of the Templar’s Estate Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment in Witham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eileen Alldritt receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment and the community in Liverpool &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christine Allen, Chief Executive of the Forum Housing Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Merseyside &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rose Cooke-Coton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Masefield, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heather Didwell, volunteer at Catton Grove Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John Filby receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Abridge, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Muriel Healey, board member, Havebury Housing Partnership receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to Tenants in Suffolk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Highton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in West Ealing, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asim Iftikhar receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Poplar &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Betty Koppa receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community and residents of North Curry, Taunton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shaun Lansfield receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement and to the community in Edmonton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jacqueline McGrew, Chair of the Whitebirk Tenants and Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Blackburn, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew Milnes, founder of the Scholemoor Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Bradford&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Riaz Ravat, Development Manager, St Philip’s Centre, Leicester receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to inter-faith understanding in Leicester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Smith receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Leyland, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60903</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T19:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T19:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/general-normal-schwarzkopf-tribute"/>
    <title>General Norman Schwarzkopf tribute </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Chief of the Defence Staff has paid tribute to the retired US General Norman Schwarzkopf, who died yesterday, 27 December 2012, aged 78.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Schwarzkopf was commander of coalition forces in the first Gulf War from 1990-91.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, &lt;a href="/government/people/david-richards" title="General Sir David Richards"&gt;General Sir David Richards&lt;/a&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General Norman Schwarzkopf’s command in the Gulf was an example of the finest qualities of American leadership: decisive, inclusive and measured. At the head of a coalition of forces from around the world, including many from the region, he played a pivotal role in the liberation of Kuwait. The operation was not only a UN act but marked the transition from a Cold War doctrine of dissuasion and balance to a new world where force could be used for good. As its first practitioner General Schwarzkopf accomplished what so few can: he shaped his times. He was the first of what are now many US generals to lead British forces in this kind of conflict, rather than in Cold War stasis of the previous decades. For that, and his inspirational command in war, he will be remembered on this side of the Atlantic with respect. The Anglo-American alliance has gone from strength to strength since his time, but it started with him. My thoughts are with his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16790</id>
    <published>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-28T17:55:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-illustrious-visits-malta"/>
    <title>HMS Illustrious visits Malta</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>HMS Illustrious has arrived at the Mediterranean island of Malta for a five-day visit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 1,500 sailors and marines lined the deck of the Portsmouth-based helicopter carrier as she entered the port of Valletta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an onboard reception for the Earl and Countess of Wessex, the ship will be holding an affiliation event for representatives from the Maltese cities of Senglea, Vittoriosa and L’Isla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helicopter carrier is twinned with the three cities due to a previous HMS Illustrious which was bombed during the Second World War and underwent extensive repair at the Grand Harbour in Malta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Martin Connell, Commanding Officer of HMS Illustrious, said it was a proud moment for him to be sailing HMS Illustrious into Valletta. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very much aware of not just the history of this ship but also the previous Illustrious and what the people of Malta did to help save her in 1941.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1157/IL120467045.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sailors line the deck of HMS Illustrious as she enters the port of Valletta [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.gov.mt/" title="Government of Malta"&gt;Maltese Government&lt;/a&gt; also allowed the Grand Harbour in Valletta to be used for berthing by HMS Cumberland and HMS York following their evacuation of British nationals from Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time in Grand Harbour, sailors and marines from HMS Illustrious will be helping out with a variety of worthy causes including a clean-up of outdoor spaces in collaboration with the Nature Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the week &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;HMS Illustrious&lt;/a&gt; will be joined by the Royal Navy fleet flagship, HMS Bulwark, and Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship Mounts Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Illustrious is part of the Cougar 12 deployment - a three-month work-up of the Royal Navy’s Response Force Task Group (RFTG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1158/IL120467008.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Illustrious enters Malta's Grand Harbour [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Ray Jones, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deployment is a test of the RFTG’s capability should it be called into action at short notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The force is designed to respond to rapidly unfolding world events - the last time being Libya in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of Cougar 12, the ships have been working with Royal Marines commando units and the Fleet Air Arm to put their amphibious capability to the test - the power to transfer marines from ships onto the beaches of hostile nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as exercising the 3,000 British sailors, marines and airmen, the task force has worked alongside French and Albanian forces to ensure the nations could co-operate on a military level in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-news"&gt;Related News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/BritishAndAlbanianNaviesWorkTogetherInTheAdriatic.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;British and Albanian navies work together in the Adriatic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/HmsIllustriousTrainsWithFrenchNavy.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious trains with French Navy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/EquipmentAndLogistics/HmsIllustriousReturnsToPortsmouthAfterUpgrade.htm" title="Read full story"&gt;HMS Illustrious returns to Portsmouth after upgrade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
