<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T00:55:52+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/4030</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:55:52+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:55:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/army-and-navy-bomb-specialists-tackle-v2-rocket"/>
    <title>Army and Navy bomb specialists tackle V2 rocket</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 4-foot-long (1.2-metre) section of the German Second World War missile was pulled from mudflats at low tide on the River Stour between Harwich and Felixstowe on Saturday, 31 March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6-man Navy team from &lt;a href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport/Southern-Diving-Group%20Southern%20Diving%20Group%20(SDG)"&gt;Southern Diving Unit 2&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="Southern Diving Unit 2"&gt;SDU 2&lt;/abbr&gt;) in &lt;a href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth%20Portsmouth%20Naval%20Base"&gt;Portsmouth&lt;/a&gt; worked with the &lt;a href="http://www.army.mod.uk/%20British%20Army"&gt;British Army&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="http://www.army.mod.uk/royalengineers/units/852.aspx%20101%20(City%20of%20London)%20Engineer%20Regiment%20(Explosive%20Ordnance%20Disposal)"&gt;101 Engineer Regiment&lt;/a&gt; bomb disposal team to lift the section of weapon from the mud onto a barge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had first excavated around the lowest part of the V2 to discover that the warhead section was not there - meaning there was no safety risk to the local population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Venturi section of the rocket, named after a scientific reaction that happens when fluid passes through a narrow pipe, could now be donated to the nearby sailing club who have passed it in the mud for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Servicemen retrieving the V2 rocket section" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/864/FN120004_14.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British servicemen at work retrieving the V2 rocket section at Harwich [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Gaz Armes, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Dan Herridge, Officer-in-Command of &lt;abbr title="Southern Diving Unit 2"&gt;SDU 2&lt;/abbr&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was a successful result to the operation and means people using the waterways and living locally can have confidence that this was not a dangerous piece of ordnance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are grateful for the support of our colleagues from 101 Engineer Regiment for helping remove this section of the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first the Royal Navy team was sceptical it was a V2 rocket because the missiles plunged to earth at more than twice the speed of sound having reached heights of up to 128 miles (206 kilometres) above the earth’s surface – so normally there was nothing left of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On closer inspection the rocket was indeed identified as a V2. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The retrieved Venturi section of the V2 rocket" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/865/FN120004_15.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The retrieved Venturi section of the V2 rocket [Picture: Petty Officer Airman (Photographer) Gaz Armes, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rocket was submerged nose down and was projecting about 2 feet (60 centimetres) out of the mud, around 300 feet (90 metres) from the Harwich shoreline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V2 rocket was developed by pioneering scientist Werner von Braun - who went on to be a key figure behind the American effort to put a man on the moon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Built by concentration camp prisoners, more than 3,000 V2s were launched from the continent at London, south-east England and the Belgian port of Antwerp - with the aim of demoralising the civilian populace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The missile attacks resulted in the death of an estimated 7,250 people, mostly civilians. Of these, more than 2,750 were killed in London - and another 6,523 injured. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16964</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:50:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:50:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1st-royal-tank-regiment-takes-part-in-homecoming-parade-in-glasgow"/>
    <title>1st Royal Tank Regiment takes part in homecoming parade in Glasgow</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The soldiers of D Squadron took part in the homecoming parade in Glasgow on Saturday 24 November 2012 to mark their recent return from operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1 RTR&lt;/abbr&gt; deployed to Afghanistan throughout 2012 and took on a variety of roles during the deployments. The Regimental Headquarters filled a number of positions throughout Helmand province, from support roles in Camp Bastion to key staff roles in the Brigade Headquarters. Other roles included training the Afghan Local Police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1 RTR&lt;/abbr&gt;, Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Britton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am extremely proud of what the regiment achieved in Afghanistan. The soldiers make many sacrifices to fulfil their role, and recognition of that by those at home is deeply appreciated. It means a great deal to the soldiers and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glasgow’s Lord Provost, Sadie Docherty, in her capacity as Lord-Lieutenant, took the salute at the parade in George Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the honours I have as Lord-Lieutenant is taking the salute at homecoming parades. It is always a privilege to welcome our brave men and women serving in conflicts across the globe. I am delighted that all of D Squadron have made it home safe and sound in time for Christmas with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/armoured/regiments/26877.aspx" title="1st Royal Tank Regiment"&gt;1st Royal Tank Regiment&lt;/a&gt;  is based at RAF Honington in Suffolk and recruits from Scotland and the North West of England. The majority of soldiers come from Liverpool and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48079</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T19:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa hails Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’ following successful elections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the National Electoral Committee announced the Presidential election results, Mark Simmonds said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I congratulate John Dramani Mahama on his election as President of Ghana and on elections that were widely recognised to be free, fair and transparent. Ghana has now seen six successful elections since military government ended in 1992 and it is rightly seen as a beacon of democracy in the region. I commend the Ghanaian people, political parties and civil society on the peaceful environment in which the elections were held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The relationship between the UK and Ghana is strong and vibrant. It is rooted in our long-standing economic, political and cultural connections, our shared values, and the deep links between our peoples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to continuing a constructive and productive working relationship with President Mahama and his government, one that continues to bring our countries closer together.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18772</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-the-overseas-territories-and-overseas-territory-leaders-issue-joint-communique-following-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Minister for the Overseas Territories and Overseas Territory leaders issue joint communiqué following Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council, chaired by Minister Simmonds and attended by Premiers, Chief Ministers and other elected representatives from Britain’s Overseas Territories, closed today with the agreement of a joint communiqué which sets out priority issues and a comprehensive action plan for joint work in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the second day of the Council also saw the Prime Minister welcome Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said in his foreword in the White Paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom’s 14 Overseas Territories are an integral part of Britain’s life and history. This Government is ambitious for our Territories as we are ambitious for the United Kingdom.  We want to see our communities flourish in partnership, with strong and sustainable local economies. We see an important opportunity to set world standards in our stewardship of the extraordinary natural environments we have inherited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out a very positive vision for the Overseas Territories. This first meeting of the Joint Ministerial Council has helped us identify an ambitious list of priority areas for action, such as encouraging economic growth; protecting the environment and making government work better. We will work closely with the Territories in the coming year to achieve what we have together set out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of my Ministerial colleagues from across Government took part in the Council this week, demonstrating that the UK Government as a whole is committed to supporting the Territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17781</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:41:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-simmonds-visits-africa-to-support-efforts-to-end-crisis-in-goma"/>
    <title>Mark Simmonds visits Africa to support efforts to end crisis in Goma</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Simmonds will first visit Uganda and then travel on to Rwanda and the Democratic Republic of Congo. During his trip, he will meet regional leaders to discuss the political work underway to resolve the crisis and the humanitarian situation. He will urge leaders to use any influence they have to bring an end to the crisis and limit its impact on civilian populations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am travelling to the region at short notice to show that the UK is focused on the serious and urgent crisis unfolding in Goma and to show my support to the people of the DRC. I am deeply concerned by the current crisis and I urge the M23 militia to stop their offensive and for all external support to the M23 militia to stop.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“On my visit I will be meeting with government ministers from across the region and will ask them all to find, first and foremost, a resolution that will swiftly end the fighting and produce a sustainable long term plan that will ensure peace and stability for the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/44286</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/skiiers-avoid-injury-and-expensive-medical-bills"/>
    <title>Skiers: avoid injury and expensive medical bills</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are launching a campaign aimed at Britons visiting European winter sports resorts this winter to explain the dangers of attempting slopes beyond your level of ability, or going off piste without the correct safety equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re heading off a ski or snowboarding holiday this winter, please don’t put yourself at risk by trying to keep up with more experienced members of your party. The number of reported accidents on French slopes in 2012 was high, including seven deaths out of 12 serious incidents*. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="research"&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to new research from the FCO**, of those British nationals that go on winter sports holidays the majority class themselves as beginner or intermediate. Only 1% of respondents classed themselves as expert. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly two thirds (65%) of winter sports travellers admitted they would ski or snowboard on slopes above their experience in order to stay with a group. More than half (53%) also said they would follow a group of mates off piste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventy per cent admitted they do not always wear a helmet when skiing or snowboarding, and one in five (21%) said they wouldn’t wear a helmet if others in their group weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor, Consul, based in Marseille, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last year we saw a high number of British nationals end up in hospital with serious injuries. Sadly this included a number of deaths. Many of these accidents can be prevented by taking simple precautionary steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of assuming you’ll be fine if you’re with more experienced skiers or snowboarders. It is significant that a large number of cases we have dealt with have involved off piste skiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those lucky enough to survive an accident and end up in hospital can face months of recovery, so it is important to think carefully beforehand about the very real risks out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="insurance"&gt;Insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third (38%) of winter sports holidaymakers admitted that they don’t always take out travel insurance. One in three (31%) also said they don’t always check their policy to ensure they are covered for winter sports activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Taylor continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many people will be unaware that failing to wear a helmet or skiing off piste can invalidate some insurance policies, so if something does go wrong you could end up with hefty medical bills. In many cases family members then have to help with funds which can put a huge strain on families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The FCO cannot pay for hospital treatment or for medical repatriation back to the UK, which is why it is so important to check your insurance covers you for everything you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="top-tips-to-stay-safe-on-the-slopes"&gt;Top tips to stay safe on the slopes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take out insurance – and check what it covers. It might not cover off piste skiing unless you are with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a check-up before you ski - one of the major causes of hospitalisation and death on the slopes is heart attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t drink and ski. Alcohol can affect you more quickly at high altitudes and dangerously limits your awareness of risk and cold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most skiing injuries are caused by collisions with other skiers – watch your speed and distance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t attempt slopes you’re not experienced or fit enough to tackle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to go off piste, go with a qualified guide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If going off piste carry a shovel, a probe and a transceiver in case of an avalanche. Also remember that you need proper training on how to use a transceiver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are going out on a glacier, you must wear a harness. If you fall into a crevasse, this will help the rescue team get you out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure someone knows where you’re going and tell them of any changes to your plans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only go off piste skiing or climbing with someone you have met previously and can trust. You need to know his/her capabilities, what you’ll be doing and where.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For further tips and advice on preparing for travel abroad, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.fco.gov.uk/travel" title="FCO Travel Advice"&gt;www.fco.gov.uk/travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Figures taken from FCO 2011/12 consular assistance data &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Survey conducted by ICM. Total sample size was 2,023 UK adults aged 18 and over. Fieldwork was undertaken in November 2012. The figures have been weighted and are representative of all UK adults aged 18 and over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43707</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-2-billion-contract-awarded-for-new-attack-submarine"/>
    <title>£1.2 billion contract awarded for new attack submarine</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Audacious" title="Audacious"&gt;Audacious&lt;/a&gt; is the fourth of 7 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class" title="Astute Class"&gt;Astute Class&lt;/a&gt;  submarines being built for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt;. They are the most technologically-advanced the Royal Navy has ever sent to sea and offer a step-change in capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.www.baesystems.com/" title="BAE Systems"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; will safeguard 3,000 skilled jobs at Barrow-in-Furness in Cumbria and represents a significant step forward in the Astute submarine programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 2 boats, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/HMS-Astute" title="HMS Astute"&gt;Astute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Ambush" title="Ambush"&gt;Ambush&lt;/a&gt;, are currently undergoing sea trials to rigorously test their systems. Astute has conducted deep dive trials and successfully fired Tomahawk land attack missiles and Spearfish torpedoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambush’s ability to dive and surface has been successfully tested, as has her propulsion system, and the third boat, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Artful" title="Artful"&gt;Artful&lt;/a&gt;, is reaching the final stages of her construction at Barrow shipyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD can also confirm today that a further £1.5 billion has been committed to the remaining 3 submarines in the class. This has enabled early build work to start on the next boat (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Astute-Class/Anson" title="Anson"&gt;Anson&lt;/a&gt;) and long lead items to be ordered and bought for the as yet unnamed boats six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This £1.2 billion contract marks an important step forward in the progress of the Astute programme and moves the Royal Navy closer to adding more of these highly advanced and powerful attack submarines to its fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce today that the MOD is committing more than £1.5 billion for boats five, six and seven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Astute " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1735/45150807.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Astute sails up the Clyde estuary (library image) [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) J J Massey, Crown Copyright/MOD 2009]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding demonstrates our commitment not only to a key Royal Navy capability but also to the submarine industry in Barrow which will play a vital role in Astute for decades to come. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rear Admiral Simon Lister, MOD’s Director of Submarines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Astute Class will become the jewel in the crown of the Royal Navy’s Submarine Service and boasts much greater firepower and more advanced sonar and communications than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These submarines represent a huge leap forward in technology and will operate all over the world with the Royal Navy. These boats provide the optimum capability a submarine can offer in land strike, strategic intelligence-gathering, anti-submarine and surface ship warfare, and protection of the strategic deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Featuring the latest nuclear-powered technology, the Astute Class never need to be refuelled and can circumnavigate the world submerged, manufacturing the crew’s oxygen from seawater as they go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 7,400-tonne Astute Class are quieter than older submarines, and can operate covertly and remain undetected despite being 50% bigger than the Royal Navy’s current &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class" title="Trafalgar Class"&gt;Trafalgar Class&lt;/a&gt; submarines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43718</id>
    <published>2011-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-life-of-an-army-doctor-on-the-front-line"/>
    <title>The life of an Army doctor on the front line</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Captain Christopher Stewart these challenges are even more wide-ranging as he is currently serving on his first deployment to Afghanistan, based at a patrol base in the Nad ‘Ali area of Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a doctor with the British Army’s 16 Medical Regiment, Captain Stewart operates out of his tented medical facility within the patrol base, with his primary role focusing on the health needs of the soldiers, ensuring they are ‘fighting fit’ and operationally-effective at all times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Stewart is living and working at the base alongside troops from 1st Battalion The Royal Irish Regiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the winter weather has gripped the UK, Afghanistan has not escaped from the chill with temperatures at night dropping below zero; a sharp contrast to the scorching heat of the midday sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the extreme weather changes, a substantial proportion of the Medical Officer’s job is ensuring preventative measures are in place to safeguard against injuries from operating in such conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both frostbite and heat stroke can be witnessed in the same 24-hour period due to the wide variations in temperature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, troops are also fighting regular battles with the enemy. This means for Captain Stewart that, in addition to treating common and minor ailments, his medical facility is constantly on high readiness to receive trauma casualties resulting from roadside bombs, blasts and gunshot wounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients with serious wounds are stabilised in the medical facility by a doctor and a combat medical technician, capable of providing life-saving interventions, before being evacuated by helicopter to Camp Bastion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as providing medical care for sick and injured soldiers, British Army doctors also treat Afghan locals requiring emergency care for limb or eyesight related injuries. In the course of his time in Helmand Captain Stewart has treated a number of Afghan children and adults who have suffered injuries as a result of insurgent attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first week in Afghanistan Captain Stewart was involved along with colleagues in treating an eight-year-old girl wounded by an insurgent bullet whilst she was working in her father’s wheat field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girl was carried to the front gate of the patrol base by her uncle before being rushed to the medical centre for assessment. After emergency treatment and painkillers were provided, the girl was evacuated for further surgical treatment at Camp Bastion where the bullet was subsequently removed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, he treated a young boy who suffered an allergic reaction after being stung by a hornet, administering emergency drugs and painkillers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Stewart said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are always on standby and never know when to expect the next casualty. It is a rewarding job to be able to provide medical care both for the British troops and emergency care for Afghan locals caught up in the fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as helping local communities by providing such emergency medical treatment, Captain Stewart and his colleagues are also involved with outreach work. Recently, a health workshop was run at a patrol base in the village of Kushal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local community health and education workers from across the area were contacted and invited to the event to share their knowledge and experiences and receive advice and guidance on best practice from each other as well as the British Army’s medical experts. A manual, written in the local Dari and Pashto languages, was distributed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Stewart's colleague Major Nicola Macleod runs a health workshop for local Afghans in the village of Kushal in Helmand province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1762/The_life_of_an_Army_doctor_on_the_front_line2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Stewart's colleague Major Nicola Macleod runs a health workshop for local Afghans in the village of Kushal in Helmand province [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Stewart said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was very interesting to share our experiences of healthcare systems with the Afghan locals. They have very similar health concerns to those seen in the UK, such as how to care for a sick child, managing common ailments, and pregnancy care. In addition though, health workers in Afghanistan commonly deal with malaria and other tropical diseases which are less common for us. It was a great learning opportunity for both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the workshop, the locals, equipped with their new teaching materials, returned to their villages. The following week, the headmaster at Kushal Kalay school educated some 250 pupils, while other health workers held learning sessions in their local mosques. It was a great result and is already benefiting the local population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another effort to improve the health of local people, Captain Stewart has also engaged with a local pharmacist in the same area. He explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He was only too happy to open his shop and allow my colleagues and I to have a look around. We enquired about the health services available in the area and about the health problems he sees on a daily basis.
&amp;gt; “I was pleased to see that the pharmacist had one of the teaching books that we had previously issued and he told us about how he had been using it to educate his customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further improve healthcare provision on the front line, medical skills have been taught to soldiers of the Afghan National Army (ANA) who work alongside British troops to improve security in Afghanistan. The ANA are very receptive to medical teaching and are particularly keen to learn trauma skills and their application on the battlefield. Captain Stewart has also been involved with these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43712</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prince-of-wales-welcomes-homes-welsh-guards-from-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prince of Wales welcomes homes Welsh Guards from Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.princeofwales.gov.uk/" title="The Prince of Wales"&gt;The Prince of Wales&lt;/a&gt;, who is Colonel of the Welsh Guards, visited the battalion at Cavalry Barracks in Hounslow to present Operational Service Medals and meet battalion members and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some 350 members of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/10757.aspx" title="1st Battalion Welsh Guards"&gt;1st Battalion Welsh Guards&lt;/a&gt; lined up on parade to be greeted by their Colonel, who welcomed them home and congratulated them on their achievements on Operation HERRICK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battalion served in Afghanistan from March to October 2012, carrying out a range of duties in various locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, the Prince also presented Elizabeth Crosses in a private ceremony to the families of those killed in Afghanistan. Tragically, 3 members of the battalion were killed in action, as well as 2 attached personnel, one of them from the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanking the Prince for his close interest in the battalion and taking the time to visit them, Commanding Officer Lieutenant Colonel Dino Bossi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1746/LOND-2012-244-127.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales welcomes home members of the 1st Battalion Welsh Guards from their recent tour of Afghanistan [Picture: Sergeant Adrian Harlen, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are enormously pleased and proud to have our Colonel, His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales, with us today to present the hard-won Afghanistan medals to the battalion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are very fortunate to maintain such close links with His Royal Highness and grateful for the support and assistance he was able to give us while we were away, especially his care and attention towards our bereaved families and those of us who were wounded in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is a fitting culmination to our HERRICK 16 experience and one that will be remembered by the battalion and our families for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Thursday’s medal parade followed a ‘welcome home’ reception 2 days before when, following a march through Hounslow, the battalion was hosted by the London Borough of Hounslow, led by the Leader of the Council, Councillor Jagdish Sharma. The battalion has also recently exercised their Freedom of Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43713</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/in-pictures-armed-forces-day-celebrated-across-the-uk"/>
    <title>IN PICTURES: Armed Forces Day celebrated across the UK</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Edinburgh was the official host city, other events took place up and down the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Birmingham, crowds gathered in Victoria Square and around Paradise Forum on Saturday morning as a private ceremony was held at the Hall of Memory, Centenary Square, to honour Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Manchester, the Lord Mayor, Harry Lyons, inspected parades in front of more than 1,000 spectators - including serving personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic way for the city to thank everyone who has served our country and all those who continue to do so. Armed Forces Day reminds us of the gratitude we owe all servicemen and women past and present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in Liverpool, a service held at the Anglican Cathedral was followed by a march from the cathedral down Hope Street, to an enthusiastic reception by watching members of the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales takes the salute as troops march past at the Armed Forces Day national event in Edinburgh " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1755/IN_PICTURES_Armed_Forces_Day_celebrated_across_the_UK2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales takes the salute as troops march past at the Armed Forces Day national event in Edinburgh [Picture: LA(Phot) Sally Stimpson, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The march, led by the Band of the Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment, was made up of serving military personnel, along with veterans, the Merchant Navy, and cadets from the Merseyside Army Cadet Force and the Merseyside Wing of the Air Training Corps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Cardiff, well-wishers braved the rain to cheer on the troops. The event in Cardiff saw crowds clapping and cheering as serving troops, veterans, cadets and volunteers proudly marched from Cardiff Castle and made their way down St Mary Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the national event in Edinburgh, the Prince of Wales and the Duchess of Cornwall watched a parade of 2,500 veterans, cadets and serving members of the Armed Forces, before meeting veterans and families of those who have served in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Plymouth, the day was marked on the Hoe with a marching band and exhibitions and displays on land, sea and air. At the event Armed Forces Minister Nick Harvey also announced that Plymouth is to host the fourth UK Armed Forces Day on 30 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Harvey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Armed Forces day is coming home and it’s richly deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The warmth and hospitality the city has shown our Armed Forces, our veterans, cadets and their families over the years has been outstanding, and truly demonstrates the historic link between the military and the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is clear from previous Armed Forces Day celebrations held in Plymouth that the city is well placed to host the national event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Council leader Vivien Pengelly said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a real honour for the city and testament to the overwhelming public support shown for Plymouth’s servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Plans will now be getting under way to stage our biggest Armed Forces Week yet and do the city’s Armed Forces Community proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43845</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-lancs-are-first-of-500-homecoming-troops"/>
    <title>1 LANCS are first of 500 homecoming troops</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The soldiers of Burma Company of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/14818.aspx" title="1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;1 LANCS&lt;/abbr&gt;) are the first of 500 Service personnel to come home as security in their area of Helmand province is handed over to Afghan forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have returned to their barracks at Catterick Garrison, North Yorkshire, following the closure of their patrol base in Lashkar Gah and the Afghan Uniform Police (&lt;abbr title="Afghan Uniform Police"&gt;AUP&lt;/abbr&gt;) taking responsibility for security in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;1 LANCS&lt;/abbr&gt; are part of Task Force Helmand, currently led by the British Army’s 4th Mechanized Brigade, known as ‘The Black Rats’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The troops were based at Patrol Base Nahidullah in the Lashkar Gah district of Helmand province as part of an Adviser Team Enabling Company (&lt;abbr title="Adviser Team Enabling Company"&gt;ATEC&lt;/abbr&gt;) supporting the 8th Precinct of the &lt;abbr title="Afghan Uniform Police"&gt;AUP&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their role was to advise, train and support the police to bring security and stability to the region, but that job is now complete. Nahidullah is the first base of its size to have been closed down in Task Force Helmand’s area of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander of 4th Mechanized Brigade, Brigadier Bob Bruce, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In terms of the campaign this is the most obvious example of progress during our tour so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The important thing has been enabling the Afghans to take a firm hand on the security situation in this area allowing the Task Force to close Nahidullah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Kingsman Carl Day " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1796/AMOCCCT-2012-245-124.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kingsman Carl Day checks his baggage in for his flight back to the UK [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Ed Fraser, the Officer Commanding Burma Company in charge of the &lt;abbr title="Adviser Team Enabling Company"&gt;ATEC&lt;/abbr&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This area was hard fought over but a very active police force has come in over the last couple of years. There are over 200 police officers serving here and they have security locked down effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The police are ready to take on the security of the area. They are running their own operations independently; they have asked for little bits of support but they were operating very much on their own from the beginning of October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the larger bases, Nahidullah had support from civilian contractors who provided everything from satellite television and internet access to laundry facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the closure process, the facilities were removed and the base reduced to a more basic level for the troops that remained until the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kingsman Kurt Pollock, whose wife is expecting their second baby, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We went to the area but the Afghan police had pretty much been leading most of the operations anyway. We’re coming home early because the job has been done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m chuffed about going home; I’m looking forward to seeing my wife and son, as well as looking at the photographs of the scan of the baby on the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Kingsmen from Burma Company of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1797/AMOCCCT-2012-245-201.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kingsmen from Burma Company of 1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment on board an RAF C-17 Globemaster aircraft [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Rob McCormack said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghans were brilliant, they were happy to get out and conduct their own operations. A lot of the time they didn’t really ask for our help; when we tried to spur them on to do stuff they were already doing it proactively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The troops are generally happy about going home; however they still have friends out here so sometimes they have the feeling that they want to stay with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Through the welfare system my wife has been told we’re going home and she’s very happy I’m coming back to see her and the dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kingsman Kurtis Done said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I feel the tour has been worthwhile. We didn’t get into any conflict with the enemy because we were doing a proper job. I can’t wait to go home though. I think my mum is more excited than I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a period of leave, the troops from &lt;abbr title="1st Battalion The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;1 LANCS&lt;/abbr&gt; will be responsible for providing support to the battle groups deploying to  &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinafghanistan.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Afghanistan"&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/a&gt; in April 2013, when Burma Company will be reunited with the rest of the battalion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary announced last year that 500 British personnel would be withdrawn from Afghanistan by the end of 2012, reflecting the continuing progress being made in Helmand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown is consistent with the process of transition to Afghan forces agreed by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; nations at Lisbon in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary has emphasised the UK’s commitment to Afghanistan for the long term, committing £70 million per annum in funding for the Afghan security forces, in addition to taking the lead in setting up an Afghan National Army Officers’ Academy in Kabul after the combat mission ends in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43570</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers and Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/43538</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:04:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:04:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-boost-to-councils-and-communities-through-the-new-homes-bonus"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk: boost to councils and communities through the New Homes Bonus</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Council efforts to get Britain building are to be rewarded with a multi-million pound &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus" title="New Homes Bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, Housing Minister Mark Prisk announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share a cash payout of £661 million, after delivering 142,000 new homes, including 58,000 affordable properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding also rewards councils for bringing 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s provisional allocation, to be paid in the 2013 to 2014 financial year, means councils will have received £1.3 billion through the New Homes Bonus scheme since its launch in April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This total recognises over 400,000 new builds and conversions, and over 50,000 empty properties being brought back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued that the New Homes Bonus had proved critical in ensuring communities see the benefit of housing growth in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For years, developers found themselves at loggerheads with communities unconvinced that their plans for growth would benefit them. But the New Homes Bonus is turning this around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The £1.3 billion paid out to councils to date has meant that now local people are able to see the rewards of new developments in their area - paving the way for thousands of much-needed, locally-supported homes to be delivered across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="getting-britain-building"&gt;Getting Britain building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils across the country have made the most of this additional funding to directly benefit their local communities. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Tyneside Council, which has allocated some of its New Homes Bonus funding towards a £3.1 million revamp of a library which overlooks a Georgian square in the heart of North Shields. The library scheme forms part of the regeneration of the square, which also includes the refurbishment of properties, bringing it back into residential use for the first time in decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warwick Council, which has entered in a 10-year partnership with the Waterloo Housing Group to deliver new affordable homes in the area, with all New Homes Bonus payments generated by additional new homes built recycled back into the scheme to deliver additional housing and bring empty homes back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uttlesford District Council is allocating some of its new Homes Bonus to fund a hi-tech shelter for teenagers in a new play park at Carver Barracks. Those using the shelter can generate their own power through crank handles located around the room, with the energy generated able to support the use of Bluetooth and MP3 players. The idea for the project came from a committee - The Rowney Community Park Fund - made up of soldiers’ wives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A full list of provisional allocations of New Homes Bonus for the 2013 to 2014 financial year can be found &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/28978/121210_Provisional_allocations_New_Homes_Bonus.xls" title="New Homes Bonus provisional allocations 2013 - 2014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/41713</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/road-safety"/>
    <title>Road safety</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wanted to update the House on the launch of the government’s latest Think! Road Safety campaign, targeted at drink driving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action by successive governments over the last 30 years has meant that the number of people killed in drink drive accidents has been reduced by over three-quarters since 1979.  But drink driving remains a problem, 280 people lost their lives in 2011 in drink drive accidents on Britain’s roads. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in partnership with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.acpo.police.uk/"&gt;Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, so that people see education and enforcement working together, the government has just relaunched its successful Think! campaign aimed at reminding drivers – particularly young drivers, who are over-represented in the casualty figures – of the risks of getting behind the wheel after consuming alcohol: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://think.direct.gov.uk/"&gt;http://think.direct.gov.uk/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; enforcement anti-drink and drug driving enforcement campaign seeks particularly to focus on well-intentioned drivers who do not think they are breaking the law but may be over the legal limit by the time they get into their cars in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, at the end of last week I launched a further round of the very successful &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/campaign-to-reward-designated-drivers-launched-by-coca-cola-great-britain-and-think"&gt;designated driver campaign, in partnership with Coca-Cola&lt;/a&gt;. Now in its 5th year, the nationwide campaign offers designated drivers a ‘buy one get one free’ deal on Coca-Cola, Diet Coke and Coca-Cola Zero at participating pubs.  The campaign began last Thursday and will run until the end of December. Further details are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/"&gt;http://www.coca-cola.co.uk/designated-driver/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16641</id>
    <published>2012-12-09T20:35:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-09T20:35:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rafs-ii-ac-squadron-returns-from-afghanistan"/>
    <title>RAF's II (AC) Squadron returns from Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The personnel flew directly into the Norfolk base where they were greeted by RAF Marham’s Station Commander, Group Captain David Cooper, before being transported across to where their families eagerly awaited their arrival. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personnel are now looking forward to spending some time with their families after what has been an extremely eventful year for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/2squadron.cfm" title="II(Army Cooperation) Squadron"&gt;II(AC) Squadron&lt;/a&gt; or ‘Shiny Two’, as it is known. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The squadron has taken part in a major exercise in North America, and participated in a number of ceremonies to mark the squadron’s centenary, before turning their attention to the Operation HERRICK work-up and their subsequent deployment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, after four-and-a-half months, II (AC) Squadron’s deployment on Operation HERRICK has come to a close and it was fitting that the squadron, whose initial role was supporting ground troops back in 1912, has continued to do precisely that, 100 years after its formation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday 17 November II(AC) Squadron formally handed over to its sister squadron &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/9squadron.cfm" title="IX (Bomber) Squadron"&gt;IX (Bomber)&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/" title="RAF Marham"&gt;RAF Marham&lt;/a&gt;. This is familiar territory for both squadrons as it was only last year that the squadrons handed over to one another on Operation ELLAMY over Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="II (Army Cooperation) Squadron personnel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1140/MAR-UNCLASS-20121120-1366-0081.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;II (Army Cooperation) Squadron personnel returning to RAF Marham from their Afghanistan deployment [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Simon Armstrong, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;IX (Bomber) Squadron, under the leadership of Wing Commander Andy Turk, will be in residence at Kandahar Airfield in Afghanistan over Christmas and the New Year before handing over to the third RAF Marham-based squadron, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/organisation/31squadron.cfm" title="31 Squadron"&gt;31 Squadron&lt;/a&gt;, next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deploying at the height of summer, II (AC) Squadron can reflect and take pride in a job extremely well done. It has been a highly successful four-and-a-half month detachment, with the squadron flying over 2,000 hours in support of UK and coalition forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engineering challenge has also been significant, particularly with the high temperatures. However, the pragmatism, enthusiasm and dedication of the engineers ensured continued aircraft availability for daily and ground close air support taskings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Officer Commanding II (AC) Squadron, Wing Commander Nick Tucker-Lowe, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This has been a tremendously successful deployment for ‘Shiny Two’. With an operational pedigree that is ‘second-to-none’ the squadron always strives for operational excellence and, due to the consistent diligence and determination of all of the squadron’s personnel, that is exactly what we have achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39676</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities Ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish Community have made, and continue to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39721</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-marines-storm-former-cold-war-base"/>
    <title>Royal Marines storm former Cold War base</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a scenario based around a hostile occupying force, the Royal Marines from the Lead Commando Group (&lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;) joined up with their Albanian counterparts to practise their training for contingent operations as part of Royal Navy exercise Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the cover of smoke grenades, the combined forces quickly pounced on the ‘enemy’ lurking in the old submarine base on Sazan Island, taking them by surprise and then fighting their way through a complex labyrinth of bunkers and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 16 hours the Anglo-Albanian forces chased the enemy down, pushing them back all the time as they exercised the skills being practiced under Cougar 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ric Moat of Zulu Company, 45 Commando Royal Marines, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The size and scale of Sazan Island is impressive. It provides a unique training opportunity for amphibious forces. It is a stern test, it is realistic, and it is demanding training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Raiding from the sea is clearly a different challenge to our land operations in Afghanistan, but it is no less challenging to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the old Soviet submarine base, Sazan Island is home to a chemical and biological weapons plant and there are more than 100 buildings and 5.7 square kilometres of trenches and bunkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1487/Royal_Marines_storm_former_Cold_War_base2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British and Albanian forces taking part in Exercise Albanian Lion on Sazan Island [Picture: Petty Officer (Photographer) Sean Clee, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major Richard Alston of 3 Commando Brigade said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The complexity of the exercise should not be underestimated. We have completed two consecutive night raids and have now pushed reconnaissance teams 110 miles [177km] inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a non-combatant evacuation exercise with the British embassy staff as part of the exercise scenario and have achieved all this in three days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Response Force Task Group, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt;, made up of 45 Commando and 3 Commando Brigade, are inserted by sea and Royal Navy warships into trouble spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operations, such as Libya last year, require a rapid reaction force to quickly deploy in response to unexpected world events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cougar 12 involves more than 3,000 sailors, marines and airmen in addition to four Royal Navy warships and one Royal Fleet Auxiliary ship which provide the platforms to plan the operations and also protect the troops from the sea and air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having practiced their skills alongside French Marines and soldiers in Corsica in October, the &lt;abbr title="Lead Commando Group"&gt;LCG&lt;/abbr&gt; will complete Albanian Lion before heading back to the UK at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39686</id>
    <published>2012-09-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/success-for-british-teams-in-world-helicopter-championship"/>
    <title>Success for British teams in World Helicopter Championship</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The competition, in its 14th year, was held outside the Russian capital with two teams from the British Services taking part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Helicopter Club of Great Britain invited the crews to compete as part of the British team following their successes at the British and German Championships in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Championship requires the crews to exercise their skills through a number of flying tests including an obstacle course which involves dangling a bucket of water below the helicopter whilst negotiating a slalom course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two teams comprised instructors from the Defence Helicopter Flying School (DHFS), whose day job is to teach all UK military helicopter pilots and crews for all three Services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main team, comprising Squadron Leader Craig Finch and Mr John ‘JJ’ Jackson, an ex-RAF airman, are the current British champions, and were successful at both the UK and European competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also taking part in the competition was the second team, which paired Flight Lieutenant Mark Lazenby with Lieutenant Jim Fraser of the Royal Navy and was managed by Flying Officer Ryan Stowe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two Squirrel helicopters flown by the British teams were provided by FBHeliservices who own and operate the aircraft flown at RAF Shawbury. Mr Gareth Mayfield from FBHeliservices travelled with the aircraft to provide engineering support throughout the Championship. The company has been instrumental in ensuring that the teams have been able to compete at the highest level.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Championship ran from 22 to 26 August at Drakino Airfield in Russia, with 50 teams taking part from across the world. Twenty-five of those teams were made up of Russian or Belarusian crews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six teams competed for the team prize with the UK pairing of Finch and Jackson taking the silver medal having finished a creditable second behind Russia. In the overall competition the pair finished 13th out of 50 whilst the pairing of Lazenby/Fraser finished in 30th place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The medal presentation took place on Sunday 26 August and was attended by the Moscow Defence Attache. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flight Lieutenant Lazenby said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The DHFS crews’ attendance at the WHC reflected their pre-eminence at the National Helicopter Championships and their long-standing success at these and other international events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful performance of the DHFS crews ably demonstrated the professionalism and skill of UK military aircrew and the success of the military/civil partnership at DHFS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lead DHFS team was the highest-ranked team outside of Russia/Belarus, beating all military and civilian crews from Germany, Austria, Switzerland, China, Poland, France and Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39681</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-attends-manama-dialogue"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary attends Manama Dialogue</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary today arrived in Bahrain to take part in the Manama Dialogue. The Dialogue, hosted by the think tank International Institute for Strategic Studies, is a leading forum for governments and non-government experts to discuss regional security issues in the Middle East. These issues are a top priority for the UK and the event provides an important opportunity to discuss shared concerns with representatives from the region and key members of the international community. The Foreign Secretary is leading a UK delegation, which also includes Lord Astor of Hever, MOD Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State and Government Spokesperson, and General Sir David Richards, the Chief of the Defence Staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will meet members of the Government of Bahrain during his visit. As a close friend and ally, the UK has consistently encouraged the Government to take further steps to implement promised reforms and urged all sides to enter into an inclusive and constructive dialogue.  While progress is being made in some areas, we believe there is still more to be done to achieve long term stability and prosperity in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of the visit, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to attend the Manama Dialogue, which brings together key figures from a variety of backgrounds to discuss events and regional security in the Middle East. I will lead discussions in a session on the influence of sectarian politics in the region, highlighting the importance of universal human rights and access to justice as the most effective ways to tackle the tensions that sectarianism inflames.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will also meet representatives of the Government of Bahrain to continue our discussions on the need for full and timely implementation of their reform programme, and the UK’s offer of support.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
