<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56690</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/louise-casey-calls-for-family-intervention-approach"/>
    <title>Louise Casey calls for family intervention approach</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a look at the academic evidence, alongside consultation with practitioners and families themselves, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/louise-casey"&gt;Louise Casey&lt;/a&gt; today published a new report that shows the life-changing results that good family intervention can have on even the most challenging households, along with a guide to best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;‘Working with Troubled Families’ report&lt;/a&gt; outlines that family intervention reduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involvement in anti-social behaviour by 59%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;involvement in crime by 45%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truancy, exclusion, bad behaviour at school by 52%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also points to the 5 key features of effective family intervention being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated worker, dedicated to a family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ‘hands on’ support &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a persistent, assertive and challenging approach &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;considering the family as a whole - gathering the intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common purpose and agreed action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey is now calling on councils to review their own ways of working with troubled families and adopt these principles in order to ensure that the significant momentum that has built up behind the programme - with all eligible local authorities in England on board and committed to working with over 40,000 families in this financial year - continues in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to push on with this work and make further progress towards the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015, the Department for Communities and Local Government will also be holding a series of training academies for local authorities in the new year to help share best practice on family intervention and provide masterclasses from some of its leading exponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the government’s Troubled Families programme Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My last report was about listening to troubled families themselves and some of the stories from families were truly appalling. However these were families successfully going through family intervention and the results were impressive - so I wanted to ensure that this practice is adopted as widely as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This report makes a strong case about what works - family intervention that involves one dedicated worker for each family, providing tough but persistent challenge and support, has a dramatic impact, not just on the life chances of those within the families, but on the communities around them who suffer from the effects of truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This important piece of work is a crucial step towards building a wide campaign of support behind the work we are doing to break an inter-generational cycle of misery and failure with these families. It will put rocket boosters under the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around 120,000 troubled families by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Effective family intervention also demonstrates that savings can be made for taxpayers by putting families back on the right track for the long run, rather than wasting money on simply reacting to their problems. We must have aspiration for every family and this work will reach all corners of the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Clare Tickell, Chief Executive of Action for Children, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since developing the initial model, we’ve seen how family intervention can really help vulnerable families facing multiple difficulties in their lives. It works by forming effective relationships with families and building on their strengths. This timely guide is a welcome resource, which will help people understand the key features of the model, learn what really works and ensure that projects are delivered to a high quality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;Working with Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"&gt;Listening to Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, July 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All eligible local authorities are running troubled families programmes in their area and between them have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is today also publishing management information on the work of family intervention projects and services in England up to 31 March 2012. This reports the latest data at a national level for all participating family intervention services. It includes information on the families worked with and the percentage of families considered to have a successful outcome in relation to family functioning and risk, crime/ anti-social behaviour, health and education/ employment. This data was collected by the National Centre for Social Research (NatCen) which ran a secure web-based information system into which family intervention project staff recorded details of the families they worked with between 2007-2012. It can be found at Annex B of the ‘Working With Troubled Families’ report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56672</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next three years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow ing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeking Intellectual Property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the Agri-food, Built Environment, Space industries, Energy, Water and Waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for Agri-Food, Built Environment and Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual property advisers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56700</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:45:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:45:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-innovation-workshop"/>
    <title>Support for Innovation Workshop</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library, NE1 8AX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30th January 2013, 9.30am to 3.30pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying competitive and growing a business in today’s challenging trading conditions is tough.  However, a range of Government support and funding is available to help your business innovate and grow. Find out more at this free practical workshop for small and medium sized businesses with the appetite and potential to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus will be on the importance of innovation to future success and how government schemes can help you develop, protect and commercialise new ideas. Subjects include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-innovation"&gt;Importance of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Addison, innovation specialist and pioneer of Procter &amp;amp; Gamble’s open innovation programme, will describe how innovation is vital for growth. In particular, P&amp;amp;G’s approach to open innovation could be reused in your business for sourcing and commercialising new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="support-for-innovation"&gt;Support for Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering grants and other support for R&amp;amp;D through the Technology Strategy Board and the R&amp;amp;D Tax Credit scheme run by HMRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-your-innovation"&gt;Protecting Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering support from the Intellectual Property Office to protect your IP and how schemes like Patent Box can make it much more cost effective to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commercialising-your-innovation"&gt;Commercialising Your Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including support from the Design Council to enhance product value through design and how Growth Accelerator can support your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Register for the free workshop at &lt;a href="www.business-events.org.uk"&gt;www.business-events.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is being held at the Business &amp;amp; IP Centre, Newcastle City Library. The Centre is designed to support entrepreneurs, inventors and small businesses from that first spark of inspiration to successfully launching and developing a business. It is the first regional centre based on the British Library’s model and have been running since September 2011. Since the launch, over 2,000 entrepreneurs have used the Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre is a partnership between the British Library, Newcastle City Council, Newcastle Science City and Northumbria University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56622</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/guidance-will-help-support-development-and-get-infrastructure-built"/>
    <title>Guidance will help support development and get infrastructure built</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance has been revised with the active participation of councils and developers to provide certainty on key issues. It has been updated to reflect reforms to the planning system and will help councils looking to introduce the levy, as well as providing clarity to those paying the levy about how it works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; ensures there is no double charging to developers by clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance reflects existing best practice and ensures councils in the process of developing proposals do not need to start their levy setting process from the beginning. Support will be available to councils who choose to review their levy as a result of the new guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ensures a robust evidence base is used for assessing levy rates and provides advice on the 2012 regulations that improve the operation of the levy. The guidance also makes clear that there is no obligation for councils to charge the levy, and that they can set a low or zero rate if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Government has worked actively with councils and developers to get this guidance right and make clear how we expect the levy to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The guidance ensures that councils who have already adopted their levy will not need to do anything new and only councils developing levy rates will need to consider this new guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will continue to listen to issues being raised, such as the need for greater clarity at an earlier stage on how the levy will be spent. We will also be considering the suggestion to move the 2014 date when councils will be limited in their use of pooled Section 106 planning obligations for infrastructure that can be funded by the levy. The government expects to consult on further regulatory changes in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy has the potential to raise an estimated £1 billion a year of funding by 2016 to support growth locally. It gives councils more choice and flexibility in how they fund the infrastructure that their communities want and need, and provides developers with much more ‘up front’ certainty about the amount of money they will be expected to contribute for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Peace from the British Property Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development industry has raised a number of concerns about the Community Infrastructure Levy. We have been closely involved in the development of this document and are pleased that it clearly sets out what local authorities must do when they are looking to charge the levy. These revisions should help support development by ensuring the levy is being implemented effectively. We look forward to continuing our work with the department on other Community Infrastructure Levy issues next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Mike Jones, Leader, Cheshire West and Chester Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils are keen to continue work with the development industry in a positive and productive way that enables much needed development to take place in a way that is fair and equitable to developers and to local people. Discussions on the Community Infrastructure Levy have been conducted in this spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Builders Federation Executive Chairman Stewart Baseley said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been closely involved in the process to improve the Community Infrastructure Levy guidance. We are pleased that it assists in clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations and sets out the importance of robust evidence and transparency when deciding on levy rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recently introduced changes to ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged the Community Infrastructure Levy. Applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents (via a Section 73 planning application) without having to pay another levy on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56640</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-funding-to-unlock-delivery-of-12-000-new-homes"/>
    <title>Government funding to unlock delivery of 12,000 new homes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intervention will accelerate building on 2 large sites in East Devon and near Milton Keynes; unlocking development and bringing forward construction to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £20 million injection of funding for the new town of Cranbrook, near Exeter, will enable local partners to bring forward the delivery of new homes included in the local plan, and create 1,500 jobs in the town that will include 6,300 homes and a new rail station with links to London and Exeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money will also unlock construction of a new high street and transport infrastructure needed to develop the town centre, as well as 2 new schools in the next phase of development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cranbrook, the minister met local construction apprentices who would work on the scheme. He said the government’s investment would create jobs for young people and bring a powerful economic boost to the area, while giving the consortium behind the new town the confidence and resources to drive forward its completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk with construction apprentices" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5640/Mark-Prisk-meets-apprentice.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk meets apprentices who will work on the new town at Cranbrook&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also revealed that the construction of 6,000 new homes on the Fairfield development in Milton Keynes will also be brought forward without the need for direct funding, following discussions with the developer behind the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intervention builds on the deal made earlier this year for the Eastern Quarry development near Ebbsfleet in Kent, a site for over 22,000 homes, bringing total number of potential homes unlocked through these schemes to over 34,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the minister also pledged support for housing programmes near Wokingham, where £2.5 million will enable local partners to solve key transport issues in the town in order to unlock the potential for over 10,000 new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the government is making strong progress to boost house building despite the difficult economic circumstances, and he was in discussions with other schemes across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is serious about building more homes. That’s why we have been looking carefully at how we can accelerate large, planned housing schemes that already have the support of local people, but need help to move forward in the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I’m delighted that today I can announce our intervention will unlock the delivery of 12,000 new homes, and create thousands of jobs for local people. In the months ahead I will be announcing support for similar schemes. That means more investment, more jobs for our young people and more affordable homes for families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have set aside considerable funding to assist large housing programmes like Cranbrook, and I would urge anyone with similar proposals to come forward and contact my department.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East Devon District Council Leader Councillor Paul Diviani said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a unique opportunity here to create Cranbrook’s town centre as a shining exemplar of how all town centres can function!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Currently the town centre is a blank canvas; we are not restricted by existing buildings or street formations. With support from central government our vision of a town centre that is vibrant, attractive, welcoming, the beating heart of the new community, can become a reality much sooner than previously expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement is the first allocation of £225 million, earmarked by the Chancellor in last week’s Autumn Statement, for the delivery of 50,000 new homes in large, locally-supported housing programmes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding programme for planned, large-scale sites, administered by the Homes and Communities Agency, will be targeted at schemes that could deliver real benefits to their communities, but are struggling to move forward because the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside funding to unlock new construction, the schemes will receive a package of support, including help to facilitate close co-operation with the local council and community during planning and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-on-public-land"&gt;Progress on public land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said an expert review published today also demonstrates the government is taking the right steps to quickly release its previously-used, surplus land for building new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the recommendations in the report, led by the chairman of Berkley Group, Tony Pidgley, are already shaping measures being taken forward by the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date enough land has been sold to build up to 33,000 new homes, and last week’s Autumn Statement included a £290 million fund for the Home and Communities Agency to introduce measures that will quickly bring forward new sites for development, such as installing the right infrastructure so the land can be used for building new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Pidgley, chair of the Expert Advisory Panel said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a golden opportunity to deliver growth and great places. It’s surplus public land. It doesn’t need new legislation. All that’s required is a simple system to dispose of the land, alongside investment in infrastructure, and then the private sector can get on with building these much needed homes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further reaction to the funding support for Cranbrook: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the consortium partners - Hallam Land, Persimmon Homes and Taylor Wimpey - Mike Owen, project manager for Cranbrook, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were privileged to give Mark Prisk a tour of the development which gave him an insight into the brand new community being created. From the very start the development of Cranbrook has been about partnership and this announcement of funding support for phase 2 continues that process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without this phase 2 Cranbrook would have been delayed at the end of phase 1. Instead, we have certainty in the delivery of phase 2, we can move ahead now and commit with confidence to the next key stages of the project and delivering further community infrastructure and bringing forward much needed private and affordable homes. The success of Cranbrook to-date has been underwritten by the amenities and infrastructure that we have been able to provide. In turn this has enabled the creation a real community from day one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Will Mumford, Chair of Exeter and Heart of Devon Growth Board and cabinet member for Economy, Enterprise and Employment, Devon Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Cranbrook has been recognised for its successful delivery and for the additional funding to enable us to bring phase 2 forward. This keeps the project momentum going, will secure additional jobs and investment and is a resounding vote of confidence in the partnership approach.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Molton, Homes and Communities Agency Executive Director for the South and South West, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government has shown its commitment to housing and development as a major route to driving economic growth and we welcome the confidence ministers have shown in our ability to deliver its key initiatives, supported by new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s welcome news also that Cranbrook is rightly identified as a vanguard project which will help drive economic growth in the south west, by providing the essential investment needed to deliver the second phase of the project. This is a huge opportunity, and I know that our partners will grasp it to maximise delivery of new homes and growth in Exeter and East Devon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public land review published today can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/news&amp;amp;newsArticleID=6604&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;Berkley Group website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56543</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-message-from-the-defence-secretary"/>
    <title>Christmas message from the Defence Secretary</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The full text of the message is reproduced below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 has been a busy and challenging year for Defence - on operations in Afghanistan, on our many other overseas commitments, and here at home, delivering security for the Olympics and beginning the huge process of Defence Transformation. You should be proud of what you have achieved in the last 12 months - military and civilian personnel working together to protect our security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, 20th Armoured Brigade, 12th Mechanized Brigade, and now 4th Mechanized Brigade, have built on the hard work and sacrifice of their predecessors. This has been another tough year in Helmand province and we should remember, in particular, the members of our Armed Forces who have lost their lives or who have been seriously injured. Their sacrifice will not be forgotten. However, we should be in no doubt about the importance of the mission or the significant progress that we are making with our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; (International Security Assistance Force) partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; (Afghan National Security Forces) take on ever more responsibility for security, we will be able to make further significant reduction in UK troop numbers in theatre next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home, this summer, at short notice, you stepped in to undertake the largest peacetime operation since World War II, helping to make the Olympic and Paralympic Games such a resounding success, and in the process you demonstrated to the British public and visitors from across the world that your reputation for the highest standards of professionalism is well deserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our main effort has been on operations, we have also continued the vital task of transforming Defence to ensure that we have the people, equipment and training to maintain our battle-winning edge in the post-Afghanistan security environment. A balanced budget is the foundation upon which this rests and we must continue to ensure that we maintain our budget discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I know that achieving that balanced budget, and in particular reducing the number of military and civilian personnel, has been a painful process for many. I also recognise that there is a need for certainty over the future laydown of the Armed Forces and the structure of DE&amp;amp;S (Defence Equipment and Support). These are both complex tasks, but I will announce the outcomes and provide that certainty as soon as I can next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we undertake this process of transformation, it is important to keep in mind what we are aiming for: the most capable, deployable and best-trained armed forces in the world, supported by a lean, efficient MOD and a procurement operation that delivers the maximum effect for every pound of taxpayers’ money. There is still a long way to go to deliver this, but I want everyone, whether military or civilian, to be proud of what we are achieving in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to thank you all for the hard work, commitment and professionalism you have shown in 2012. I am proud to lead such a capable team of men and women. To those of you spending Christmas away from home, you will be in our thoughts. For those of you not on operations, I hope you enjoy the Christmas break. Merry Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Right Honourable Philip Hammond MP&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56611</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:57:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-welcomes-new-counter-terrorism-centre-in-uae"/>
    <title>UK welcomes new counter terrorism centre in UAE</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the broad experience and expertise of the 30 Global Counter-Terrorism Forum (GCTF) founding member nations, the Centre will lead global research on the drivers of terrorism, deliver training to address these, and identify practical, operational initiatives to reduce the threat from terrorism. It was launched at the third ministerial meeting of the GCTF in the United Arab Emirates (UAE), which was attended by representatives from all member nations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tunisia, where he is on an official visit, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s launch in Abu Dhabi of the Centre of Excellence for Countering Violent Extremism (CVE) is an important milestone in the global fight against terrorism. In particular I welcome the leadership that His Excellency Foreign Minister Abdullah bin Zayed has shown and the Emirati commitment to host the Centre and make it a reality. The UK will continue to give it our full support. We have nominated an expert to serve as a Member of the International Steering Board and are seconding a Director of Training &amp;amp; Capacity-Building into the Centre’s senior management team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to do our utmost to tackle the root causes of terrorism by ensuring a collaborative international approach to the common threat of terrorism. The Global Counter Terrorism Forum offers us an excellent platform from which to address this constantly changing challenge, drawing on the expertise and experience of its members”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thegctf.org/web/guest/about" title="Global Counter-Terrorism Forum"&gt;Global Counter-Terrorism Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56641</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/meet-more-millies-heroes"/>
    <title>Meet more Millies heroes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-1---operation-olympics"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 1 - Operation Olympics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympians Victoria Pendleton and Greg Rutherford presented the first of two Judges’ Special Recognition Awards to the Armed Forces for their contribution to the London 2012 Olympics. At its height, more than 17,500 personnel stepped in when G4S were not able to provide sufficient guards for all the venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victoria said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone I’ve met has been incredible; individuals who’ve achieved so much. I feel in awe because all I did was ride round in circles on a wooden track with a bike with no brakes and one gear and this is real life. I can’t not be moved and it makes me feel very proud to be British.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear the military personnel treasured their experiences. Senior Aircraftwoman Afyah Bubb, an RAF medic who volunteered to be part of the security team at the Olympic Park, saw it as a ‘once-in-a-lifetime opportunity’. She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were there to do a job but I unexpectedly got the chance to see Ellie Simmonds break some swimming records which was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squadron Leader Brian Fahy added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were really proud to be part of the Games this summer and see the superb performance of our athletes. Who wouldn’t want to be part of the greatest show in town?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic long jump gold medallist Greg Rutherford said backstage: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m hugely proud of the Armed Forces; the whole evening has been a massive highlight and getting involved feels out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5637/award_for_headley_court.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Anne Brannagan and members of the Headley Court Complex Trauma Team with their Special Recognition Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a light-hearted moment, Greg joked that he hadn’t packed enough tissues. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I get emotional so easily and seeing videos of these incredible people moves me to tears every time. It’s completely surreal to be here; I’ve got friends in the Armed Forces including my best friend who is now going through training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to be invited to such a prestigious night, and to show our respect and thanks to these guys is an honour. The troops came in with happy smiley faces and gave high fives and absolutely saved the day! A huge thank you, you were absolutely spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="judges-special-recognition-award-2---complex-trauma-team-headley-court"&gt;Judges’ Special Recognition Award 2 - Complex Trauma Team, Headley Court&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second Judges’ Special Recognition Award honoured the Complex Trauma Team at the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/Militarymedicine/Pages/HeadleyCourt.aspx" title="Headley Court"&gt;Headley Court&lt;/a&gt;. It is the remarkable skill and dedication of the 110-strong Trauma Team that help many critically wounded soldiers overcome life-changing injuries so they can get back to leading active lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex trauma manager Anne Brannagan received the award on behalf of Headley Court from actor Kevin Spacey who congratulated and shook hands with each of the 10 team members on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group Captain Clare Walton, Commanding Officer at Headley Court, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kevin Spacey was just very complimentary, it was great, and to have someone of his level of superstardom even know who we are is lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony tonight (14 December) on ITV1 at 2100hrs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56578</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/change-of-her-majesty-s-ambassador-to-turkey"/>
    <title>Change of Her Majesty’s Ambassador to Turkey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will succeed Mr David Reddaway CMG MBE. Mr Moore will take up his appointment in January 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Moore was Director for Europe, Latin America and Globalisation until November 2012. He joined the FCO in 1987 and has worked in London on the Middle East and security policy before becoming Director of Programmes and Change. A Turkish speaker, he has served overseas in Vietnam, Turkey, Pakistan and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment as Her Majesty’s Ambassador to the Republic of Turkey, Mr Moore has said “I am delighted to be returning to Turkey where I served early in my diplomatic career. I look forward to working with this close NATO ally, EU candidate and increasingly important political and trading partner, to build an even stronger relationship of trust and friendship between Britain and Turkey in the years ahead.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Full name:&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Richard Peter Moore&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Married to:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Margaret Patricia Isabel Moore (k.a. Maggie)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Children:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;One son, one daughter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010-present&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director Europe, Latin America and Globalisation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008-2010&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director Programmes and Change&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Stanford Executive Programme&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005-2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Deputy Director Middle East&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001-2005&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kuala Lumpur, Counsellor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1998-2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Section Head, Security Policy Group&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995-1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Islamabad, First Secretary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1992-1995&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Desk Officer, Iran&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1991-1992&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Istanbul, Consul (Political and Press)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ankara, Second Secretary (Political)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1988&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hanoi, Third Secretary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1987&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Joined Her Majesty’s Diplomatic Service&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55783</id>
    <published>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/living-through-the-guilt-of-surviving"/>
    <title>Living through the guilt of surviving</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rifle muzzle protruded from his chest, piercing just millimetres above the main artery going into his heart, his radio had gone through his arm, and the explosion had fired shrapnel, gravel and metal the length of his back to the soles of his feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His legs burned from the fierce heat of the metal fragments piercing his skin, his trousers were all but gone - shredded in the blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his own injuries, he tried to help carry the other wounded from the ensuing fire fight, instinctively pulling the rifle muzzle from his chest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years on and Guardsman Pearson’s body remains scarred, with shrapnel still coming out of his skin every day. The hidden mental scars, however, have damaged him more than any physical injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Torturing myself’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having had both types of injuries, physical and mental, the physical side of it was far easier to get over,” said the 21-year-old Grenadier Guard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mental side of it, well it’s just taking so long to get over. You finally think you are there and then one little thing happens and it all comes back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="British soldiers carrying a simulated casualty during an exercise in Wales (stock image)" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5618/Living_through_the_guilt_of_surviving_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;British soldiers carrying a simulated casualty during an exercise in Wales (stock image) [Picture: Corporal Paul Morrison, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hardest thing to deal with has been the reaction of people he had considered friends - their ignorance of post-traumatic stress disorder leading them to think he was faking flashbacks, nightmares and crippling insomnia to get out of soldiering:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The things people have said about me since admitting my post-traumatic stress are, to be fair, what I would have thought about anyone else too… before it happened to me,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone says just man up, and that’s what I had been doing for so long, but it came to a point where I couldn’t man up any more. I had to go get help to get through it because it was only going to get worse, not better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was short-tempered and angry, drinking too much and arguing, and I was having difficulty sleeping. I was getting paranoid about sleeping in the same room as the other blokes in case they took the mick out of me for screaming in the night from the nightmares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was torturing myself with ‘what ifs’, and if that had happened what would have come out of it. But I still thought there was nothing wrong with me, that it was everyone else and they just hadn’t adapted to me coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My now wife, Loren, begged me to realise what I was doing, and how hard I was making other people’s lives with my arguing. It would be over the stupidest little things. But I thought it was everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk through the explosion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The turning point came when Guardsman Pearson reacted badly to a joke made at a family wedding, and Loren’s father took him outside for a little chat, warning him that if he continued he would lose Loren and destroy everything he had:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I went to the med centre as soon as I got back to work,” he said. “I didn’t want to hurt anyone, and I was starting to worry about how much of a hold I had over myself during the flashbacks and the drinking. I didn’t know what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after reporting to the medical centre, Guardsman Pearson was referred to the Department of Community Mental Health in Woolwich for assessment and then psychotherapy, and was encouraged to talk through the explosion in Nad ‘Ali - breaking it down into little bits to look at each action from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this he could slowly see that he had done nothing wrong, and that nothing he could have done would have saved his friend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I first went to the sessions my intention was just to forget everything, I didn’t want to relive it,” he said. “I wanted everything out of my mind so I could finally get a decent night’s sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We tried things like the breathing techniques to deal with my anger, but it just didn’t work with me - it’s easier said than done to sit there and think of a happy place when all you want to do is be angry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But breaking things down and looking at it from different ways did make me feel better as I could see I did what any normal soldier would have done in the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More good days than bad days&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It takes a lot of time. There is no quick fix. It’s been nearly two years for me now, and it’s a constant cycle of good and bad days. It feels like you are stuck and you can’t go that little bit further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Initially though it was like a roundabout - sometimes I would go to the therapist and there would be absolutely nothing wrong and it would all be fine, and then a week later I would go back and there would be loads I needed to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now the memories only tend to come back on days like Remembrance Sunday, whereas before it was every night and I would remember that little bit more than I did the night before - so it would play on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I still have my good days and my bad days, but now it’s more good days than bad days. And when my mood swings Loren will tell me to stop me going into them so much. She knows the signs when I am starting to go downhill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The biggest thing for me is being back at work though - it keeps you busy and your mind off other things. I just hope others will be able to make the most of my experiences to go and seek help, and this campaign [Don’t Bottle It Up] will change the way people think about mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_If you are in need of mental health support or advice for you or a family member please see the Mental Health Support and Contact Details page at Related Links.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is also World Mental Health Day - see Related Links._&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56579</id>
    <published>2012-07-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/light-dragoons-step-up-mentoring-in-helmand"/>
    <title>Light Dragoons step up mentoring in Helmand</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Boasting a proud recent history as a distinguished reconnaissance regiment, the Light Dragoons have trained diligently for another tour on the outer extremes of Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working remotely has become a reality for elements of the Norfolk-based unit on Op HERRICK 16, others have seen their job description change significantly after less than two months in theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having deployed to southern Afghanistan in a formation reconnaissance role, personnel from A Squadron are now playing their part in the continuing transition effort after accepting a new tasking within the Police Mentoring and Advisory Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the move and how they are preparing for the challenge that lies ahead, on the eve of their training in Camp Bastion Lieutenant Jamie Harle said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was very much last minute but we are eager for it. I deployed on my last HERRICK in 2006 and that was all kinetic, but anyone thinking this tour would be the same is misguided. This is all about transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghans we have spoken to are really proud of what they are doing; they want to return security to their family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were undertaking screening tasks in the desert, identifying areas of population and routes, while providing a visible deterrent. It was very successful but the main effort has switched for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now focusing on expanding the mentoring side so the locals can look after these routes and population centres themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Op HERRICK 16 is the third Afghan deployment for Corporal Scott Mallen and the junior non-commissioned officer thinks the timescale for transition is achievable after witnessing the progress that has already been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Life on the ground for soldiers of the Light Dragoons is very different to previous tours " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5616/Light_Dragoons_step_up_mentoring_in_Helmand_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Life on the ground for soldiers of the Light Dragoons is very different to previous tours [Picture: Graeme Main, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;And with the situation on the ground changing, he believes A Squadron can add to the success in its new role training the Afghan Police:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From what I have seen everything is shaping up for the handover,” he said. “It has quietened down in terms of kinetic activity and that is one of the main reasons why forward reconnaissance is coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the end of the day the Afghans want a better life. The country’s army is up and running and the ANP [Afghan National Police] are now manning checkpoints in certain areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Op HERRICK 5 it was really kicking off and we were the Brigade Reconnaissance Force on Op HERRICK 10. That was lethal and everyone had a hard time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fact it is now quieter shows we are doing a job out here. The ANP are performing their role and they are not afraid to have a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these soldiers are relishing the opportunity of testing themselves in a new environment, the remainder of the squadron will continue with their formation reconnaissance day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brief has seen them providing overwatch for ground forces, pushing forward on scouting missions and playing a key role in identifying enemy positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldiers of 3rd Troop at Forward Operating Base Ouellette have discovered that life on the ground is very different to previous tours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was here on Op HERRICK 10 and it was kinetic every day, but now it is quieter and the enemy are on the back foot,” explained Trooper Neil Nutton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Babaji was a Taliban stronghold; we took that and I think it has broken them. We are getting tighter and tighter on them and all they can do is ‘shoot and scoot’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operating in Helmand province has become a family affair for the soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His brother Trooper Anthony Nutton is serving with B Squadron of the Light Dragoons as part of the Brigade Reconnaissance Force, while older sibling Rifleman John Nutton, 2nd Battalion The Rifles, deployed on Op HERRICK 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I met John in Camp Bastion and he said hardly anything happened during his tour. He only had a few contacts and did a lot of patrolling with the ANP, “ said Trooper Neil Hutton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought that couldn’t be right, but I believe it now, it has been quiet. In the formation reconnaissance squadron our main role is to go out and see what the enemy are doing, to see where they are and where the IEDs may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can do that for a couple of weeks if needed - it is about building the picture and getting information ahead of any operations. We are the eyes and ears of the battle group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as taking the fight to the enemy, the tour has reaffirmed the positive role being played by the Army within Afghan communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attached medic Lance Corporal Lee Robson, Royal Army Medical Corps, was delighted to report that he has seen a distinct lack of British casualties in the area thus far, meaning his attention has been focused elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have been hands-on with the locals, treating children and adults for minor ailments through to serious injuries such as broken ankles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a medic it is always nice to offer help to anyone, especially if they have no healthcare system of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It all goes back to the hearts and minds mantra. We are showing them that we are not a force to be frightened of - we are here to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldiers from A Squadron have again proved how the British Army is producing personnel that can adapt to a variety of roles in the heat of Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with transition set for 2014, the efforts of these troops over the coming months will go a long way to ensuring this ambition becomes a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_This article is taken from the July 2012 edition of Soldier - magazine of the British Army. _&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please tell us what you think about government news on the web by filling in the short survey at Related Links.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56576</id>
    <published>2011-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-police-launch-defence-road-safety-week-road-show"/>
    <title>MOD Police launch Defence Road Safety Week Road Show</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of Defence Road Safety Week a Ministry of Defence Police (MDP) Road Show will take a mobile police station to different MOD establishments under the banner of its Home Front Community Safety Partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiative supports National Road Safety Week, promoted by Brake, the road safety charity, and both events run from Monday 21 November to Sunday 27 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDP Community Safety Manager for the North East, Sergeant Gavin Alcroft, who is managing the initiative for the MDP, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This will be the sixth year we have carried out a national road show event. We provide information on road safety but we also have equipment on board that allows us to carry out interactive activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We show high impact road safety films and we encourage visitors to take a Highway Code quiz with the chance to win a goody bag!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The national theme of Road Safety Week 2011 is ‘Too Young to Die’ and it focuses on the fact that road crashes are sudden, violent events that can rip families apart by ending lives too soon and causing life-changing injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of those affected are young and these casualties send shock waves through families and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDP Community Safety Manager for Scotland, Sergeant George Smart, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These casualties are preventable as they are often caused by factors such as driving too fast, overtaking dangerously, driving while using a mobile, driving whilst over the limit, drug driving, driving when tired or failing to use a seat belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest official figures show that there were 1,850 road casualties in the UK overall in 2010 - a reduction of 17 per cent on 2009. Within the MOD, road casualty trends and statistics are down too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="PC Colin Everett helps get the road safety message across at RAF Wittering" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5612/MOD_Police_launch_Defence_Road_Safety_Week_Road_Show_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;PC Colin Everett helps get the road safety message across at RAF Wittering [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, 37 military personnel were killed in on and off duty road traffic incidents. The statistics show that Armed Services personnel are twice as likely to be killed in a road traffic incident as their civilian counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Moate, of the Defence Road Safety Team, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the first six months of 2011, six out of the ten MOD fatalities recorded were of personnel riding motorcycles. These statistics cover any MOD employee killed as a result of a road traffic accident, irrespective of circumstance, and include passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everything that we can do to help lower this figure through extra training and workshops, using the support of local authorities and the police, is time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDP have Community Police Officers and Community Safety Officers stationed across the country who can be contacted for information on road safety activities and initiatives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to remain focused on raising awareness of road safety and promoting safer driving across the Defence Estate,” said Sergeant Alcroft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are keen to target attitudes to driving and road use - on and off duty - for military personnel, particularly the younger element, as well as raising awareness in Service families of those important safety messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although the national theme is important, we are also mindful of local issues and problems. Where these are identified, they are targeted by our local officers, so please approach them if you have concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road show is scheduled to carry out visits to the Defence Munitions centres at Beith and Longtown, MOD St Athan, the Atomic Weapons Establishment at Aldermaston and HM Naval Base Clyde - covering defence communities in Scotland, England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56574</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lost-wwii-raf-crew-laid-to-rest-in-malaysia"/>
    <title>Lost WWII RAF crew laid to rest in Malaysia</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liberator KL654, with its crew of eight from 356 Squadron, left the Cocos Islands on 23 August 1945 to drop supplies into central Malaysia. No message, or signal, was received from the aircraft after take-off and it failed to return from its mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reports at the time spoke of an unidentified aircraft being heard over the target area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the aircraft’s route took it over the sea and Sumatran jungle and poor weather conditions were reported, with low cloud over the hills and localised thunderstorms, the aircraft was believed to have crashed in the sea or jungle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;46 years later in 1991 the wreckage was discovered by the indigenous Orang Asli people in the jungle of Kuala Pilah. Following subsequent numerous expeditions to the crash site by military and non-military teams, a privately-funded expedition in 2009 unearthed the remains of the fallen servicemen which have now finally been laid to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A Consolidated Liberator B Mark VI of 356 Squadron landing on three engines at Brown's West Island in the Cocos Islands after completing a sortie on 6 August 1945" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5609/Lost_WWII_RAF_crew_laid_to_rest_in_Malaysia_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Consolidated Liberator B Mark VI of 356 Squadron landing on three engines at Brown's West Island in the Cocos Islands after completing a sortie on 6 August 1945 [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 1945]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reverend (Wing Commander) Jonathan Beach, the RAF chaplain who conducted the graveside service, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is an important occasion for the families of the crew of KL654 and also for all of us as we reflect and honour the ultimate sacrifice made by these men for their country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased that so many family members of the fallen were able to make the trip to Malaysia to witness their burial and say their final goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the families who had made the 13,000-mile (20,900km) round trip looked on, members of the Queen’s Colour Squadron bore the single coffin carrying the remains of the crew to their final resting place on a hillside overlooking the city of Kuala Lumpur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crew were: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pilot - Flight Lieutenant John Selwyn Watts&lt;br&gt;
Co-pilot - Flying Officer Edward Donald Mason&lt;br&gt;
Navigator - Flying Officer William Kenneth Dovey&lt;br&gt;
Air Bomber - Flying Officer John Trevor Bromfield&lt;br&gt;
Wireless Operator/Air Gunner - Flight Sergeant Arthur Turner&lt;br&gt;
Flight Engineer - Flight Sergeant Jack Blakey&lt;br&gt;
Wireless Operator/Air Gunner - Flight Sergeant Raymond Arthur Towell&lt;br&gt;
Air Gunner - Flight Sergeant William Ross&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of the family members the day was about closure and bringing to an end the uncertainty of knowing how their loved ones died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lynn Thornhill, daughter of co-pilot Flying Officer Mason, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My mother never really wanted to talk to me about my father, so I grew up not knowing much about him. Finding out how he died and finally being able to lay him to rest has provided some form of closure for me and my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Ken Taylor Royal Navy, the Defence Adviser at the British High Commission in Kuala Lumpur, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is indeed a very moving and emotional occasion, not just for the families of the servicemen who lost their lives for their country, but I suspect for British people everywhere, including those living here in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These fallen servicemen will now receive the military honours they deserve and their families will have the closure they seek. We are thankful to those who have made this possible, both from the UK and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56556</id>
    <published>2011-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dr-liam-fox-responds-to-defence-committee-report-on-sdsr"/>
    <title>Dr Liam Fox responds to Defence Committee report on SDSR</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since January, the House of Commons Defence Committee (HCDC) has been reviewing the SDSR and the NSS. It has taken oral evidence from sources including the Defence Secretary, the Armed Forces Minister, the Single Service Chiefs, the Vice Chief of the Defence Staff, the Chief of Defence Materiel, the Deputy Chief of Defence Staff (Personnel), and Lord Stirrup (Chief of the Defence Staff when the SDSR was published). The Department has also provided extensive written evidence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HCDC says the report seeks to establish whether the new National Security Council has led to a more coherent and well-defined security policy in terms of the NSS and the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its report, the HCDC agrees with the logic underpinning the SDSR, including the prioritisation of operational requirements for Afghanistan, the adaptable posture, the validity of Future Force 2020, and the strategic priority and national security imperative of dealing with the budget deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the HCDC also says that it is not convinced that, given the current financial climate and the drawdown of capabilities arising from the SDSR, UK Armed Forces will be able do what is asked of them after 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chair of the Committee, the Right Honourable James Arbuthnot MP, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government appears to believe that the UK can maintain its influence while reducing spending in Defence and at the Foreign Office. We do not agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5603/Liam_Fox_responds_to_Defence_Committee_report_on_SDSR_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from J Company, 42 Commando, on a routine patrol around Chah-e Anjir in northern Nad 'Ali, Helmand province, southern Afghanistan [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Dave Hillhouse, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report also expresses concerns over the realisation of what is called ‘Future Force 2020’ - the Government’s intended shape of the Armed Forces from 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Arbuthnot said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Decisions for post-2015 funding will have to be made in the very near future to ensure progress towards Future Force 2020. If the ambition of a real-terms funding increase is not realised, we will have failed our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Defence Review had not been conducted for 12 years, resulting in an equipment programme that was woefully unaffordable. A multi-billion pound deficit was plaguing Defence, and tough, but necessary, decisions had to be taken. As the Committee rightly acknowledges, dealing with the deficit was a national security imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Committee is also right to say that Future Force 2020 is only achievable with extra funding. That is why I announced two weeks ago that the military equipment budget will rise in real terms by over £3bn between 2015 and 2020, with new helicopters being ordered, new money for our armoured vehicles, the carrier programme, and guaranteed spending on the Joint Strike Fighter. Our future equipment programme is no longer an unfunded aspiration, but one that provides real money for real equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We continue to have the fourth largest military budget in the world and the SDSR has put Defence back on a stable footing with highly capable Armed Forces and certainty for our personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pushing through radical reforms to ensure that the mistakes of the past are not repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we have seen in the US, no country is immune to the global financial problems, and even the world’s biggest military power is now grappling with how to make defence cuts and reform for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General Sir David Richards, Chief of the Defence Staff, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SDSR was based on an assessment of the threats we face now and in the future. We have had to take some tough decisions, but as we move towards Future Force 2020 we will remain a formidable fighting force on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will remain capable of sustaining our operations in Afghanistan and Libya before rebalancing will give us the flexibility to maintain our ability to project power across our spheres of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are continually working with our international allies to share operational requirements, including utilising basing and overflight rights for Libya - measures we rightly assessed in the SDSR could be relied upon to mitigate capability gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD will respond formally to the Defence Committee regarding today’s report in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56552</id>
    <published>2011-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dr-liam-fox-resigns"/>
    <title>Dr Liam Fox resigns</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the text of Dr Fox’s letter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear David, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, I have always placed a great deal of importance on accountability and responsibility. As I said in the House of Commons on Monday, I mistakenly allowed the distinction between my personal interest and my government activities to become blurred. The consequences of this have become clearer in recent days. I am very sorry for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also repeatedly said that the national interest must always come before personal interest. I now have to hold myself to my own standard. I have therefore decided, with great sadness, to resign from my post as Secretary of State for Defence - a position which I have been immensely proud and honoured to have held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly proud to have overseen the long overdue reforms to the Ministry of Defence and to our Armed Forces, which will shape them to meet the challenges of the future and keep this country safe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud also to have played a part in helping to liberate the people of Libya, and I regret that I will not see through to its conclusion Britain’s role in Afghanistan, where so much progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I am honoured and humbled to have worked with the superb men and women in our Armed Forces. Their bravery, dedication and professionalism are second-to-none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate all the support you have given me - and will continue to support the vital work of this government, above all in controlling the enormous budget deficit we inherited, which is a threat not just to this country’s economic prosperity but also to its national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to continuing to represent my constituents in North Somerset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours ever,  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liam &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56473</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19th-regiment-royal-artillery-becomes-the-scottish-gunners"/>
    <title>19th Regiment Royal Artillery becomes The Scottish Gunners</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/artillery/regiments/24667.aspx" title="The Highland Gunners"&gt;19th Regiment Royal Artillery&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;) has become The Scottish Gunners as a result of 40th Regiment Royal Artillery (The Lowland Gunners) being put into suspended animation as part of the Army 2020 restructuring process. In addition, 38 (Seringapatam) Battery has been subordinated to &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the only Scottish Artillery Regiment remaining, &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt; becomes The Scottish Gunners in order to continue the proud heritage of both the Highland and Lowland Gunners and retain its links with Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parade, which took place at Bhurtpore Barracks, Tidworth Camp, Wiltshire, on Wednesday 12 December, was attended by the Honorary Regimental Colonel Brigadier Will Bramble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Andrew Dawes, Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think today is significant and I think everyone has really enjoyed what we marked today. It is important for the regiment and their understanding of where it fits into our precious fabric and I think it is important for what we represent to Scotland as well and not just the Highlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Gunner Richard Caffrey " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5561/LAND-2012-218_19_Regt_Name_Change_079g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gunner Richard Caffrey was presented with a new pipe banner for his pipes [Picture: Corporal Richard Cave RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We put a lot of effort into staying connected with the areas which are most important to us and they are a long way away from Wiltshire. The soldiers get up to Scotland on a fairly regular basis and we make room in our programme to enable that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But in terms of identity and being remembered and staying in the conscience of the civic dignitaries and the cities that are important to us, you have got to put the effort in to get something out and we have really tried to do that this year despite being away on operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think the homecoming parades in Dundee and Inverness were very fitting and a great tribute to everything the lads and lassies have put into Afghanistan on behalf of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the soldiers taking a central role in proceedings was Gunner Richard Caffrey, who was the event’s piper and was presented with a new pipe banner for his pipes. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was a brilliant experience being out in front and recognised by the field regiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lance Bombardier Markie " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5562/LAND-2012-218_19_Regt_Name_Change_006g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lance Bombardier Markie taking part in the parade at Bhurtpore Barracks to mark the change of name of 19th Regiment Royal Artillery [Picture: Corporal Richard Cave RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have been playing for 11 years now and as a civilian I competed, and when I joined the Army I wanted to know what it would be like playing in a field pipe band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards a stone with a plaque made from brass cartridges fired on Operation HERRICK 16 was unveiled at the base of the flag poles on the parade square at &lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Dawes explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have captured on the brass plate all of the tours and all the various sub-units involved and I myself have done several of those tours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a great opportunity to get Brigadier Bramble to unveil this for us, because he of course was the commanding officer on one of those previous tours as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="19th Regiment Royal Artillery"&gt;19 Regt RA&lt;/abbr&gt; returned to its base in Wiltshire in October after a demanding but successful deployment as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29026.aspx" title="12th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;12th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; in Helmand province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regiment was employed between March and October this year across Helmand province, supporting 5 battlegroups in its Joint Fires role and operating both on foot and from protected mobility vehicles such as the Jackal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit’s main piece of equipment was the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/equipment/artillery-air-defence/1511.aspx" title="L118 Light Gun"&gt;L118 Light Gun&lt;/a&gt;. During its tour the regiment played a significant role in the mentoring and monitoring of the Afghan National Police and Army and made significant progress in helping to achieve security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Dawes commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think this has been a really important year and really important chapter in our history. I am really proud of everything they have done on tour. We knew it would be a tough tour and we trained very carefully, very intelligently and very hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It came with an impact on our families and our own support networks but they have come through, they have supported everything we have done, and I am proud to say we all came back and are now getting back into family life and need a well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56532</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:56:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-fire-chief-to-lead-efficiency-review-of-fire-and-rescue"/>
    <title>Government fire chief to lead efficiency review of fire and rescue</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the public sector deficit, the government has protected fire and rescue authority funding. Some reduction was unavoidable but it was back-loaded so sensible savings could be made without impacting the service the public gets. Overall, fire and rescue authority spending power reductions - which takes into account grants from central government and council tax, was limited to 2.2% in 2011-12 and 0.5% in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is to be conducted by former firefighter and out-going government Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, in the new year. The review will seek to identify ways fire and rescue authorities can pinpoint savings and improvements without reducing the quality life-saving services that the country’s fire firefighters are known for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many authorities have begun making efficiencies, but there is more that can be done to be more transparent about spending or introduce joint working with other emergency services liked shared senior management structures, improved procurement practices and better use of estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire deaths and incidents are at an all time low. Over the last decade attendance at incidences has fallen by 39% and attendance at fires by 48%. The review will help today’s fire service reflect that change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conducting the review, Sir Ken Knight will talk to key partners to help develop his findings including the Local Government Association, Fire Sector Federation, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association and the Fire Brigades Union, as well as individual authorities and other emergency services. The report is expected to be completed in the spring of 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We all recognise our firefighters perform an incredibly important public service. That is why spending for fire and rescue authorities, like other blue light services, has been protected. But we cannot escape the reality that every bit of the public sector has to help reduce the deficit we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Public safety is always our first concern and this review will make sure no stone has been left unturned in the quest for the most efficient and effective front-line fire service there can be. I know Sir Ken is passionate about the quality of fire and rescue services and he will bring an enormous amount of experience and knowledge to the task.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With over 40 years in the fire service, I know firefighters care deeply about public safety and want to provide the best possible service, but we need to make sure that service is as effective and efficient as possible. Many authorities have made great strides already, but there is much more that can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This review is a real opportunity to get to grips with what is happening on the ground, to highlight best practice and make sure that every option for efficient working is being explored. I will be talking to firefighters, fire authorities and union reps about how we can get there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="terms-of-reference"&gt;Terms of reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review the ways in which fire and rescue authorities may deliver further efficiencies and operational improvements without reducing the quality of front-line services to the public. The review will examine options for savings both within and beyond the current Spending Review period, including through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firefighter training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flexible staffing and crewing arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of retained firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaboration with emergency services and other organisations on service delivery and estates &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sickness management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing of senior staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;locally led mergers and operational collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new fire-fighting technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;preventative approaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with local businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conducting this review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sir Ken Knight will talk to key organisations in the fire sector, including the Local Government Association, the Chief Fire Officers’ Association, the Fire Brigades Union, the Fire Sector Federation, individual fire and rescue authorities and others who Sir Ken deems relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sir Ken will undertake up to 10 visits to a representative range of fire and rescue authorities, including those covering urban and rural areas, and those constituted as metropolitan, county and combined authorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the department will provide Sir Ken with analytical support, in particular in looking at examples of efficiencies from outside of the fire sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will take into account the findings of previous reviews and reports and their recommendations, including the 2002 ‘Independent Review of the Fire Service’ (the Bain Report), the Audit Commission’s 2008 ‘Community Safety National Report’, ‘Rising to the Challenge’, the 2010 Fire Futures review, and the 2011/2012 ‘Independent Review of Police Officer’ and ‘Staff Remuneration and Conditions’ (the Winsor Reports).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="timeline"&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Announce review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;December 2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct field work and analysis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;January to March 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Write and present report to DCLG ministers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spring 2013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3 id="contact-details-for-responses"&gt;Contact details for responses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;firereview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sir-ken-knight-biography"&gt;Sir Ken Knight biography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Ken Knight has been the UK Government’s Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser for England since October 2007, advising ministers and senior officials on policy matters including the structure, organisation and performance of fire and rescue services and crucially, providing advice during major and catastrophic emergencies. He is also responsible for the enforcement Regulatory Reform (Fire Safety) Order 2005 in Crown premises in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56545</id>
    <published>2010-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-outlines-reform-of-the-ministry-of-defence"/>
    <title>Liam Fox outlines reform of the Ministry of Defence</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to an audience at the Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors in Westminster, Dr Fox announced that he is launching a full review of how the Ministry of Defence is run and how the Armed Forces can be reformed to ‘produce more efficient provision of defence capability, and generation and sustainment of operations’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech Dr Fox began by describing the background to the changes, highlighting the fact that the country faces a legacy of debt - the interest on which for the next year alone will exceed the budget of the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that it was a ‘disgrace’ that there had not been a Defence Review for 12 years, despite our Armed Forces being committed to conflicts in the Balkans, Sierra Leone, Iraq and Afghanistan and with enormous changes in the global security picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR) will not simply be a random selection of cuts but an objective process by which the shape of the Armed Forces required will be reached by the end of the decade. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The National Security Council has agreed that the overarching strategic posture should be to address the most immediate threats to our national security while maintaining the ability to identify and deal with emerging ones before they become bigger threats to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This flexible, adaptable posture will maintain the ability to safeguard international peace and security, to deter and contain those who threaten the UK and its interests, and where necessary to intervene on multiple fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will also, crucially, keep our options open for a future in which we can expect our highest priorities to change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said we need to ‘invest in programmes that we will require to put our defence on a sound footing for the years ahead and divest ourselves of the capabilities which we are unlikely to need in a world where the moral climate demands precision weaponry and where the battlespace increasingly embraces the unmanned and cyber domains’, adding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are contrasting cost-savings and the capability implications with the risks that we face in the real global security environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This requires assessing any proposed change in a current programme or platform against a series of criteria, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, the cost-saving in years zero to five, five to ten, and beyond ten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Second, the capability implications - what capability will be lost as a result of this decision and what other assets do we possess that might give us the same or a similar capability?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Third, the operational implications - what operations that we currently carry out, or are likely to carry out, will we be unable to undertake as a result of this change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fourth, the ability to regenerate the capability, at what cost and in what timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And fifth, the risk in the real world that this capability currently protects us from or is likely to protect us from in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In alliance with the SDSR Dr Fox said that the Ministry of Defence itself was in need of reform and to this end he announced that a Defence Reform Unit would be established to carry out the required changes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this he said there are two broad principles that would be followed. The first is a structural reform which will see the Department reorganised into the three pillars of Policy and Strategy, the Armed Forces, and Procurement and Estates. The second is a cultural shift which will see a leaner and less centralised organisation combined with devolved processors which carry greater accountability and transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He stressed that a logical management structure would be ‘foreign policy leading to a defence strategy, then portfolio management which identified capability gaps, followed by specific programme identification and finally physical procurement’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new three pillar structure is designed to make this easier and to stop the constant over-specification and then re-specification of programmes which has led to cost overruns and programme delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work will be led by the Defence Reform Unit. Dr Fox described this as ‘a heavy-hitting steering group of internal and external experts [who] will guide the hard thinking and challenge preconceptions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene will chair this group and will be supported from outside the MOD by Baroness Sheila Noakes, George Iacobescu, Dr David Allen, Björn Conway and Raymond McKeeve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, it will be supported by a civil service implementation team with a remit to complete their blueprint for reform by September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also announced that there will be a review of how the Armed Forces undertake the tasks of force generation and sustainability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to challenge some of the fundamental assumptions which drive force generation, such as tour lengths and intervals, taking into account the varying pressures on our personnel resulting from widely varying missions to see if we can update our practices and produce greater efficiency while implementing the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State said he will be asking the First Sea Lord, Admiral Sir Mark Stanhope, the Chief of the Air Staff, Air Chief Marshal Sir Stephen Dalton, and the new Chief of the General Staff, General Sir Peter Wall, to begin this review once the SDSR has been completed, with a view to completing their work by the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Defence Reform Unit will work with the Chief of the Defence Staff and the Service Chiefs to find ways of giving greater devolution for the running of the Services themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Department must get away from the over-centralising tendency that has become the hallmark of the MOD in recent years and said they will also consider whether the current senior rank structure across the Services is appropriate for the post-SDSR world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We cannot demand efficiency from the lower ranks while exempting those at the top,” Dr Fox said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded by saying that taken together the SDSR and these changes represent a radical agenda for change and show how the Government is committed to governing not in their own interest, but in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56544</id>
    <published>2010-06-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2010-06-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liam-fox-nato-support-crucial-to-building-afghan-forces"/>
    <title>Liam Fox: NATO support crucial to building Afghan forces</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He confirmed Afghanistan as the highest foreign policy priority of the new British Coalition Government, and the top priority for the Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the last day of his first NATO meeting in Brussels, Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Government supports both the mission and the counter-insurgency strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I encourage allies to demonstrate strategic patience and give time for the counter-insurgency strategy to work, but stress the need to be able to show significant progress, consolidating ISAF’s hold in central Helmand, and accelerating the training of the Afghan security forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to step up our approach to communicating the vital importance of the mission in Afghanistan. We need to produce a stronger narrative alongside the political leadership we are providing to ensure that our troops get the support they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that the NATO Training Mission is key to ISAF’s strategy for transition, to ensure the Afghans can take the lead in securing their own country in future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;General McChrystal told this meeting that the Afghan National Security Forces [ANSF] are making quick progress in terms of training, but we still have some way to go in terms of improving the Afghan National Police and getting the numbers and quality of training up to the level we require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the vital role of the training mission. We will assess whether we can contribute more and urge others to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let me be direct: we are aware of the difficulties that some countries face in sending combat troops - politically and even constitutionally. However, there is no excuse for any country here not to send trainers to the Afghan mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we fail in the NATO Training Mission it will signify a lack of political will and a failure of moral resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to ensure we can build up that critical mass of the ANSF, so that when we do leave Afghanistan, we leave behind a secure country, and not a security vacuum. There is a moral duty on every member of NATO to contribute to that training mission, and that’s the message I give to our NATO partners today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5594/Liam_Fox-_NATO_support_crucial_to_building_Afghan_forces_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dr Liam Fox (right) meets NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, in Brussels [Picture: NATO, 2010]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox welcomed progress that is beginning to be made on planning for transition, in advance of the Kabul Conference in July:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important to ensure that both ISAF contributors and the Government of Afghanistan are involved in developing the plan for transition and that the process should be transparent, allowing ISAF partners to communicate progress towards transition to domestic audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Security criteria should be the most important in assessing readiness for transition. Though some level of governance and development is essential for delivering security, we must not set the bar too high. Governance and development efforts will continue through and beyond transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox also reaffirmed that NATO remains the most important strategic relationship for the United Kingdom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NATO is the core of the security and defence of all its members, on both sides of the Atlantic. It is the UK’s instrument of first resort for collective security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why NATO remains so important and so successful is its ability to change as risks and threats evolve. Afghanistan is one example of a task that would have been inconceivable a decade ago. Then the alliance was being told to go out of area or out of business. Today, it is very much in business but facing even greater challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox emphasised that NATO has primacy in terms of Europe’s security and the starting point should be that the EU only acts militarily when NATO cannot or chooses not to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I recognise, of course, that there will be occasions when it is appropriate for the EU to intervene but the EU should avoid duplicating the functions NATO already performs and the capabilities it already possesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In today’s economic climate, the last thing any Defence Minister needs to put to his or her Finance Minister or Generals is a case for militarily unnecessary duplication. NATO and the EU need the strongest possible links and what matters most is what works best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox expressed concern over the state of NATO’s finances but said that he was encouraged by the Secretary General’s report to members which made it clear that much has been done to bring these under proper control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During two days of meetings in NATO Headquarters, Defence Ministers discussed NATO reform, resources, capabilities and missile defence, and met in ISAF and KFOR formats to discuss Afghanistan and Kosovo. There were also meetings of the NATO-Ukraine Commission, the NATO-Georgia Commission and the Nuclear Planning Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the margins of the formal meetings, Dr Fox met the NATO Secretary General and the Defence Ministers of the Czech Republic, Estonia, Norway, Denmark, Poland, the Netherlands, France, Afghanistan, Canada, Turkey, Portugal, Latvia, Australia, the United States and Hungary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
