<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60311</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/clear-up-initiative-saving-economy-millions-by-reopening-roads-quicker"/>
    <title>Clear-up initiative saving economy millions by reopening roads quicker</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An initiative to improve incident clear-up times is saving the economy tens of millions of pounds annually.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motorists and the economy are seeing huge benefits from a government-led initiative to reopen motorways and roads quickly following major incidents, Roads Minister Stephen Hammond announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;’ (collision, lead, evaluate, act and reopen) initiative - launched by the Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) last year to improve incident clear-up times – is helping to save the economy tens of millions of pounds annually, with even more savings to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key achievement has been the success of 38 &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;/police-funded 3D laser scanners which allow police forces to capture evidence quickly following collisions - helping to reopen major roads and motorways more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show an average time saving of 44 minutes per investigation – a 5 minute improvement on test estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other initiatives include the launch of a new hands-free smart phone app that notifies users of incidents and congestion, as well as the planned roll out of incident screens to shield collisions and prevent rubber necking. Time savings associated with screens alone can be up to several hundred thousand pounds per incident.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is confident these measures will help reduce the estimated £750 million cost to the economy that incidents cause on the strategic road network in England annually.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Minister Stephen Hammond said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more frustrating than being stuck in a traffic jam for hours on end.  There is also the shocking cost of those lost hours for our economy. That is why we are improving the clear-up of incidents so we can get our motorways and major roads re-opened as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are now witnessing even greater than expected time savings as a result of the roll out of laser scanning programme. This and other elements of the initiative, such as the use of incident screens, will help to keep traffic moving and save the economy tens of millions of pounds a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very encouraged by the cooperation shown by the Highways Agency, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Police and other emergency services, and fully expect these initiatives to result in further time and cost savings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assistant Chief Constable Sean White, lead on collision investigations for the Association of Chief Police Officers (&lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This equipment allows police to manage critical events in a more efficient way and present the most accurate and detailed evidence to criminal, civil and coroners’ courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The time saved by using this technology is more economically friendly and reduces disruption on the roads, while allowing for thorough investigations to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the success of this equipment, which has reduced delays for road users and proved extremely important in police investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Highways Agency signing a memorandum of understanding to facilitate data sharing about heavy goods vehicles. Studies have shown this type of vehicle is involved in a high proportion of the longest incidents. &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working closely with operators to make sure problems are addressed   &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the roll out by the Highways Agency of new towing equipment (load cells) to remove heavier vehicles obstructing live lanes and spill kits to clear spillages from motorway lanes. Time savings associated with the use of load cells have been estimated at several million pounds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the production and distribution of a &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; booklet to emergency responders outlining the roles and responsibilities of key organisations involved in managing incidents on the strategic road network. The Highways Agency has also produced a film reinforcing the booklet’s messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of emergency response guidance, training and learning to take on board &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the revision of the 2007 Road Death Investigation Manual (RDIM) – the guiding doctrine of &lt;abbr title="Association of Chief Police Officers"&gt;ACPO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the 43 police forces of England and Wales to investigate and report on collisions that have resulted in a death. This is expected to be published in early 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report which sets out the next steps of &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; is currently being finalised for publication next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="laser-scanners"&gt;Laser scanners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laser Scanning Technology (LST) saves time by quickly making a 3D image of the whole incident scene, rather than investigators painstakingly surveying multiple sections of a scene. This digital image of the site can then be viewed on a computer screen remotely allowing investigators to take measurements of where vehicles are in relation to each other and examine other important evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009, the Highways Agency carried out an independent trial of 3D laser scanning technology using results from separate trials conducted by the Metropolitan Police Service and Humberside Police. The trials found that on average using laser scanners saved a total of 39 minutes on investigation time per incident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;38 laser scanners were funded by &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Police for use by 27 police authorities at a cost of £4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latest figures relate to information compiled from incidents over 4 months from forces using them on the strategic road network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="clear"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2010 the Police, Highways Agency, Ambulance and Fire Services, &lt;abbr title="Vehicle and Operator Services Agency"&gt;VOSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and related sponsoring departments came together to review evidence and knowledge about the handling of motorway incidents, and to make recommendations for improvement  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/review-of-investigation-and-closure-procedures-for-motorway-incidents-preliminary-report/review-of-investigation-closure-procedures-motorway-incidents.pdf"&gt;resultant report, published in May 2011 as the ‘Review of investigation and closure procedures for motorways incidents’ (PDF, 345KB)&lt;/a&gt;, made 10 recommendations and came together as the &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; initiative. The recommendations included further analytical work and some more immediate actions around, for example, supporting the wider roll out of laser scanning technology for the police to assist in speeding up incident investigation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congestion on the strategic road network is estimated to cost the economy £3 billion each year, 25% of which is caused by incidents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single incident that closes a 3 lane motorway for 4 hours can cost several million pounds in lost time, and there are some 80,000 incidents that impact at least one motorway lane each year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If &lt;abbr title="Collision, Lead, Evaluate, Act and Reopen"&gt;CLEAR&lt;/abbr&gt; makes just 5% difference to the cost of congestion on the &lt;abbr title="Strategic Road Network"&gt;SRN&lt;/abbr&gt; it could save over £30 million.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="incident-screens"&gt;Incident screens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 105 sets of incident screens which will be made available for use by the Highways Agency next year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each set has 30 screens which are loaded onto purpose-built trailers and can screen up to 75 metres if used end-to-end (the individual screens are approximately 2.1 by two metres high)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They cost £2.3 million with each set costing £22,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="smart-phone-app"&gt;Smart phone app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	The Highways Agency app received 5,000 hits within the first 2 months of its launch. Further &lt;a rel="external" href="http://press.highways.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Hands-free-traffic-app-makes-Highways-Agency-data-available-to-road-users-ready-for-summer-67e24.aspx"&gt;information is available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spill-kits"&gt;Spill kits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Highways Agency"&gt;HA&lt;/abbr&gt; traffic officers will be equipped with spill kits to clear up small spillages such as fuel or other fluids which leak onto the carriageways from vehicles. The spill kits will absorb small spills and will allow the road to be safely re-opened while reducing damage to the carriageway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="load-cells"&gt;Load Cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load cells will be fitted to the tow straps used by traffic officers and will allow them to clear live lanes - moving heavier or damaged vehicles to the nearest place of safety.  The load cell acts as a strain gauge and will ensure that the safe towing load is not exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60863</id>
    <published>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:02:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/british-forces-mark-christmas-in-helmand"/>
    <title>British Forces mark Christmas in Helmand </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British forces in southern Afghanistan mark Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;British forces serving in southern Afghanistan have been marking Christmas at military bases across Helmand Province today (25 December).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities took place as the troops completed a full day of operational duties.  Many soldiers from the UK-led Task Force Helmand spent the day on patrol in support of the Afghan security forces, yet still most found time to open presents and ring home – and enjoy a freshly-prepared Christmas lunch with all the trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-post"&gt;Christmas post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last-minute festive cheer was provided by the Post and Courier Squadron as tonnes of mail arrived at a number of forward locations, delivered by Chinook helicopter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing last minute festive cheer on Christmas morning, 78 sacks of post (1 tonne) arrived by helicopter in Main Operating Base (&lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt;) Lashkar Gah – home to the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/structure/29027.aspx" title="4th Mechanized Brigade"&gt;4th Mechanized Brigade&lt;/a&gt; (‘Black Rats’) headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5819/Xmas_post_delivery_helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Mail bags containing Christmas parcels being dropped off at a Patrol base in Helmand Province, Afghanistan&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a chilly Christmas morning, in &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; over 100 soldiers and civilians took part in the ‘Lash Dash’ 5km run around the base.  Many completed the course in fancy dress, with proceeds from the event split between two charities: the Lashkar Gah Orphanage and The Black Rat Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the male and female winners were Danish soldiers. The Brits fared better in the fancy dress competition with Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant’s General Corps, Royal Military Police) winning by running dressed as a well-wrapped Christmas present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5818/LashDash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Winner of the 'Lash Dash'. Cpl Calum Frazer (Adjutant General Corps, Royal Military Police) won the fancy dress prize for running as a Christmas present&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="working-day"&gt;Working day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, is another working day for all military here in Helmand. As the sun rose on Christmas morning, troops from the Royal Dragoon Guards and the Royal Military Police set off on patrol to the Provincial Police Headquarters to train Afghan Police. The ‘train the trainer’ course sees Afghan Police qualifying to teach police skills. This will allow British troops to step back as the Afghan Security Forces take the lead in training their own forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="christmas-lunches-and-all-the-trimmings"&gt;Christmas lunches and all the trimmings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full Christmas lunch, including all the trimmings, was served in the cookhouses of Camp Bastion, &lt;abbr title="Main Operating Base"&gt;MOB&lt;/abbr&gt; Lashkar Gah and patrol bases across Helmand. Even the troops manning the security towers or sangars surrounding Camp Bastion were not forgotten and enjoyed personal deliveries of hot food.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion." src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5820/Xmas_dinner_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Flight Lieutenant Leah Parle from Banbury (left) and Signaller Alex Williams from Newport, enjoying Christmas Dinner in Camp Bastion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Baldwin kitchen manager from KBR in Camp Bastion said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today is the full Christmas celebration for the troops in Bastion.  This includes a traditional Christmas lunch consisting of roast beef, pork, turkey, sprouts, roast potatoes and pudding and mince pies. We are cooking for roughly about 4,000 people - ranging from 140 joints of beef, 200 turkeys, 120 gammons – that’s what it take to feed these guys.  Also using 40 boxes of brussel spouts, 150 bags of potatoes, it’s on a massive scale.  It also includes litres of gravy, tomato soup – it’s a big operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="presents-for-all-serving-personnel"&gt;Presents for all serving personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5821/Xmas_presents_in_Helmand.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Warrant Offficer Class 2 Andy Morris, Lance Corporal Thelma Goddard and Lance Corporal Rory Mortimer opening parcels on Christmas morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing a little Christmas cheer to forces overseas every year is the UK based charity called &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4uThanks!"&gt;uk4uThanks!&lt;/a&gt;  This is an organisation funded by money donated by members of the public. The presents (affectionately known as the ‘square stocking’) act as a gift from the nation to all those serving in the UK Armed Forces overseas away from their families and loved ones on Christmas Day.  The boxes, containing a host of goodies from business sponsors and bought with money donated from members of the public, were delivered in time to be opened on Christmas Day.  Much speculation abounds as to the contents of the boxes and it is never a disappointment as much thought is put into providing amusing and useful gifts away from home at Christmas time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60858</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:43:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>"Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New style local settlement to reward striving councils with more income.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles spelled out 50 sensible savings, a Council Tax freeze and a fair funding deal as the “right road” for councils to protect residents and local services, as a major shake up of local finance was initiated today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister signalled the watershed moment for councils as he unveiled a new look local government finance settlement that will reward councils that strive to improve their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dramatic shift in spending power from Whitehall to the town hall means an estimated 70% of council income will now be raised locally compared to 56% under the centrally distributed ‘begging-bowl’ formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013 councils can channel this greater local control into encouraging local jobs and local firms via a new business rate retention incentive that rewards them for growth. It could potentially add £10 billion to the economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, councils account for a quarter of all public spending - with English councils still spending £114 billion - so it is vital they continue to play their part tackling the inherited budget deficit by making sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help councils in that regard a document containing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;50 practical ways to make sensible savings&lt;/a&gt; was published today. It shows how a culture change by councils can unearth significantly more taxpayer savings and help make services more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must keep doing their bit to tackle the inherited budget deficit because they account for a quarter of all public spending and still get through over £114 billion of taxpayers money each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement is a fair funding deal that will reward councils ready to strive for their communities and gives them another year to get their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must do 3 things to get on the right road for their residents: put our fair funding deal to work; do every single one of our 50 ways to save; and accept our Council Tax freeze offer. Councils that cry wolf without having done all of this are letting their residents down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils that put their thinking caps on now can save precious taxpayer pennies next year by cutting out waste and transforming frontline services that vulnerable people rely on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s fair funding deal arms councils with an average spending power of £2,240 per household. Local authorities have been protected from further spending reductions for 2013 to 2014. Overall the average spending power reduction for councils in 2013 to 2014 is expected to be limited to just 1.7% per household, less than last year’s comparable figure of 3.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe this important concession gives councils the time they need to transform service delivery, build up their local business rate income, improve procurement and comprehensively complete the suggested 50 savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total start-up funding assessment for councils 2013 to 2014 apportions £26 billion in a fair and sustainable way that ensures the smallest reductions for the councils most reliant on government support. More weighting has been given to areas with the highest levels of assessed need. For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is setting aside an extra £450 million over the next 2 years to help local government in England to freeze their Council Tax, equivalent to a 1% rise. A third year’s combined Council Tax freeze is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government confirmed today that where a council rejects the freeze, the majority will have to secure electoral agreement through a ‘local tax lock’ referendum to hike band D bills by more than 2%. Smaller authorities with a track record of low Council Tax will be given slightly more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘50 ways to save’ include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing back offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting Community Budgets to bring staff and money together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using transparency to cut waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clamping down on corporate charge cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting special spending controls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling the £2 billion of local fraud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising £16 billion of non-school reserves creatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve collection rates to reduce the £2.4 billion of uncollected Council Tax across England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage direct debit and e-billing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve property management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close subsidised council canteens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing senior pay and posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut spending on consultants and agency staff which had risen to £4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stop translating documents into foreign languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut expensive travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce printing costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hire out the town hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; for the full list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 20 December 2012, the day after the provisional Local Government Finance Settlement, Local Government Minister Brandon Lewis MP hosted a teleconference call for local authorities and fire &amp;amp; rescue services, fielding more than 25 questions from 200 callers. You can listen to the call &lt;a rel="external" href="http://bit.ly/Ul5u6X"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 to 2014 spending power calculation includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£26.07 billion start up funding assessment (which includes £10.9 billion of locally retained business rates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£23.9 billion in Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£859 million for NHS funding to support social care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£661 million via New Homes Bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£240 million for 2013 to 2014 Council Tax freeze grant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition local authorities will also benefit from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£112 million via the Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£33.5 million via New Burdens for Council Tax Support in 2013 to 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/spending-power-by-local-authority"&gt;Spending power data by local authority for 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;No authority will see a spending power reduction of more than 8.8% because of decisions taken by ministers to make an efficiency support grant available. The ‘per household’ figures are calculated using total spending power a combination of the new start up funding assessment and Council Tax, and the number of dwellings by Council Tax band for each administrative area in England. The counts are calculated from data for England extracted from the Valuation Office Agency’s database on 12 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-and-the-local-government-finance-settlement-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;plain English guide&lt;/a&gt; to cut through Whitehall jargon and explain the new settlement system is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a period of statutory consultation on the settlement which runs to 15 January 2013. Ministers will then finalise their proposals and the settlement for 2013 to 2014 will be debated in Parliament in February in time for councils to set their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement committed the government to relinquishing control over excessive Council Tax increases and giving that democratic power directly to local communities. This was legislated for through the Localism Act. The government has today published the Council Tax principles it is proposing for 2013 to 2014. Council Tax increases would trigger a referendum, if they exceed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2% for most principal authorities; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 (which ever is higher) in the case of shire district councils, police and crime commissioners and fire and rescue authorities that set the lowest quartile of Council Tax in their class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final principles for 2013 to 2014 will be set out in a report for the approval of the House of Commons early next year, at the same time as the final report on the local government finance settlement. No equivalent principles are being proposed for town and parish councils for 2013 to 2014, although they may in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical data for the 2013-14 Local Government Finance Settlement can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;Local Government Finance site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have been protected with savings back loaded to allow time for sensible savings; they have also benefited from the protection to local government in 2013 to 2014. In addition the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, has been asked to carry out a review to pinpoint ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money. The government intends to announce the breakdown of £140 million of capital grant money to fire and rescue authorities. The money for 2013 to 2015 will be distributed by a combination of formula and for projects to fire and rescue authorities that have been successful through bidding. All fire and rescue authorities will receive some capital funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60315</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T10:07:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-warship-spends-christmas-on-operations"/>
    <title>Royal Navy warship spends Christmas on operations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sailors of HMS Monmouth keeping the oceans safe from criminals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While their families celebrate Christmas at home, the crew of  the Plymouth-based Type 23 frigate, will be spending Christmas engaged in countering piracy, smuggling and similar illegal activity. The ship, also known as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="the Black Duke"&gt;the Black Duke&lt;/a&gt; after its traitor namesake, is part of a coalition naval force policing the Gulf and keeping crucial trade routes safe for the UK’s imports and exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of the busy programme, members of the crew have found some time to prepare for the festivities with both the chaplain and the chefs limbering-up for the seasonal cheer and religious service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Chef Paul Gough said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve stocked the freezers in anticipation that we’ll be getting through more than two hundred pounds of turkey, beef and gammon for Christmas lunch; and yes, we’ve also made sure we’ve got plenty of sprouts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5807/Xmas_operations_room__HMS_Monmouth_2012.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It's beginning to look at lot like Christmas in HMS Monmouth's operations room&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reverend Andrew Allcock, the ship’s chaplain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas is often a time for both celebration and reflection – the latter probably more so this year as we are away from home. It’s my hope that most people on board will have an opportunity to do both with our Christmas services including a traditional midnight communion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship will be patrolling the Gulf region until her return to the UK in the spring. While principal tasks on this deployment involve intercepting and boarding suspect vessels, HMS Monmouth is also ready and equipped to provide humanitarian aid or mount an evacuation in the case of war or natural disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60856</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T09:14:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T09:14:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-baroness-warsi-statement-on-the-murder-of-bashir-ahmed-bilour"/>
    <title>FCO Minister Baroness Warsi statement on the murder of Bashir Ahmed Bilour</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Senior Minister of State Baroness Warsi expresses her sadness at the murder of Pakistani minister Bashir Ahmed Bilour on Saturday.
 </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was deeply saddened to hear of the death of Bashir Ahmed Bilour and my thoughts are with his family and friends and those of the others killed and wounded in this vicious attack, an attack which I and the UK Government utterly condemns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr Bilour was a courageous and vocal opponent of extremism and refused to be silenced by those who threatened him.  His absence will be felt keenly in Pakistani politics. His enduring legacy will be the many people he inspired to speak out against terror and work to build a peaceful, democratic society for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60828</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:06:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-shocked-by-violence-in-tana-river-kenya"/>
    <title>UK shocked by violence in Tana River, Kenya</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds: "My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds comments following renewed outbreak of violence in Kenya’s Tana River Delta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked at the tragic news of renewed violence in the Tana River Delta area of Kenya this morning and the high casualties reported. My sympathies go to the families of those who have been killed and wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish to reiterate the UK government’s deep concern at this ongoing violence, which we have made clear to the Government of Kenya at the highest levels. I urge restraint on all sides and dialogue between the communities. It is imperative for the underlying grievances behind this conflict to be addressed urgently. The UK continues to support efforts towards reconciliation in Kenya.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60830</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:23:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/greater-freedom-for-local-councils-to-prevent-unauthorised-traveller-sites--2"/>
    <title>Greater freedom for local councils to prevent unauthorised traveller sites</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposals to give councils more freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites have been published for consultation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils would be given greater freedom to stop unauthorised traveller sites being set up and prevent long, drawn-out stalemates like Dale Farm, under proposals published for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/changes-to-temporary-stop-notices-consultation"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="temporary-stop-notices"&gt;Temporary Stop Notices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals would allow councils greater freedom to use temporary stop notices in relation to caravans that are in breach of planning control, and are used as a person’s main residence. This would be backed up with the potential for heavy fines of up to £20,000 on indictment or an unlimited fine on summary conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the current system councils are constrained as to when they can use these powers against caravans that are main residences, which can result in long delays and high costs to stop unauthorised development of this kind.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Brandon Lewis said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long a small minority have abused the planning system, often at the expense of local communities who are forced to put up with unauthorised development in their area. This government believes in fair play, with everyone abiding by the same rules. These proposals will assist local councils in taking effective action against those who don’t.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-powers"&gt;Stronger powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporary Stop Notices enable councils to take action with immediate effect against unauthorised development without having to wait three days for a Stop Notice, or 28 days for an enforcement notice to come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to the outcome of the consultation, today’s proposals would remove restrictions on the use of temporary stop notices so councils can act quickly against new unauthorised sites, and save on the costs of enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60566</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T14:06:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-diamond-arrives-home-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Diamond arrives home in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy warship HMS Diamond has returned home to Portsmouth today following her maiden deployment to the Middle East.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers" title="Type 45 Destroyers"&gt;Type 45 destroyer&lt;/a&gt; sailed more than 31,000 miles (50,000 kilometres) on security and counter-piracy patrols in the Indian Ocean, Gulf of Oman and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; left Portsmouth in June shortly after launching the nation’s Diamond Jubilee celebrations with a ceremonial entry into the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Portsmouth" title="Portsmouth Naval Base"&gt;naval base&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After travelling through the Mediterranean she transited the Suez Canal before taking over from sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Daring" title="HMS Daring"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Daring&lt;/a&gt;. Diamond then spent the following 5 months as part of the Combined Task Force, a 27-nation partnership promoting security in the area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship worked with the French Carrier Group in the Mediterranean and three United States Carrier Strike Groups (&lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the Middle East, including the escort of the US carriers through the Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s fighter controllers exercised with the US Navy’s F18 Hornets and controlled F22 Raptor and F15 Strike Eagle aircraft from the United States Air Force. The ship’s Lynx aircraft also demonstrated its ability to conduct air intercepts for the task groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also exercised with the navies of Australia, Canada, France, Kuwait, and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While conducting counter-piracy operations the ship’s specialist embarked military force carried out assurance visits to local fishermen and traders and held boarding training with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Commander Ian Clarke is greeted by his family" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5814/FX120552013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond's Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, is greeted by his wife, Joanne, and daughter Rebecca, aged 3 [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Guy Pool, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diamond’s Commanding Officer, Commander Ian Clarke, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have achieved a tremendous amount this deployment and I pay tribute to my fantastic ship’s company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have provided reassurance in the Middle East, under the Combined Maritime Forces, worked closely with regional allies and three US &lt;abbr title="Carrier Strike Groups"&gt;CSGs&lt;/abbr&gt; and really pushed the air defence capability of these fantastic new destroyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamond also worked alongside other &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; assets, such as minehunters based out of Bahrain and their support ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Bay-Class-Landing-Ships/RFA-Cardigan-Bay" title="RFA Cardigan Bay"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Cardigan Bay&lt;/a&gt;. Helicopters of the Fleet Air Arm were also involved - with the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Sea-King-ASaC" title="Sea King Mk7 Airborne Surveillance and Control"&gt;Sea King Mark 7&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/854" title="854 Squadron"&gt;854 Squadron&lt;/a&gt; making its first ever landing on a Type 45 - while Merlin aircraft also interacted with Diamond at sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as time at sea in the region, she has visited Bahrain, Jordan, Kuwait, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, as well as Gibraltar and Crete and the cities of Athens and Barcelona while on transit to and from the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer David Turner said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a busy few months but working with the other navies has been enjoyable, as have all the fascinating places we have visited. Although what we have achieved has been immensely rewarding, after six months away it is good to know that we are back in time to be reunited with our loved ones for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commodore The Hon Michael Cochrane, Commander Portsmouth Flotilla, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We welcome Diamond back after what has been an exciting and high-profile deployment for the ship’s company, whose work has seen them entering new fields of interest for the air defence community. I am sure they will enjoy their well-earned period of leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond is the third of the UK’s fleet of six Type 45 destroyers. She was launched in 2007, arrived in Portsmouth in the autumn of 2010 and was commissioned in the spring of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60750</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:56:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"/>
    <title>Planning practice guidance should be simpler</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An external review of planning practice guidance has recommended rationalising advice and making it easier to use.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review group, lead by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system but did not review planning policy. They were not tasked with revaluating green belt policy or other countryside protections, which continue to be safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that the existing guidance is unwieldy in its current form and recommends that it be shorter but retain key elements, and be more accessible to be useful to everyone using the planning system. They stated that guidance is important to ensuring planning decisions are properly informed but should not place undue burdens on users of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that a vast range of materials are being considered guidance, and that ‘living documents’ intended to be updated on a regular basis had not been amended since publication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; to consider the group’s recommendations was launched today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is very clear that the old way of doing things is no longer fit for purpose. We have made recommendations for a modern web-based resource that is clear, up-to-date, coherent and easily usable, not just by planners and developers, but the public too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very grateful to the group for all the work they have done on this. We will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and I would urge other users of the planning system to have their say by responding to the consultation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group consists of Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones. They are sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;External review of government planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;Review of planning practice guidance - consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt;, Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60139</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:15:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-choir-a-year-with-the-military-wives"/>
    <title>The Choir: a year with the Military Wives</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Choirmaster Gareth Malone and key members of the Military Wives Choir reflect on their extraordinary journey in a Christmas Day television special.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, Gareth Malone went to the military base at Chivenor to set up a choir for the wives left at home alone while their men are on duty for months at a time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html" title="The Choir: a year with the Military Wives"&gt;the Christmas Day show&lt;/a&gt;, we hear from Gareth and key members of the choir as they reflect on their extraordinary journey including their performance of a song, specially written by royal composer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paulmealor.com/" title="Paul Mealor website"&gt;Paul Mealor&lt;/a&gt;, at The Royal Albert Hall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rehearsals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5783/choirpractise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Gareth Malone and Military Wives rehearse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film shows the women as they launch their first single, which topped the Christmas charts, visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="10 Downing Street website"&gt;10 Downing Street&lt;/a&gt;, perform at the Golden Jubilee and win a Classical Brit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also hear of the legacy of the original choir - the setting up of a charitable foundation that provides the support for a growing network of over 60 military wives choirs in bases across the UK, Europe and the Falkland Islands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soloist Sam Stevenson says: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was Gareth’s dream and it came true and not many people can say their dreams have come true in life. I don’t even think I could express to Gareth how grateful we all are for it, it’s just, he’s really changed our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2012/52/the-choir.html"&gt;The Choir: A year with the Military Wives&lt;/a&gt; will be on Christmas Day, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo" title="BBC Two website"&gt;BBC2&lt;/a&gt; at 8.45pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60323</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:04:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-gives-blueprint-to-potential-infrastructure-partners"/>
    <title>MOD gives blueprint to potential infrastructure partners</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Defence Infrastructure Organisation (DIO), the Ministry of Defence's (MOD) property and services provider, has issued the document which allows the three short-listed teams to prepare detailed bids to potentially become its Strategic Business Partner (SBP).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Invitation to Negotiate (&lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt;) asks each team to further prove it can provide the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; with a proposal to bring the right skills and expertise, before the organisation makes a final decision regarding its preferred option next summer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organisation, which manages the delivery of infrastructure projects and services for the UK Armed Forces and its civilian support staff, will introduce new ways of working from Spring 2013. However, procuring a &lt;abbr title="Strategic Business Partner"&gt;SBP&lt;/abbr&gt; could realise further savings to benefit Defence as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Manley, Chief Executive, &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s principle objective is to support our military personnel in its Standing Commitments and in preparing for operations. We do this by providing and maintaining the places where they live, work and train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In addition &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; is central to supporting the Government’s wider objectives in construction, property management and the delivery of supporting the services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Changing the way we deliver infrastructure services offers a real opportunity to build a leading-edge infrastructure delivery organisation that will serve the needs of our Armed Forces long into the future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are striving to create a high-performing and innovative enterprise. Our search for a Strategic Business Partner is expected to extend our capability by allowing &lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; further access to private sector skills and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Defence Infrastructure Organisation"&gt;DIO&lt;/abbr&gt; has been working to ensure that the &lt;abbr title="Invitation to Negotiate"&gt;ITN&lt;/abbr&gt; provides a robust platform to effectively explore the use of private sector expertise. However, a contract will only be awarded if it can be found to provide value for money to the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; and the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a robust procurement exercise, launched in May 2012, three teams were selected to participate in the next stage of the competition. They consist of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.telerealtrillium.com/" title="Telereal Trillium website"&gt;Telereal Trillium&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.kpmg.com/uk/en/pages/default.aspx" title="KPMG website"&gt;KPMG&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.macegroup.com/" title="Mace website"&gt;Mace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.serco.com/" title="Serco website"&gt;Serco&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dtz.com/UK" title="DTZ website"&gt;DTZ&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bechtel.com/" title="Bechtel website"&gt;Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.capita.co.uk/Pages/default.aspx" title="Capita website"&gt;Capita&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.urscorp.com/" title="URS website"&gt;URS&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.paconsulting.co.uk/" title="PA Consulting website"&gt;PA Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60310</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/david-cameron-visits-troops-in-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>David Cameron visits troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Prime Minister praised armed forces success during visit to Camp Bastion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister flew into Afghanistan yesterday morning, 20 December. He visited Camp Bastion, where he met with military commanders before joining troops for an early Christmas dinner and a carol service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s visit came a day after he told &lt;abbr title="Members of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Parliament that troop numbers will almost halve to around 5,200 by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron meets troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5805/PMmeetstroops.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;David Cameron visits Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told journalists on the trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is still a difficult and dangerous place but we’ve made real progress. It is tough, it is difficult, and we’ve paid a high price but their efforts have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander Task Force Helmand, reiterated confidence in the growing capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is now absolutely appropriate we hand more and more control over to the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Cameron met troops who he praised for their service in Afghanistan and thanked them for making the country “prouder than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a message to the armed forces, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well it is a good time to come to Afghanistan and say a really big thank you to our troops for everything they do, and particularly at Christmas time when they’re away from loved ones.  But I think it’s an opportunity to say to all our forces all over the world…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You make us incredibly proud; we’re always proud of you, and this year perhaps prouder than ever for your extraordinary work in Afghanistan, for the amazing things you do over the whole of Africa to keep us safe from terrorism and piracy, for the extraordinary things you did at the Olympics where the military stepped up, put a smiling face on the greatest show on earth, won a lot of medals too and made the country very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military really are the best of the best and we can’t thank them enough for what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60313</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:29:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/change-of-governor-of-the-falklands-islands"/>
    <title>Change of Governor of the Falklands Islands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Mr Colin Roberts CVO has been appointed Governor of the Falkland Islands and Commissioner of South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will succeed Mr Nigel Robert Haywood CVO, who will be transferring to another Diplomatic Service appointment. Mr Roberts will take up his appointment during April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Roberts joined the FCO in 1989. He is currently Director for Eastern Europe and Central Asia having served as Director for the Overseas Territories from  2008-2012. His FCO career has covered a wide range of roles including European Union affairs, security policy, Eastern Europe and the Far East as well as the Overseas Territories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment as Governor of the Falkland Islands, Mr Roberts has said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be appointed as Governor of the Falkland Islands and HM Commissioner for South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands. I am a great admirer of the achievements of the people of the Falkland Islands. I look forward to working with the community and their elected representatives for a secure and prosperous future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="curriculum-vitae"&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full name:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Colin Roberts&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Married to:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Camilla&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Children:&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oliver (b. 2002), Alexander (b.2004)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012 – present&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director, Eastern Europe and Central Asia Directorate&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008 – 2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Director, Overseas Territories Directorate, Her Majesty’s Commissioner, British Antarctic Territory and Her Majesty’s Commissioner, British Indian Ocean Territory&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2004 – 2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Her Majesty’s Ambassador, Vilnius&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001 – 2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, Political Counsellor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1998 – 2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head, EU Common Foreign and Security Policy Department&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1997 – 1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paris, First Secretary for Politico-Military Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995 – 1996&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head of Justice and Home Affairs Section, European Union Department (Internal)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Head of Gibraltar Section, European Union Department (Internal)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1993 – 1994&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, First Secretary for Political Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990 – 1992&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tokyo, Second Secretary for Economic and Financial Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Economic Advisers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1989 – 1990&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FCO, Desk officer for the Republic of Ireland&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60283</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-for-transports-boost-to-train-builders"/>
    <title>Department for Transport's boost to train builders</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New train carriages procured by Southern Railway. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train builders have received a year-end boost as the government announces its backing for two new train orders, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of government support, Southern Railway has now procured 40 new carriages from Bombardier based in Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 40 carriages, the government is also supporting Southern’s tendering process for 116 new electric carriages with the option for a further 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our support for Southern will not only boost capacity but help secure British jobs. The deal for the 40 new carriages, helped along by my department, demonstrates the government’s ongoing commitment to invest in Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My officials are working with Southern to accelerate their procurement process for up to 256 carriages because our ambitious electrification plans requires additional rolling stock on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2011 Southern Railway, with government support, announced its plans to buy 130 carriages from Bombardier to run on services in south London, Surrey, Sussex and Kent. Southern expects these will be in service by December 2013. As part of this deal Southern had the option to buy the additional 40 carriages at a later stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July the government announced the biggest programme of rail modernisation since the Victorian era. At the heart of the scheme was the electrification of the Midland Main Line, from London to Sheffield, with additional spurs linking it to the Great Western Main Line and the Port of Southampton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Southern progresses with the procurement, these 116 new vehicles, and potentially 140 more, could initially be used on the Thameslink routes. Once the expected new Thameslink trains are operational these carriages will be moved to the newly electrified routes, which could include the Midland Main Line to Corby and North Transpennine Routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60272</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T17:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T17:04:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/princess-royal-attends-naval-cadets-passing-out-parade"/>
    <title>Princess Royal attends naval cadets' passing out parade</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Her Royal Highness The Princess Royal has attended a parade performed by cadets passing out from Britannia Royal Naval College (BRNC).</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royal.gov.uk/thecurrentroyalfamily/theprincessroyal/theprincessroyal.aspx" title="The Princess Royal"&gt;The Princess Royal&lt;/a&gt;, accompanied by her husband, Vice Admiral Sir Tim Laurence, was the guest of honour at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s final passing-out-parade of the year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rain eased off, and with the Royal Marines band playing festive tunes, the Princess Royal was invited to inspect the cadets and take the salute during the march past. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parade signified the end of 30 weeks intensive training for the 67 Officer Cadets who can now enjoy Christmas with their families before embarking on the next stage of their Royal Navy careers. Among those passing-out were cadets from 10 overseas nations, who regularly send their personnel to &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; for training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanding Officer of &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt;, Captain Jerry Kyd, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We were very honoured to have Her Royal Highness visit us for our final parade of the year. These Cadets have been given a thorough induction into the Royal Navy and worked hard to earn their place on the parade ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Princess Royal chats to cadets" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5796/DSC_0146.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Princess Royal chats to one of the cadets during the parade [Picture: Copyright Craig Keating]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They spent the last nine weeks of their training at sea. Some were assigned to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Illustrious" title="HMS Illustrious"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Illustrious&lt;/a&gt;, while others were on board the fleet flagship, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/the-fleet/ships/assault-ships/hms-bulwark" title="HMS Bulwark"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Bulwark&lt;/a&gt;. Both warships were involved in the Royal Navy’s Cougar 12 deployment working as part of the UK’s Response Force Task Group, exercising with a multitude of other nations in the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was an excellent opportunity for the cadets to see at first hand the Royal Navy in operation, working in partnership with our allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Princess Royal has a long association with the Royal Navy. She holds the rank of Rear Admiral as Chief Commandant for Women in the Royal Navy and has special relationships with &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Submarines/Fleet-Submarines/Trafalgar-Class/HMS-Talent" title="HMS Talent"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Talent&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Assault-Ships/HMS-Albion" title="HMS Albion"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Albion&lt;/a&gt;. The Princess Royal is also Commodore-in-Chief for Portsmouth and last attended a parade at &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2002, when she represented Her Majesty The Queen at Lord High Admiral’s Divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total 237 &lt;abbr title="Britannia Royal Naval College"&gt;BRNC&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and cadets at varying stages of their training were on parade with music provided by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalmarinesbands.co.uk/reference/band_ply.htm" title="The Band of Her Majesty's Royal Marines Plymouth"&gt;Band of Her Majesty’s Royal Marines Plymouth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a period of leave, the College will re-open in January 2013 for what will be the 150th year of Royal Navy officer training in Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
