<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60074</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T18:21:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-regime-harassment-of-iranian-blogger-s-family"/>
    <title>UK condemns regime harassment of Iranian blogger’s family</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sattar Beheshti, a young Iranian citizen, died in detention in early November. Mr Beheshti’s only crime appears to have been using the internet to advocate the defence of human rights. Commenting on reports that Iranian security forces disrupted a family ceremony mourning his death, a  Foreign Office Spokesperson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are dismayed by the Iranian security forces’ harassment of the family of blogger Sattar Beheshti during the mourning ceremony on 13th December to mark his death. Mr Beheshti died in suspicious circumstances while in custody. This is not the first time the family of a victim of the regime has received such treatment, which is completely unacceptable. Iran must respect the family’s right to mourn their loss in peace, as well as make serious attempts to bring those responsible for Mr Beheshti’s death to justice. The impunity enjoyed by agents of the state must end. We reiterate our condolences to Mr Beheshti’s family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60061</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/commonwealth-reform-package-endorsed-by-commonwealth-heads-of-government"/>
    <title>Commonwealth reform package endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A landmark Commonwealth Charter and a package of reforms to modernise and sharpen the impact of the Commonwealth have been endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings to a close discussion on Commonwealth reform which began at the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Perth, Australia, in October 2011, and included consideration of the Eminent Persons Group report A Commonwealth of the People: Time for Urgent Action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreed proposals include a new Commonwealth Charter setting out the core values and aspirations of the Commonwealth and its members, and commitments to strengthen the Secretariat’s work on election observation and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Commonwealth, the Rt. Hon. Hugo Swire MP, commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Commonwealth Heads of Government have agreed a new Commonwealth Charter and endorsed a package of reforms to strengthen the Commonwealth. This marks an important milestone in Commonwealth modernisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Commonwealth Ministers devoted a great deal of effort to achieve this result. This reflects our belief that the Commonwealth can make a strong, positive contribution on a range of global issues and nurturing democratic standards worldwide.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms, now adopted, show vision and a genuine desire by all members to increase the Commonwealth’s impact and relevance. All parts of the Commonwealth family must now work together to implement these reforms, to ensure that the organisation is as strong and effective as it can be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ability to protect core democratic values is central to the Commonwealth’s credibility. I hope that the Charter becomes a useful tool to promote these values throughout the Commonwealth. We look forward to events in the coming months to officially launch the Charter, and will play our part in raising its profile in the UK.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/news/34580/252051/191212epgcharter.htm"&gt;Commonwealth Secretariat press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-take-steps-to-strengthen-the-commonwealth?id=816829782&amp;amp;view=News"&gt;Ministerial statement, Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60063</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:12:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fair-funding-sensible-savings-and-bill-freeze-right-is-the-right-road-for-councils-says-eric-pickles"/>
    <title>"Fair funding, sensible savings and bill freeze is the right road for councils" says Eric Pickles</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles spelled out 50 sensible savings, a Council Tax freeze and a fair funding deal as the “right road” for councils to protect residents and local services, as a major shake up of local finance was initiated today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister signalled the watershed moment for councils as he unveiled a new look local government finance settlement that will reward councils that strive to improve their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dramatic shift in spending power from Whitehall to the town hall means an estimated 70% of council income will now be raised locally compared to 56% under the centrally distributed ‘begging-bowl’ formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April 2013 councils can channel this greater local control into encouraging local jobs and local firms via a new business rate retention incentive that rewards them for growth. It could potentially add £10 billion to the economy by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, councils account for a quarter of all public spending - with English councils still spending £114 billion - so it is vital they continue to play their part tackling the inherited budget deficit by making sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help councils in that regard a document containing &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;50 practical ways to make sensible savings&lt;/a&gt; was published today. It shows how a culture change by councils can unearth significantly more taxpayer savings and help make services more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must keep doing their bit to tackle the inherited budget deficit because they account for a quarter of all public spending and still get through over £114 billion of taxpayers money each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement is a fair funding deal that will reward councils ready to strive for their communities and gives them another year to get their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils must do 3 things to get on the right road for their residents: put our fair funding deal to work; do every single one of our 50 ways to save; and accept our Council Tax freeze offer. Councils that cry wolf without having done all of this are letting their residents down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils that put their thinking caps on now can save precious taxpayer pennies next year by cutting out waste and transforming frontline services that vulnerable people rely on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s fair funding deal arms councils with an average spending power of £2,240 per household. Local authorities have been protected from further spending reductions for 2013 to 2014. Overall the average spending power reduction for councils in 2013 to 2014 is expected to be limited to just 1.7% per household, less than last year’s comparable figure of 3.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe this important concession gives councils the time they need to transform service delivery, build up their local business rate income, improve procurement and comprehensively complete the suggested 50 savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total start-up funding assessment for councils 2013 to 2014 apportions £26 billion in a fair and sustainable way that ensures the smallest reductions for the councils most reliant on government support. More weighting has been given to areas with the highest levels of assessed need. For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is setting aside an extra £450 million over the next 2 years to help local government in England to freeze their Council Tax, equivalent to a 1% rise. A third year’s combined Council Tax freeze is potentially worth over £200 to band D residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government confirmed today that where a council rejects the freeze, the majority will have to secure electoral agreement through a ‘local tax lock’ referendum to hike band D bills by more than 2%. Smaller authorities with a track record of low Council Tax will be given slightly more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘50 ways to save’ include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing back offices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting Community Budgets to bring staff and money together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using transparency to cut waste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clamping down on corporate charge cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting special spending controls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling the £2 billion of local fraud&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;utilising £16 billion of non-school reserves creatively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve collection rates to reduce the £2.4 billion of uncollected Council Tax across England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage direct debit and e-billing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve property management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close subsidised council canteens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing senior pay and posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut spending on consultants and agency staff which had risen to £4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stop translating documents into foreign languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cut expensive travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce printing costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hire out the town hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/50-ways-to-save-examples-of-sensible-savings-in-local-government"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; for the full list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 to 2014 spending power calculation includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£26.07 billion start up funding assessment (which includes £10.9 billion of locally retained business rates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£23.9 billion in Council Tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£859 million for NHS funding to support social care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£661 million via New Homes Bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£240 million for 2013 to 2014 Council Tax freeze grant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition local authorities will also benefit from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£112 million via the Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£33.5 million via New Burdens for Council Tax Support in 2013 to 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/39394/Local_Authority_briefing_table_201314.xls"&gt;Spending power data by local authority for 2013 to 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;No authority will see a spending power reduction of more than 8.8% because of decisions taken by ministers to make an efficiency support grant available. The ‘per household’ figures are calculated using total spending power a combination of the new start up funding assessment and Council Tax, and the number of dwellings by Council Tax band for each administrative area in England. The counts are calculated from data for England extracted from the Valuation Office Agency’s database on 12 September 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/plainenglishguide.pdf"&gt;plain English guide&lt;/a&gt; to cut through Whitehall jargon and explain the new settlement system is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a period of statutory consultation on the settlement which runs to 15 January 2013. Ministers will then finalise their proposals and the settlement for 2013 to 2014 will be debated in Parliament in February in time for councils to set their budgets for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement committed the government to relinquishing control over excessive Council Tax increases and giving that democratic power directly to local communities. This was legislated for through the Localism Act. The government has today published the Council Tax principles it is proposing for 2013 to 2014. Council Tax increases would trigger a referendum, if they exceed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2% for most principal authorities; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£5 (which ever is higher) in the case of shire district councils, police and crime commissioners and fire and rescue authorities that set the lowest quartile of Council Tax in their class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final principles for 2013 to 2014 will be set out in a report for the approval of the House of Commons early next year, at the same time as the final report on the local government finance settlement. No equivalent principles are being proposed for town and parish councils for 2013 to 2014, although they may in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical data for the 2013-14 Local Government Finance Settlement can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/1314/settle.htm"&gt;Local Government Finance site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities have been protected with savings back loaded to allow time for sensible savings; they have also benefited from the protection to local government in 2013 to 2014. In addition the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, has been asked to carry out a review to pinpoint ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money. The government intends to announce the breakdown of £140 million of capital grant money to fire and rescue authorities. The money for 2013 to 2015 will be distributed by a combination of formula and for projects to fire and rescue authorities that have been successful through bidding. All fire and rescue authorities will receive some capital funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T13:41:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T13:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59922</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:03+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/passengers-come-first-in-new-civil-aviation-act"/>
    <title>Passengers come first in new Civil Aviation Act </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers have today been placed firmly at the heart of UK airport regulation as a new Civil Aviation Act becomes law. The Act paves the way for the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) to motivate airports to deliver better facilities, provide more information for passengers and give greater incentives for airports to prepare for disruptive events such as severe weather. The Act also makes provisions for future reforms to the Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing (&lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme, which offers financial protection for holiday makers in the event of their tour operator going bust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Act sees a number of key changes to the powers and responsibilities of the aviation regulator, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;giving the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; a single overriding duty, for its airport economic functions, to further the interests of passengers and owners of cargo in the provision of airport operation services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a flexible licensing regime for regulated airports, enabling the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; to include licence conditions that require airports to respond more effectively when things go wrong (e.g. severe weather)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;, where appropriate, to replace fixed price caps on airports with lighter touch forms of regulation and removing unnecessary central government involvement from airport regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; more effective enforcement powers, allowing it to impose sanctions of up to 10% of an airport operator’s annual turnover and daily amounts of 0.1% of turnover for breaching licence conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; with a new role in promoting better public information about airline and airport performance levels, enabling passengers to make informed decisions when making travel arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; with a new role to promote better public information about the environmental effects of aviation and measures taken to mitigate adverse effects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conferring certain aviation security functions currently carried out by the Department for Transport, on to the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;. Responsibility for aviation security policy, and giving aviation security directions to industry, will remain with the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Act also enables Ministers to make future changes to the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; holiday protection scheme, including the ability to bring holidays sold by airlines into the scope of the scheme. Earlier this year, the government introduced secondary legislation to update the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; holiday protection scheme, making it more relevant to today’s market. The new powers in the Act will enable the protection available to consumers to be further strengthened. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is an important milestone in our drive to put the passenger experience unequivocally at the heart of how our airports are run.  Aviation is vital for providing the UK with the connections we need to do business, travel for leisure and visit our friends and families around the world.  I am grateful for the cross-party support this Act has received during its passage through Parliament – ensuring passengers and those sending cargo can enjoy the benefits of this new regime as swiftly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the Act has received Royal Assent, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will work to bring the new airport economic regulatory framework fully into force in April 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act introduces, and enables, reform in 4 main areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the framework for economic regulation of airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the legislative framework of the Civil Aviation Authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing scheme (&lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conferring certain aviation security functions currently carried out by the Department for Transport, on to the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; - responsibility for aviation security policy remains with the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the new regulatory regime for airports, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; is empowered to carry out a market power test, as set out in the Act, to determine whether an airport operator should or should not be subject to economic regulation. This replaces the designation of airports for price control regulation by the Secretary of State. Heathrow, Gatwick and Stansted airports are currently designated and their current price controls, set under the Airports Act 1986, will continue to run until 31 March 2014. Over the next 18 months, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will determine how to apply the new regime set out in the Act to the airports that are subject to economic regulation after this date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the existing regime, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; has 4 duties for the purposes of economic regulation, these are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to further the reasonable interests of users of airports within the UK. Users comprises airlines, passengers and other user of air transport services at the airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote the efficient, economic and profitable operation of such airports &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to encourage investment in new facilities at airports in time to satisfy anticipated demands by the users of such airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to impose the minimum restrictions that are consistent with the performance by the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; of its functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also required to take account of international obligations notified to it by the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures set out today will replace these with a single primary duty and a number of further duties to which the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; must have regard in carrying out the primary duty for the purposes of airport economic regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="primary-duty"&gt;Primary duty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to further the interests of passengers and owners of cargo (both present and future), in the provision of airport operation services and to do so, wherever appropriate, by promoting competition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="further-duties"&gt;Further duties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to ensure that licence holders are able to finance their provision of airport operation services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to secure that all reasonable demands for airport operation services are met&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to promote economy and efficiency on the part of licence holders in their provision of airport operation services at regulated airports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to secure that licence holders are able to take reasonable measures to reduce, control or mitigate adverse environmental effects of the airport to which the licence relates and aircraft using that airport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to guidance issued by the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to any international obligation of the UK notified to it by the Secretary of State&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have regard to the principles of better regulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; will have a duty not to impose or maintain unnecessary burdens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expanded regulation-making powers in the Act would allow more holidays to be included in the &lt;abbr title="Air Travel Organisers’ Licensing"&gt;ATOL&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme and would provide even greater clarity for consumers whilst ensuring a level regulatory playing field for businesses selling flight-inclusive holidays. The government’s intention is that such a step would only be taken following full consultation with stakeholders including an impact assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60044</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-announces-reduction-in-uk-troop-numbers-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Prime Minister announces reduction in UK troop numbers in Afghanistan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/" title="Number 10"&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt; told &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/" title="UK Parliament"&gt;Parliament&lt;/a&gt; that UK forces would shift from mentoring Afghan troops at battalion level to brigade level next year. This reflects the progress made in Helmand and the increasing ability and confidence of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;) to lead security operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawdown, agreed by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/national-security-council" title="National Security Council"&gt;National Security Council&lt;/a&gt; this week, is in line and consistent with both UK military advice and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;North Atlantic Treaty Organization&lt;/a&gt; strategy agreed at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natolive/events_66529.htm" title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization Summit, Lisbon 2010"&gt;Lisbon Summit in 2010&lt;/a&gt;, under which &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.isaf.nato.int/" title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;International Security Assistance Force&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt;) forces continue to operate across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK forces will end combat operations by the end of 2014. It is part of transition to an enduring commitment to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement comes as the previously announced reduction of UK force levels from 9,500 to 9,000 is being achieved with service personnel due to arrive home in time for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed work on how force levels will reduce in 2013 is ongoing and will be conducted in line with operational requirements and the transition process which remains on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Afghan forces increasingly take the lead, UK combat operations will give way to an increasing focus on training and advising. By the end of 2013, it is expected that UK forces will not routinely need to mentor Afghan forces below brigade level, allowing the reduction in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real progress being made on the ground in Helmand province will allow us, on current planning, to reduce British troops to around 5,200 by the end of 2013. This is a direct result of the success of the Afghan National Security Forces in assuming a lead role in delivering security for the Afghan people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The phased process of transition of security responsibility agreed at the Lisbon Summit is well advanced and on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have consistently said that there will not be a cliff-edge reduction in troop numbers at the end of 2014. This gradual drawdown is firmly in line with the planning of our &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; partners and the advice of military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UK forces will continue to operate alongside their Afghan counterparts, albeit in lower numbers, until our combat operations cease at the end of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There remain huge challenges ahead for the Afghan people. Our combat mission is drawing to a close, but our commitment to the Afghan people is long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Members of the Afghan National Army" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5775/JMOCCCT-2012-014_Op_Horhari_Afghan_004.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Members of the Afghan National Army take part in an operation in Helmand province (stock image) [Picture: Sergeant Steve Blake RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chief of the Defence Staff, General Sir David Richards, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Afghan National Army and Police have greatly improved in the past years. Their capability has increased so that today they enjoy the trust of some 84 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As they develop, and in agreement with the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, the efforts of our Armed Forces will continue to shift from a combat role to one that focuses on training, advice and assistance. That will allow us to make appropriate and measured reductions in our force levels in line with the &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; plan and our Chicago commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These drawdown plans are based on military advice and following discussion with General Allen [Commander &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Forces]. I am confident that the progress we have seen in Helmand and across Afghanistan can be maintained and that we can complete the tasks we have been set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be in the position where we are now able to commit to reducing UK force levels to around 5,200 by the end of next year is testament to the professionalism and courage of those personnel who have served, and continue to serve, in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We must remember that the UK’s commitment to the operation in Afghanistan will continue beyond the end of 2014 as &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dfid.gov.uk/" title="Department for International Development"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for International Development"&gt;DFID&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [Department for International Development] and the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign Office&lt;/a&gt; continue to build the government and nation while the UK’s pledge to support the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;, including training the military’s officers, will be ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significant progress in Afghanistan continues with 75% of the Afghan population now being secured by the &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt; and at least 80% of all patrols being &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;-led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of 80 UK bases at the start of the HERRICK 16 deployment this April, only 32 remain active with the others having been handed over to Afghan forces or closed. Afghan National Army numbers in Helmand province now stand at about 18,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59961</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:56:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-monmouth-reassures-shipping-with-anti-piracy-exercise"/>
    <title>HMS Monmouth reassures shipping with anti-piracy exercise</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Plymouth frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; joined forces with a United States warship and air power for an exercise involving the military and merchant shipping to show how the two can work together to ensure safe passage on the high seas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, known as the Black Duke, was given the task of providing close-in protection to two huge tankers - including the Bahamian-registered Arcturus Voyager (333 metres long and displacing 160,000 tonnes) which travels at only 5 knots/6 miles per hour (9.26 kilometres per hour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK warship was supported by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.navy.mil/" title="US Navy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy&lt;/a&gt; and coast guard patrol ships, a supply vessel and the air-defence destroyer &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.churchill.navy.mil/" title="USS Winston S Churchill"&gt;&lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Winston S Churchill&lt;/a&gt; - with a Royal Navy navigator aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5766/HMSMonmouth_USwarshipg.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth (foreground) and a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; warship [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aircraft involved were a &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Seahawk helicopter, Orion eye-in-the-sky patrol aircraft, F18 Super Hornets and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s own &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Lynx-Mk8" title="Lynx Mk8"&gt;Lynx helicopter&lt;/a&gt; which landed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; boarding team by rapid roping on to the Arcturus Voyager while smaller boats delivered the rest of the boarders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrated how the Royal Navy responds to pirates or terrorists threatening merchant vessels - exactly as Royal Marine commandos from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Royal-Fleet-Auxiliary/Stores/RFA-Fort-Victoria" title="RFA Fort Victoria"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Fleet Auxiliary"&gt;RFA&lt;/abbr&gt; Fort Victoria&lt;/a&gt; did on the Italian MV Montecristo in 2011, to free the crew from pirates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Chris Hollingworth, principal warfare officer in &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise with a tanker " src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5767/HMS_Monmouth_exercises_with_tanker_in_Gulf_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise with a tanker in the Gulf [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was great to be able to demonstrate to the tanker captains how we would be able to deal with threats and offer them a level of protection. We were able to neutralise potential threats by both directing support aircraft and using our 4.5-inch [114 millimetres] Mk8 gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s commanding officer Commander Gordon Ruddock said of the exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will give confidence to the merchant marine community that we are ready, willing and able to protect them should they need us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With fully-laden cargos of over 150,000 tonnes, it is important that merchant ships such as these are able to transport their cargo around the world without fear of piracy or other attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5768/HMS_Monmouth_Gulf_exercise_with_US_Navy___tankers_2012g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth on exercise in the Gulf with &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Navy and tankers [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;His ship has recently taken over from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Destroyers/Type-45-Destroyers/HMS-Diamond" title="HMS Diamond"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Diamond&lt;/a&gt; on patrol until returning to Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrol is vital to UK and world trade because each day 17 million barrels of oil pass through the Strait of Hormuz, while 3-4 million barrels are moved through the Bab-al-Mandeb Strait, gateway to the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a typical week, more than 500 ships pass through Hormuz - 3 in every 5 of them energy carriers (including liquefied natural gas which is used in the UK).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise tested mock crisis centre staff in Bahrain, merchant sailors and the military response should shipping come under terrorist attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59945</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:34:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice"/>
    <title>Christmas Holiday Travel Advice</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you do get into problems while abroad then we are here to help, but you can avoid a lot of difficulties in the first place by following these basic tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/staying-safe/travel-insurance/" title="Travel insurance"&gt;take out comprehensive travel insurance&lt;/a&gt; - make sure it covers you for any activities you are likely to undertake such as extreme or water sports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nathnac.org/" title="NaTHNaC"&gt;The National Travel Health Network and Centre’s website&lt;/a&gt;T or contact your GP’s surgery as early as possible before you travel to find out if you need any vaccinations or other medication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for certain countries your passport must be valid for six months after the date you travel - check the entry requirements section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/" title="Travel advice by country"&gt;Travel Advice for the country you are visiting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take enough money for your trip and some back-up funds in a mix of cash and cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-pack-explore-a-new-guide-for-travellers" title="Plan. Pack. Explore. – a new guide for travellers"&gt;download our Plan. Pack. Explore. app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="winter-sports"&gt;Winter sports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New research reveals that a third of people taking their first winter sports holiday risk serious injury because they are not sufficiently in shape when they hit the slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research also reveals that two out of five winter sports enthusiasts have injured themselves at least once, highlighting the importance of getting in shape and warming up properly before skiing or snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/get-fit-for-ski" title="Get Fit For Ski"&gt;Find out more about our Get Fit For Ski campaign.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visiting-friends-or-family-abroad"&gt;Visiting friends or family abroad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You still need to take the same preparations as if you were going on holiday. Our research shows that nearly half of young people did not take out insurance the last time they stayed with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57526</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T11:07:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-protector-takes-to-the-ice-for-a-charity-santa-run"/>
    <title>HMS Protector takes to the ice for a charity Santa run</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Santas, accompanied by Rudolph, were gathered at 10am for a gentle warm-up led by the Executive Officer, Commander Don Mackinnon, who is currently in command for this Antarctic patrol, before it was ‘on your marks, get set… ho ho ho’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Santa run was conducted on ice in the waters surrounding Deception Island, a dormant, water-filled caldera volcano; one of only two known in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking through a sheet of snow-covered ice before coming to a planned stop, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Patrol-and-Minehunters/Ice-Patrol-and-Survey-Ships/HMS-Protector" title="HMS Protector"&gt;HMS Protector&lt;/a&gt; took position and disembarked her personnel to test the ice conditions and drill ice core samples to ensure the ice was safe, before Protector’s eager Father Christmasses followed via the ship’s accommodation ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amid perfect weather conditions, and under the watchful eye of two seals that had taken up post next to the ship, they completed their run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5743/protector2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses on the start line, ready for the off [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annually, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.each.org.uk/" title="East Anglian Children's Hospice"&gt;East Anglian Children’s Hospice&lt;/a&gt; conducts nine Santa runs across Essex and East Anglia throughout the festive period, raising thousands of pounds for the charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is traditional for Royal Naval ships to adopt a charity from their affiliated town so that they can fundraise whilst away from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the work that HMS Protector conducts in Antarctica, she has formed a close liaison with a number of organisations in the Cambridge area (amongst them the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.antarctica.ac.uk/" title="British Antarctic Survey"&gt;British Antarctic Survey&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.spri.cam.ac.uk/" title="Scott Polar Research Institute"&gt;Scott Polar Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;) and as such is affiliated to the City of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector has been affiliated with the East Anglian Children’s Hospice since August 2012. The East Anglian Children’s Hospice provides support to families and care for children and young people with life-threatening conditions across Cambridgeshire, Essex, Norfolk and Suffolk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) Royal Navy" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5744/protector3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rudolph (Able Seaman Scott) gets off to a flying start [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providing care and support wherever the family wishes, in families’ own homes, in the community or at the hospices, their care teams help children and their families with the emotional and physical challenges they face, helping them to make the most of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commander Don Mackinnon stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With 21 hours of daylight in every 24, our working day in Antarctica tends to be a long one. Yesterday for example our first boat group departed the ship at 0830 [8.30am] in the morning and the last one finally got back at 2300 [11pm] that night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With that sort of work pace it’s nice to be able to take a break from operations now and again, and do something both for fun, and also to help our affiliated charity at the same time. Father Christmas’s traditional home might be the North Pole… but as you can see, he has helpers that visit the other one too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector is currently in the Antarctic in order to support an international team conducting formal &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ats.aq/e/ats.htm" title="The Antarctic Treaty"&gt;Antarctic Treaty&lt;/a&gt; inspections of sites across the Peninsula, whilst maintaining a UK Sovereign presence in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://britishantarcticterritory.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;British Antarctic Territory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="HMS Protector's Father Christmasses" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5745/protector4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;HMS Protector's Father Christmasses lie on the ice to spell out EACH [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Arron Hoare, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Led by the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/foreign-commonwealth-office" title="Foreign and Commonwealth Office"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office&lt;/a&gt; and with the support of the British Antarctic Survey and observers from HMS Protector, the international Antarctic Treaty team is inspecting a number of scientific stations, historic sites, cruise vessels and yachts in the Antarctic Peninsula region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Protector will be operating in and around Antarctica until April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57512</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/operators-urged-to-tackle-crowding-on-busiest-services"/>
    <title>Operators urged to tackle crowding on busiest services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker has urged train operators to continue work to tackle congestion on their services following the publication today of the top 10 most crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London is served by some of the busiest trains in the country according to the list of crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Climbing on a crowded train where there is little space can often be an unpleasant experience and I sympathise with passengers who have to travel on these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The operators on the list are aware of the crowding problems on these particular services. I will be monitoring these services closely, and others which have not made the top 10 list, and urging train companies to reduce crowding on the busiest services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail has experienced unprecedented growth in recent years. That is why we are investing in more carriages, longer trains and better services and funding major projects like HS2, Crossrail and Thameslink, all of which will significantly boost capacity on our rail network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an important tool to give increased transparency to passengers and help the industry act to improve journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list, compiled from data collected in Autumn 2011, shows that the following services were the busiest in England and Wales (in descending order): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington – load factor 180%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:32am service from Woking to London Waterloo – load factor 164%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:13pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 162%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4:48pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 160%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington – load factor 158%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon – load factor 157%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough – load factor 155%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:17pm service from London Liverpool Street to Shenfield – load factor 154%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:14am service from Alton to London Waterloo – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5:46pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport (DfT) collects rail passenger counts from train operating companies to monitor train crowding levels. All franchises let by DfT require the train operator to address crowding and to plan their timetables in such a way as to ensure, as far as possible, that crowding is not unduly concentrated on any particular route or individual service. The table included in this paper shows the 10 most overcrowded peak services in the autumn 2011 passenger counts data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘top 10’ list is determined based on ‘load factor’, which is the number of standard class passengers on a service expressed as a percentage of the standard class passenger capacity for that service. For example, a train which has the same passenger load as the passenger capacity would have a load factor of 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Great Western has recently strengthened the 7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington by adding an additional carriage, so that the number of standard class seats has increased to 340.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From December 2012 London Midland is providing three Class 350/2 ‘high density’ units for the 6:13pm service from London to Birmingham New Street to maximise the number of seats. In the long term, London Midland has 10 new 4 car trains on order that will allow them to operate additional trains on this route from 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From September 2012, the 6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington has started from Oxford not Banbury, leaving Oxford at 7:00am. It is now operated by a different type of rolling stock which provides a higher standard class seating capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More recent counts on the 7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon suggest much lower loadings on this service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the long term, from the May 2014 timetable period, it is planned to introduce a fifth train per hour between Manchester and Leeds which should relieve capacity on the 6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 10 list can be accessed on the &lt;a href="/government/publications/top-10-overcrowded-train-services-england-and-wales"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60026</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-pension-scheme"/>
    <title>Local government pension scheme</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 12 September 2001, the then Department for Transport, Local Government and the Regions announced plans to give taxpayer-funded pensions to councillors, through access to the local government pension scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals came into force in 2003. The Councillors’ Commission report of the last administration noted that 912 councillors in England had joined that pension scheme by 2004. A Taxpayers’ Alliance survey in February 2009, across the whole United Kingdom, found that 3,527 councillors had pensions as of 2007 to 2008; a further survey in January 2012 found that figure had increased to 4,548 councillors by 2010 to 2011. The trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="abolition-of-taxpayer-funded-pensions"&gt;Abolition of taxpayer-funded pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers in this government take a fundamentally different view to the last administration. We do not believe that taxpayer-funded pensions are justified. Councillors are volunteers undertaking public service; they are not and should not be employees of the council dependent on the municipal payroll. They are not professional, full-time politicians, nor should they be encouraged to become so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors do not receive a salary; rather, they receive allowances to compensate for their out-of-pocket expenses. Yet following changes made by the last administration, allowances have slowly become a form of salary, a situation worsened by the state-funded pensions. This is a corrosive influence on local democracy and independent thought, blurring the distinction between council staff and councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bit of the public sector needs to do its bit to help pay off the deficit inherited from the last administration. Local government grants are being reduced. Ministers have cut and then frozen their salaries. Public sector pensions, including parliamentary pensions, are being reformed to reduce the burden on taxpayers. It is only right that councillors do their bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe that an occupational pension scheme intended for employees, and paid for by taxpayers, is an appropriate vehicle for councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="existing-pension-rights"&gt;Existing pension rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to consultation, we propose that there will be no access for councillors to the local government pension scheme in England from April 2014. In the interests of fairness, those councillors already in the scheme would have their accrued rights up to April 2014 fully protected, but would not be able to accrue any further benefits after that date in the existing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not prevent councillors contributing to a personal pension: if they put aside part of their (taxable) allowances into such a pension, then that is a matter for them; they will continue to receive income tax relief like any ordinary member of the population, subject to the prevailing tax rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although central records on councillors’ participation in the scheme are not held by my department, initial rough estimates suggest that this could save £7 million a year in taxpayers’ money. There is absolutely no case for increasing councillor allowances to compensate. Instead, councils may want to consider earlier, voluntary closure of the scheme to their councillors as a sensible saving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="civic-duty"&gt;Civic duty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility regulations for the local government pension scheme are overseen by my department. Although this is a centrally mandated change (as was its original introduction), we believe these reforms will assist localism and local democracy by encouraging a greater separation between councillors and officers. Robust local scrutiny of council spending requires councillors to be substantively independent of means and of thought from the body they are overseeing. Civic duty should not be bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not believe it will have any detrimental effect on people choosing to become councillors. The best thing we can do to encourage more people to take part in municipal public life is to decentralise power to local communities so being a councillor is a meaningful and rewarding role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="elected-mayors"&gt;Elected mayors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there is a greater expectation that an elected mayor is a full-time position. We therefore propose to consult on allowing elected mayors to remain in the scheme as a voluntary option (but not as an expectation), subject to local scrutiny, challenge and determination. The salaries of the mayor of London, members of the Greater London Assembly and police and crime commissioners will remain pensionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="timing"&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statutory consultation is required and will commence in due course, as part of the planned consultation on the wider reform of the local government pension scheme. We will consult with the Welsh Assembly government in respect of access to the local government pension scheme for councillors in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I would like to pay tribute to their often unsung and ongoing work in standing up for their local residents. We hope these reforms will further strengthen the integrity and independence of councillors and increase the respect within their communities for the voluntary work they undertake as champions of the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60020</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/local-government-finance-settlement-oral-statement"/>
    <title>Local government finance settlement oral statement</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission Mr Speaker, I should like to make a statement on finance for English local authorities for 2013 to 2014 and 2014 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Autumn Statement sets out how the coalition government is putting our public finances back on track [political content removed].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local government has shown great skill in reducing its budgets. Committed local authorities have protected front line services. Little wonder then that at a time of retrenchment satisfaction in council services has gone up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s settlement will see council expenditure fall in a controlled way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English local government accounts for £1 of every £4 spent on public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It spends £114 billion - that’s twice the defence budget and more than the NHS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this settlement recognises the responsibility of local government to find sensible savings and make better use of its resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It marks a new settlement for local government based on self determination and financial independence. A move from the begging bowl to pride in locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begins the biggest shake up of local finance in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are shifting power from Whitehall direct to the town hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From April, authorities will directly retain nearly £11 billion of business rates instead of returning them to the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Striving councils will benefit by doing the right thing by their communities. If they bring in jobs and business they will be rewarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, New Homes Bonus remunerates councils for building more homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year the Bonus will be worth more than £650 million and even more in 2014 to 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our reforms an estimated 70% of local authority income will be raised locally compared to a little over half under the current formula grant system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A giant step for localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start-up funding assessment, which gives each council a share of the funding - confirmed in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement - will see £26 billion shared between councils across the country - with the smallest reductions for councils most reliant on government funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consulted local authorities on our proposals over the summer. And we’ve listened to what they told us. They told us that there should be less money held back from the settlement. So we’ve reduced the amounts that we are setting aside for New Homes Bonus, for the safety net and for academies funding. In total that means an additional £1.9 billion for local authorities upfront in 2013 to 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities also told us that they wanted a stronger growth incentive. We were happy to respond. So we’ve made the scheme more generous, ensuring that at least 25 pence in every pound of business rate growth will be retained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement leaves councils with considerable total spending power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall reduction in spending power next year is just 1.7%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small number of authorities will require larger savings to be made but no councils face a loss of more than 8.8% in their spending power thanks to a new efficiency support grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, to qualify councils will have to improve services to qualify. It is unfair on the rest of local government to expect them to subsidise other councils’ failure to embrace modernity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is not about what councils can take. It’s about what they can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the settlement continues protecting fire and rescue as a blue light emergency service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we have announced £140 million of capital grant money to fire authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictably the doom mongers have been consulting their Mayan calendars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issuing dire warnings of the end of the world as we know it on Friday. A billion pound black hole in the local budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have shamefully predicted riots on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nostradamus needn’t worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because all those Malthusian predictions have come to naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns that the poorest councils or those in the north would suffer disproportionately are well wide of the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spending power for places is in the north compares well to those in the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Newcastle has a spending power per household of £2,522 which is over £700 more than the £1,814 per household in Wokingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also maintained the system of ‘damping’ - where government sets a ‘floor’ below which council funding will not fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s average grant reduction for the most dependent upper tier authorities will be less than 3%, compared to 8.7% for the wealthiest. That’s more support and protection than last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also confirm today that local authorities will be able to use the receipts from assets sales raised from 2012 to 2013 onwards to fund outstanding equal pay claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of what I’ve announced today, the Secretary of State for Health will in due course be confirming public health funding for local councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his Autumn Statement the Chancellor recognised the sector has risen to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, unlike most of central government, local government was exempted from the 1% top slice next year - worth approximately £240 million to councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as it looks to 2014 and beyond, local government needs to continue finding better, more efficient, ways of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There remains scope for sensible savings. With the exception of a handful of authorities, nobody has got to grips with procurement. More can also be done to share offices, share services, cut fraud and provide more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also asked the outgoing Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Sir Ken Knight, to pinpoint practical ways to help fire and rescue authorities save money and protect the quality and breadth of frontline fire services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is disappointing that the Shadow Fire Minister has signalled his opposition. It has been noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, and today, true to my Yorkshire roots, I’ve published 50 ways to save, setting out practical ways for councils to save money, big and small. But it all adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if councils merged their back offices like the Tri-Borough initiative in London, they could save £2 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;procurement fraud costs taxpayers almost a billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils are sitting on £16 billion of reserves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;councils aren’t collecting over £2 billion of council tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better property management could save £7 billion a year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have also announced today that further savings will be made by the abolition of pensions for councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors should be champions of the people, not the salaried staff of the town hall state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s guide gives more power to the elbow and the public to challenge crude cuts and champion sensible savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year’s exemption will give local authorities time to put their house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s remind ourselves what this is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;safeguarding vital public services &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;protecting families and pensioners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ending the something for nothing culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is why, despite financial pressures, we will continue supporting for the third year running, those who insulate residents from further council tax hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have set aside an extra £550 million for local authorities to support council tax: £450 million over the next 2 years for the freeze and an additional £100 million for council tax support will be available in new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All councils have a moral duty to freeze council tax.
It doubled under Labour. It became unsustainable. 
We’ve cut it in real terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear this years freeze grant goes into base for the spending review period and has the same status as every other item in base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who would prefer to carry on with increases and see residents miss out should be ready to answer to their local taxpayers and not dodge them by setting the increase just below the threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For next year we have set the referendum threshold at 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also introduce a flexibility to support small district, police and fire authorities that have kept council tax low for years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Rt Hon friend the Local Government Minister has set out the details in a Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is democracy in action: if you want to hike taxes, put it to the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would contrast the action we have taken to freeze council tax with the new housing tax being introduced in the Republic of Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling the deficit helps keep taxes down.
If you deny the deficit, taxes on everyday families will rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, to those who want to play the politics of division - let me say this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fair settlement - fair to north and south, rural and urban, shire and metropolitan England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this settlement is also a watershed moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in a generation, striving councils now have licence to go full steam ahead and grab a share of the wealth for their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stand tall, and seize the opportunities of enterprise, growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59931</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council"/>
    <title>Overseas Territories: Joint Ministerial Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chaired the first meeting of the Overseas Territories Joint Ministerial Council in London from 4-5 December. This Council brings together the political leaders from the Overseas Territories and UK Ministers. It provides a forum for the exchange of views on political and constitutional issues and has a mandate to lead work to review and implement the strategy and commitments in the June 2012 White Paper The Overseas Territories: Security Success and Sustainability and to promote the security and good governance of the Territories and their sustainable economic and social development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council agreed a communiqué which identified priority issues and set out a comprehensive action plan for joint work. A copy of this communiqué has been laid in the Library of the House. The communiqué reflects the commitment of the governments of the Overseas Territories and the UK to work together to support economic growth and jobs; to protect the environment and create green growth; to harness effectively the support of the EU, the Commonwealth and other international organisations; and to deliver better government, better education and stronger, healthier and safer communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with our commitment in the White Paper we will report to Parliament on progress in implementing the commitments in the communiqué by territory governments and UK Departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual Joint Ministerial Council succeeds the Overseas Territories Consultative Council set up in 1999. It was attended this year by political leaders and representatives of the following Territories: Anguilla; Bermuda; the British Virgin Islands; the Cayman Islands; the Falkland Islands; Gibraltar; Montserrat; Pitcairn; St Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha; and the Turks and Caicos Islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 5 December the Prime Minister welcomed Territory leaders to 10 Downing Street: the first time that Overseas Territory leaders have had a collective meeting with a Prime Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council" title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/overseas-territories-joint-ministerial-council-communique" title=" Joint Ministerial Council communique"&gt;Joint Ministerial Council communiqué&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/59902</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T19:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK condemns the decision by the Jerusalem District Planning Board to give approval for a plan to build 1,500 housing units in the East Jerusalem neighbourhood of Ramat Shlomo, and is extremely concerned by reports that the Board is considering giving the approval to a further 5000 housing units in East Jerusalem this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on yesterday’s announcement the Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Israeli settlements are illegal under international law, and I condemn this decision. It is deeply disappointing that despite the international community repeatedly raising our concerns, Israel continues to press ahead with plans to expand them.  Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties.  This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.  If implemented, it would make a negotiated two-state solution, with Jerusalem as a shared capital, very difficult to achieve.  We  urge Israel to reverse this decision and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity”
.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57535</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-pop-up-shop-to-showcase-high-street-entrepeneurs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens pop-up shop to showcase high street entrepreneurs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s efforts to regenerate high streets and encourage entrepreneurs, the shop is being opened in time for final Christmas present buying this week by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk, with the support of national enterprise campaign StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To directly support enterprise and showcase Britain’s best new retailers, ministers have set up the pop-up store inside their Victoria-based office building to act as a blueprint for high streets across the country to emulate through schemes such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cutting the ribbon on the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5697/ribbon-cutting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles cutting the ribbon with Mark Prisk and Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the first ever Whitehall pop-up shop with ‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell. Every fortnight six new British start-up businesses will move into the shop, sharing costs and trialling their exciting ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop will be open to the public for at least a year and will offer affordable retail space to over 150 small start-up businesses. The department is not seeking any financial return from the shop, which is being supported by sponsors Intuit, John Lewis, SNR Denton and StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5698/shop-floor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The first 6 pop-up tenants are NANUKK, Milla &amp;amp; Arti, Arthur &amp;amp; Henry, London Mummy, Morrow’s Outfitters and The English Tee Shop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe pop-ups are a great way to get empty spaces used and could be easily replicated in other town centres across the country. Mr Prisk has written to the British Property Federation to urge landlords to get on board. He said that, starting in January, all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Town Team partners will receive support to facilitate new pop-ups in their empty high street premises, which could support thousands of new businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to rejuvenating the high street. A multi-million pound strategy is backing local partnerships such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams to breathe new life into their town centres. This includes a doubling of small business rate relief; mentoring from retail experts; and workshops to address town centre challenges. A guide to opening a pop-up will be published soon and StartUp Britain has published a tool kit today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is providing over £80 million of start-up loans for young entrepreneurs, which could create over 30,000 new businesses. Ministers are also changing planning restrictions so that landlords can alter how an empty shop is used for up to two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these steps will make it easier for start-ups to find other low-cost stores to set up in. Last year 450,000 people set up new businesses and almost two thirds of new start-ups say they would benefit from trading on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are absolutely determined to support the high street and we know pop-ups are a great way to bring empty shops back to life and get new businesses going, so we thought ‘why not open one right here in the department?’. It will also showcase how we can unleash more of our best and brightest young entrepreneurs onto the country’s high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The PopUp Britain model gives retail entrepreneurs an affordable opportunity to scale up their businesses and become a part of their own high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing record numbers of people setting up businesses and they are starting out small and online. They are the driving force of the economy. This initiative offers them a chance to physically test out new markets as well as get their products in front of consumers and big buyers in a way that has never been available to them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By actively encouraging local authorities to give start-ups access to empty shops across Britain, we hope it will help accelerate British enterprise as well as providing a vibrant addition to the local British shopping experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real appetite in our town centres to get them revitalised so they remain attractive places to visit. And it’s not just talk: there are many extremely capable and serious people with some superb ideas; but they need a bit of help to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up shops are a superb way for all sorts of entrepreneurs to test their ideas. So I’m delighted that this department is opening the first pop-up shop in Whitehall and I look forward to inviting all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Towns Teams here to see how they could replicate this model across the country in the new year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a brilliant idea and it is great to see the government actively supporting business in this way. For many aspiring and growing enterprises, having access to a retail unit where new propositions and ideas can be tested directly with customers can be the catalyst to increase sales. I hope other landlords follow this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the Bright Ideas Trust, where we invest in businesses started by young unemployed people, we see many business struggle to secure retail space as they grow out of their bedrooms and away from their kitchen tables.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=neKNqnTu6qY"&gt;Pop-up shop event video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="startup-britain"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startupbritain.co/"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/a&gt; is a national campaign by entrepreneurs for entrepreneurs, harnessing the expertise and passion of Britain’s leading businesspeople to celebrate, inspire and accelerate enterprise in the UK. The campaign was founded by eight entrepreneurs and was launched in March 2011 by the Prime Minister. It has successfully run pop-up stores in Richmond, Surrey, which opened in July and which have already helped 42 businesses get access to the high street. Four in five of the tenants said the experience had been good for their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-six-pop-up-britain-victoria-tenants"&gt;First six pop-up Britain Victoria tenants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established 6 months ago by 27-year-old Shrewsbury-based designer Sarah McLeod, silk scarf company &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nanukk.com/"&gt;NANUKK&lt;/a&gt; features beautiful pieces of Art printed onto silk fabrics. All the scarves are made in England. Sarah has been labelled as one to watch, after she was awarded the River Island Graduate Fashion Week Award in 2008. 
Sarah said: “It will be great to have a physical presence in the marketplace at last! So far I’ve only been online. People will love the feel of my silk scarves and I hope it will make them buy. I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millaandarti.co.uk/"&gt;Milla &amp;amp; Arti&lt;/a&gt; was set up by product design consultant Deborah Reyner 18 months ago. Her British-made homeware collection includes bespoke lavender hearts for weddings, patchwork kits, gift ties and ribbons, collars and bows. 
Deborah said: “This is a wonderful opportunity for Milla &amp;amp; Arti and to talk about my products which are made by the British seaside and get people interested in making and doing themselves. I haven’t been able to sleep for a week before this, I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brother and sister Mark and Clare Lissaman named their ethical organic cotton men’s shirt company after their grafting grandfathers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.arthurandhenry.com/"&gt;Arthur &amp;amp; Henry&lt;/a&gt; was developed after ethical consultant Clare noticed there were no ethical formal shirts on the market. “I was at the World Congress on Organic Cotton a few years back and realised that although all the men attending were passionate about organic cotton - none were actually wearing any as they were all suited up and couldn’t find proper smart shirts in organic cotton,” Clare, from Islington, said. “So we thought we’d make some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re thrilled and delighted to have this opportunity. For a newly established, ethical menswear brand, this is an amazing opportunity to meet customers face-to-face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single mum and former interior designer Esther Gibbs, from Chiswick, created &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmummy.com/"&gt;London Mummy&lt;/a&gt; after people kept asking her where she bought the cushions and accessories she had made herself. All her products are now either made in England – some by Esther herself - or by women’s collectives in China. Her handpicked selection includes retro bed linen, colourful crochet animals, quirky kids’ stationery, classic toys and games, funky lunchboxes, wall art and more. Esther also makes beautiful children’s fabrics, which she sells in store too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther said: “I sell online but I’ll sell much more in the shop. Once people understand what the shop is about and what it’s doing for small British businesses, it will be a great asset for the high street and small businesses. I’m delighted to be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sock entrepreneur Philip Morrow, 25, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.morrowsoutfitters.com/"&gt;Morrow’s Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; last year as a way to re-establish his great-grandfather’s former gentlemen’s outfitters shop that operated in Liverpool between 1912 and 1987. His range of Loughborough-made cotton socks come in over 40 designs and colours. 
Phillip said: “Pop-up shops make a great deal of sense for small online businesses such as mine. I’m over the moon about getting the opportunity to come into PopUp Britain in Victoria.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-time English teacher and designer Alia Qadir, 30, from Ealing, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theenglishteeshop.com/"&gt;The English Tee Shop&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to combine her passion for fashion and love of grammar! All her cotton is English-made and printed. She sells online and runs her business part-time from home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia said: “Until now I have relied on my online presence to sell my brand. But my T-shirts are made from a really good quality, soft jersey, and that doesn’t come across online. I’m really delighted about this new pop-up adventure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-town-team-tool-kit"&gt;New Town team tool kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the prototype shopping concept comes a newly-developed pop-up-specific tool kit for Town Teams to implement, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a national pop-up lease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a central website with information about the initiative for town teams and new businesses interested in applying for a slot at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.popupbritain.com"&gt;www.popupbritain.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to free pop-up payment equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a step-by-step guide for setting up a PopUp Britain shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PopUp Britain branding to make the shop recognisable to the consumer as a place where they can support British enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review, the department is running a number of high street Town Team Portas Pilots in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs. Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams in May, and 15 more in July, with three from London, bringing the total to 27. They each receive up to £100,000 of funding plus support from Government and retail expert Mary Portas. More detail can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"&gt;Improving high streets and town centres pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-teams"&gt;Town Teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 330 Town Team Partners support includes: an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management; special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and support from industry experts and trade bodies including an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice; regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas; and ‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work. All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919132719/www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;List of Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="statistics"&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key statistics and evidence on start-ups in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 saw a record high for start-ups: over 450,000 people set up a company
 and became their own boss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a StartUp Britain poll revealed 82% of start-ups found the pop-up experience was valuable for their business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the UK, there are 4.8 million private sector companies employing an estimated 23.9 million people with a turnover of £3,100 billion. Small and medium-sized enterprises also account for almost half of the net growth in jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to the latest figures from the British Retail Consortium, 11.3% of shop premises in UK town centres are now vacant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to research from StartUp Britain, 63% of businesses not already on the high street think their business would benefit from a high street presence and, of these, 88% believe funding is the biggest barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="additional-quotes"&gt;Additional quotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Johnson, Chairman of StartUp Britain, former Pizza Express boss and Chairman and part-owner of Patisserie Valerie and Giraffe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new high street name that will become synonymous with buying British and supporting small British enterprise is a fantastic idea. I’m sure PopUp Britain will be embraced by town planners and local government as a way to offer tangible support to their own high streets and start-up communities.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Russell, Chief Executive of WeArePopUp, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-ups are ideal incubators for the next generation of entrepreneurs. It’s very encouraging to see the Government opening a national showcase in a high-profile location such as Cardinal Place in Victoria. Pop-ups can change the fortunes of local communities and we look forward to this support encouraging more landlords to open up their empty shops and become part of the solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosie Cann, Director at Popupspace, a property consultancy that specialises in pop ups, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find space for lots of established retailers, but the challenges for new businesses wanting to open shops are much wider. What we have here is a unique offering to smaller start-ups looking for affordable space to sell, but also for business support and a high profile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Little, UK Managing Director of Intuit, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up tenants need to be able to accept card payments but it can take weeks to get set up, the equipment and transactions can be expensive and require long-term contracts. Intuit is proud to support PopUp Britain with Intuit Pay, giving start-up retailers a way to get set up in minutes to securely take card payments on their smart phone or tablet – with no commitment and no contracts. With Intuit Pay anyone can now accept card payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the shop are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269606220/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57532</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-joy-for-old-soldier-who-finally-got-his-medal"/>
    <title>Christmas joy for old soldier who finally got his medal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Army veteran Joe McKenna, 72, who volunteers at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/" title="Duke of Lancaster's Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum"&gt;Duke of Lancaster’s Regiment Lancashire Infantry Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Preston, left the military in 1970 just months before his Northern Ireland service medal was minted and eventually decided to track down his medal after years of attending parades where he was the only veteran not wearing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Major Bob Dixon, from 2 Medical Regiment and a fellow volunteer at the museum, offered to help Joe claim his honour. Sergeant Major Dixon said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had been helping some visitors at the museum with enquiries about their service medals and so I offered to help Joe too. I got all the paperwork together, went around to his house, and we filled in the documents before sending them off to the MOD Medal Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We got a reply within 2 months, the quickest I’ve ever known; I think the turnaround was so fast because he still lives at the same address that appeared on his service papers back in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe enlisted in the Loyal Regiment, a forebear to the North West’s current infantry regiment &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/3477.aspx" title="The Duke of Lancaster's Regiment"&gt;The Duke of Lancaster’s&lt;/a&gt;, almost exactly 51 years ago and served in Kenya, Swaziland, Cyprus and Malta as well as in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern Ireland service medal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5711/Joe_smedal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Joe McKenna's Northern Ireland service medal [Picture: Sergeant Mark Garry, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;After he left the Army as a Lance Corporal in 1970, Joe worked for more than 30 years as an &lt;abbr title="Heavy Goods Vehicle"&gt;HGV&lt;/abbr&gt; driver, married Josie, with whom he had his children Sandra and Peter, and is now a grandfather of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said until recently the distractions of day-to-day life meant he just never got around to claiming what was his: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was only when I was marching at the Armed Forces Day parade in Preston last summer when I thought ‘I’m getting on a bit now and I should really get my medal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think my son would like to have it when I’m gone; he and my daughter think that it is marvellous that it’s finally here. It’s the best Christmas present ever and it makes me very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe’s wife Josie added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It really was something special to see his face when he received the medal; it was as if all his Christmases had come at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe now plans to wear his medal at his regiment’s Kimberley Day service and parade in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57555</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/hms-sutherland-returns-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>HMS Sutherland returns in time for Christmas</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship was greeted by cheering and waving families and friends wearing festive hats and holding banners with loving messages at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Devonport" title="HMNB Devonport"&gt;HM Naval Base Devonport&lt;/a&gt; in Plymouth on Saturday 15 December. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship’s Culdrose-based &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Helicopters/Merlin-MK1" title="Merlin"&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; helicopter flight arrived back separately at the Helston air station on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Sutherland" title="HMS Sutherland"&gt;HMS Sutherland&lt;/a&gt; has been busy conducting anti-piracy and terrorism patrols as part of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/Operations/Enduring-Operations/Middle-East/Combined-Maritime-Forces" title="Combined Maritime Forces"&gt;Combined Maritime Forces&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring the sea lanes and waters east of Suez and off the Horn of Africa are safe for seafarers to conduct their daily business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship conducted boarding operations on suspect vessels and also reassurance visits to build relationships with mariners and obtain information on pattern of life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="AS(ME) Dale Plumpton kissing Terri Layden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5729/Sutherland5g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Able Seaman (Marine Engineering) Dale Plumpton receives a welcome home kiss from Terri Layden [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crew also exercised with coalition and allied forces in the region to strengthen ties and improve methods of working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland’s Commanding Officer, Commander Al Wilson, said it was a ‘magic’ time to come home at Christmas. He added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The huge variety and diversity of task that Sutherland has fulfilled whilst on operations illustrates the inherent flexibility of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; in protecting and promoting UK interests worldwide, whether it is preventing piracy or terrorism at sea or strengthening bonds with regional allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, I could not have achieved this without an efficient, capable and highly motivated ship’s company and, as always, I am highly proud of what my team has achieved over the last 6 months whilst remaining cheerful and utterly professional throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My team and myself are now looking forward to spending Christmas at home with our loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Royal Navy personnel on board HMS Sutherland" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5730/Sutherland4g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Petty Officer on board HMS Sutherland waves to the waiting families on the dockside as the ship comes into port [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Vicki Benwell, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Able Rate (Communication Information Specialist) Peter Hodgkin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HMS Sutherland is my first ship and I joined her 3 months prior to deploying on operations. With this being my first deployment and first time away from the UK I was nervous, but excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There have been some tough times, but overall I have really enjoyed it, especially the team spirit of the ship and all the good work that we have achieved on operations. My most memorable moment was helping out at an orphanage in Tanzania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having handed over duties to sister ship &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;HMS Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; at the end of November, the crew of HMS Sutherland is now looking forward to spending Christmas at home and time with families and friends before a busy 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57424</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T13:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T13:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/michael-fallon-urges-banks-not-to-let-small-businesses-down"/>
    <title>Michael Fallon urges banks not to let small businesses down</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time, this provides a breakdown by individual lenders, allowing businesses to identify which banks are making most use of government assistance to increase access to finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon wrote to the Chief Executives of the five main high street banks in September to encourage them to increase their use of the Enterprise Finance Guarantee (&lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme as lending levels have been disappointing since peaking in 2009. This was despite the government, in partnership with the banks, making a number of changes to the scheme to make it more flexible and easier to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is crucial that banks play their part in making finance available to businesses and support growth in the economy.  Banks have to lend responsibly but it is clear that a number of lenders need to up their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has been made more flexible and is now available to even more businesses. Publishing lending data should encourage these financial institutions to do more to help business thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By being more transparent on lending figures, the government is giving &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; the information to best secure the finance they need to grow their business.  It also enables new market entrants to identify opportunities and drive improved competition and choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme allows banks to extend lending to small and medium-sized enterprises (&lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) by providing a government guarantee which allows banks to lend to businesses which otherwise lack the security or track record for a standard commercial loan. Access to finance is a crucial issue for &lt;abbr title="small to medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;, and over the past year the government and the banks have worked together to make a number of changes to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme to widen its availability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite these changes the level of lending through the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme for this financial year is forecast to be broadly equal to last year. The government has made £500m available for guarantees for 2012-13 but &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; lending is expected to be only £315m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past 5 years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£48,944,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£737,129,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£461,291,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£301,338,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£201,903,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; loans drawn over the past five years is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2008/09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7183&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4685&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2999&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1834&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes the government has made to the &lt;abbr title="Enterprise Finance Guarantee"&gt;EFG&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme over the past year include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the turnover limit from £25 million to £41 million&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replacing the £1 million per business lifetime scheme limit with a rolling £1 million outstanding limit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raised the level from 13 per cent to 20 per cent of the lenders annual lending portfolio to which the Government guarantee applies &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full data is available with the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-enterprise-finance-guarantee-lending"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57510</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T12:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth Land </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen visited the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office for the second time today, as the last official engagement of her Diamond Jubilee year. Her Majesty’s previous visit was in 1982 to mark the department’s bicentenary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of the building, Foreign Secretary William Hague announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory had been named ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’ in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a mark of this country’s gratitude to The Queen for Her service, we are naming a part of the British Antarctic Territory in her honour as ‘Queen Elizabeth Land’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fitting tribute at the end of Her Majesty’s Diamond Jubilee year, and I am very proud to be able to announce it as she visits the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The British Antarctic Territory is a unique and important member of the network of fourteen UK Overseas Territories. To be able to recognise the UK’s commitment to Antarctica with a permanent association with Her Majesty is a great honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area now to be known as Queen Elizabeth Land, which was previously unnamed, is around 169,000 square miles (437,000 sq km), making up just under a third of the whole land mass of the British Antarctic Territory. This is almost twice the size of the UK, which stands at 94,000 square miles (244,000 sq km).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land is bounded on the North side by the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves, to the North East by Coats Land, on the East by Dronning Maud Land and extending on the West side to a line between the South Pole and Rutford Ice Stream, east of Constellation Inlet.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty The Queen has been on the throne for 60 of the 104 years since the UK claimed territory in Antarctica in 1908. This includes the entire time it has been known as the British Antarctic Territory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Queen Elizabeth Land" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5726/QEL-Antarctica-final.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Antarctic Territory (&lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt;) extends from 20⁰ to 80⁰ West. It was claimed by the UK in 1908 and was the first official claim in Antarctica. It was designated officially as a separate Overseas Territory in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All claims to territory within Antarctica are held in abeyance under Article IV of the Antarctic Treaty, 1959, which neither confirms nor denies competing claims, but prevents new claims being made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The name Queen Elizabeth Land will now be used on all British maps. Because of the unique status of Antarctica, which is covered by an international Treaty that suspends territorial sovereignty, it is for other countries to decide whether or not they will officially recognise this name.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place naming in &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaken on the basis that a currently unnamed area requires a name for scientific or logistical purposes. This approach is fully in line with the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decisions on names are made by the Commissioner of the British Antarctic Territory, who is based in London. The Commissioner takes advice on new names from the Antarctic Place Names Committee, which meets twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="British Antarctic Territory"&gt;BAT&lt;/abbr&gt; has no permanent population. British presence is maintained via three research stations operated by the British Antarctic Survey. The Territory itself is self-financing, investing modest receipts from stamp sales and the income tax from overwintering British scientists in environmental projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is not the first time that land in Antarctica has been named after The Queen. Princess Elizabeth Land in East Antarctica, which was discovered in 1931 by the Australian Sir Douglas Mawson, was named by him after Her Royal Highness Princess Elizabeth (now Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II). And in 2006, an unnamed mountain range in the Antarctic Peninsula was named The Princess Royal Range, in recognition of Her Royal Highness’s work to support environmental and heritage protection work in Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Foreign Secretary's speech"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s speech&lt;/a&gt; welcoming Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on supporting the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/protecting-and-developing-the-overseas-territories" title="Supporting the Overseas Territories"&gt;Overseas Territories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
