<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/announcements</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/announcements.atom"/>
  <title>Inside Government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent announcements</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65367</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T17:09:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-lynx-aids-capture-of-suspected-pirates"/>
    <title>Royal Navy Lynx aids capture of suspected pirates</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A Lynx helicopter and a crew from the Royal Navy have helped arrest 12 armed suspected pirates off the coast of Somalia.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flight 217 of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; is currently deployed on board the French frigate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/News-and-Events/Latest-News/2013/January/03/121220-Blog-Surcouf" title="Read the blog from 815 Lynx Squadron on board the French frigate Surcouf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf&lt;/a&gt; as part of Operation Atalanta, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s counter-piracy mission off the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lynx was sent ahead by the French warship to find the suspected pirates after the &lt;abbr title="United States Ship"&gt;USS&lt;/abbr&gt; Halyburton, operating as part of &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.manw.nato.int/page_operation_ocean_shield.aspx" title="Operation Ocean Shield web page"&gt;Operation Ocean Shield&lt;/a&gt;, received a distress call from a merchant vessel reporting she was under attack from 6 men armed with rocket-propelled grenades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6008/20130110surcouf3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Boarding teams approach a suspected pirate vessel as Flight 217's Lynx helicopter hovers above [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;abbr title="Merchant Ship Characteristic"&gt;MSC&lt;/abbr&gt; Jasmine, sailing 260 miles off the Somali coast, managed to repel the attack themselves, a German &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; maritime patrol aircraft was scrambled to track the suspect vessel, which was by then towing another boat with several more men on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy Lynx sped to the scene and ordered the vessels to stop while French commandos from Surcouf arrived alongside in a fast boat and quickly boarded, resulting in the suspected pirates swiftly surrendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon searching the pirates’ boats, the commandos also discovered containers of diesel and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All 12 suspects are now being held on board &lt;abbr title="Frégate Légère Furtive/Light Stealth Frigate"&gt;FLF&lt;/abbr&gt; Surcouf for evidence collection in order to fully assess the possibility of prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="French frigate Sucouf seen from Lynx helicopter cockpit" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6009/20130110surcouf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of the French frigate Sucouf from the Lynx helicopter cockpit of Flight 217 from 815 Naval Air Squadron [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commander of Flight 217, Lieutenant Mike Curd, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The whole operation was an excellent exercise in teamwork, with the US ship and Surcouf co-ordinating their efforts, including both units’ helicopters, to successfully track the 2 suspect vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our Lynx actually performed the ‘stop’ and support to boarding of both the suspect vessels and provided airborne support to the subsequent boarding operations. It was a long and tiring day that began before dawn, but by the end of it we were proud of a job well done; the procedures and routines we’d practised so many times worked extremely efficiently and by nightfall we knew we had played a large part in the successful apprehension of a dozen suspected pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment of the Royal Navy’s Lynx on board the Surcouf is the first of its kind as part of the terms of the Lancaster House Treaty. Under this the &lt;abbr title="United Kingdom"&gt;UK&lt;/abbr&gt; and France agreed military co-operation to assure their international commitments and strengthen their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65345</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-health-partnership-awards-launched"/>
    <title>2013 Health Partnership Awards launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nominations are now open for this year's Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards which were launched today in Cardiff and Edinburgh.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ceremony honours the people, projects and initiatives that provide serving military personnel, including reservists, and their families and veterans with the very best in healthcare and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awards are open to civilian health staff and military medics working within the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-medical-services" title="Defence Medical Services website"&gt;Defence Medical Services&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/" title="NHS website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and private or voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 awards ceremony, to be held on 21 May, is being hosted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/" title="Welsh Government website"&gt;Welsh Government&lt;/a&gt; and, from today, people can nominate individuals or teams who provide care and support to Service personnel. Nominations close on 21 February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two launch ceremonies took place today - one at the Army’s Dreghorn Barracks in Edinburgh and one at the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/11018.aspx" title="203 Field Hospital web page"&gt;203 (Welsh) Field Hospital&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards provide a great opportunity to pay tribute to the dedication and fantastic results that our military and civilian colleagues achieve by working together to improve military health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to encourage people to visit the website to nominate all those who have provided the very best health and social care to our Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the awards in Cardiff, Welsh Health Minister Lesley Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud Wales is hosting the 2013 awards. The awards celebrate the hard work, commitment and dedication shown by health professionals from across the public, private and voluntary sectors in caring for the men and women of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important we recognise the immense contribution the Armed Forces and veterans have made to our country. We owe them a huge debt of gratitude and a duty of care, particularly those who have developed health problems as a result of their military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Tri-Service healthcare specialists" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6006/hqscot-2013-001-4476.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The awards honour the people who provide military personnel with the best health and social care [Picture: Mark Owens, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also vital we acknowledge the role of those who care for and support Service personnel and veterans, especially in recent years when the Armed Forces have been heavily engaged overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would encourage people to consider nominating either themselves or others for these awards as it is important we recognise their contribution to improving the lives of Service personnel and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Health Minister Dr Dan Poulter said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These awards will shine a light on the efforts of the military, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Service charities to make sure members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans have the best care possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such important work should not go unnoticed. I urge people to put themselves or their colleagues forward to have their efforts and achievements in caring for our Armed Forces, their families and veterans recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;203 Field Hospital was founded in 1914 and consists of reservist volunteers made up of civilian, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and military medics. The unit has already begun preparations for its upcoming deployment to Afghanistan in support of the Regular Army on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event included a demonstration of the treatment of a casualty from ambulance to resuscitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Lesley Griffiths was accompanied by Surgeon Rear Admiral Calum McArthur, Brigadier Philip Napier, Commander of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/28224.aspx" title="160 (Wales) Brigade web page"&gt;160 (Wales) Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, and Colonel Tina Donnelly, Commanding Officer of 203 Field Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the awards, including how to apply or nominate, are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org/" title="Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards website"&gt;www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65329</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister condemns killing of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alistair Burt reiterates UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Sri Lankan national, Ms Rizana Nafeek, was executed yesterday in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn the execution of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia yesterday, despite the many appeals for her sentence to be commuted. The UK opposes all use of the death penalty as a matter of principle, whatever the crime committed. The beheading of Ms Nafeek is particularly concerning as reports suggest she may have been a child of 17 at the time the crime was committed. We also find the practice of beheading to be particularly cruel and inhuman. We continue to raise our concerns about human rights with the Saudi authorities, including its frequent use of the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65403</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/million-pound-boost-to-extend-homelessness-help-to-thousands"/>
    <title>Million pound boost to extend homelessness help to thousands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A cash injection of £1.2 million will help thousands of vulnerable people into the rented homes they need, Mark Prisk said today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting the London Crisis Skylight Centre, the minister said the cash will extend the charity’s work through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.privaterentedsector.org.uk/prs-funding.asp"&gt;Crisis Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme&lt;/a&gt; to provide housing help for single people at risk of homelessness, who are unable to find private accommodation on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk at the Crisis Skylight centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6010/mark_prisk_crisis.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk speaks to Steve Grant at Crisis Skylight to hear the problems faced by single homeless people&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="helping-vulnerable-people-into-rental-homes"&gt;Helping vulnerable people into rental homes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Private Rented Sector Access Scheme, run by Crisis with government support, has helped nearly 4,000 people find the rented homes they need in the last 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already established in 120 areas across England, the scheme offers single people the advice and support they need to find and sustain a private rented tenancy, helping them overcome hurdles like budgeting and paying a deposit and working with local landlords to ensure the homes provided are suitable, safe and secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s £1.2 million cash injection will extend the programme, creating a further 23 local schemes. By focussing on helping those most at risk of homelessness, including young people, it aims to help a further 1,300 people in the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government has a strong safety net in place to prevent homelessness and Crisis’s programme has been a vital part of this, helping nearly 4,000 vulnerable people in just two years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why today I’m providing 1.2 million to extend that support even further. With another 23 areas on board, the scheme is set to help many more single people at risk of homelessness to find and keep the long-term home they need, providing the safety and security to get their lives back on track.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leslie Morphy, chief executive of Crisis, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To have already helped 4,000 homeless people into decent homes is an incredible achievement for the Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme and the local organisations working hard to support tenants and landlords. Challenging conditions in the private rented sector make this work difficult but all the more important as people struggle to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement of funding is for a further 23 schemes that will focus on helping particularly vulnerable people with no home of their own including young people and those leaving prison - groups that too often struggle to find a home and have often not been a priority for assistance through other schemes and programmes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The department has provided £10.8 million to Crisis to run the private rented sector scheme. The £1.2 million funding announced today is part of that investment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organisations that will help deliver the extended programme include:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homeless Action Resource Project (HARP), Southend on Sea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Giles Trust,	London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadway, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hope Worldwide (HWW), London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAYSH, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Mungo Community Housing Association Ltd, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DePaul UK, North Tyneside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton &amp;amp; District Advice &amp;amp; Information Service, Stockton on Tees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquila Way, Gateshead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hyndburn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crewe YMCA, Crewe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real Lettings South, Portsmouth and Southampton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Society of St James, Hampshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Southdown Housing Association, West Sussex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leatherhead Start, Mole Valley and Epsom and Ewell &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next Steps, Tandridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelter The National Campaign for Homeless People Limited, Cornwall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Threshold Housing Link, Swindon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1625 Independent People, Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encompass, Torridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SIFA Fireside, Sandwell&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hambleton&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fusion Housing, Kirklees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos of the visit to the London Crisis Skylight Centre are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632484931391/with/8368181276/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65312</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:50:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sailors-help-african-community"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sailors help African community</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During a break from anti-piracy and maritime security operations off the east coast of Africa, sailors from HMS Northumberland helped villagers to renovate their community centre.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;25 volunteers from the Plymouth-based frigate’s company headed to the village of Kigamboni while their ship was berthed in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. The sailors helped to install windows and doors in the community centre building, repaired fencing, and built ‘hugle beds’, which will be used to grow vegetables in dry conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading Physical Trainer Andrew Davidson said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All my shipmates were moved by the day at the &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt;. We felt a great sense of achievement knowing that we’d helped in every way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6001/N-land_sailor_2013.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A sailor pictured during work to renovate the Kigamboni Community Centre in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ship’s captain Commander Paddy Dowsett said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our visit to Dar es Salaam has been a real success.  Not only has it reaffirmed and strengthened the commitment the United Kingdom has to Tanzania, it has also allowed my team to give something to the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community centre was set up in 2006 to offer shelter and education to children, but also runs a mobile library and promotes adult learning initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sign of their appreciation the community centre members performed an impressive musical and acrobatic dance – demonstrating just some of the skills they’re taught at Kigamboni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The centre’s founder, Festo Chengula, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The place looks great after all the hard work. The &lt;abbr title="Kigamboni Community Centre"&gt;KCC&lt;/abbr&gt; members love having guests and you are all welcome to visit again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A young boy squeezes a sailor's face" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6002/N-land_Tanzania_child_2013.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A young boy squeezes a sailor's face in a gesture of affection  [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer)Maxine Davies, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an exchange of gifts &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Northumberland" title="HMS Northumberland"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Northumberland&lt;/a&gt; donated 85 football shirts, courtesy of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavyfa.com/" title="Royal Navy Football Association website"&gt;Royal Navy Football Association&lt;/a&gt;, together with a rugby ball, football and Northumberland crest and commemorative coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship is still in the early stages of a patrol of the Indian Ocean and due home in Plymouth in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65301</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:02:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sweet-deal-for-growth-in-birmingham"/>
    <title>Sweet deal for growth in Birmingham</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A raft of initiatives to boost economic growth in Birmingham will be on the agenda today as Business Minister Michael Fallon visits the city to champion government support for the area’s economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will be putting the seal of approval to a new deal to cut red tape for Mondelez International, owner of the Cadbury’s brand which will reduce duplication and costs whilst maintaining high safety standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal, known as a primary authority partnership, means Birmingham City Council will provide advice to all of Mondelez International’s UK sites on regulations including food safety and hygiene and has already lead to Mondelez International cutting £250,000 in packaging costs alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Fallon will then visit Quality Plated Products (QPP), a manufacturing company in Great Barr who have been awarded a loan of £245,000 from the government’s Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative. The company uses a unique technology to supply metal plated plastic to the automotive industry. Thanks to the government support it will be increasing capacity, creating an additional 11 jobs and starting a new apprenticeship scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Michael Fallon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Birmingham has long been an engine of the country’s economy, and my tour around the city has shown that’s certainly the case today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The government is doing all it can to support the West Midlands; whether that’s direct support through our Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative to companies like QPP, rolling out ultra fast broadband, or helping household names like Cadbury by reducing the amount of red tape they have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By taking clear and decisive action and giving direct help to companies and regions they can realise their growth potential and compete in the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister’s tour will also see him visiting Aero Engine Controls, a leading aerospace and defence manufacturing company. This is part of a series visits today by Business Ministers to discuss how business and government can work more effectively together to tackle barriers to growth, boost exports and grow high value jobs in the UK. The Minister will also meet members of the Greater Birmingham and Solihull Local Enterprise Partnership to discuss their ‘Strategy for Growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary Authority partnerships can be formed to cover key aspects of environmental health, trading standards and fire safety services, including health and safety, fair trading, food standards and product safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are now more than 600 businesses and 97 local authorities operating one or more of the 2,016 primary authority partnerships. The scheme covers more than 58,500 premises. 37% of businesses involved are SMEs. It was introduced in 2009 and is administered by the Better Regulation Delivery Office (BRDO), part of the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority"&gt;http://www.bis.gov.uk/brdo/primary-authority&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Advanced Manufacturing Supply Chain Initiative is a national fund of up to £125m to create more competitive supply chains, sustain or create new employment opportunities, and create better synergies and sustained collaborative relationships throughout supply chains that participate in this initiative. More information is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx"&gt;http://www.innovateuk.org/content/competition/advanced-manufacturing-supply-chain-initiative.ashx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s industrial strategy is about looking to the future, presenting a long-term, whole of government approach to supporting British business, giving them the confidence they need to invest, hire staff and grow. Long-term strategies are being developed in partnership with industry in key sectors including aerospace, nuclear, and the information economy - the aerospace strategy will be published in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65304</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"/>
    <title>Government's rail strategy receives independent endorsement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent review of the government’s rail franchising strategy, following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition, has backed the overall policy while delivering advice for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Richard Brown, Chairman of Eurostar, to conduct a thorough investigation into how the government should manage its franchising programme following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key conclusions from the Brown review stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the rail industry works, and that there is no credible case for major structural change (paragraph 1.4, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;passenger numbers have grown by 92% since privatisation… punctuality and passenger satisfaction are running at much improved levels… it is highly unlikely that these successes could have been delivered if franchising was fundamentally flawed (paragraph 1.5, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have now had nearly two decades’ experience of franchising and therefore a good idea as to what has worked and what still needs to be addressed (paragraph 1.6, p4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown’s report, published by the department today, recommends that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the department’s capability should be strengthened to manage future franchising programmes (paragraph 1.12, p8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise should be strengthened and simplified (paragraph 3.13, p23)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans should be put in place to devolve more English franchises to the relevant authorities (paragraph 5.5, p37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Brown said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In carrying out this review I have come to the conclusion that the franchising system is not broken, but rather it has made a major contribution to Britain’s increasingly successful rail network. It is therefore essential for both passengers and the wider rail market that the franchising programme is restarted as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To achieve this goal, my review has identified a series of practical proposals and recommendations which, if implemented, will result in a stronger and more effective approach to franchising. In addition, I have provided the department with three broad options for them to consider where a strengthened franchising organisation might be located. As set out in both my review and the Laidlaw Report, the department must look to strengthen its franchising capability as a top priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passengers cannot wait whilst theoretical discussions are held about the structure of railways. It is essential to get on with the franchising programme in order to maintain the momentum of investment in increasing capacity and improving services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The review has confirmed that government’s approach to rail franchising system is still the best way to secure the rail services for tax payers and fare payers alike. It has identified a number of detailed improvements, which I will carefully consider before publishing a further statement regarding the government’s franchising policy in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any delays to the franchising programme will not affect services for rail passengers and they will continue to receive the services they depend upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brown review was launched by the Department for Transport in October and follows work conducted by Sam Laidlaw, Chief Executive of Centrica and a non-executive DfT board member into what went wrong with the West Coast competition directly. His report was published in December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has recommended that by February the government should publish its plans for the Essex Thameside; Great Western; and the Thameslink, Southern and Great Northern franchise competitions which were put on hold last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government considers that, until those plans had been agreed, it would be inappropriate to publish the specific recommendations about these three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is planning to set out a programme for future franchise competitions in the spring alongside a further statement of franchising policy in light of the Brown Review and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"&gt;Rail franchising written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;br&gt;
Brown inquiry team press enquiries: 07584 115 270 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65289</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:38:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:38:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"/>
    <title>Travel advice: Bushfires in Australia </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>British nationals in Australia should be aware of the risk of bushfires and check local state authorities for information.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Huge bushfires have been raging in parts of New South Wales, Victoria and Tasmania this week, the fires have destroyed hundreds of houses and thousands of people have been evacuated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fires follow days of extremely high temperatures and despite cooler weather yesterday, record temperatures are expected to return at the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British people travelling in Australia should be aware of the risk of bushfires, they can happen unexpectedly if there are high temperatures and strong winds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travellers should check with local State authorities for information on bushfires in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cfa.vic.gov.au/" title="Victoria"&gt;Victoria&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cfs.sa.gov.au/site/home.jsp" title="South Australia"&gt;South Australia&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rfs.nsw.gov.au/" title="New South Wales"&gt;New South Wales&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="www.fire.tas.gov.au" title="Tasmania"&gt;Tasmania&lt;/a&gt; and check the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/asia-oceania/australia#natural" title="FCO travel advice"&gt;FCO travel advice&lt;/a&gt; page for updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the Foreign Office travel advice on twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/fcotravel" title="Foreign Office travel advice on twitter"&gt;@fcotravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinaustralia.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="British High Commission in Canberra"&gt;British High Commission in Canberra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65293</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-to-receive-cash-boost-for-choosing-development"/>
    <title>Communities to receive cash boost for choosing development</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles announces new cash incentives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities that tackle the legacy of inadequate house-building and choose to accept new housing will benefit directly from new generous cash incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods that take a proactive approach by drawing up a neighbourhood development plan, and securing the consent of local people in a referendum, will receive 25% of the revenues from the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; arising from the development that they choose to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cash boost will be paid directly to parish and town councils and can be used to back the community’s priorities for example to re-roof a village hall, refurbish a municipal pool or take over a community pub. Neighbourhoods without a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood development plan&lt;/a&gt; but where the levy is still charged will still receive a capped 15% share of the levy revenue arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities without a parish or town council will still benefit from this incentive, with the local planning authority retaining it and spending it in accordance with the wishes of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of hectoring people and forcing development on communities, the government believes that we need to persuade communities that development is in everyone’s interest. Incentives are key to getting the homes built that we both need for today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital this country increases the number of homes it builds to meet the needs of its increasing population. The failure of previous administrations to build enough homes, latterly despite the credit boom, led to a severe housing shortage that has been made worse by the rapid increase in the number of households. The number of people living alone has rocketed, and immigration has led to an influx of 1.7 million people into England in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to tackle this housing shortage and make best use of what we already have the government has invested £160 million to deal with the 250,000 homes empty for more than 6 months - 50,000 fewer then in 2009. This money combined with a share of £300 million announced in September’s housing growth package, will help put more than 15,000 empty homes back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also made clear that planning should encourage the effective use of land, including brownfield land that is not of high environmental value. The majority of all new homes - 76% of those completed in 2010 - were built on brownfield land. But this will not be enough and some undeveloped land will need to be made available for house-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a simple choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. We can shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or we can accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land and resolve that we will make these decisions locally and build beautiful places like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is determined to persuade communities to accept more house-building by giving them a tangible share of the benefits it brings. By undertaking a neighbourhood plan that makes space for new development, communities can secure revenues to make the community more attractive for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is an important way to make sure that development has the backing of the community. It is right that the areas that have organised themselves to bring forward a neighbourhood plan and have taken the plan through all the stages of the neighbourhood planning (including a successful examination and referendum) should be rewarded for their positive, pro-active approach to delivering growth. This is why they are entitled to an extra 10% of the levy arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy amount passed to neighbourhoods reflects the rates the local planning authority set for the levy. These charge a rate or different rates for development in the local area in pounds per square metre. The neighbourhood funding element will be calculated based on the levy receipts from the relevant development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The levy’s charges will become due from the date that a chargeable development is commenced. The neighbourhood funding element will be passed to parish or community councils in accordance with a timetable agreed between the local planning authority and the local council.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the money is transferred to a parish council (in England) or a community council (in Wales) they will decide how the money will be spent - although they will be expected to work with the local planning authority. Where the money stays with the local planning authority (in areas without a parish or community council) the local planning authority will engage with the communities where the development has happened to agree how best to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In areas that have not been subject to neighbourhood planning there will be a cap of £100 per council tax dwelling on the neighbourhood funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We aim to have these incentives in place from Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We previously &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;consulted&lt;/a&gt; on allowing councils the choice whether to spend their levy receipts on affordable housing but given other ongoing policies to support housing, we are not proposing to make this change at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also going to enable a mayoral development corporation to impose a Community Infrastructure Levy charge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65317</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:17:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/royal-navy-sails-into-london-boat-show"/>
    <title>Royal Navy sails into London Boat Show</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Royal Navy looks set to be a major draw at the London Boat Show, which opens at the ExCel exhibition centre this weekend.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an island nation, the UK’s prosperity and security is dependent on its ability to access the sea. That is why the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk" title="Royal Navy website"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; is globally deployed and has a range of versatile ships, submarines and aircraft operated by professional sailors, aviators and Royal Marine Commandos. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy will be at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonboatshow.com/2013/home.aspx" title="London Boat Show website"&gt;London Boat Show&lt;/a&gt; from 12 to 20 January, where visitors can learn more about naval life and how, every minute of every day, somewhere in the world they are protecting the nation’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cougar beach landing rehearsal" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5921/offshoreraidingcraft.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Royal Marines from 45 Commando Royal Marines and marines from HMS Bulwark carry out a beach assault in Plymouth. [Picture: Leading Airman (Photographer) Rob Gillies, Crown Copyright/MOD]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as celebrating the Navy’s rich heritage, show visitors can learn how they operate across a variety of missions from anti-terrorism, counter-narcotics, disaster relief and peacekeeping operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navy stand will include an opportunity to get up close to an advanced Offshore Raiding Craft (&lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt;). Measuring 9 metres long and able to travel in excess of 35 knots, the craft were part of the Navy’s commitment to keeping the public safe during the Olympic Games. The &lt;abbr title="Offshore Raiding Craft"&gt;ORC&lt;/abbr&gt; can also be equipped with general purpose machine guns, making them a highly-flexible and potent deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Boat Show, a Navy search and rescue Mark 5 Sea King will take to the skies beside ExCeL at 1400hrs on Saturday, 12 January, to illustrate what a rescue operation entails. The renowned Mark 5 is now the Navy’s workhorse of choice, operating in extreme conditions and ready to respond at a moment’s notice in an emergency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A four-man crew from 771 Naval Air Squadron in Cornwall will manoeuvre the helicopter with precision to make a simulated rescue from the dock. The helicopter will return on Sunday, 13 January, for a further demonstration at 1130hrs before heading back to its Cornish base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the show, the search and rescue crew will be at the C180 stand to meet the public and answer questions about the service, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/About-the-Royal-Navy/The-Navy-and-the-Environment/In-the-Air" title="Fleet Air Arm web page"&gt;Fleet Air Arm&lt;/a&gt; and the wider Royal Navy. There will also be the opportunity to attend a free daily presentation exploring the role of search and rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The London Boat Show takes place at Excel Arena from 12 to 20 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65346</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:27:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/housing-the-next-generation"/>
    <title>Housing the next generation</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Planning Minister Nick Boles at an event hosted by Policy Exchange.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;[This version of the speech excludes party political content].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last September, the Prime Minister declared that our mission is “to build an ‘aspiration nation’”, in which we “get behind people who want to get on in life.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s what’s always made our hearts beat faster,” he said. “It’s not just an economic mission” - but “a moral one” too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to that speech as one of David Cameron’s newest and most junior ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, though I find the Prime Minister’s message inspiring, implicit in it was a challenge that keeps me awake at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No aspiration is more deeply embedded in the British psyche than the desire to own your own home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the prospect of doing so has been slipping ever further out of the reach of millions of hard-working people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a result of our decades-long failure to build enough houses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the root cause of that is our decades-long refusal to release enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are other problems affecting the housing market in the short term: most of all, the lack of finance for buyers and developers since the credit crunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These the government is already tackling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers"&gt;FirstBuy&lt;/a&gt;, which helps reduce the deposit first-time buyers need to find to just 5% of the price of their new home, will invest £460 million, matched by housebuilders, to help 27,000 people by 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme"&gt;NewBuy&lt;/a&gt; enables other households to access 95% mortgages for new build homes, and the Prime Minister announced on Monday that we will bring forward further measures to increase the availability of affordable mortgages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my colleague, Mark Prisk, is deploying £570 million in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/get-britain-building"&gt;Get Britain Building fund&lt;/a&gt; to get building going on sites that already have planning permission, and using the £225 million fund that the Deputy Prime Minister announced to accelerate the delivery of housing on large sites like Cranbrook in Devon and Ebbsfleet in Kent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the long term, the original source of our housing crisis is the failure of past governments to provide enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As planning minister, it is my job to persuade local authorities to make more land available so that more homes can be built and the price of new homes comes down - and thereby reverse the trend that has been heading in the wrong direction for decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now can you understand why I sleep a little uneasily?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2011 census revealed that, in the ‘noughties’, home ownership in England fell, for the first time in 60 years: from 68% to 63%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because houses became too expensive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homelessness charity, Shelter, has shown that if the price of food had risen as fast as the price of housing in the last 30 years, a supermarket chicken would now cost £47 - and a jar of instant coffee would cost £20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, the average person setting aside 5% of their income each week could save up for a deposit on a house after 8 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it would take the same person 47 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some say that this trend is inevitable, given a growing population, rising incomes and a finite supply of land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Germany real house prices have remained constant since 2000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the Netherlands, which has shared the UK’s rapid growth in population, real house prices rose by a little bit more than a fifth in the same decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did they nearly double in the UK? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve built too few houses to keep up with the rapid increase in the number of households needing a place to live, especially the dizzying increase in the number of people living on their own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons for this growth in the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some we should celebrate - like the fact that people are living longer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others we should regret - like the high rate of divorce or the immigration policies that led to a net influx of 1.7 million people into England in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of these changes have happened and all of the people concerned have the right to a decent home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, Shelter estimated that we would need to build 240,000 new homes a year in England to cater for all of these new households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2012, Alan Holmans from the Cambridge Centre for Housing and Planning Research updated these estimates using my department’s publication of new projections of the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded, that, to keep pace with this trend, we now need to build 270,000 new homes a year, leading to a net increase of 250,000 a year as 20,000 of them would replace existing homes that have to be demolished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether Mr Holman’s projections will prove accurate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do know that the house-building that took place during the ‘noughties’ fell woefully short of what was necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a decade of easy credit and an explicit target to build 213,000 new homes a year in England, an annual average of only 147,000 new homes were completed between 2000 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period the population went up by 3.4 million and, from 1998 to 2008, the number of households went up by 1.7 million. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, in each year of the ‘noughties’, the Netherlands built over 4.4 new homes for every 1,000 inhabitants and the French built over 5.6 for every 1,000 inhabitants. In England, we built just 2.9. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in spite the fact that, between 2000 and 2010, total mortgage debt in the UK more than doubled - from £500 billion to £1.2 trillion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because this debt just fuelled a massive boom in prices - and did little to boost the supply of new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those homes that were built got smaller and smaller, as land prices went up and up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2001 to 2003 the new houses we built in England were smaller than the ones we’ve already got - and 30% smaller than the new houses being built in the Netherlands, a country that is more densely populated than ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For housing, as in so many areas of our national life, the ‘noughties’ were a wasted decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loads of money sloshing around, lots of top-down targets, but very little to show for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we have to build even more houses to make up the ground lost and to keep pace with future growth in the number of households needing homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s assuming we continue to tighten our grip on immigration so that net migration falls below 100,000 a year by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I do really understand why the idea of a lot more house-building makes people nervous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I certainly don’t want to see more open land developed than is absolutely necessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately there is no painless way to make homes affordable for working people earning ordinary wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the empty homes?” people ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are certainly right to suggest that we should make full use of our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes"&gt;existing housing stock&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most empty homes are only empty for short periods while they change hands or are renovated or are caught up in probate after the last owner’s death. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are around 259,000 houses that have been empty for more than 6 months, 50,000 fewer than in 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has already invested £160 million and that, together with a share of the £300 million additional spending announced in September’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;Housing Growth Package&lt;/a&gt;, should help put over 15,000 empty properties back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to see good homes standing empty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can’t make more than a marginal contribution to the hundreds of thousands of new homes that we need every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the brownfield land?” people then ask - and they point to the Campaign to Protect Rural England (&lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt;) estimate that England has enough brownfield land to support 1.5 million homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to maximise the number of homes we build on previously developed land - not least because such land tends to benefit from existing links to our road and rail networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; admitted that we would only get 450,000 new homes out of brownfield sites in those parts of the country where most of the new homes are needed - London, the South East and the South West. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And achieving that number would require us to build on every scrap of brownfield land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that we are already building most new homes on brownfield land: 76% of all the homes completed in 2010 as against 56% in 1997. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simply can’t squeeze much more out of brownfield sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To restrict new house-building to brownfield land would leave us a long way short of the number of new homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So “what about the developers’ land banks?” people then ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, I do understand why it riles people that their local councils have to find new sites for development, when the major house-builders are sitting on land with permission to build hundreds of thousands of new homes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m afraid this concern is also misplaced, resting on a misunderstanding about how the British house-building industry works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of September 2012, on sites of 10 or more units, there were 487,000 units with detailed planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 246,000 of them were on sites where no building has even started - and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; that I am taking through Parliament with colleagues will make it easier for developers to renegotiate the unaffordable Section 106 agreements that have made many of these schemes unviable and caused them to stall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most sites with planning permission are for schemes of 150 units or more which developers generally build out over 3 to 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are going to have any prospect of getting our current house-builders to build the number of new homes we need, we need them to have a pipeline of sites representing 3 to 5 years’ supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s over a million units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with developers’ land banks is not that they exist - but that they are currently much too small to feed the level of house-building that we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am afraid that we have a simple choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can turn a blind eye while the dream of a property-owning democracy shrivels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th Century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t believe that anyone really wants to go down that road. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we believe in anything, we believe in the power of home ownership to motivate people to work hard, raise strong families and build healthy communities, to put down roots, take responsibility for their surroundings and look out for their neighbours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron said, “We get behind people who want to get on in life, the young people who dream of their first pay-cheque, their first car, their first home - and are ready and willing to work hard to get those things.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to resolve that we will make these decisions locally, and that we will build beautiful places like we used to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way England can remain the green and pleasant land we all love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start from a good position. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, contrary to media myth, we’ve got plenty of undistinguished, undeveloped land to spare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By overlaying satellite imagery onto Ordnance Survey maps, the Centre for Ecology and Hydrology’s 2007 Land Cover Map shows that 8.9% of England is built up or developed as gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that over 90% is not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty together account for around 30% - more than 3 times the amount that is built on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we include the green belts that stop our cities sprawling without limit then that goes up to around 40% of England is protected from development - more than 4 times the area that is built on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are ancient woodlands and other irreplaceable habitats which are protected by the National Planning Policy Framework, and other important sites which lie outside the official designations, that are rightly championed by organisations like the &lt;abbr title="Royal Society for the Protection of Birds"&gt;RSPB&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Woodland Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is high quality agricultural land which all of us want to see used for the essential purpose of growing food. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are much loved open spaces in villages and towns, which local people understandably want to keep intact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done will undermine the protection of National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty and the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or stop good agricultural land being used for farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or prevent councils from identifying ancient woodland and green spaces that local people want them to protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done involves telling communities how many new houses they should accept or where they should be built. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional top-down housing targets caused enormous resentment and as we have seen failed to deliver the goods - house-building has fallen to its lowest peacetime level since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have already revoked the regional strategy for the East of England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, having considered the responses to the consultation on the environmental report, I can announce today that I have decided to revoke the equivalent edict for Yorkshire and the Humber while saving the policies to protect York’s green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making decisions about the other regional strategies in due course, once the consultations on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;other environmental reports&lt;/a&gt; have closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the localism that Eric Pickles has unleashed is not and never has been a one-way street. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has always said, with power comes responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; spells it out very clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they draw up their local plans, councils must assess their local housing need in an objective way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they must identify immediately developable sites sufficient to supply all of the new homes that are needed over the next 5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, many councils are embracing this duty with energy and imagination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some are dragging their feet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a few are looking for ways to evade their responsibilities - or slough them off onto their neighbours because the politics of house-building is just too difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is not acceptable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils which do not produce credible plans to meet local housing need will find that the presumption in favour of sustainable development will trump local decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will have to explain to local residents why their failure to produce a robust local plan exposed their communities to speculative development in places where it is not welcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not defend and the government will not support those local councils who abdicate their responsibility to meet their fair share of our common housing needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to pretend that it will be easy for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors will have to find a way to persuade the people who elect them that substantial further house-building is in the interest of the whole community, including those who are living there now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are giving them the tools they need to go about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that people want is input into the plans for development in their neighbourhood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not just perfunctory consultation that is acknowledged but then ignored. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But real involvement and a vote on the outcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve created the option of a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood plan&lt;/a&gt;, which is drawn up by representatives of a defined community and subject to a referendum of all their neighbours, before it can be adopted and form part of the statutory plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;300 localities are already pursuing a neighbourhood plan - from Thame in South Oxfordshire to St James’ ward in central Exeter to central Milton Keynes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailblazer is Upper Eden in Cumbria, where I was on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their neighbourhood plan will be the first to be put to the test in a local referendum in March of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing people want, aside from local input and local control, is a share in the benefits that new development can bring, whether that takes the form of a boost in the local authority’s tax revenues or an investment in new community facilities or better infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt; that gives local councils over £8,000 over 6 years for every new Council Tax Band D home that gets built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils received £430 million in New Homes Bonus in 2012 to 2013 and are provisionally set to receive £660 million in 2013 to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need incentives, as Policy Exchange has pointed out, that are even more local - so that the people who have to live with new housing developments get a direct benefit from them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I am pleased to be able to announce that in areas that charge the new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; neighbourhoods which accept new development will get 15% of the revenues from the Levy (up to a maximum of £100 per existing household).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because I believe, and this government believes, that neighbourhood plans are the key to unlocking more house-building, those communities that draw up a neighbourhood plan and have it approved by local people in a referendum will receive 25% of these revenues with no upper limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to re-roof your village hall, build a permanent home for your community shop, refurbish the municipal swimming pool, implement a new landscape design in your local park or save your local pub, look no further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jump on the bandwagon and get yourself a neighbourhood plan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government believes in localism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that if you give people power, they will use it responsibly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you explain to them what their community and their country needs, they will do their bit to make sure it is provided. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you give them a stake in a future in which beautifully designed homes with easy access to green space are, once again affordable for working people on ordinary wages, they will do what it takes to bring that future about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my perch on the lower branches at the Department for Communities and Local Government, I look around the great wood that is the British government and I see other ministers battering away at the barriers that hold people back with gusto and grit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain Duncan Smith reforming the benefits system to ensure that work always pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gove giving schools control over their own destinies while ramping up expectations of the standards that they will achieve for their students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are an inspiration and a goad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inspiration because they are ministers who have identified a shocking injustice in the way our society works and are fearless in their determination to “spread the privilege” of a good education and a decent job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A goad because we are more than half way through this Parliament, and it’s now up to me to make sure that our reformed planning system provides enough land to build the houses that England’s next generation so desperately needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does, I’m sure I will have no problem sleeping at nights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65332</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:36:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary updates Parliament on Syria</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated Parliament on the crisis in Syria and set out further UK action in the coming weeks.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;AS DELIVERED&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mr Speaker, with permission I will make a statement to update the House on the crisis in Syria; a crisis which is still intensifying. 60,000 Syrians are now believed to have died, six hundred thousand people have become refugees, 2 million people are internally displaced and four million people are in desperate need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the true horror of this conflict, 1,000 civilians were reportedly killed in one six-day period over Christmas. On Christmas Day opposition activists reported that seventeen people were executed at a checkpoint in the Damascus suburbs – nine of them from one family. The regime has used SCUD missiles to target populated areas, and deployed cluster munitions. Entire urban districts have been reduced to rubble in cities like Homs and Aleppo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House will join me in expressing our solidarity with millions of courageous Syrian people in the face of this appalling brutality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continue to believe that the best way to end this bloodshed and to protect all Syria’s communities is through a political transition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside. And we are determined that all our actions will uphold UK and international law, and support justice and accountability for the Syrian people themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks we will focus on six principal areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we will intensify our diplomatic efforts to reach a political transition. We are actively supporting the efforts of UN/Arab League Special Representative Lakhdar Brahimi who has travelled to Damascus, to Moscow for talks with the Russian Government, and who is due to hold trilateral talks with Russian and the United States this week. My Ministerial colleagues and I are in regular contact with him and expect to hold further talks with him in London later this month. Our goal remains to persuade Russia and China to join us in putting the full weight of the UN Security Council behind a political transition plan for Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we will continue our work to help the Syrian National Coalition develop its plans for the future of Syria. Since I last updated the House I attended the Friends of Syria meeting in Marrakech, where the US and many other countries followed us in recognising the National Coalition as the sole legitimate representative of the Syrian people, and where $150m dollars was pledged to support the humanitarian effort. The Coalition is enlarging its membership to include Christian, Kurdish and other minority communities. At a meeting in Istanbul this week we saw encouraging signs of the Coalition making every effort to broaden its support further and build on its legitimacy, although much work remains to be done.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working to strengthen moderate political forces in Syria committed to a democratic future for the country. We’ve provided £7.4 million of non-lethal support to the Syrian Opposition, civil society and human rights defenders, and I can announce now that we will provide an additional two million pounds of support, bringing the total to £9.4m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All our assistance is designed to help to save lives, or to mitigate the impact of the conflict, or to support people trying to achieve a free and democratic Syria. It includes solar powered lighting, generators, communication equipment and water purification kits to help opposition groups, and satellite communication devices for activists to document Human Rights violations and abuses so that one day the perpetrators of appalling crimes can be brought to justice. It involves support for local level administration councils providing services to Syrian people during the conflict. We’ve given training to more than 300 Syrian journalists, who are striving to develop alternative sources of media and freedom of the press in Syria, and are training activists working to create a network of peace building committees across five cities in Syria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also helping the National Coalition to coordinate the international humanitarian response, and have provided a humanitarian adviser to work with them. At all times we urge the Coalition to ensure that all opposition groups meet their commitments on human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we will continue to increase the pressure on the regime to stop the violence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December we argued that the EU sanctions regime on Syria, including the arms embargo, should be rolled over for three months until 1 March rather than for twelve months, so that there would be an earlier review of it. And we have secured this position. We believed it was important not to freeze EU policy for a whole year just as a new opposition Coalition was being launched and the conflict was intensifying on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No decisions have yet been made to change the support we provide to the Syrian National Coalition or the Syrian people. But European countries now have the flexibility to consider taking additional steps to try to save lives if there is no progress in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly the best outcome for the Syrian people would be a diplomatic breakthrough, bring an end to the bloodshed and establishing a new Syrian government able to restore stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we must keep open options to help save lives in Syria and to assist opposition groups opposed to extremism if the violence continues. We should send a strong signal to Assad that all options are on the table. We will therefore seek to amend the EU sanctions so that the possibility of additional assistance is not closed off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one can be sure how the situation in Syria will develop in the coming months. There is no guarantee that Mr Brahimi’s efforts will be successful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Assad’s speech last week urged the Syrian people to unite in a “war” against his opponents. Given the regime’s intransigence and brutality there is a serious risk that the violence will indeed worsen in the coming months. If that happens, the international community’s response will have to be stepped up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will not rule out any options to save lives and protect civilians in the absence of a political transition in Syria. We will ensure that our efforts are legal, that they are aimed at saving life and that they support at all times the objective of a political transition and encouraging moderate political forces in Syria, and we will keep the House properly informed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, we continue to increase our life-saving humanitarian assistance to the Syrian people. The UK is the second largest bilateral donor to UN relief efforts, supporting more than 100,000 people across the region with food parcels, blankets and warm clothing. On 21 December my Right Honourable Friend the International Development Secretary announced a further £15 million in humanitarian aid, bringing our total support to £68.5 million so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members on all sides of the House will have seen images of Syrian refugees struggling with rain and cold in refugee camps across the region, The latest £15 million pounds of funding will be used to provide food, clean water, blankets and shelter to help Syrians cope with the misery of these winter months, medical supplies to treat the sick and wounded since so many Syrian medical facilities have been destroyed, and armoured vehicles to enable humanitarian agencies to deliver aid safely inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN has appealed for $1.5 billion for the first six months of 2013. This is the largest ever short-term UN appeal, but it remains seriously under-funded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the donor conference to be hosted by Kuwait and the UN Secretary-General later this month we will again call on other countries to pledge the additional humanitarian aid that is desperately needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pay tribute Mr Speaker to the twenty-six humanitarian workers who have been killed in Syria since the fighting began, and deplore the rise in attacks on medical facilities, which are contrary to international law and an affront to basic humanity. We urge all parties to stop the violence and allow humanitarian agencies to deliver assistance safely and without interference, in accordance with international law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifth, we are continuing detailed planning for how we can help a future Syrian government with the many challenges Syria will face during transition. This process must be led by the Syrian people. But they will need help from the international community as they repair schools, roads and hospitals destroyed during the conflict, and restart their ravaged economy. Today we are hosting leading members of the Syrian opposition and representatives of 14 countries and international organisations at a Wilton Park conference designed to advance detailed planning of that support, including on political reform, security, institution-building and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And sixth, we are supporting UN efforts to document and deter human rights abuses in Syria. The Human Rights Council’s Commission of Inquiry on Syria published their latest report on 20 December. It shows that the international human rights violations highlighted in its previous reports are continuing unabated. We will continue to do all we can to support their work. And we are providing specific leadership in efforts to confront rape and sexual violence in Syria. We’ve deployed experts to the region to provide training in how to respond to reports of sexual violence, to improve the prospect of future investigation and prosecutions, and we will intensify this work as a matter of urgency. We are also urging the Syrian National Coalition to commit themselves to ensuring justice and accountability for the Syrian people, including drawing their attention to the right of a future government in Syria to refer their situation to the International Criminal Court, even though some members of the UN Security Council are blocking that option at present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is our approach: intensifying our efforts to forge agreement at the UN, pursing a political transition on the ground while ruling out no option to save lives if the situation deteriorates, supporting the opposition and the Syrian people, increasing the pressure on the regime and being prepared to do so in new ways if necessary, working to deter human rights violations and abuses, and planning to help Syria get back on its feet once the conflict comes to an end.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian people are enduring unimaginable suffering. They are at the heart of this crisis, their future is at stake, and our country and the world must not abandon them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK hosts &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;conference on Syrian-led political transition.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65306</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:03:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I took the decision last October to cancel the competition for the InterCity West Coast rail franchise and to put the wider franchising process on hold, I commissioned two independent reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am today laying before the House the second of these, by Richard Brown, the Chairman of Eurostar and a highly respected industry figure. His report sets out his recommendations on how best to get the franchising programme back on course. I welcome this report, and am grateful to Mr Brown and his team for their swift and thorough consideration of the issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown concludes that franchising is a fundamentally sound approach for securing the passenger railway services on which so many people rely.  He has identified a number of detailed recommendations for improving the way that franchises are specified and franchise competitions are run. The issues he has identified deserve, and will get, very careful consideration. His recommendations include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that the franchising programme should be restarted as soon as possible, but at a pace that both the department and the industry can sustain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that franchise term should be determined by the circumstances and size of each individual franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals to strengthen and simplify the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals for the financial and contractual structure of future franchises, including in relation to risk allocation and capital requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that the government should plan to devolve responsibility for further English franchises to the relevant authorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also makes recommendations on how to strengthen my department’s capability to manage the future franchising programme, echoing the findings of Sam Laidlaw’s independent inquiry into the lessons to be learnt from the InterCity West Coast competition.  My department has already published a response to Mr Laidlaw’s report, setting out a series of actions that will allow it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible.  The Permanent Secretary has now appointed a single director-general with responsibility for rail, including franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review recommends that the government should determine, by February, our plans for the three franchise competitions which I put on hold last October.  I accept that recommendation, and I will update the House when I have determined those plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, however, I consider that it would be inappropriate to publish Mr Brown’s specific recommendations about these three franchise competitions because of their stock market sensitivity, and so I have redacted the relevant paragraphs from the version of the report I have published today.  I will publish the redacted paragraphs once I have decided the way forward for those three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also recommends that we should set out a clear programme for future franchise competitions.  I will do so in the Spring, alongside a further statement of the government’s rail franchising policy in light of Mr Brown’s recommendations and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020&lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"&gt;Government’s rail strategy receives independent endorsement press notice, 10 January 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/letter-from-the-secretary-of-state-to-richard-brown"&gt;Letter from the Secretary of State to Richard Brown, 15 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/west-coast-main-line-franchise-competition-cancelled"&gt;West Coast Main Line franchise competition cancelled press notice, 3 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/statement-on-west-coast-main-line-and-franchising"&gt;West Coast Main Line and franchising oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 29 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65197</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T22:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T22:04:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/fatalities/sapper-richard-reginald-walker-killed-in-afghanistan"/>
    <title>Sapper Richard Reginald Walker killed in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>Fatality notice</category>
    <summary>It is with great sadness that the Ministry of Defence must confirm that Sapper Richard Reginald Walker from 28 Engineer Regiment, attached to 21 Engineer Regiment as part of the Task Force Helmand Engineer Group, was killed in Afghanistan on Monday 7 January 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was shot in an apparent ‘insider attack’ by a member of the Afghan National Army (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt;) at Patrol Base Hazrat in the Nahr-e Saraj district of Helmand province on Monday 7 January 2013. He was working on a construction task with other military engineers from his Troop, as part of the preparations to hand the camp over to Afghan security forces, when the Afghan soldier turned his weapon on &lt;abbr title="Afghan National Army"&gt;ANA&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="International Security Assistance Force"&gt;ISAF&lt;/abbr&gt; soldiers at the base. The incident resulted in a number of casualties, all of whom were extracted to the Bastion Role 3 medical facility where Sapper Walker was pronounced dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sapper-richard-reginald-walker-corps-of-royal-engineers"&gt;Sapper Richard Reginald Walker, Corps of Royal Engineers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sapper Richard Walker [Picture: via MOD]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5924/130107-NRI-TFH_Engr-Eulogy-WALKER.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sapper Richard Walker&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sapper Richard Walker was born on 7 February 1989 in Leeds. He worked as a technician for Vauxhall before joining the Army in July 2008. Upon joining the Royal Engineers he completed his basic training at the Army Training Regiment Bassingbourn before moving on to Gibraltar Barracks, Minley, where he completed his Phase Two Combat Engineer Training. He then moved to the Defence School of Transport Leconfield where he completed his trade training to become a driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He joined his first unit, 28 Engineer Regiment in Hameln, Germany, in September 2009, deploying with them to Canada and then Kenya on major exercises. His Troop, from 42 Field Squadron, was attached to 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron (73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt;) based in Ripon, North Yorkshire for Operation Herrick 17. His Troop joined 73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt; in August 2012 and deployed with the Squadron to Afghanistan at the start of September as part of the Task Force Helmand Engineer Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was a valued member of 73 &lt;abbr title="Armoured Engineer Squadron"&gt;AES&lt;/abbr&gt; and deployed on every single Troop task. He was a popular and well respected member of his Troop and upon joining the Squadron he quickly gained friends across the spectrum of ranks; a testament to his likeable character and willingness to join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An avid football fan, Sapper Walker represented his Regiment at football and spent endless hours in the gym. He even managed to spend some time trying to learn to play the guitar albeit one chord at a time. Above all he was a devoted father and would talk for hours on end about his love for his daughter Lilly-Faith who sadly he only knew for 18 months before his deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was destined to go on to greater things – his willingness to learn, unswerving sense of duty and personal motivation to pursue a successful career would have seen him progress far. Above all he will be remembered for his charisma and team spirit; a true all-rounder, his loss will be felt for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker’s family paid the following tribute to their son and brother:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richard held two things close to his heart – his daughter and his colleagues in the Army. A proud, patriotic man, he died doing a job he loved, supporting his friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Chas Story &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Commanding Officer, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was the epitome of a true Sapper, one who would roll up his sleeves and get on with the task in hand no matter what, but importantly he would do it with great humour. He made sure that he made the most of every opportunity, both in the Army and at home; it is without doubt that he had a lot to offer and a bright future. He was hugely respected as a fit, professional soldier with a massive character. This was his first tour of Afghanistan but anyone would have thought he was a seasoned expert, such was his ability and professionalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our thoughts and prayers are with his family, including his young daughter Lilly-Faith, at this very difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Jack Nicholson &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Commanding Officer, 21 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the short time that Sapper Walker served with my Regiment he struck me as being a driven young man, full of ambition and oozing with professional pride and confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An outstanding soldier in the best traditions of The Corps of Royal Engineers, he made an immediate impact on all those who had the privilege of serving alongside him. Although on his first operational tour, he acted like a veteran of many years’ experience and clearly relished the challenges he faced with his Troop in Afghanistan. Hard working and utterly loyal to his mates, he was a real character who had established himself as a man of action within his adopted Squadron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His tragic loss has stunned the whole Engineer Group and we are all trying desperately to come to terms with this awful event. Our heartfelt condolences are with his family and friends at this terrible time, most especially his young daughter Lilly-Faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Chloe Plimmer &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Officer Commanding, 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron, 21 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I first met Sapper Walker when he arrived with his Troop to join our Squadron for the forthcoming deployment to Afghanistan. He immediately struck me as a very likeable character; a polite and motivated young soldier who was very keen to deploy on his first operational tour. He saw it as the culmination of all his training and was excited about the prospect of operational service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the initial months spent in theatre Sapper Walker was a key member of his Troop and was crucial to facilitating every task that they undertook; he had the skill-set to operate a number of critical vehicles. His enthusiasm for his role and the success that the Troop achieved during this time were undoubtedly testament to his professionalism; always keen to be involved, he would give his best at all times even when under considerable pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whenever I saw Sapper Walker he always made a point of saying ‘hello’ and I felt that I got to know him better than many other soldiers in the Squadron. I never once doubted his motivation and he always said he was ‘living the dream’. He was a bright, cheerful, fun soldier who was relishing the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We in 73 Armoured Engineer Squadron have been hugely privileged to have Sapper Walker’s Troop attached to us and as an individual he was a shining example to all ranks across the board. His positive attitude and excellent performance ensured that he was seen as one of our own, and our heartfelt sympathies go out to all of those in his Troop and also his friends and colleagues in 42 Field Support Squadron and 28 Engineer Regiment back in Germany. He was one of the very best and we are all left feeling hollow and saddened by his loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To his family, there are no amount of words that can reduce the pain of losing such a brave son, brother and doting father to Lilly-Faith. Our deepest condolences are with them at this extremely difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Brad Southall &lt;abbr title="Royal Engineers"&gt;RE&lt;/abbr&gt;, Support Troop Commander, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker was a shining star. When I took command of my troop I was struck by his charisma, his devotion to duty and his immense capability; he was the older brother whom everyone looked up to. To his friends he was hugely loyal and he was headstrong too. I could discuss tasks with him at length but he would always end up doing things his way; he was so determined. I began to accept that over time it was his view that counted and I learned to trust him immeasurably. He was passionate and committed to his work – a consummate professional. He died doing the job he loved and I am proud to have served alongside him; a fellow Sapper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He spoke often of his daughter, Lilly-Faith, and was a proud and devoted father. My thoughts and condolences are with his family and friends at this most tragic time. The Regiment has lost one of its best men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Sean Eaton, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have had the privilege of knowing Sapper Richie Walker for well over a year now. Firstly in my Troop in Kenya last year and now on Operation Herrick 17. Sapper Walker was a character and always present to give a small quip when required. As a soldier he remained professional in all that was asked of him. He had started a physical training regime with the aspiration to box on return from Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Walker has a young daughter, Lilly-Faith, who was never far from his mind. He would often speak about her with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I only knew Richie for a short time, but he has left a lasting impression on me and will never be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My thoughts go out to his family at this difficult time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lance Corporal Terry Burke, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve have had the privilege of knowing Richie since he joined 28 Engineer Regiment through the Regimental Football Team. However, I really got to know him throughout the last year when I joined his Troop in 42 Squadron back in Hameln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I class Richie as a close friend who was always there with a smile on his face, especially when he was talking about his daughter Lilly-Faith; he was a very proud dad. I had only spoken to him on 3 January 2013 while on R&amp;amp;R and he told me how much he had enjoyed spending time with his daughter at the beginning of December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As well as being in the next bed space to me out here, we tended to go the gym together where Richie was keen on getting the perfect six-pack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of the lads that have ever met Richie know what a great friend he was. He will be sorely missed. All our thoughts are with his daughter Lilly-Faith at this sad time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Liam Ballantyne, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I first met Richie in October 2009 when I joined 42 Field Squadron. I was allocated a bed space in the same room and we hit it off as friends immediately. Richie was always willing to assist me with anything that I needed having come straight from Training Regiment myself. It was clear to me from the start that he was an extremely caring and thoughtful individual to all around him and he immediately became a very loyal friend. We would have done anything for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the years, we visited each other in our home towns and we got to know each other’s families during these visits. We enjoyed some great times and his family always extended their greatest hospitality to me whenever I stayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie was a devoted father who would have done anything for his daughter, Lilly-Faith. He never stopped talking about her wherever we were. I even remember being on stag in the Kenyan bush with him and all he could talk about was his daughter, despite the ever present threat of lions roaming close by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie, you were a truly wonderful person and that is why people were naturally drawn towards you as a friend. You were a true brother to me; you will never be forgotten and you will be sadly missed by all who knew you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapper Matthew Cunningham, 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sapper Richie ‘Guns’ Walker – comrade, friend, father and much-loved son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I knew Richie for 3 years and was privileged to be able to call him my best mate. He was thoughtful, funny and a big character in any group he found himself amongst, but he always put others first. He was very wise and mature for such a young lad. I have so many good memories from over the last three years but the one that stands out the most for me was the day that he christened his daughter Lilly-Faith. He was so proud of her; that day I remember him standing that extra inch taller and his smile beaming more than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You will be sorely missed brother, gone but never forgotten until we meet again at the bar in the sky… RIP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all members of 8 Troop, 42 Field Squadron, 28 Engineer Regiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We had the privilege of knowing and working with Richie from the start of Operation Herrick 17. In this time we have found out that he is a joy to work with, plus an amiable character amongst the Troop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Richie was always talking about his daughter, Lilly-Faith, and from this you could tell he was a devoted father and loved his little Princess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He was a top bloke and our condolences go out to his family; he will be sorely missed by all who were fortunate enough to have known him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State for Defence, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was deeply saddened to learn of the death of Sapper Richard Walker. The tributes of his colleagues speak of a popular, committed soldier who was devoted to his unit and a dedicated family man. I send my deepest condolences to his family and loved ones at this sad time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64980</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T18:00:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T18:00:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"/>
    <title>UK hosts conference on Syrian-led political transition </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK meeting aims to galvanise international support for Syrian-led transition to a stable democratic country</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK is hosting a private meeting of the Syrian National Coalition, leading international partners and international experts on 9-10 January to consider how the international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the meeting a Foreign Office spokesperson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As announced by the Foreign Secretary to the Friends of Syria meeting in Marrakech on 12 December, the UK is intensifying its support for a Syrian-led transition process. With the escalating violence and suffering Syria has endured over the past 22 months, the international community has an important responsibility to ensure it is ready to help a future Syrian government achieve political transition and stability quickly. Therefore, it is vital that the international community is ready to react to change on the ground, which could happen suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting"&gt;Foreign Secretary’s remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64952</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T13:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T13:15:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-viscount-younger-of-leckie-appointed-as-business-minister"/>
    <title>The Viscount Younger of Leckie appointed as Business Minister</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Lord Younger appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger was appointed as Parliamentary Under Secretary of State at the Department for Business Innovation and Skills, by the Prime Minister today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Younger will be responsible for all of the  Department for Business Innovation and Skills business in the House of Lords, in particular steering the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill through its final stages in the Lords. He will also have responsibility for the Intellectual Property portfolio. Lord Younger was previously a Government Whip in the House of Lords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Lord Younger said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to have been asked by the Prime Minister to do this important job; the business department is central to the Government’s drive for balanced and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I look forward to making a real contribution to supporting business to generate new private sector employment and boost our international competiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to entering the House of Lords Lord Younger had a 25 year career in the human resources industry and financial services.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Full list of Lord Younger’s Ministerial responsibilities will be published shortly. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64330</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:47:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/libya-operation-recognition-for-naval-air-squadron-personnel"/>
    <title>Libya operation recognition for Naval Air Squadron personnel</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Navy personnel from 815 Naval Air Squadron have received medals for their part in the NATO-led Libya operation in 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 4 servicemen from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Aircraft/Naval-Air-Squadrons/815" title="815 Naval Air Squadron web page"&gt;815 Naval Air Squadron&lt;/a&gt; are among 1,500 Royal Navy personnel to receive medals for their part in the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt;-led Libya operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aircrew and engineers, based at Royal Naval Air Station Yeovilton, were presented with &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; Operation Unified Protector medals for their participation in the Libya operation while serving with 217 Flight on board &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Decommissioned-Units/HMS-Liverpool" title="HMS Liverpool web page"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Naval Air Squadron personnel with their Operation Unified Protector medals" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5919/HMS_Liverpool_Flight_NATO_Medals_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: Lieutenant Alastair Crawford, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Lieutenant Craig Farquharson with their Operation Unified Protector medals [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The four who received medals for the operation were Lieutenant Alistair Crawford, Lieutenant Craig Farquharson, Petty Officer Paul Perry and Air Engineering Technician Matthew Parker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Crawford, from Yeovil, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;217 Flight and &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool made a vital contribution to Operation Unified Protector, always at the forefront of helping to protect Libyan civilians and just show the flexibility of the Royal Navy and Fleet Air Arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petty Officer Perry, from Worcester, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud to have had the opportunity to help the Libyan civilians and put my years of experience to the best possible use. Medals are nice but that is the real reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They formed part of the high-profile &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; task force to provide maritime embargo operations and to control the no-fly zone to help protect the Libyan civilian population. The Flight were pivotal to the success of the maritime operation as they provided surface search and routine maritime patrols to counter the threat posed by pro-Gaddafi forces in laying mines in the vicinity of Libyan ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of the oldest warships in the Royal Navy, the team of aircrew and engineers regularly operated at high readiness, which required them to be on 15 minutes’ standby to launch over many nights, and all this achieved in spite of the sustained exposure to the harsh environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all of the problems they encountered, their aircraft flew over 270 hours in support of the &lt;abbr title="North Atlantic Treaty Organization"&gt;NATO&lt;/abbr&gt; mission, including 75 hours in August 2011 alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout their 8-month operational deployment, 217 Flight continually demonstrated an unquestionable commitment in support of the overall task group output. The engineering effort was pivotal to the exceptional aircraft availability enjoyed by &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Liverpool’s command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64320</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T12:13:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/marines-train-to-tackle-pirates"/>
    <title>Marines train to tackle pirates </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Royal Marines based on the deployed warship HMS Monmouth have been practising their ship-boarding skills to combat pirates and smugglers.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the ship’s company of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Ships/Frigates/HMS-Monmouth" title="HMS Monmouth website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth&lt;/a&gt; is a detachment of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="The Royal Marines website"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt;, vital for &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s tasking at sea. One of the major roles of the Marines is conducting boarding missions against suspected pirates and smugglers. To hone these skills they used their time on land to visit a specialist ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ facility owned by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard in Bahrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5912/20130109commandos02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Marine Ryan Billington goes low while Marine Jack Brent goes high during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Ship-in-a-Box’ recreates a realistic section of a ship in which ‘room clearance’ drills may be practised and perfected with a dramatic sense of realism. High-powered Airsoft simulation weapons are used in the facility, which range from rifles, shotguns and pistols to claymore mines. They really pack a punch, so much so that personal protective equipment must be worn when magazines are fitted and rounds are flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team of Royal Marines are on detachment from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines/3-Commando-Brigade/43-Cdo-Fleet-Protection-Group" title="43 Commando Fleet Protection Group Royal Marines website"&gt;43 Commando Fleet Protection Group&lt;/a&gt;, based at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/Naval-Bases/Clyde" title="Her Majesty's Naval Base Clyde website"&gt;HM Naval Base Clyde&lt;/a&gt;, Faslane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5914/20130109commandos04.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM during the walkthrough before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Will Hall, Officer Commanding &lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth’s Royal Marines detachment, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My Marines really benefited from the training provided by the &lt;abbr title="United States"&gt;US&lt;/abbr&gt; Coast Guard at their facility in Bahrain - the instructors were incredibly hospitable and approachable, whilst the use of Airsoft weapons added a level of realism to the scenarios that is difficult to achieve in the training environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The team is now prepared and ready to put their skills to use during boarding operations in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5913/20130109commandos01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Captain Will Hall RM debriefs members of the team before the firing exercise [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Marines’ exercise comes after a busy time at sea over Christmas and has given the rest of the ship’s company time to recharge their batteries in preparation for the challenges of the New Year in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Her Majesty's Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/abbr&gt; Monmouth continues her 7-month deployment of the region, conducting maritime security patrols the Arabian Sea, the northern Indian Ocean and the Gulf of Aden. Whilst deployed, Monmouth will also be carrying out security patrols and exercises with coalition forces in the region to strengthen ties with foreign allies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64307</id>
    <published>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-09T10:03:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review--3"/>
    <title>Implementation of the Penfold Review</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Proposals to simplify the process of stopping up or diverting a highway will be announced in a consultation response today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a government response to the consultation that closed on 24 August detailing proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up or diversion of a highway, where this is required for the purposes of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main options presented in the consultation were to permit applications for a stopping up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission and to devolve decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided not to devolve the stopping up and diversion order process to a local level. Consultation responses suggested that any devolution should be accompanied by a charging regime; additional costs and charges would be borne by both local authorities and those making applications, with no guarantee of a simpler or faster process. The government does not feel that placing additional burdens on local authorities and costs on developers is right at this time. And the government is aware that the speed of processing applications for stopping up or diversion orders has increased considerably in the last year. Additionally, we do not propose to reform or encourage a greater use of section 116 of the Highways Act 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government continues to support the first option, to allow stopping up and diversion applications to be made alongside planning applications. The government considers this will remove a significant barrier to growth, by speeding up the process and allowing a reduction of burdens on both applicants and local authorities, as both applications can be considered concurrently. Legislation currently in Parliament, as part of the Growth and Infrastructure Bill, will give effect to this measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government response will be available in the libraries of both Houses and on the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/stopping-up-and-diversion-orders-reform-of-the-application-process-for-local-highways"&gt;department’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9720</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T14:33:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T14:33:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-taskforce-to-end-the-problem-of-beds-in-sheds--3"/>
    <title>National taskforce to end the problem of 'beds in sheds'</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new national taskforce has been set up to tackle the issue of “beds in sheds” by taking action against criminal landlords and removing illegal immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Housing Minister Grant Shapps and Immigration Minister Damian Green held the first in a series of cross-Whitehall summits with representatives from the police, the UK Border Agency and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meetings will find ways to close down thousands of sheds and outbuildings being rented out illegally to migrants, including some with no right to be in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘tenants’ are being exploited by ruthless landlords who charge them extortionate rents to live in cramped conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These modern day shanty towns, often visible on websites such as Google Earth, can be plagued with rats and cockroaches - and are potential death traps with dodgy wiring and poor sanitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some foreign ‘tenants’ wish to return home but, after destroying their passports to avoid removal, find it difficult to do so quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Mr Shapps and Mr Green discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encouraging councils to make greater use of legal powers across planning, fire safety, housing and environmental health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to better measure the extent and nature of the problem, drawing on information collected by Whitehall and Town Halls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how best to ensure councils and the police share the intelligence available and enforcement activity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;closer working with organisations such as the Indian High Commission to help those wanting to return home; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;steps to prevent more “beds in sheds” from being created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a scandal that these back garden slums exist to exploit people, many of whom are prepared to return voluntarily to their home country but instead find themselves trapped into paying extortionate rents to live in these cramped conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I want to see a crackdown on these criminal landlords. So today we are launching a national taskforce, made up of the police, local councils, the UK Border Agency and HM Revenue and Customs to close down these ‘beds in sheds’, help those living there to be reunited with their families and ensure their so-called landlords feel the full force of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immigration Minister Damian Green said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those with no right to be in the UK must leave the country. If they volunteer to leave, we will help. If they refuse, we will enforce their removal.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The UK Border Agency will do whatever is necessary, working with local authorities and the police, to clear up this problem and enforce our laws against those who are in the UK illegally and the employers who exploit them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This work is well under way - many individuals have already been removed from the UK and further enforcement visits will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some councils have argued that they need to have a new legal power of entry into premises without notice. However, councils already have this ability provided they obtain a magistrates’ warrant - which provides a proportionate check and balance on the use of such powers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
