<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-21T19:49:48+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/8516</id>
    <published>2012-10-21T19:49:48+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-21T19:49:48+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-04-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 04/2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new powers to protect learner drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a partnership deal brings tests closer to candidates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the latest driving test stats being published&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; inviting special needs groups to discuss the theory test&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jelly being awarded the contract to refresh the hazard perception test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round up of other latest news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/7788</id>
    <published>2012-10-21T19:38:04+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-21T19:38:04+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-05-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 05/2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continuing professional development staying voluntary for approved driving instructors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marketing you and your business online&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s new logo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driver Certificate of Professional Competence training benefits bus and coach industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting standards for bus and lorry drivers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8286</id>
    <published>2012-10-21T15:35:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-21T15:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/building-a-sustainable-future"/>
    <title>Building a sustainable future</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, distinguished guests. Today I want to talk to you about how we go about building a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case I’m going to make has three core arguments: The first is that “sustainability” must be defined in its widest sense; a policy will only, in practice, be sustainable if it supports our environmental and economic goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that while there may sometimes be a tension, there is not necessarily conflict between these two crucially important objectives - it is possible to achieve both in tandem. And the third is that, along with power generation, transport has an absolutely pivotal role in delivering that sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="paying-tribute-to-japans-unbreakable-spirit"&gt;Paying tribute to Japan’s unbreakable spirit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go on to make those arguments, I’d like to take this opportunity to say a few words about the earthquake and tsunami that struck Japan back in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like everyone in Britain, I was shocked and saddened by the destruction and the tragic loss of life caused by that terrible event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have also been deeply impressed, by the resilience of the Japanese people and their almost super-human efforts to recover from the effects of the disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work you have done, the progress you have made and the determination you have shown is hugely impressive and, on behalf of my Government and my country, I want to pay tribute to Japan’s unbreakable spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="global-challenges---environmental-and-economic"&gt;Global challenges - environmental and economic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake and tsunami were, of course, natural disasters. So, while we can always prepare for events like these, we will never be able to prevent them, or stop them in their tracks. The same cannot be said of climate change. Climate change threatens our planet and imperils our future. That’s not science fiction, it’s science fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is a man-made problem - which means that it is possible for us to do something about it. Individually as countries, and collectively as an international community, it is within our power to tackle climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in order to build a sustainable future it is imperative that we meet this global challenge. But Japan, Britain, all of the mature economies, face a second global challenge - the challenge of maintaining economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earthquake and tsunami took a heart-breaking toll in human lives. But they have also hit Japan’s economy - from a recovery bill totalling trillions of Yen, to the inevitable downward pressure on national GDP as output dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because Japan is one of the biggest economies in our increasingly inter-connected world, there has been an inevitable knock-on effect for the entire global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, the global economic consequences of what happened in March would have been serious and significant. But they were also part of an unprecedented coincidence of international events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year has witnessed the euro-zone debt crisis, the downgrading of America’s credit rating and rocketing commodity prices in everything from food and oil, to copper and gold - as well as the tsunami and earthquake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, their impact has been magnified beyond the sum of their parts. In effect they have conspired to grind-down confidence and whip-up uncertainty in the financial markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End result - right around the world the conditions for generating growth have become much, much tougher. And, just as it is vital that countries reduce their deficits and live within their means, so it is crucial that we grow our economies. That’s the only way to secure the recovery, put people back to work and spread prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if we want that sustainable future, not only must we commit ourselves to the fight against climate change, we must also commit ourselves to delivering economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am clear that those objectives do not need to be incompatible. There does not have to be a choice between safeguarding the environment and generating economic growth. This is not a zero sum game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the key areas where we will see this truth demonstrated is in transport. When the coalition government came to power in Britain last May, we inherited a deficit greater than any in our nation’s peacetime history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual, no family, no business can carry on spending more than they earn indefinitely. There will always come a day of reckoning when the credit card bill lands on the doormat and you either pay off the debt or go bust. The recent upheaval in the global financial markets reminds us that, ultimately, the same goes for governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, from day one in office, our government was clear that our number one priority was - and is - restoring Britain’s public finances to order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, British governments have responded to fiscal pressure by slashing capital investment - avoiding the politically challenging cuts in current spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not this time. In spite of intense pressure on budgets, we made the choice to invest in infrastructure, and transport infrastructure in particular. And for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that transport investment is a key economic driver - strengthening the arteries of commerce, moving people to the workplace and goods to the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, transport investment supports job creation through the development, manufacture and application of new technologies and the construction and maintenance of infrastructure across the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the longer term, it drives the productivity growth which is the key to future competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this investment will also be a key part of our plan to make Britain cleaner and greener. Economic growth and decarbonisation. Being delivered hand in hand across the transport sector. Let me take you through some of the steps we have taken in pursuit of our double-headed goal of sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sparking-a-green-motoring-revolution"&gt;Sparking a green motoring revolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few years, UK government policy, focussed on the need to tackle climate change, drifted into what appeared to be an unthinking hostility to cars and motoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a “war on the motorist” is not sustainable. Motorists are voters, and a sustainable policy, in a democracy, must be a policy that voters will support. So our government recognises the absolute centrality of the car to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many journeys it is, and will remain, the only practical and convenient choice. Indeed, 84% of all journeys in the UK are undertaken by car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enemy is not the car, it’s the carbon. So, in Britain we have ended the war on the motorist and are prosecuting the war on carbon - sparking a green revolution in motoring with a blend of supportive public policy and dynamic private enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say that Japanese investment and Japanese companies are playing a central role by committing early and clearly to our “Plug-In Car Grant” which gives consumers a 25% subsidy, up to  £5,000, if they buy an ultra-low emission car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this new grant is our “Plugged-In-Places” Programme, designed to meet the infrastructure needs of electric car drivers, setting up a targeted network of electric vehicle recharging points around the country - everywhere from streets, to car parks, to retail and leisure facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re using it to understand how the infrastructure to support electric vehicles needs to develop. That will differ from country to country - depending on culture, travel and work patterns and existing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us, in Britain, on-street re-charging is certainly part of the answer. But we have concluded that putting a charge-point on every street corner is not the right approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many drivers, perhaps most, will find it better suits their daily routine to plug-in at home, at night-time when electricity is cheaper, or while they’re at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are reforming planning controls to make it easier for private enterprise to play its part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By committing to this programme, we have ensured that the UK has been and is an attractive launch market for ultra-low emission vehicles and an attractive location for major private sector companies to build these new products for the European market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nissan is leading the way by constructing a plant to manufacture its electric vehicles and batteries in the North East of England. Others will follow and the supply chain and supporting technology development companies are already moving in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly sustainable approach, promoting the change that will deliver our environmental objectives - while creating high quality jobs, regenerating our regions and rebalancing our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, reduced emissions from private cars can be mandated by regulation - but must ultimately be delivered by the private sector. Our government also believes it’s important to support more environmentally friendly forms of public transport - an area where we have more direct levers to influence behaviour. For example, in promoting low carbon buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These use at least 30 per cent less fuel and emit nearly a third less carbon than a conventional bus. Yet, when my government came to office, they made up just 0.2 per cent of the country’s bus fleet. So, we have invested in a multi-million pound Green Bus Fund which will kick-start the market by helping operators with the up-front cost of buying low carbon buses - as well as maintaining ongoing enhanced subsidy for green bus operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We estimate that, by March next year, this will result in more than 500 new hybrid and electric low carbon buses being on the roads - meaning that public transport will be making a contribution to shrinking the carbon footprint of road transport, just as the private sector is beginning to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The railways are another essential part of Britain’s public transport networks. And they offer carbon reduction possibilities in everything from regenerative braking to trackside energy storage. Making existing rail journeys more carbon efficient, and attracting more and more passengers from other, less carbon-efficient, modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important way that our government is tapping into this potential is through a major programme of rail electrification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric trains emit no air pollution at the trackside and they generate less CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; than their diesel counterparts. So electrification of the railway - going hand in hand with de-carbonisation of the power generation sector, makes good environmental sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But investing in electrification makes good business sense too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because electric trains are much more reliable than diesels, they are cheaper to operate and often cheaper to buy, they require less maintenance and have lower energy costs and they are also lighter and so cause less damage to the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon reduction - and greater efficiency. Environmental and economic benefits, hand in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as part of that electrification programme, we have given the go ahead for the £4.5 billion Inter-city express programme - which will mean new trains, more capacity and better reliability for passengers using some of Britain’s busiest rail routes. And, again, a Japanese company, Hitachi, is helping us to deliver this project as part of a consortium with the British infrastructure company John Laing. With Hitachi building a new train factory in a high unemployment area of Britain and creating 600 jobs, here is another example of transport investment providing an economic shot in the arm, as well as delivering the goods for passengers and for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="high-speed-rail"&gt;High speed rail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Japan, you will also know the potential of high speed rail networks to attract passengers on to trains and away from more environmentally damaging forms of travel, such as long-distance driving and short-haul flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, you will understand the way that high speed rail can transform a nation’s social and economic geography for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan has a long and proud record as a high speed rail pioneer. Indeed, we in Britain have looked on with admiration at your achievements in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have learned from your experience, as well as admired your progress. And now we are proposing a national high speed rail network in our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that, as in Japan and in France and Spain, such a network would not only slash journey times between our major cities and regions, but transform the way our economy works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving connectivity for our communities and our businesses; boosting productivity and improving competitiveness. And by making high speed rail the mode of choice for long-distance inter-city journeys, we will reduce the carbon footprint of domestic travel still further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aviation"&gt;Aviation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot talk about reducing transport emissions without highlighting the urgent need to tackle the aviation sector’s fast growing emissions. Aviation plays a vital role in the global economy. However, in Europe and increasingly in other parts of the world, governments are facing demands to ensure that aviation is put on a sustainable path that it can deliver growth with decarbonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that aviation emissions will best be managed at international level, but this can take a painfully long time. That is why, alongside operational and technological measures, the UK fully supports the inclusion of aviation in the EU Emissions Trading System or ETS. The ETS delivers an emissions cap in a cost effective, monetised and flexible way, allowing airlines to choose how best to meet their emissions quotas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise the concerns that have been raised in the last few months, but doing nothing is not an option. In addition to taking concrete steps, we will continue to work with like-minded states, such as Japan, in international negotiations in the International Civil Aviation Organization (&lt;abbr title="International Civil Aviation Organization"&gt;ICAO&lt;/abbr&gt;) in the hope that we can deliver an ambitious global agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="shipping"&gt;Shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maritime transport is another area where carbon emissions must be reduced. The adoption of the Energy Efficiency Design Index, as championed by Japan at the International Maritime Organization earlier this year, was very gratifying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an important first step towards securing a comprehensive global agreement. So some progress has been made - but not yet enough. Once again, the EU is prepared to set the pace with a unilateral scheme if IMO cannot deliver the goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, in the UK, look forward to working with the new Secretary-General, Mr Sekimizu, on this and IMO’s many other challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In speaking to you today I have argued that, in our present circumstances, the only sustainable policies are those which deliver carbon reduction and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything else will be rejected by an electorate that is more currently focussed on jobs and prosperity than the climate change agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must focus on initiatives where there is overlap in delivery of these twin objectives and prioritise them, for the moment at least, over those where environmental objectives are at odds with the urgent need for growth and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud to say that the transport sector can lead the way in demonstrating the path to green growth; in showing how we can maintain the momentum of decarbonisation while delivering the growth and jobs our electorates demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The twin challenges of economic growth and climate change; both urgent and both fundamental to our future. To meet them will require a particular focus and determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not unlike the focus and determination Japan has shown in response to the effects of the earthquake and tsunami. This country and its people have reminded us that all things are possible with courage, determination and vision. And we will need plenty of all three to meet the twin challenges of climate change and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Japan’s example, I know that it’s possible for us to come together, and work together, to build that truly sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/8514</id>
    <published>2012-10-21T14:59:04+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-21T14:59:04+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/midland-metro-line-one"/>
    <title>Midland Metro Line One</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following on from the spending review’s reaffirmation of the government’s commitment to the Midland Metro Line One extension in Birmingham, Minister for Local and Regional Transport Norman Baker visited Snow Hill station.
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ELZoxAWDotE"&gt;Midland Metro Line One&lt;/a&gt;
Date filmed: 21 October 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrator: Following on from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/about/spendingreview"&gt;spending review’s&lt;/a&gt; reaffirmation of the government’s commitment to the Midland Metro Line One extension in Birmingham, Minister for Local and Regional Transport Norman Baker visited Snow Hill station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Metro has become an integral part of the city’s transport system, and this proposed scheme, through the city centre, will run to a new terminus outside the main entrance to Birmingham New Street Station. The aim is to not only provide a better link to the national rail network and help to reduce congestion, but also help towards regeneration and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they develop the scheme, the Department for Transport will work closely with Centro, the West Midlands Passenger Transport Executive, as they develop this scheme to ensure value for money for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7672</id>
    <published>2011-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-21T14:41:40+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/statistical-release-error"/>
    <title>Statistical release error</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An error has been identified in the congestion statistics that were published by DfT earlier today. The error affects the A428 which was identified in the statistics release as a poor performing route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the data for sections of the A428 has now been found to be faulty; this contributed to the artificially low reliability figures for the A428 up to February 2011, which we do not believe reflect the actual journey times on the route. We are urgently reviewing our data checking procedures to establish why this error was not identified earlier and ensure this does not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because there was an error in one of the detailed routes all individual routes have been withdrawn for further checks. We will reinstate this data as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revised publication can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110907095518/http://www.dft.gov.uk/pgr/statistics/datatablespublications/roads/congestion/"&gt;http://www.dft.gov.uk/pgr/statistics/datatablespublications/roads/congestion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8296</id>
    <published>2012-10-20T17:56:38+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-20T17:56:38+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/making-hs2-happen"/>
    <title>Making HS2 happen</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;[Introduced by Professor David Begg, Publisher of Transport Times.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that kind introduction David… it’s a pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many thanks to you… and to everybody at Transport Times and the Railway Industry Association… for organising this event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t think of too many people or organisations that could have got a conference like this up and running… or brought together an audience as expert and distinguished as this… at such a short notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My congratulations for delivering it on time, presumably on budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation"&gt;Consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement I made a fortnight ago was the culmination of a vast programme of work over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/high-speed-rail/consultation/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; consultation&lt;/a&gt; was one of the largest in the Department for Transport’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had five months of intensive engagement. 41 days of roadshow attended by almost 33,000 people. And almost 55,000 consultation responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And systematically going through the evidence and the alternatives, it was clear to me that the argument in favour of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/high-speed-rail/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modern,fast reliable, railway that will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transform connections between our cities, regions and the Continent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truly rebalance our economic geography, with a legacy of jobs, growth and opportunity for generations to come&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and change the way we travel, just as the first railway did in the 19th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But behind the headline statistics, &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is also about believing in better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we believe in just making do. Is that all we have to offer our future generations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government passionately believes they deserve so much more. In the same way that we are not prepared to leave them with a fiscal deficit, neither should we leave them with an infrastructure deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the children and students I meet at my local primary and secondary school - what kind of a Britain do we want to create for them? And, how can we make sure our country will be able to match their ambition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long in this country, we have failed to grasp the nettle on the decisions that will help us achieve our long term aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t simply hope for a better, more prosperous future - we will have to build it. We won’t suddenly wake up to a successful Britain, we have to create it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to live in a country that can compete and thrive in the global economy, and where our children can realise their full potential, then we have to tackle the problems that are holding us back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is all about…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about understanding that we have a responsibility to make choices today that will improve our economy and people’s quality of life, not just in the next four or five years, but in the next four or five decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="restating-the-case"&gt;Restating the case&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are some people who question the size of our ambitions. Who say that Britain cannot support such a scheme in such austere times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well today I’d like to reassure them that this is the right scheme at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to do that, I think I need to clear up some of the claims about &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; that I’ve read in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some commentators have said we are spending £32bn building a new line between London and Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I have good news for them. £32bn will buy us a national high speed network, linking London and Birmingham with Leeds, Manchester, South Yorkshire and the East Midlands - and forming the base of what we hope is an even bigger network extending to Scotland in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have focused purely on &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s time savings - claiming the investment is poor value just to shave a few minutes off today’s journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will certainly reduce journey times. In fact it will slash the trip from Birmingham to Leeds in half, and cut the Manchester to London time from 2hrs 8mins today to just 1hr 8mins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are dramatic time savings that will offer a step change in services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuable as faster journeys are - and passengers tell us that the time factor is very important to them - more crucial is the substantial capacity boost that &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will deliver, reducing the increasingly overwhelming pressure on existing road and rail networks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rail network that will simply end up full in many places. If we don’t take action, people say put more trains on the track, have more carriages on the trains on the track, well that’s what we’ve been doing! There’s no other way we would have lasted on a Victorian railway network otherwise. But common sense tells you that can’t go on forever. And after 110 years we’ve nearly got to the end of forever. On some of our tracks there is simply isn’t going to be any more space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… so we need MORE track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But high speed rail will provide up to 18 high speed trains per hour, each with up to 1000 seats… more room on the current railway as well… greater reliability; better performance; and more comfortable long distance travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without investment in new capacity, our main rail arteries will grind to a halt during the 2020s, with disruption, overcrowding, and damage to our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With demand for long-distance rail doubling over the past 15 years, inter-city trains are already becoming overcrowded, and commuters who may have no practical alternative to train travel are forced to stand on long journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unreliable, congested, transport would send out a message to investors that Britain doesn’t really care about its infrastructure… or that we are incapable of delivering major projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a modern, developed economy, that’s not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to continue to ignore the problem is no more an option that pretending our A-road system would have managed without the motorways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we are doing what we can to modernise our current railway with £18bn of investment committed in the Spending Review, and pressing ahead with our plans to max out the capacity on the current track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even with that investment, the scope for squeezing out ever-more out of our ageing rail infrastructure is diminishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is simply not good enough to criticise schemes like &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; unless there is a practical alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those alternatives that have been proposed have fallen short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgrading existing major north-south lines would only provide a short term fix, and would consign passengers to years of disruption, delays and misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And high speed offers much better value than a new conventional north-south rail line - delivering £6.2bn more in benefits for an extra investment of just £1.4bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So high speed will give an additional return on the investment of more than four to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the evidence has been considered. And we are clear that the only long term solution to the capacity crunch we face on our railways is high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people think the capacity crunch will somehow naturally melt away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One commentator claimed that high speed rail would soon be obsolete, because the advance in computers will mean that more people work from home. And rather than speed up, he actually suggested we ought to find ways to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I don’t share his analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen mobile and Internet connectivity through technology transform in the past 15 years - and people have never travelled by train more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will not get people back to work and secure economic recovery by putting a brake on progress, and telling passengers they have got to put up with slower journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the world is moving ever faster. Technology is always developing. And we have to prepare for a faster future if we want Britain to prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who wants slower broadband? Who would choose to have a slow train journey rather than a fast one? And how can businesses hope to compete if they cannot transport goods around the country quickly and efficiently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern manufacturers and retailers rely on just-in-time distribution to maintain profitability. Slowing down transport would merely act as a further barrier to investment, and as a drain on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is about the nuts and bolts of Britain, and making our infrastructure work for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In country after country around the world, high speed rail has proved to be hugely popular with a wide market. Countries that have it invariably build more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, high speed rail is a success around the world because it has a mass market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will benefit every type of traveller - not just on the new network, but on existing lines too. More space and capacity freed up will help drive competition on the railway, changing the way rail travel is marketed and sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do though, of course, accept that there is no easy way to build a train line through our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand and respect the concerns of people living or working near the line and we have gone to very great lengths to mitigate its impact - including a package of extra alterations announced on January 10th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 13 miles through the Chilterns Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty, less than 2 miles will be at or above the surface… the rest will be in deep cutting or tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes will bring significant benefits to communities and the environment; and, in fact, compared to the consultation route there will be a more than 50 per cent increase in tunnel or green tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I welcome the comments of Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of the Campaign to Protect Rural England, who said the government had been sensitive to the impact that &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; would have on communities and the countryside; and that their legitimate concerns about the effects of high speed on the landscape had been heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will do my level best to work closely with communities as the High Speed project progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry-opportunities"&gt;Industry opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course there is another very key benefit of high speed that has not been reflected in much of the coverage over the past two weeks: the opportunities and jobs it will it provide for the rail industry in Britain; the jobs it will create for your companies and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For engineering and technology companies; rail operators; suppliers and component manufacturers; for infrastructure specialists; and many, many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stand to gain as we write a new chapter in the story of rail innovation in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will present this industry with a massive challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering a major national programme on time and on budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we can meet that challenge and I believe we can develop expertise so British companies can compete successfully for key contracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s National Infrastructure Plan sets out the importance of a predictable and transparent long-term pipeline of infrastructure projects that will help the private sector plan ahead and invest in technology and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will form a key element of that long-term pipeline, providing certainty about future contracting opportunities following the completion of Crossrail in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that the UK-based supply chain is in a position to benefit as far as possible from this project, this government will open a dialogue with potential UK-based suppliers to ensure they are well-placed to bid competitively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are already helping us deliver Crossrail, Thameslink, upgrades to major rail hubs like Reading and Birmingham New Street, and a major programme of electrification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also want to put our best minds to work on high speed rail. To find uniquely British solutions to the challenges we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want Britain to become a centre of excellence for high speed rail technologies and services, with a world-class R&amp;amp;D capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we may collaborate with companies from other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from the very start our priority must be to develop the home-grown skills and capabilities that will not only help deliver &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; - but that can then be used in other markets as high speed rail is increasingly adopted by countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="looking-ahead"&gt;Looking ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to reject the short termism of the past, and get our long term future back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence from around the world is clear: as a fast, sustainable and viable way of long-distance, mass transport, high speed rail has no modern equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the right transport programme for passengers; for freight; and for rebalancing our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen the incredible enthusiasm for &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; across our great cities. Manchester, Birmingham, Leeds, Sheffield, these cities know the transformational value high speed rail will have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They rightly believe that the future success of their regions and their communities depends on schemes like this - which will create opportunities on their doorstep. I will work hand-in-hand with them to make sure the jobs and the growth that we all hope for, actually happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know most of us here today are convinced of the case for high speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are many who perfectly understandably will want to continue the debate. I welcome the opportunity to set out our case. Because it is strong and compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also important those who understand the benefits of &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; continue to make their voices heard, and continue to highlight the transformational impact it will have on our railway and on our economy. Now more than ever our case needs to be made positively, clearly and fully informed by the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will prepare for a hybrid bill by the end of 2013, including a detailed Environmental Impact Assessment to provide the necessary powers to construct and operate the line from London to Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spring we will consult on the draft directions for safeguarding the proposed route from London to the West Midlands, as well as separately consulting on detailed compensation proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hs2.org.uk/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd&lt;/a&gt; will advise me on route and station options to Manchester, Leeds and Heathrow, and later in 2012 we will start informal consultation on a preferred route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, these plans will set in motion the most important transport project in this country since the coming of the motorways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I warmly welcome the political consensus on &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, on the basis that it will help ensure that the planning and construction of this transformational scheme is carried through to completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an incredibly exciting time for everyone who cares about Britain’s railway and preserving its critical role supporting our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the benefits of &lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will be felt well beyond the network and the passengers who use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a national scheme in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about raising our sights. Future-proofing Britain’s railway so we don’t wake up in 20 years’ time with a gridlocked railway regretting that we hadn’t been bolder today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remembering that Britain can no more turn its back on the positive potential of high-speed rail than it could have opted out of the steam age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will build high speed two. We will make sure our country and our cities are connected for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will have in place the railway capacity that our future generations need for their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They need our plans put into action more than any of us here today and this government will not let them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed Two"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8295</id>
    <published>2012-10-20T17:37:01+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-20T17:37:01+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/association-of-directors-of-environment-economy-planning-and-transport-annual-dinner"/>
    <title>Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport annual dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you Matthew for that introduction (Matthew Lugg - &lt;abbr title="Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport"&gt;ADEPT&lt;/abbr&gt; President).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for inviting me along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport"&gt;ADEPT&lt;/abbr&gt; and its members don’t just help to shape the transport debate in this country - you also help to set the transport agenda, so it’s a real pleasure to be with you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are two important lessons I’ve learned since going into politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that the words, “I wish the Minister had gone on longer…” are rarely on the lips of an audience at the end of a speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the second is that you don’t win applause, or for that matter any votes, by keeping people from their well-earned dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with both of those lessons in mind, I promise to keep my speech brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="good-transport-equals-good-economics"&gt;Good transport equals good economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am honoured and proud to be the Transport Secretary, just as I was honoured and proud to serve as a Treasury Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in each of these roles, I have come to understand the crucial importance of a certain equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as equations go, it’s a pretty straightforward one. But it drives my policy approach at the DfT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation I’m talking about is this: good transport equals good economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cutting commuting times and speeding up journey times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving people and products faster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;connecting our businesses and wealth creators with the global economy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s how you generate growth and put people back to work. That’s how you make Britain’s competitive edge razor sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plain truth is that we cannot afford to sit back and look on while other countries invest in world class transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the emerging economies of Asia and Latin America, In the Middle East and Africa, and even in the United States and the European Union, nation after nation is upgrading and expanding their infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are our competition in the international marketplace, in the race to win the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bridge they repair and every road they improve, every rail track they lay and every global gateway they open drives their growth and increases their prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if Britain is to out-produce, out-innovate and out-compete the rest of the world, then we too must update our transport infrastructure and make it fit for the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely what this government is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-different-choice"&gt;A different choice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that ageing, past their best transport links are a tax on British businesses and British families. They cost them time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why we made a different choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of taking the axe to capital investment, as previous governments did when the fiscal going got tough, we looked long-term and chose to invest in transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last year’s ‘Spending review’ - over £30 billion for road, rail and local transport across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up the £560 million Local Sustainable Transport Fund - a fund to give local communities more power to design and deliver local transport schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put in place a Growing Places Fund - half a billion pounds worth of support to help kick-start infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, a multi-billion pound investment package in which transport took centre-stage - everything from electrifying more of our rail network, to easing congestion on our motorways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hs2-decision"&gt;HS2 decision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government made a different choice about transport investment because we were looking well beyond the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking decisions to improve our national well-being, not just for the next four or five years, but for the next four or five decades. And not in spite of the economic challenges we face, but as a means to overcome them. And it’s that same long-term national interest which motivated my recent decision to give the go-ahead to HS2 - a national high speed rail network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2 will slash journey times, shrink our country and radically improve the connections between our cities and regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will help to create jobs and generate growth, promote social mobility and spread prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I am absolutely convinced that pushing this project over the finishing line is the right thing to do for our country’s success and our children’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-matters"&gt;Local matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just the big-ticket national projects that can make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving our quality of life and enhancing our economic prospects also means investing in transport at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all journeys start, or end, on local transport networks. And those journeys can shape your entire day, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only takes a late bus, a packed train or a congested road and a short commute becomes an endurance test and a good day turns into a bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as the members of &lt;abbr title="Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport"&gt;ADEPT&lt;/abbr&gt; know better than anyone, local matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because it matters so much, not only did we announce 20 local transport schemes in the ‘Autumn statement’, just before Christmas I gave the green light for a further 21 local major transport schemes. That’s an investment package worth £854 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="smart-localism"&gt;Smart localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modernising local transport networks, getting the very best out of them, isn’t simply about putting in the resources, as crucial as that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about devolving power - giving local people a real say over the transport services and issues that affect their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s what I call smart localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart because it recognises that a one size fits all approach cannot work in the modern, consumer focused world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart because it enables local services, like transport, to be tailored to local needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me walk you through just a few of the ways we’re making smart localism an everyday reality. We’ve simplified funding, cutting the number of separate local transport grant streams from 26 to just four and transferring some funding into formula grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the end result of this radical reform? Local communities will have greater flexibility and freedom to decide their own priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are cutting red tape and ending pointless top-down bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One practical example: after the biggest review into Britain’s traffic signing system for forty years we published a new framework that will free up local councils to remove expensive and unsightly clutter from our roads - a reform that will save money and improve the local environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at ways to devolve more responsibility for commissioning local and regional rail services - a move that could increase transparency, strengthen accountability and, by doing so, improve the passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are also committed to implementing a more devolved system for local major schemes beyond 2015 - enabling local communities and businesses to take real decisions about the transport improvements in their areas; constructing a system that’s much more responsive to local economic conditions and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with greater devolution must follow greater local accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example making sure new schemes achieve genuine value for money. We are ready to work with individual transport bodies to put in place a system that works for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to publish a paper soon and invite views on early proposals for a new system and I look forward to seeing your response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks---productive-partnership"&gt;Concluding remarks - productive partnership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment, reform, localism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all important ways of transforming our country’s prospects by transforming its transport system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But so is productive partnership - government and stakeholders coming together and working together, pulling in the same direction to bring about real and positive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say that partnerships don’t come more productive than the one between my department and this association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s helping us improve winter resilience in the transport sector; leading work streams in the Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme; or assisting us to review future options for the Integrated Transport Block allocation, &lt;abbr title="Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport"&gt;ADEPT&lt;/abbr&gt; and its members have shown that they are sector leaders as well as productive partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I conclude, and more importantly, fulfil my pledge not to keep you from dinner for too long, there’s one final thing I’d like to do - and that’s pay tribute to the work you do and the difference you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, you have been at the forefront of the transport debate, both as the County Surveyors’ Society, and more recently, as &lt;abbr title="Association of Directors of Environment, Economy, Planning and Transport"&gt;ADEPT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, you have played a vital role in managing and maintaining our infrastructure, and strengthening the links between transport and other drivers of sustainable growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, you are helping to shape the agenda on many key areas of government policy - including planning, waste management, housing, and climate change, as well as transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is precisely because these issues are all closely connected that makes your work so valuable, and your contribution so appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening and I look forward to taking some questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8294</id>
    <published>2012-10-20T17:24:12+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-20T17:24:12+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/olympic-travel-event"/>
    <title>Olympic travel event</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks for that introduction Jo (Baroness Jo Valentine, Chief Exec London First), I’m delighted to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the clock ticking, and the 2012 Opening Ceremony edging ever closer, this is an important event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a big thank-you to London First, to TfL and to everyone who’s helped organise it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="getting-the-transport-right"&gt;Getting the transport right&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond doubt the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games will give sport in this country a once in a generation boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will be our nation’s global shop window, our golden opportunity to showcase the best of Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we simply have to make them a success - make them the very best they can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But delivering success in 2012 isn’t just about fantastic venues or British athletes winning medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about getting the transport right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I say that, not just because I am the Transport Secretary, but because I am also a London MP and, like so many of us here today, I depend on the tubes, trains and roads that serve and support our capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like my constituents - and just like millions of others - the commuters; the mums and dads taking their kids to school; the people going shopping or just visiting friends and family, London’s transport networks are part and parcel of my working and personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the journey to work and the journey home again can shape your entire day, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that, at times, the daily commute can be pretty long and stressful as it is, before the additional pressures the Olympics will bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my message to you is this - I get it. I know just how much transport will matter in 2012 - for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-city-open-for-business"&gt;A city open for business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s precisely because of this that we’ve invested some £6.5 billion in upgrading and extending transport links, to increase capacity, enhance resilience and improve services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ambitious modernisation programme is already providing an impressive transport legacy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the upgraded North London line - with new, higher frequency, more reliable trains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the extension of the East London line and the DLR to Woolwich and to Stratford International&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the high speed Javelin service from St Pancras to Stratford Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and new and improved walking and cycling routes to the Olympic Park, and to other venues, inside and outside London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All these transport projects, and more, will still be delivering benefits years into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they also mean that London will be ready and able to be a world-class host next summer - a city that’s open for business in a country that’s open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="planning-ahead"&gt;Planning ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do understand the scale of that challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without any question we face a big test. Indeed the proof is there in the transport heat-maps that TfL are publishing today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the investment and the improvements, the stress and strain placed on our transport system will be unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily, up to 800,000 spectators and 55,000 athletes, officials, organisers and members of the media will be travelling to and from the Olympic venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, while, on an average London workday 24 million trips take place, on the busiest Games’ day an extra 3 million trips could be added to that total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does that mean in practical terms for companies, for employers and for the travelling public, Londoners going about their business?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it means that at various times on key transport routes there are going to be a lot more people travelling… which, in turn, means there will be transport pinch points and travel hotspots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it doesn’t mean is that London will grind to a standstill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I acknowledge that, come the Games, we will have to think about how we can work differently and travel differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, equally, I believe that if we all plan ahead, then we will keep London and the rest of Britain moving next summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I am already struck by just how much planning is already in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was over with Peter (Hendy) last week, looking at how TfL are using new techniques to manage traffic on the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will have monitoring on a scale never seen before - really sophisticated models of where queues are likely to arise and how to get traffic flowing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to a transport legacy for London, I think this understanding of how to cope with so many extra visitors is a really big deal - something that will have benefits for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should also take advantage of the other opportunities that could arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some firms may want to use the Games as an opportunity to think about how and when they get their deliveries or despatch their goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other businesses might see this as an ideal chance to make much more use of communications technologies like video and tele-conferencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some organisations could grab the opportunity to trial new ways of working - whether it’s their staff working from home on some days, or coming in at more flexible times on others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those individuals travelling for work or for leisure, the period during the Games could be their chance to try a different route, stagger their journey time or work more flexibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who live near work, or travel short distances within central London, it could even be the excuse they need to cycle or walk part of their journey, or maybe even all of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="giving-a-lead-working-in-partnership"&gt;Giving a lead, working in partnership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No doubt, planning ahead can therefore help you meet the 2012 transport challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can also help you to adapt and evolve and, in doing so, make the most of the very real opportunities the Games will bring to London, its people and its businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what our transport strategy, and this event, are all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure you have the information and tools, the advice and the options you need to get from A to B, to run your businesses and to do your jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, government has to give a lead and set an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my department recently ran a trial to reduce its travel footprint, during which people managed to positively change 69 percent of their commuting and business travel, while still getting their work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say that, next February, departments right across Whitehall will be following suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Games themselves the DfT is committed to shrinking our travel footprint by half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re working right now with staff to make sure we achieve that by changing our commuting, business and visitor travel, as well as our deliveries and collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as I say, it’s right that we do these things. Because, we don’t simply have a responsibility to work and communicate with key players like those of you here today, we must also play our part to lessen demand, ease overcrowding and minimise disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But partnership matters too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s vital that we all work together to meet the 2012 transport challenge… central government and local government, the Mayor and TfL, LOCOG and the ODA, the business community and transport providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us doing our bit - 100 percent committed to keeping this city running and thriving during the Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am certainly going to do what I can - getting the message across, working alongside businesses and taking the decisions that will keep London and Londoners moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, rather than having an M4 Games lane that nobody else can use for the entire Olympics, the decision I’ve taken is that we will have a flexible lane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it’s needed for Games family traffic, it will be used for that, and shared with buses, taxis and coaches. But when it’s not needed, we’ll switch it off and it will be open to the whole public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something else I’ll be doing is to encourage other MPs in the capital to make sure their constituencies are ready for the challenge that awaits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using their local knowledge and their local networks, MPs are uniquely placed to inform and advise their local communities and employers about what they can expect and what they can do to make things run smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Peter and I will be holding a comprehensive briefing for MPs after Parliament returns from the holidays, making sure the wealth of information and advice that is being prepared gets to the people who need to know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at next year’s Games through the prism of transport and it soon becomes clear that the challenge we face is real and it is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am convinced it’s a challenge that can be met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test we face is tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, with planning, preparation and partnership we can keep our Capital and our country moving; we can stage a Games to remember; and we can do Britain proud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8293</id>
    <published>2012-10-20T17:14:50+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-20T17:14:50+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-delivery-group-industry-forum"/>
    <title>Rail Delivery Group Industry Forum</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for inviting me along today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of you are key players in a key industry and so I’m delighted to have a chance to make my own small contribution to this important event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do need to make an apology though. And that’s because other government commitments mean I can’t stay as long as I’d like to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m pleased to say that my colleague, the Minister of State for Rail Theresa Villiers, is also here today to answer your questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="investing-in-rail-is-good-economics"&gt;Investing in rail is good economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear to me in my job at the Treasury, and it’s even clearer to me as Transport Secretary - investing in rail is good economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting commuting times and speeding up journey times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving people and products faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting our communities and supporting our businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how we can create jobs, generate growth and help Britain out-compete and out-produce the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And “investing in rail” is exactly what this government is doing with  £18 billion of rail funding in last year’s ‘Spending review’ and the biggest programme of railway modernisation since the Victorian era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we recognise that each investment, each modernisation can have a tremendous ripple effect, whether it’s less congestion and more capacity, or fewer delays and greater reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, focusing resources on our railways, renewing and re-building our infrastructure - these things make a positive difference to services and to passengers, to our economy and our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the rail reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="change-and-reform-for-a-purpose"&gt;Change and reform for a purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is another inescapable rail reality. And it’s one that I know you all recognise: investment must be accompanied by change and modernisation must go hand-in-hand with reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not talking about change and reform for their own sake, but change and reform for a purpose - ensuring our railways are efficient and affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in a Europe where our neighbours are competitors as well as partners, there are many areas where I want Britain to be number one, ahead of the pack and top of the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the most expensive railway is definitely not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as Sir Roy McNulty concluded, that’s exactly the position our railways are in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will know, even after allowing for unavoidable differences, Sir Roy estimates that UK rail costs are 20 to 30% higher than they should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little wonder that he found significant scope in our railway system to eliminate waste and cut costs. Potential savings of up to £1 billion a year could be found by the end of this decade-. and all without any reductions in services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are some other facts that should make us all sit up and take notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1996-97 passenger numbers have risen by around 57%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against this background you’d expect unit costs to fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, today, they remain almost exactly the same in real terms as they were in 1996-97.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, as a former chartered accountant, let alone as Transport Secretary, that just doesn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="efficient-and-affordable-equals-successful-and-sustainable"&gt;Efficient and affordable equals successful and sustainable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long the railway has relied on ever-increasing public subsidies on one hand and ever rising rail fares on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means we face a choice on this… two very different options which would lead to two very different futures for the rail industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option one is that we deliver value for money for taxpayers and fare-payers… that we drive down costs and drive up efficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option two is that we do nothing and stick with a status quo of expensive to build, expensive to run and expensive to maintain railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a stark choice. But it’s an easy choice because the “do-nothing option” is actually no option at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is straightforward and undeniable: the rail industry will only be able to compete for future investment if its long-term cost issues are addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s be frank, if you don’t cut costs then, eventually, your only alternatives are to cut services, hike fares even higher or do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there was ever a business model designed to condemn the industry to short-term stagnation at best, and long-term decline at worst, then it is definitely this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our only option, our only course of action, is to deliver better value for money on our railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without question such an approach will boost the business prospects of this vital national industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will improve the travelling experience of rail users too, by releasing resources that can be re-invested in services and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could even mean an end to inflation-busting rises in regulated fares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, for me, it’s a very straightforward rail equation -.efficient and affordable equals successful and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-must-play-its-part"&gt;Government must play its part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the challenge we face - costs down, efficiency up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And government must play our full part in meeting that challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are constructing a supportive policy framework, hence our reforms of rail franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By introducing longer, less prescriptive franchises, we want to give the industry more freedom to innovate, as well as a stronger incentive to invest in better services and address passenger needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also bringing the days of Whitehall micro-management to an end, devolving more responsibility for managing the railways to local levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change and reform must always work for and make sense to the people and businesses that use and depend on rail, whether it’s commuters or freight customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the government wants to help fare-payers by moving towards a simpler, fairer and much more user friendly system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we recognise the importance of increasing transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail customers must be able to benchmark performance and taxpayers must be able to see how their money is spent and what their subsidy is buying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potentially greater transparency could result in greater feedback for the industry, helping the industry to really know their customers, to understand what they want from rail services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also determined to build on the value for money work carried out by Sir Roy McNulty… which means setting out our wider vision for a sustainable and successful railway, including reform of Network Rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, last week, I announced my intention to publish a command paper early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve done so because, as a new Transport Secretary, I am determined to give this the focus and attention it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publishing our command paper early next year will therefore give me time to consider all the key issues around rail reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also enable me to look at what emerges from the government’s growth review, a landmark review that I am certain will shape the future of our economy and vital transport infrastructure like rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, equally as important, it will mean the command paper can properly reflect the consequences of my decision following our consultation on a national high speed rail network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the command paper I also plan to consult on the scope to devolve responsibility for some rail passenger services in parts of England to sub-national bodies, and on issues relating to the review of fares and ticketing announced in May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the ORR expects to consult later this year on possible changes to its role, particularly in respect of future franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accept there are some who were keen for every last dot and comma of our reform proposals to be written, ready and published this side of the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that the decision to publish the command paper early next year is not one that I have taken lightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But rail reform matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my priority is to get our proposals right, not rush them through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry-leadership"&gt;Industry leadership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If government must play its part in meeting the big challenges facing our railways, then so too must the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say that this group, and this event, demonstrate the industry’s willingness to step up to the plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your leadership counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions you make and the actions you take - they can all have a positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And government wants to help and support you as you meet the challenges and make the changes because we understand that all of us have a stake in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us can pursue reform alone or in isolation. There needs to be a new culture of partnership and collaboration, as exemplified by the RDG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade unions and train operators, Network Rail and the ORR, government and industry. We must all work together. We must all do our bit because we all stand to lose if rail becomes ever less competitive and ever less affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks---the-only-game-in-town"&gt;Concluding remarks - the only game in town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This audience knows better than anyone that our railways cost more than they used to and more than they ought to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also know that such a state of affairs is as unsustainable as it is unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left unaddressed it will hurt passengers, freight operators and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately it will hit the industry and, in the long term, perhaps even damage our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can’t afford to side-step this issue or kick it down the tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we invest and modernise we must also change and reform - that really is the only game in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a railway that is efficient, that helps to drive our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A railway that is affordable for hard pressed taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A railway that, first, last and always, delivers for the people who are its commercial life blood - its passengers, its customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that’s a huge challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires us to be brave enough to think differently and bold enough to act decisively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it demands that we work together and work smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when I come to events like this - and when I think about the expertise and experience that the RDG, and key industry players like all of you, bring to this task - I am convinced it’s a challenge we can and will meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8290</id>
    <published>2012-10-20T17:02:58+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-20T17:02:58+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-at-the-northern-rail-conference"/>
    <title>Speech at the Northern Rail conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Anton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to be back in Leeds to take part in Northern Rail’s conference today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to congratulate their parent group, Abellio, on winning the Greater Anglia short franchise today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are half as successful with this new contract as they have been with Northern, I’m sure passengers in East Anglia will be in for a really high quality service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course it’s been all change at the Department for Transport over the last week and this is a welcome opportunity to pass on the good wishes of the new Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like her predecessor, Justine Greening fully recognises the crucial role rail plays in our economy and the vital importance of improving rail infrastructure in the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so today I propose to take you through some of our key goals and ambitions for rail in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="context-three-years-of-change"&gt;Context: Three years of change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s three years since Northern hosted its first Rail Summit in Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you who were at the inaugural summit may remember the theme that day was the role of rail in delivering growth - a well chosen theme, considering the crisis in our economy in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew then that the road to recovery would be long and tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still paying the price for Gordon Brown’s reckless decision to borrow excessively during the boom years leaving the cupboard absolutely bare when the bad times arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget that it was only May last year when the coalition inherited the largest deficit in our nation’s peacetime history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And across government, we are taking the tough action needed to tackle the deficit, support growth, and cut carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With tight control on spending, combined with a robust plan to stimulate enterprise and jobs, we’re taking the right route - the only credible route - to a brighter future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every department and every industry has a contribution to make, including the rail sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For nearly 200 years, the railway has been bringing prosperity to the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting people with the workplace, and goods with the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing the links on which businesses rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we believe that rail can play a vital role in spurring growth in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the coalition is today overseeing the biggest rail upgrade programme since the Victorian era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, British governments have responded to the need to rein in spending by reducing capital investment - typically in large scale infrastructure schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly not because it makes economic sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that capital projects traditionally lose out during times of fiscal retrenchment because cutting other areas of public spending is more politically difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, though, our priorities are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll do what’s best for our economy, and what’s best for our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite severe pressure on budgets, we have made a strategic choice to increase capital investment in those parts of the infrastructure that best deliver sustainable economic growth - including rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why rail was allocated £18bn of funding in last year’s ‘Spending review’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has come with a downside - an RPI +3% increase in fares for three years to help fund the vital improvements we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even taking that into account, rail came out of the spending review far more strongly than anyone expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think the outgoing Secretary of State deserved all the many accolades he received for his part in securing that result in the CSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rail-investment-in-the-north"&gt;Rail investment in the north&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of reasons why the Chancellor chose to prioritise investment in rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can rail deliver growth. It can deliver more balanced sustainable economic growth across the country, helping to tackle the prosperity gap that continues to divide north and south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So £300m will be invested in rail electrification in the north west over the next 6 years, upgrading crucial routes between Manchester, Liverpool, and Wigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will deliver significant environmental, economic and passenger benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also allow these lines to benefit from the rolling stock cascade triggered by the Thameslink programme and allow existing diesel trains to be used on other routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty years after it was first proposed, the Ordsall Chord has finally got the go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase one of the Northern Hub programme, the Ordsall Chord project will tackle a major bottleneck in the network, and enable faster and much more frequent services to run across the north of England - including between Liverpool, Manchester, Leeds, Newcastle, and Hull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real investment in rail in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And real support for the northern economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also recognise the benefits that the remainder of the Northern Hub programme could offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be looking very seriously at the whole proposal in the run up to next July’s HLOS 2 statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s no doubt that the package as a whole is an expensive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affordability issues will need careful consideration, and it will be necessary to make a judgment on the different components individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is unlikely to be an ‘all-or-nothing’ decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside measures to improve the infrastructure, we’re also modernising our rolling stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next generation of Intercity Express trains is due to be built by Hitachi at a new assembly plant in County Durham… creating at least 500 jobs directly, plus thousands more in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, we’re investing in 2,700 new carriages across the rail network to ease overcrowding on many routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right here in Leeds commuters are set to benefit from an extra 2,000 seats a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know that talking about rolling stock in the north of England can be risky if you’re the rail minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many passengers would like to see the Pacers heading into retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you here in this room will know that building a business case for new rolling stock is always going to be difficult when fares in much of the north of England lag so very far behind the rest of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget the growing importance of light rail in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investing up to £350 million over the next 10 years to upgrade the Tyne and Wear metro… the largest renewal project since the metro was built more than 30 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Metrolink extension is going ahead in Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The network was built under a conservative government - and this conservative-led government continues to recognise the great benefits trams and light rail can bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tram Train Project between Sheffield and Rotherham is also progressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are currently considering proposals to develop the trolleybus scheme here in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="high-speed"&gt;High speed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our very significant commitment to updating and improving the existing railway, we also recognise its inherent constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a 19th century network - valiantly struggling to support a 21st century economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It simply will not be able to absorb the growth in demand that we expect to see over the next few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why in 2008, in opposition, I championed high speed rail - at a time when the Labour government had dismissed it as an option and ruled it out of their 30 year strategy for the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said then and I continue to believe that this is a project which can transform the economic and social geography of Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the allegations made by its detractors, HS2 is not, and never has been, about shaving a few minutes off the journey time to Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about meeting the long term transport needs of our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about delivering the intercity transport links that are absolutely crucial for future economic success&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that high speed rail will do more to tackle the economic imbalance between the north and south than any policy tried by long the succession of governments that have grappled with this seemingly intractable problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we are clear that the scheme will deliver benefits to the whole country, it is the north that stands to get most from HS2 - in the same way regional cities around Europe have flourished when connected to high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High speed would not only transform journey times, reliability, and choice on our railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also free up huge amounts of capacity on existing lines, providing space for more commuter, regional and freight services on the West Coast, East Coast and Midland Main lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after one of the largest and most complex public consultations in government history, we are currently analysing thousands of responses from passengers, local communities, environmental groups, businesses, local authorities, and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will publish our response towards the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="value-for-moneydevolution"&gt;Value for money/devolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improvements I’ve outlined this morning will deliver more capacity, better connectivity, and better services for rail passengers in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on their own they’re not enough to meet the challenges faced by all of us who care about the UK’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you know the issue I’m coming to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, of course, value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Roy McNulty’s study set out the scale of the challenge - with his conclusion that Britain’s rail network is now up to 40% more expensive per passenger mile than those of our European competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has contributed to increasing public concern about the level of rail fares in many parts of the country, particularly the south east.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also led to some of the highest levels of public subsidy in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This high-cost status quo is neither acceptable nor sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are carefully considering carefully the detailed recommendations that Sir Roy produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That includes assessing the scope there is to devolve more responsibility for commissioning local and regional services from the centre to local bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we do in so many areas, this government recognises the benefits localised decision-making can bring to transport. Strengthening accountability to local communities and passengers, deploying local knowledge and understanding of the consequences of different choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of community rail gives us a hint of the benefits local input and commitment can bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The refranchising process for Northern and TPE will provide a real opportunity to test the case for devolving more decisions to local authorities and PTEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussions are ongoing between the DfT and the PTEs, with a number of options on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many issues to resolve, not least of which is whether to devolve right down to a very local area or try to create a consortia of local authorities to input into decisions across more of the Northern franchise network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as well as a more localist approach, we also want a more transparent one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing the public with more visibility over where rail subsidy is being spent won’t be without controversy - but it is an important part of our strategy for reducing costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the department’s business plan, we have made a firm commitment to greater transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already started to publish information about where subsidy is allocated, on a franchise by franchise basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes direct TOC funding from the government and an estimate of how much of Network Rail’s grant can be attributed to the infrastructure used by each franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re moving towards breaking down performance data by line rather than just the overall figures for the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we want to go further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in due course we want passengers to know the real cost of the services they are using, and how much their fares are contributing to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key area for reform is franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pressed ahead with this from the early days of the coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition agreement commits us to longer more flexible franchises and a departure from the excessive micro-management that characterised the approach of the previous government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By introducing longer, less prescriptive franchises, we want to give the industry more freedom to innovate, and a stronger incentive to invest in better services and address passenger needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, our draft specification for the West Coast franchise published in the summer represents a significantly more flexible approach than the rigid timetable and service specifications of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft ITT set out a framework which continued to mandate key elements of service, such as minimum numbers of station stops per week and per day but give the winning bidder greater scope to organise services in a more commercial way and to respond to peaks and troughs of passenger demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re replacing the “cap and collar” revenue support system with a GDP risk-sharing arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will continue to offer train operators some protection from the big macro-economic risks that it’s expensive for them to take on; but it avoids some of the perversities of the cap and collar regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will build on these changes in future franchise competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, West Coast is a staging post in a progressive reform we will roll out as our major programme of refranchising moves forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the future we propose to include in franchises the sort of aligned incentives that Sir Roy McNulty identified as a key way to address the high unit cost of the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much work remains to be done but Network Rail is already devolving its operations to give route managers more autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And work is actively underway between Network Rail and operators such as Scotrail and SWT to develop the alliances that could play an important part of delivering the strong shared incentives needed to get costs down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps most difficult of all, we’ll be reviewing fares regulation to see if we can eliminate some of the many anomalies it contains, smooth out the most extreme cliff edges, and better incentivise off-peak travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me make it absolutely clear that as part of this process I will be expecting the rail industry to step up to the plate to ensure that they deliver a more user-friendly system for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modern fares system that helps fill up empty trains and spends less on transport thin air is bound to involve some complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So an important component of a successful reform should be aimed at ensuring that when passengers buy tickets, they can navigate the choices available and find the best ticket for their journey without too much uncertainty and too much hassle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, ladies and gentlemen, I genuinely believe that the measures I have outlined today represent a serious and credible programme to generate growth and strengthen the competitiveness of the north of England by improving its transport infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think they give us the chance to deliver a real shot in the arm for the northern economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chance to deliver the improved capacity and connections that cities and communities across the north need to grow and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us should underestimate the scale of the task on which we have embarked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering the change we need will require a huge effort from both industry and government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that an industry that has achieved so much in recent years - an industry that has reversed a long term trend of decline - will be equal the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
