<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-24T20:53:17+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuide/8558</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T16:02:49+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T20:53:17+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-days-at-sea-scheme"/>
    <title>The Days at Sea Scheme: Cod Recovery Zone</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Days at Sea Scheme is a UK initiative restricting the number of days per year that vessels can fish in the Cod Recovery Zone (&lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt;). The aim of the scheme is to allow cod and sole stocks to recover in this area, improving long-term sustainability, and allows the UK to comply with EU Regulation 1342/2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the scheme, if you wish to operate a fishing vessel in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; you will need to apply for an annual allocation of days you may fish, according to the type of fishing gear you use. The scheme is administered in the UK by the Marine Management Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide explains how the Days at Sea Scheme may affect your cod fishing vessel, potential exemptions and penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notification-of-intention-to-carry-regulated-gears"&gt;Notification of intention to carry regulated gears&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the master of a vessel (or their representative), in order to receive your days at sea allocation you must notify the local &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; coastal office as to which categories of regulated gear the vessel will carry in the forthcoming period. You should make an application before the first day of each management period. The port office will provide you with the application form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An application to transfer in days for a vessel which does not have eligibility in its own right will also count as notification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A management period can be a period of one or more months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you apply for a new management period that ends the previous management period with a deficit (that is, where the allocated days have been used before the end of the management period), no allocation will be made for the new period until more days are transferred in to eliminate the deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if a fisherman is allocated 135 days for TR1 gears (whitefish gear) for 12 months, but uses them in 10 months and then opts to begin a new management period using a different gear type, the previous management period will have ended with a deficit of 22.5 days. Therefore, no allocation can be made for the remaining two months of the original 12-month period until more days are transferred in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any days remaining at the end of a management period will not be transferred into the new management period. Days not used by the end of a management period are therefore lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vessels are allowed to carry only one type of regulated gear at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="regulated-gears"&gt;Regulated gears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulated gears are listed in Annex 1 to EC Regulation 1342/2008. You can &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:348:0020:01:EN:HTML"&gt;read the regulation&lt;/a&gt; on the Eur-LEX website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be eligible to use them, you must also have a record of fishing activity with those gears at some point during the years 2001-05 or inherited eligibility by a single licence transfer or aggregation from a vessel or vessels with a track record, where this has been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vessels eligible to notify gear category TR1 may carry any category of regulated gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For advice, you can call the Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team - Days at Sea Scheme on 0191 376 2596 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="days-at-sea-allocation"&gt;Days at sea allocation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team will send letters to eligible vessels giving their allocation of days for the management period. You should carry this letter on board at all times when fishing in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; with regulated gears. The letter will also specify areas where your vessel may fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should apply for an allocation for a single grouping of regulated gears, such as TR1 and TR2, or a combination. If you notify for more than one category of gear, your allocation of days will be the average of the rates for the categories notified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flat rates for basic allocations for the gear groups in 2012-13 are set out in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="flat-rates-for-basic-allocations-for-the-gear-groups-in-2012-13"&gt;Flat rates for basic allocations for the gear groups in 2012-13&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Gear type&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number of days and transfer limits&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;North Sea&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;West of Scotland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Irish Sea&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TR1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TR2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;82 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75 (20% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TR3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;BT1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;BT2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;152 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GN1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GT1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LL1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172 (30% maximum)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vessels will receive an allocation of days in proportion to the duration of the management period notified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="vessels-catching-less-than-5-cod"&gt;Vessels catching less than 5% cod&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you agree to catch less than 5% cod when notifying any regulated gear, you will be allocated additional days at sea. If you make any trip that involves activity within the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; for all or part of the trip, the 5% limit on cod catches will need to be observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be allocated 200 days and can choose to use any combination you wish if notifying multiple gears. For example 150 TR2 days and 50 TR1 days or 100 TR2 days and 100 TR1 days, or any other variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fishermen wanting to transit through the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; to fish outside it must lash and stow their gear whilst in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; (both there and back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vessel will revert to the standard allocation for the rest of the scheme year if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on one occasion it lands more than 5% cod by live weight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an inspection at sea records a catch of cod that is 5% or more of the total catch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could be required to transfer days if your vessel has already exceeded the standard allocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="allocation-of-additional-days-at-sea-buy-backs"&gt;Allocation of additional days at sea (buy backs)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also apply to receive extra allocated days if you agree to fish exclusively using specified gear during the management period. The options are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Eliminator trawl – available to TR1 vessels and vessels using this receive an extra 24 days allocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Orkney trawl – available to TR1 vessels and vessels using this receive an extra 20 days allocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;130 millimetres cod end – available to TR1 vessels carrying gear with a cod end of mesh size 130 millimetres or greater, and vessels using this receive an extra 8 days allocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nephrops square mesh panel (&lt;abbr title="Square mesh panel"&gt;SMP&lt;/abbr&gt;) – the insertion of a 120 mm &lt;abbr title="Square mesh panel"&gt;SMP&lt;/abbr&gt; of minimum length 3 metres in the straight extension of the net or a 130 mm &lt;abbr title="Square mesh panel"&gt;SMP&lt;/abbr&gt; in the taper where the rearmost row of the meshes of the &lt;abbr title="Square mesh panel"&gt;SMP&lt;/abbr&gt; shall be no more that 12 metres from the cod line, available to TR2 vessels and vessels adopting this will receive an extra 8 days allocation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can call the Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team - Days at Sea Scheme on 0191 376 2596 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitions of the Eliminator trawl and the Orkney trawl are in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/documents/days_cod_rules.pdf"&gt;Days at Sea Scheme 2012/13: Cod Recovery Zone scheme rules (PDF 234KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transferring-days-at-sea"&gt;Transferring days at sea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transfers of days at sea are subject to controls. They are also limited to a set percentage of a vessel’s allocation - 20% for TR1 and TR2 gears and 30% for other gears. This means that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any vessel that benefits from the extra 5% cod entitlement can transfer days in but not transfer days out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a vessel donating days to another can only donate up to that percentage of its allocation of days to other vessels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once days are transferred to a vessel they may not be transferred out (this is to prevent the accumulation of days onto individual vessels as a form of banking – however, the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; will consider allowing such transfers out in some circumstances)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recipient vessels are not restricted in terms of how many days they can receive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transfers of effort will only be allowed where the donor and recipient vessels are both administered by the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for vessels receiving extra days at sea by complying with special conditions (such as the 5% limit on cod catches), they can only transfer days from vessels that are operating under the same conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vessels that are ineligible to carry regulated gears may transfer in days from eligible vessels to allow them to fish in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where a transfer takes place, the number of days received by the recipient will be adjusted in proportion to its fishing capacity (measured in engine power) compared to the other vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can call the Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team - Days at Sea Scheme on 0191 376 2596 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="penalties-for-breaching-days-at-sea-rules"&gt;Penalties for breaching days at sea rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Penalties for breaching the days at sea scheme rules are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fishing in an area of seasonal closure, when in effect – a deduction of 7 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fishing in an area of real time closure, when in effect – a deduction of 5 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;carrying more than one category of regulated gear onboard – a deduction of 5 days for each occasion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fishing in an area of advised cod avoidance after notifying the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; that you will not fish in these areas – on each occasion a deduction of days awarded in relation to avoidance of area in the management period, including any days used from that additional allocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;failing to fish exclusively with specified gear after notifying the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; that you will – on each occasion a deduction of days awarded in relation to use of gear in the management period, including any days used from that additional allocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;failing to accept an observer on board in response to a reasonable request – on the first occasion there is no penalty, on each subsequent occasion, a deduction of 5 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team will give consideration to any exceptional circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the team is considering applying a penalty, it will notify you in writing of the intention to impose the penalty, and the reasons for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On receipt of this notification, you may appeal. Such appeals should in the first instance be lodged with the team. However, any appeal will be considered by a senior officer within the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; outside the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can call the Fisheries Management and Effort Control Team - Days at Sea Scheme on 0191 376 2596 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;daysatsea.transferrequests@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fisheries-management-and-control-team---days-at-sea-scheme"&gt;Fisheries Management and Control Team - Days at Sea Scheme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0191 376 2596&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:348:0020:01:EN:HTML"&gt;Read Regulation 1342/2008 on the Eur-LEX website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/documents/days_cod_rules.pdf"&gt;Days at Sea Scheme 2012/13: Cod Recovery Zone scheme rules (PDF 234KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/forms/crz_gear_notification.pdf"&gt;Notification of gears to be used in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; form (PDF 156KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/forms/crz_allocated.pdf"&gt;Application form to be allocated days for vessels catching less than 5% cod (PDF 122KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/forms/crz_transfer.pdf"&gt;Application to transfer days at sea for use in the &lt;abbr title="Cod Recovery Zone"&gt;CRZ&lt;/abbr&gt; form (PDF 143KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/management/forms/crz_conservation.pdf"&gt;Form to notify of a vessel’s intention to undertake additional conservation measures (PDF 130KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuide/8599</id>
    <published>2012-09-17T16:05:44+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T20:51:32+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/european-fisheries-fund-projects"/>
    <title>European Fisheries Fund overview</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-european-fisheries-fund"&gt;What is the European Fisheries Fund?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has set aside approximately £38 million from the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; between 2007 and 2013 to help the fisheries industry adapt to changing requirements under the Common Fisheries Policy. This funding is broken down as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Axis 1: Measures for the adaptation of the European Community fishing fleet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 2: Measures for investments in aquaculture and processing and marketing of fishery and aquaculture products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 3: Measures of common interest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 4: Measures of the sustainable development of fisheries areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Axis 4 programme is delivered through fisheries local action groups (FLAGs) who represent different area. These FLAGs have been set up in six areas in England, covering around 20 per cent of the English coastline. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_axis4.htm"&gt;Read more about Axis 4 on the Marine Management Organisation (&lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;) website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-can-apply"&gt;Who can apply?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, as the applicant, must sign the application form, even if you had help completing it as you will be responsible for making sure that all of the terms and conditions of the grant are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different funding streams are available to different people or sectors. For example, Axis 1 is available to vessel owners in the private sector, but Axis 2 aquaculture projects are available to micro, small or medium sized in the public or private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="when-can-you-apply"&gt;When can you apply?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can apply at any time until 31 December 2013, which is the end of the programme. If your application is for a large amount of money or is more complicated, your form and business case may have to be assessed by a selection panel. The panels are usually held 3 times a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; may have to close the programme earlier if the allocated funds have been used up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-things-may-be-eligible-for-a-grant"&gt;What things may be eligible for a grant?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kinds of projects that are eligible for a grant vary depending on the axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Axis 1 is aimed at improvements to on board safety, working conditions, hygience, product quality, selectivity of fishing gear, energy efficiency and engine replacement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 2 is aimed at investments in aquaculture and processing, and for marketing of fishery and aquaculture products so may include buildings, equipment, fees, infrastructure and vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 3 is aimed at common interests so may include advertising and promotion, equipment, products not intended for human consumption and VAT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grants are not awarded for projects that will increase fishing efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any work that starts before a decision has been made on an application is automatically not eligible for a grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-much-grant-will-i-get"&gt;How much grant will I get?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; programme is competitive, and only projects that most effectively meet its aims will be awarded a grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will receive a percentage of the total eligible cost of your project if you are successful. The amount you receive depends on your type or project, and your location. The different axes have different requirements both in terms of minimum and maximum grants you can apply for, and the percentages available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Axis 1 has a £500 minimum and £60,000 maximum (except engine replacements where the maximum is £100,000), and the maximum percentage you will receive wil be between 20 and 60 per cent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 2 has a £400 minimum and three maximums depending on the type of project, and the maximum percentage you will receive will be between 80 and 100 per cent, 20 and 40 per cent, and 20 and 40 per cent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Axis 3 has 5 different kinds of projects with their own minimums and maximums, and different maximum percentages depending on the applicant (public or private), and location (Cornwall and the Isles of Scilly or the rest of England)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For advice on the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; or to find out if your project is eligible, you can call the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676, email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; or write to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team
Lancaster House
Hampshire Court
Newcastle upon Tyne
NE4 7YH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-to-apply-for-funding"&gt;How to apply for funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should submit the relevant application form to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;. You should use the application form that matches the appropriate axis of the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your application must include a detailed business case that shows that your project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has quantified outputs and clear and attainable targets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will provide an additional and sustainable benefit to the fishing industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has a justified need for grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will provide good value for money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should also include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a full description of your project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why the work is needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the benefits of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financial, environmental and other benefits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a cost-benefit analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an analysis of quotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the results you expect from the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will monitor the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will manage risks to delivery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Smaller projects just require a simple statement of costs and benefits with the appropriate number of quotes along with copies of your company accounts will be sufficient for the projects involving:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to working conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety equipment additional to that required by Maritime and Coastguard Agency rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;facilities to maximise fish quality where the costs are less than £1,250&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the adoption of sustainable catching methods where the costs are less than £1,250 (in this case, we will also need the details of your current and future fishing position)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should make sure that you describe all the costs and benefits of your project without double counting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For advice on applying to the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;, you should contact the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-in-the-offer-letter"&gt;What is in the offer letter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offer letter sets out details of the conditions of the grant and any agreed performance targets and ooutputs for the project. You must comply with the conditions along with details of eligible expenditure to allow us to pay your grant claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some general conditions that apply to all grants, as well as conditions specific to your project. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/forms/eff/conditions.pdf"&gt;Read the general conditions of &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; grant for projects in England on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF 93KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should read your offer letter carefully, sign one copy and return it to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; within 4 weeks before you start your project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your application will be treated as commercially confidential throughout the assessment stage. Once approved, the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; will make some details public – the name of the applicant, the amount approved, the nature of the project. By accepting the offer you are agreeing that this information can be made public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must inform the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; in writing if you plan to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modify your project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;change the funding package&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;change the contractors and/or suppliers specified in the offer letter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;change the timetable of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sell any item of infrastructure or stop or relocate any activity that the project is dependent on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your letter to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; should provide justification for any changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-to-include-in-your-business-case"&gt;What to include in your business case&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must provide a detailed business case with your application. Your business case must show that your project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has quantified outputs and clear, attainable targets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will provide an additional and sustainable benefit to the fishing industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has a justified need for grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will provide good value for money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The information to include in your business case varies depending on the axis and the project but generally includes among other items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;full description of your project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;benefits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cost-benefit analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;analysis of different quotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expected results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will monitor the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will manage risks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information about your business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-claim-funding-from-the-eff"&gt;How to claim funding from the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are eligible for funding under the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;, you can claim your grant by submitting a claim form by the date specified in your offer letter to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; at the following address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Relations Team&lt;br&gt;
Marine Management Organisation&lt;br&gt;
Lancaster House
Hampshire Court
Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;br&gt;
NE4 7YH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_success.htm"&gt;Download the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claim form and guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should normally submit a single full and final claim by the date specified in your offer letter. You may be allowed to submit one or more interim claims but the final claim must still be submitted by the date specified in the offer letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; aims to pay the grant within 8 weeks once all the necessary information to consider your claim is received. The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; accept no liability in respect of loss attributable to any delay in the payment of claims or to any suspension, reduction or cancellation of grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The payment will be made electronically into your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="completing-the-claim-form"&gt;Completing the claim form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You or someone acting on your behalf should complete the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claim form and provide supporting documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When filling in the claim form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the name of the claimant should be the person who originally applied for the grant – if different, a covering note of explanation should be attached&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the project number can be found on the offer letter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the title of the project should be a brief description of the project, as set out in the application form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the approval date is the date of the offer letter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the start and completion dates should relate to the project and not the claim – you should enter the expected date of completion of the project for interim claims&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the total grant aid available as set out in the offer letter and details of any grant already received, the amount you are currently claiming and any remaining funding to be claimed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;claims made and remaining should include details of payments still to be made – all figures must normally exclude VAT unless you are not registered&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the work carried out table must show the breakdown of work as set out in the offer letter – the amounts shown in the table should be exactly as quoted on the invoice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes in cost should show the differences between expected and actual costs – you should give brief reasons for any differences greater than 10 per cent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;progress report should show what the project has achieved compared to the targets set out in the offer letter: you should give brief reasons where targets have not been achieved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you, or a person authorised to sign on your behalf, must sign the form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For advice on completing the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claim form, you can call the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supporting-documentation-for-eff-claims"&gt;Supporting documentation for &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claims&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All claims must be accompanied by a progress report. If the progress report for your project is not satisfactory, the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; may not be able to pay your claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must submit the originals of all invoices and other sales dockets in support of each item listed in Section 2(c)1 of the claim form – the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; will retain all original documents. If you cannot, for a legitimate reason, provide originals, you must provide copies which are certified by the supplier as true copies of the originals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; requires a BACs remittance or bank statement showing payment of each of the invoices in order to verify payment of the items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; also ask you to number the invoices in the order they are listed. You will be required to demonstrate that services or goods are costed at market rates and that documentation has a probative value similar to receipts that will satisfy the scheme’s auditors for payments in kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some expenditure incurred in non-capital projects may not involve invoices. In such cases, you must provide appropriate documentation to confirm that the expenditure was incurred and defrayed, such as rail tickets for attendance at trade fairs.
For claims in respect of structural work, a statement from an independent architect or surveyor on letter headed paper is required, confirming that the work has been carried out in accordance with the terms of the original application. Where the work has not been carried out in accordance with such terms, give reasons for the differences and refer to dates on which modifications were authorised by the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further advice, you should contact the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="managing-a-eff-project"&gt;Managing a &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage a project that is supported by the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;, you will have to abide by these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="inspections"&gt;Inspections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must allow inspection of your project by officials authorised by the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;, together with any person accompanying them (which may, from time to time, include an official of the European Commission). You must also provide them with access to relevant documents, and give them reasonable assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All records held by you or the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; may have to be made available for inspection by the Commission and the National Audit Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="progress-reports"&gt;Progress reports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be asked to provide updates on the progress of your project every 6 months. You will also be required to submit a progress report on your business and performance of the project on an annual basis for 3 years from the date of the final payment of the grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="retaining-records"&gt;Retaining records&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; will retain original copies of all documents, invoices and other evidence of payment for reference by authorities such as the Commission or European Court of Auditors. You must also keep documentary evidence of expenditure for 6 years from the date of final payment of grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentary evidence includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;order forms and delivery notes for plant and equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bills of quantity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tenders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;estimates and quotations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;architects’ certificates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;statements and invoices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relevant books of account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;drawings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans and technical specifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="changing-or-cancelling-your-project"&gt;Changing or cancelling your project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class="call-to-action"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the approved project needs to be modified, you should get the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s agreement before the modification takes place. If you do not, you may lose your entitlement to the grant award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modifications include changes in the supplier’s name, status of the beneficiary, change of location and takeover of the company as well as changes in the design and purpose of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If for any reason you decide not to proceed with the project, you should notify the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; as soon as possible that you are giving up the grant. You should send a written notification to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; at this address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Relations Team&lt;br&gt;
Marine Management Organisation&lt;br&gt;
Lancaster House
Hampshire Court
Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;br&gt;
NE4 7YH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further advice, you can call the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="mmo-business-relations-team"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_eff_axis1.htm"&gt;Axis 1 information and application forms on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_eff_axis2.htm"&gt;Axis 2 information and application forms on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_eff_axis3.htm"&gt;Axis 3 information and application forms on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/eff_success.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claim form and guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/8846</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T20:24:41+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T20:24:41+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-03-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 03/2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;driving tests during the Olympics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your comments on sample hazard perception test clips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the launch of the Highway Code app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark Magee, the new Approved Driving Instructor Registrar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check tests dos and dont’s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/8845</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T20:20:37+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T20:20:37+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-02-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 02/2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more driving test candidates benefitting from better local services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the motorcycle test review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;renewing your approved driving instructor registration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lesley Young, the new Chief Driving Examiner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes to driving licence rules in Great Britain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/8844</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T20:16:05+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T20:16:05+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/despatch-ezine-issue-01-2012"/>
    <title>Despatch ezine: issue 01/2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This issue has articles about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;theory test questions no longer being published&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes to motorcycle licence rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;red tape being cut for drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; calling for vigilance over stolen vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the government to establishing an expert panel on drug driving &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a round-up of other news from &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8819</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T19:18:48+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T19:18:48+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/draft-aviation-policy-framework"/>
    <title>Draft aviation policy framework</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s primary objective is to achieve long-term economic growth. The aviation sector is a major contributor to the economy, and we support its growth within a framework which maintains a balance between the benefits of aviation and its costs, particularly climate change and noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially important for those who live close to airports and bear a particular burden of the costs. We therefore want to strengthen the arrangements for involving communities near airports in decisions which affect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is equally important that the aviation industry has confidence that the framework is sufficiently stable to underpin long-term planning and investment in aircraft and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-we-are-consulting"&gt;Why we are consulting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document sets out our draft sustainable framework for UK aviation (referred to as the “aviation policy framework”). It is a consultation document and has been informed by the over 600 responses we received to our scoping document. It is a high-level strategy, setting out our overall objectives for aviation and our policies to achieve those objectives. It is underpinned by two core principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;collaboration:&lt;/strong&gt; by working together with industry, regulators, experts, local communities and others at all levels - international, national and local - we believe we will be better able to identify workable solutions to challenges and share the benefits of aviation in a fairer way than in the past&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;transparency:&lt;/strong&gt; to facilitate improved collaboration, it is crucial to have clear and independent information and processes in place - those involved in and affected by aviation need to have a clearer understanding of the facts and the confidence that proportionate action will be taken at the international, national or local level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that in this consultation, we are seeking views and information relating to the questions that follow. We intend to issue, later this year, a call for evidence on maintaining the UK’s international connectivity. This will include an opportunity to comment on what, if any, new airport capacity may be required to meet the UK’s needs in the medium and long term. If you wish to make such comments you are encouraged to wait until the call for evidence as these would be outside the scope of the current consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-09/"&gt;Developing a sustainable framework for UK aviation: scoping document&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120712b"&gt;Foundations laid for future growth of aviation as government unveils long-term strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//news/statements/greening-20120712a"&gt;Aviation Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8119</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T18:03:03+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T18:03:03+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/policy-on-service-areas-and-other-roadside-facilities-on-motorways-and-all-purpose-trunk-roads-in-england"/>
    <title>Policy on service areas and other roadside facilities on motorways and all-purpose trunk roads in England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statement is to inform the House that following closure of the roadside facilities policy consultation on 2 July last year, I have reviewed the responses and am introducing a change to the policy to permit the development of truckstops on the motorway network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation identified strong support from the haulage industry for the development of truckstops. Proposals for dedicated truckstop facilities will now be considered in the context of existing and/or proposed rest facilities on the strategic road network, and will be determined on their individual merit. This will include truckstop facilities that can be accessed direct from motorways - motorway truckstops - which are a type of facility not permitted until now. Where there is evidence to demonstrate that demand for lorry parking exceeds supply, the development of truckstop facilities at existing service areas would be viewed favourably. Proposals for motorway truckstops are unlikely to be supported if they would prevent a potential motorway service area (&lt;abbr title="Motorway Service Area"&gt;MSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) being built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed advice on the mandatory and permitted features of all categories of truckstop is set out in the table that is attached at Appendix 1 to the written copy of my statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes supplement ‘DfT circular 01/2008 (April 2008)’.  Aspects of policy not touched on in this statement will continue to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently considering ways to reduce regulation, increase competition and improve still further the quality of motorway service areas. To this end, I have instructed officials in my department to identify those elements of the policy that might instead be better determined at a local level through the current planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also instructed my officials to work with the Department for Communities and Local Government to consider how best to take these issues forward in the context of the national planning policy framework. Separately, we will produce an associated DfT technical note, setting out requirements in respect of road safety and operational issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach accords with the government’s twin aims of decentralisation and localism, reducing the burden of bureaucracy and strengthening local accountability. It will encourage competition and, through this, improve service for users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="appendix-1"&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truckstops serving the Strategic Road Network - features and levels of provision&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Features and levels of provision&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Truckstops on Motorways&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Truckstops signed from  Motorways&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Truckstops on All- Purpose Trunkroads&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Opening times
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
24 hours a day, 365 days a year.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
24 hours a day, 365 days a year.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Minimum 12 hours per day, every day except Christmas Day, Boxing Day and New Year’s Day.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Provision of fuel.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Provision of facilities to enable electric powered vehicle transfer (i.e. on-route exchange of un-charged vehicles for charged vehicles) or the exchange of used and charged battery cells.&lt;br&gt;Parking bays may be designated with recharging facilities for use by electric powered vehicles, for which a payment may be levied.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted for HGVs
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted for HGVs
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted for HGVs
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Parking and provision at the levels laid down in Policy Annex B of DfT Circular 01/2008:&lt;br&gt;
      – HGVs (3,500kg or above) (including self-propelled horse boxes)&lt;br&gt;
      – Abnormal loads
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 
Mandatory&lt;br&gt;
        Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 
Mandatory&lt;br&gt;
        Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 
Mandatory&lt;br&gt;
        Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Free parking for up to two hours. Subsequent payment for parking must be possible as an on-site cash transaction.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Provision of high security parking for which an additional charge can be levied after an initial two hour period.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Free toilets and hand-washing facilities for all roadside facility users (at the levels laid down in DfT Circular 01/2008) with no obligation to make a purchase.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Shower and washing facilities for HGV drivers, including secure lockers in the shower/washing area. To be located near to HGV parking, at the levels laid down in DfT Circular 01/2008.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Maximum retail floor space (net internal area for both online and junction sites).  Additional areas may be used for retail storage, but there shall be no public access and    sales shall not be permitted from these areas. The allowance for retail space excludes restaurant facilities preparing food &amp;amp; drink for consumption on the premises.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 500m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 500m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 500m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Trading on bridges connecting two sites across motorway.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Traffic information points to help the public make informed travel decisions and plan their onward journeys.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Games and/or exercise area floor space (games, gaming machines, or exercise machines) for use by Lorry drivers only. Uses that specifically generate traffic will not be permitted.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 100m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 100m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted maximum 100m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Facilities for waste recycling in the amenity building and picnic areas.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Access to a cash-operated telephone (card phones alone will not suffice).
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Advertisements situated within roadside facilities that are visible from the strategic road network (including advertisements mounted internally or externally on footbridges or connecting road bridges).
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Sale or consumption of alcohol on thepremises.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Subject to licensing procedures
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Subject to licensing procedures
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Hot substantial food, snacks and hot drinks available between 05:00 to 10:00 &amp;amp; 17:00 to 22:00.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Access for up to two hours for those carrying out emergency repairs to broken-down vehicles.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Access for parties carrying out duties for and on behalf of the Secretary of State for Transport.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Site must also comply with all applicable equality legislation.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Mandatory
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Bridge or underpass connecting facilities on opposite sides of a motorway.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Use as an operating centre for the purposes of the Goods Vehicles (Licensing of Operators) Act 1995 or the Public Passenger Vehicles Act 1981.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Subject to impact assessment.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Hotels offering overnight accommodation for lorry drivers without generating additional new journeys, additional traffic or a net increase in vehicle mileage.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Permitted
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
All other development.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Prohibited
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Subject to impact assessment
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8105</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T17:13:06+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T17:13:06+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/sale-of-trust-ports--3"/>
    <title>Sale of trust ports</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today launching a consultation on the criteria that the government considers particularly relevant to the consideration of the appropriateness of sale of a major trust port [&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;] in England or Wales under the Ports Act 1991.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the consultation period, which will run for 6 weeks until 27 June 2011, I am seeking the views of interested parties on the following criteria, which I propose to adopt in place of those set out in the written ministerial statement on the sale of trust ports of 25 January 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In view of this consultation, I have asked my Rt Hon Friend the Minister of State to suspend her consideration of the application for a transfer of the port undertaking made by Dover Harbour Board under the Ports Act 1991 until I announce a decision on the proposed criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-proposed-criteria"&gt;The Proposed Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following criteria are those which the government considers particularly relevant when considering an application under the Ports Act 1991 for the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales. This covers the consideration of any proposal for a transfer scheme submitted under section 9 or 10 of the 1991 Act, together with the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions in respect of the subsequent sale of the port to which the scheme relates. The Secretary of State also intends to have particular regard to the policy considerations set out below before making a transfer scheme himself under section 12 of the 1991 Act or subsequently approving the sale of a port to which his scheme relates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-participation"&gt;Community participation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will not approve an application for the sale of a trust port under the 1991 Act unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an ongoing and significant level of community participation in the port. Such participation could take a variety of forms, but must include the ability to influence the port’s long term development and may include the right to receive a share in the profits of the port, or the future increase in its value. It does not necessarily require a community role in the operation of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="future-development-of-the-port"&gt;Future Development of the Port&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an ownership model with the capability and access to capital to meet future investment needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fair-price"&gt;Fair price&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to represent good value for money, having regard not only to Exchequer proceeds and market conditions, but also to other benefits including those to the community and the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fair-competition"&gt;Fair competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will not approve an application that is likely to deliver an ownership model which results in unsatisfactory levels of competition in the relevant sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-networks"&gt;Transport networks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is highly desirable for an application to be likely to deliver an ownership model which will cause the port to be operated so as to contribute to reliable and efficient transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sale-process"&gt;Sale process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is highly desirable that the sale should be conducted in such a way as to give all bona fide prospective purchasers a fair and equitable opportunity to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="employee-involvement"&gt;Employee involvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is desirable for an application to be likely to deliver port employee participation in the ownership of the port, such as the right to receive equity shares or a share in its future success. [&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the purposes of the Act, a ‘major trust port’ is a trust port with an annual turnover above a certain limit (currently £7.6 million). In England and Wales this currently includes Dover, Tyne, Milford Haven, Shoreham, Poole, Harwich Haven and the Port of London Authority (though the latter is excluded from provisions on privatisation contained in the Act).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is without prejudice to the Ports Act 1991 section 5(3) requirement to have particular regard to the desirability of encouraging the disposal of the whole or a substantial part of the equity share capital of the successor company to managers or other persons employed by the port company etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8099</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T17:01:55+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T17:01:55+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/directive-of-the-european-parliament-and-of-the-council-facilitating-cross-border-enforcement-in-the-field-of-road-safety"/>
    <title>Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council facilitating cross-border enforcement in the field of road safety</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform the House that the government has decided not to opt in to the proposed directive facilitating cross-border enforcement in the field of road safety at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft directive intends to improve enforcement of certain road traffic offences committed using vehicles registered in another member state. It aims to facilitate the exchange of registered keeper data between member states’ registration authorities, to help identify offenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While broadly supportive of the objectives behind this measure, the UK did not opt in to the directive because, on balance, it did not appear to be in the UK’s interests to do so at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we prosecute drivers for road traffic offences, rather than vehicle keepers. Given that the directive only provides for the exchange of vehicle keeper information, we had concerns around our ability to effectively pursue fines against the drivers of the vehicles, in the absence of effective provision to compel foreign registered keepers to disclose who was driving the vehicle when the offence was committed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We questioned the interaction of the directive with the Prum Council Decisions, which the UK has signed up to, but not yet implemented, (“Prum” provides for the exchange of keeper data between member states in relation to criminal offences) and were concerned about how the necessary data protection mechanisms could be enforced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we did not consider that a fine would have enough of a deterrent effect to bring about increased behavioural change, since domestically, research shows that it is the fear of points on a licence, or losing the licence altogether which have the main effect on increasing compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had concerns around affordability. There would be significant start-up and running costs were our police to use keeper information obtained under the proposed directive for enforcement purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not opting in at this stage will give us the opportunity to carefully scrutinise the actual costs for setup and implementation of this directive across member states, informing any future decision on a possible post-adoption opt-in, which the government will look at longer term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decision not to opt in to this particular directive does not prevent the UK from engaging with the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; on other matters relating to road safety nor cooperating on enforcement and exchanging data where there are strong, mutual interests for this. The UK continues to plays a prominent part in developing &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; strategy in these areas. We also expect that we will be able to continue to play a part in negotiating the final text of the directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A copy of this statement has been placed in the libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8104</id>
    <published>2012-10-24T16:57:24+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T16:57:24+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-equality-act-2010-work-on-ships-and-hovercraft-regulations-2011"/>
    <title>The Equality Act 2010 (Work on Ships and Hovercraft) Regulations 2011</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have today laid before the House draft affirmative regulations which, if approved, will apply Part 5 (Work) of the Equality Act 2010 to work on ships and hovercraft and to seafarers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations will ensure that, as far as possible, the level of protection afforded under Part 5 of the Equality Act 2010 is extended to those working at sea. This was not done at the time that Part 5 of the Equality Act 2010 was commenced because further consideration needed to be given to the issue of seafarers’ pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the law currently stands, section 9 of the Race Relations Act, 1976, provides that it is not unlawful for seafarers to be paid different rates of pay on the basis of their nationality if they were recruited outside Great Britain. This includes seafarers from &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; States and designated states, which are states with particular bilateral agreements with the European Union. The European Commission has been investigating a complaint that UK law does not comply with European Law and in January this year it issued a reasoned opinion on that basis.  In order to meet its treaty obligations, the government is obliged to bring UK law into line with European law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations which I have laid before the House today will, if approved, apply Part 5 of the Equality Act to work on ships and hovercraft and to seafarers. The government is already committed to the Equality Act 2010, most of which, including Part 5, was commenced on 1 October 2010.  The international nature of the shipping industry requires further clarity in specifying to which seafarers, working on which vessels, operating in which waters, Part 5 of the Act applies. The relevant provisions legislate in respect of employment, offering protection from discrimination, harassment and victimisation in relation to certain protected characteristics, these being age, disability, gender reassignment, pregnancy and maternity, race, religion and belief, sex and sexual orientation.  Section 81 of the Act contains the power to achieve this by means of an affirmative statutory instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power within section 81 of the Act is also wide enough to legislate in respect of differential pay.  The regulations will, if approved, provide that it is not unlawful to offer to pay or pay different rates of pay to seafarers (applicants, employees and contract workers), other than those from &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; or designated states, if a person applies for work as a seafarer or is recruited as a seafarer outside Great Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under section 19 of the Equality Act 2010 (indirect discrimination), where an apparently neutral provision, criterion or practice has an effect which particularly disadvantages seafarers from &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; or designated states in terms of a difference in pay, this will nevertheless be lawful if the employer can show that the provision, criterion or practice is objectively justified.  If differential pay were challenged by a seafarer from an &lt;abbr title="European Economic Area"&gt;EEA&lt;/abbr&gt; or designated state, it would be for the employer to satisfy an employment tribunal as to that justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has consulted with ship owners and the Chamber of Shipping as well as the trades unions before proceeding with this measure and has prepared an impact assessment.  In preparing these regulations, we have applied the principles of our Reducing Regulation initiative and taken every care to ensure that the regulations meet the requirements of EU law without unwarranted elaboration, the better to safeguard the continued competitiveness of the UK fleet. We remain committed to the Red Ensign and to maintaining a sizeable, high quality and highly competitive fleet under the UK flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with government policy on transforming the role of regulation in our society and reducing regulation, these regulations will be reviewed every five years and the conclusions of such reviews will be published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regulations will apply in England, Wales and Scotland while Northern Ireland will shortly be introducing similar regulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
