<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-02T22:04:30+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10154</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T22:04:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T22:04:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-hs2-london-to-west-midlands-appraisal-of-sustainability"/>
    <title>Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="executive-summary"&gt;Executive summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is HS2 Ltd’s advice to government on the outcomes of the review of responses to the consultation regarding the appraisal of sustainability (&lt;abbr title="Appraisal of Sustainability"&gt;AoS&lt;/abbr&gt;) for HS2 London to West Midlands. The ‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future’ consultation was launched on 28 February 2011 with a closing date for responses of 29 July 2011. That consultation covered both the government’s strategy for high speed rail, and the line of route for phase one from London to the West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report considers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;general comments about the approach to environment and sustainability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;energy, greenhouse gas emissions, combating climate change and issues of modal shift in relation to the consultation route&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;air quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;natural and cultural resources: protection and enhancement of the environment in relation to the consultation route&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;specific impacts to species and habitats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;community related route impacts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;jobs and regeneration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a decision is taken to proceed with HS2 London to West Midlands we would undertake a full Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) necessary to accompany the hybrid bill required to authorise the proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EIA would follow the requirements of the Parliamentary Standing Orders including the development of a scope and methodology for the assessment, the determination of significant environmental effects to be brought before the decision makers through the Parliamentary process and identification of relevant mitigation measures. This would be presented as the project’s Environmental Statement (&lt;abbr title="Environmental Statement"&gt;ES&lt;/abbr&gt;). The process of developing the EIA and mitigation would include a plan of engagement and consultation with local people and relevant authorities. A Statement of Public Participation (SPP) would form part of the &lt;abbr title="Environmental Statement"&gt;ES&lt;/abbr&gt; considered through parliamentary scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have carefully considered the views expressed including criticisms of the &lt;abbr title="Appraisal of Sustainability"&gt;AoS&lt;/abbr&gt; in consultation responses. In a number of cases these have identified areas that would require further investigation and the development of mitigation as part of the EIA mentioned above. In a number of locations, in response to issues raised during consultation, we have recommended changes to the line of route to mitigate environmental impacts. These are set out in the Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands Route report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultation responses did not identify an alternative approach that we would consider to be appropriate for the project. Having analysed consultation responses we are confident that the approach we took to examining the impacts on the environment and sustainability through the &lt;abbr title="Appraisal of Sustainability"&gt;AoS&lt;/abbr&gt; is an appropriate one for the stage of development of the proposals. We consider our appraisal represents a sound basis on which the Secretary of State can make a decision.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: Update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20111005090740/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/appraisal-sustainability"&gt;HS2 London to the West Midlands appraisal of sustainability, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10155</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:56:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:56:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-possible-refinements-to-the-proposed-hs2-london-to-west-midlands-route"/>
    <title>Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="executive-summary"&gt;Executive summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is HS2 Ltd’s report to government on the outcomes of our studies into, and recommendations for, potential line of route alignment changes to HS2 London to West Midlands in response to issues raised during consultation. We used these to develop a programme of local studies to consider options for mitigating impacts and enhancing the line of route. The ‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation’ was launched on 28 February 2011 with a closing date for responses of 29 July 2011. That consultation covered both the government’s strategy for high speed rail, and the proposed line of route for phase one from London to West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing engineering issues, environmental issues, costs and benefits we recommend that, if a decision is taken to proceed with HS2, the following changes be considered for inclusion in the line of route to be taken forward to preliminary design and Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increase the clearance of HS2 over the Trent and Mersey Canal near Lichfield to ensure that it remains navigable. We also recommend a slight alteration to the alignment to ensure that it would be compatible with a future extended high speed network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move the route slightly further away from Middleton to reduce local impacts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a shallower cutting and longer green tunnel at Burton Green to further mitigate local impacts and reduce spoil generation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mitigation of impacts on Balsall Common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move the route slightly further east to avoid Kenilworth Golf Club, lower it further into cutting through the National Agricultural Centre, and introduce a retained cutting through South Cubbington Wood to reduce impacts on this ancient woodland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce a longer bored tunnel at Long Itchington Wood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce a longer green tunnel past Chipping Warden and Aston le Walls, and to curve the route to avoid a cluster of important heritage sites at Edgcote&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lower the alignment and introduce a green tunnel past Greatworth, and a short green tunnel at Turweston&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move the route further away from Twyford&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lower the alignment past Aylesbury and Stoke Mandeville to reduce local impacts and eliminate the need for larger scale works to local roads and the Chiltern Line&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce a longer green tunnel to reduce impacts around Wendover, and an extension to the green tunnel at South Heath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce a longer, continuous tunnel from Little Missenden to the M25 through the Chilterns &lt;abbr title="Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty"&gt;AONB&lt;/abbr&gt; to reduce the need for deep cutting and to avoid an aquifer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce a 2.75 mile (4.4 kilometre) bored tunnel along the Northolt corridor to reduce impacts on local communities and avoid major works to the Chiltern Line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken together we consider that these changes would be a considerable enhancement to the consultation route. The number of properties that would be at risk of land take, either during or after construction, would be reduced. Noise impacts would be substantially lower. It would result in a small reduction in the number of properties that would be demolished, and a much larger reduction in the number that would be at risk of land take. There would be reduced impacts on communities and the landscape of the Chilterns &lt;abbr title="Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty"&gt;AONB&lt;/abbr&gt; due to an increased length of tunnelling and green tunnels, while the adoption of additional green tunnels elsewhere along the route would reduce impacts on the landscape, biodiversity and local communities. Through the Chilterns &lt;abbr title="Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty"&gt;AONB&lt;/abbr&gt; this would mean that seven and a half miles would be in tunnel or green tunnel. More than three and a half miles would be hidden in deep cutting, reducing visual impacts, meaning less than two miles would be visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These improvements can be achieved without impacting on journey times and with an overall reduction in construction costs compared to the consultation route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the studies have identified an opportunity to improve the route in a number of places at this stage, this would not be the final opportunity to refine or mitigate the route. That would finally be decided through ongoing engagement as part of the EIA and through the hybrid bill process in Parliament. If a decision is taken to proceed with HS2 along this route we would use consultation responses to support preliminary design and inform the development of mitigation measures along the length of the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="erratum"&gt;Erratum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paragraph 4.3.11 on page 33 has been amended to clarify that the figures in the rest of the paragraph relate to the route within the Chilterns &lt;abbr title="Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty"&gt;AONB&lt;/abbr&gt;, and not between Wendover and the M25 as the original report suggested. An incorrectly hyperlinked reference on the copyright page has also been corrected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paragraph 4.3.6 on page 31 has been amended to to clarify that the depth of the cutting has been reduced between South Heath and Wendover Dean, and not South Heath and Little Missenden as the original report suggested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: Update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10157</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:44:31+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:44:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-strategic-alternatives-to-high-speed-two"/>
    <title>Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="executive-summary"&gt;Executive summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s consultation on high speed rail proposed that a new line, called High Speed 2 (HS2), should be built initially between London and the West Midlands, to be extended to Manchester, the East Midlands and Yorkshire in a further phase of work. The new line would provide additional capacity as long distance services transfer from existing routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) has asked Network Rail to review two proposals (produced by consultants for 51M1 and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) that suggest alternative strategies to HS2, both of which aim to provide additional capacity on the West Coast Main Line (&lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;). The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; has also asked Network Rail to review a high level proposal of an alternative option that aims to provide additional capacity on the Midland Main Line (&lt;abbr title="Midland Main Line"&gt;MML&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the East Coast Main Line (&lt;abbr title="East Coast Main Line"&gt;ECML&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work undertaken to review the proposals has considered the outputs, feasibility, deliverability and costs of the interventions suggested on the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;. The proposals both clearly provide benefits to some flows on the route, although this is at a cost to particular locations through loss of capacity or connectivity. The key issues identified are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;neither proposal would provide sufficient capacity to meet forecast demand on the suburban commuter services at the south end of the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the intensive off-peak service pattern in the alternative strategy produced for the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; would mean that freight growth could not be accommodated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;both proposals would likely necessitate remodelling at London Euston station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;both proposals would result in long periods of disruption along the route while the infrastructure interventions are constructed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the high utilisation of the fast lines in both proposals would negatively impact on route performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;both service specifications increase long distance high speed (&lt;abbr title="long distance high speed"&gt;LDHS&lt;/abbr&gt;) connectivity on some flows, however this is at the expense of other intermediate flows, where connectivity severely worsens. In some cases this results in leaving stations without a train service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assessment of the proposals produced for the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; to provide additional capacity on the &lt;abbr title="East Coast Main Line"&gt;ECML&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Midland Main Line"&gt;MML&lt;/abbr&gt; has also concluded that it is not a suitable long-term strategy for the corridors in question for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is considered that neither route option could deliver the stated outputs with the infrastructure that is proposed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in some cases considerably more infrastructure could be required, such as terminal station remodelling or the building of additional running lines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;both routes would undergo a lengthy and disruptive programme of significant infrastructure upgrades&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="East Coast Main Line"&gt;ECML&lt;/abbr&gt; proposition leaves no clear way to solve the capacity gap that is forecast on services from the outer suburban area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Network Rail’s assessment of the proposals has concluded that these incremental infrastructure and rolling stock enhancements are not the right solution to the overall capacity problem on the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;. Whilst such improvements could provide some relief from overcrowding on certain services, they leave other issues unresolved and, as they fail to provide sufficient capacity for commuters at the south end of the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;, do not solve the main capacity constraint that is the primary driver for intervention on the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a heavy disruption impact to deliver the enhancement projects in all three proposals, as each of the infrastructure interventions required to provide the proposed outputs necessarily affects the operational railway. This is on routes which are more popular and are being used more intensively than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail aims to provide a ‘seven day railway’ for its customers, minimising disruption, particularly on key interurban routes. When part of a route has to be closed diversionary routes are used where possible and if not, passenger journeys are transferred to buses. Freight traffic is even more difficult to accommodate elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cumulative impact of these separate schemes on current services (not including the growth expected in other markets that these outputs do not provide for) would be very significant, involving a sustained period of regular disruption on the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt; (and &lt;abbr title="Midland Main Line"&gt;MML&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="East Coast Main Line"&gt;ECML&lt;/abbr&gt;) similar to that required for the West Coast Route Modernisation (WCRM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some markets the proposals make the situation worse than today on the &lt;abbr title="West Coast Main Line"&gt;WCML&lt;/abbr&gt;, such as removing the capacity for freight growth in the strategy produced for &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;, leaving some stations without a train service (such as Stone and Atherstone) or the reduction in train service for stations south of Tring in 51M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost estimates for the infrastructure interventions included in the proposals are broadly realistic, but the scope which has been priced is less than what would be required to deliver the proposed outputs (for example at London Euston station or for platform extensions), meaning the estimates are insufficient. The cost of disruption has also been underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed interventions deliver considerably fewer benefits than a new line, particularly with regard to reduced journey times between urban centres and the ability to use the resultant freed capacity on the classic network to develop new markets and provide for continuing freight growth. So whilst some of the proposed enhancements may offer limited and short term opportunities for improving capacity on some areas of the route, the requirement for a new line to relieve capacity in the longer term remains and therefore would have to be delivered, in addition to these proposals, in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/12168</id>
    <published>2012-09-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:44:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-standards-for-lorry-and-bus-drivers"/>
    <title>Driving standards for lorry and bus drivers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DSA worked with the haulage and passenger transport industries to develop these and they address specific issues such as the use of tachographs and the dangers of continuous driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-safe-responsible-driving-category-c-standard"&gt;The National Driving Standard Category C™ (lorry)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-safe-responsible-driving-category-d-standard"&gt;the National Driving Standard Category D™ (bus and coach)&lt;/a&gt; outline what drivers need to know, understand and be able to do in areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preparing a vehicle and its occupants for a journey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;guiding and controlling a vehicle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using the road in accordance with the Highway Code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;driving safely and responsibly in the traffic system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reviewing and adjusting driver behaviour over a lifetime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;DSA chief executive, Rosemary Thew, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The haulage and passenger transport industries are a vital part of Britain’s economy and have an important role to play in keeping our roads among the safest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The publication of these Standards will help to ensure that all bus and lorry drivers acquire the right skills, knowledge and attitude to use our roads safely and responsibly, as well as contributing to cutting the human and financial cost of road accidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to thank the haulage and passenger transport industries and the sector skills councils for their input into the development of the Standards. These will enhance the excellent training that is already available and contribute to the work the DSA is doing to set standards for everyone who uses a motorised vehicle on the public roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Standards should form the basis of training that a lorry, bus or coach driver receives – and so the training industry is encouraged to create courses that address them. This includes both the training that drivers complete to professionally (Driver CPC) and training for those who don’t drive for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Standards build on National Driving Standard Category B™ that defines safe and responsible driving for car and light van drivers. They are based on evidence, open to challenge and regularly reviewed to ensure they are relevant and up to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of the Standards fulfils the commitment made in the Government’s Strategic Framework for Road Safety to extend the standards framework to cover categories C and D.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10158</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:23:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:23:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-the-governments-strategy-for-a-national-high-speed-rail-network"/>
    <title>Review of the government's strategy for a national high speed rail network</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="about-this-document"&gt;About this document&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document reviews the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network in light of responses to the ‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future’ consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government received a wide variety of responses to this consultation, ranging from views and concerns to substantiated evidence. Responses were received from a variety of stakeholders, ranging from private individuals to representative bodies. All of this material, provided to the government in written responses to the consultation as well as at consultation events, was considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document provides analysis of the main strategic issues raised, to support the Secretary of State for Transport’s decisions set out in ‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: Update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-technical-specification/"&gt;Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10159</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:15:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:15:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-the-technical-specification-for-high-speed-rail-in-the-uk"/>
    <title>Review of the technical specification for high speed rail in the UK</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="executive-summary"&gt;Executive summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is HS2 Ltd’s report to government which presents the outcomes of the review of responses to the consultation regarding the technical specification for HS2. The ‘High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future’ consultation was launched on 28 February 2011 with a closing date for responses of 29 July 2011. That consultation covered both the government’s strategy for high speed rail, and the line of route for phase one from London to the West Midlands. Consultation responses expressed concern around a number of areas which this report specifically considers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specifying proven technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capacity of HS2: 18 trains per hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a design speed of 250 mph (400 kph)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hours of operation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gauge of HS2 trains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the specification of the classic compatible trains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;impact on other existing rail services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freight on HS2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interconnectivity with other transport networks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;operational safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To address these we established a programme to review existing work and, where appropriate, undertake new analysis. This work has highlighted a number of areas that would require careful consideration during the subsequent design stages of HS2 and its interface with the classic network and, if a decision is taken to proceed with HS2, we would seek to address these in our future work programme. We have also identified a small programme of adjustments to infrastructure on the West Coast Main Line (WCML) that would be needed to mitigate impacts on journey times for classic compatible services north of Lichfield. These have been included in revised cost estimates for HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, we conclude that the specification developed for HS2 is robust and appropriate for the stage of development of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-governments-decisions/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - the government’s decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-decisions-and-next-steps/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future - decisions and next steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-consultation-summary/"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategy/"&gt;Review of the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-strategic-alternatives-study-update/"&gt;High speed rail strategic alternatives study: Update following consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-strategic-alternatives/"&gt;Review of strategic alternatives to High Speed Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-appraisal-update/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Updated appraisal of transport user benefits and wider economic benefits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-economic-case-value-for-money/"&gt;Economic case for HS2: Value for money statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-possible-route-refinements/"&gt;Review of possible refinements to the proposed HS2 London to West Midlands route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-effects-of-route-refinements/"&gt;Summary of effects of HS2 London to West Midlands route refinements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-route-selection-and-speed/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands route selection and speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-appraisal-of-sustainability/"&gt;Review of HS2 London to West Midlands appraisal of sustainability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-review-of-property-issues/"&gt;Review of property issues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-are-you-affected-by-the-route/"&gt;Do you think you are affected by the HS2 route?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20111005090740/http://highspeedrail.dft.gov.uk/library/documents/route-engineering-report"&gt;HS2 route engineering report, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110228"&gt;High speed rail: Investing in Britain’s future consultation, 28 February 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10166</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:08:53+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:08:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/cambridgeshire-county-council-huntingdon-west-of-town-centre-link--3"/>
    <title>Cambridgeshire County Council (Huntingdon west of town centre link)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report written by the Inspector who held inquiries into the objections to Cambridgeshire County Council’s (Huntingdon west of town centre link) highway scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-authority-orders-decision-letter"&gt;Local authority orders decision letter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/lao-20120319/"&gt;Local authority orders decision letter for the Huntingdon west of town centre link side roads order and compulsory purchase order&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10171</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:04:11+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:04:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/impact-assessment-for-historic-vehicle-mot-exemption-review"/>
    <title>Impact assessment for historic vehicle MOT exemption review</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is proposing to exempt vehicles of historic interest (vehicles manufactured prior to 1 January 1960) from statutory MOT test, as allowed under Article 4(2) of the EU Directive 2009/40/EC, and bring the age of vehicles requiring the statutory MOT test in line with The Goods Vehicles (Plating and Testing) Regulations 1988. The purpose of this consultation is to invite views on this proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation"&gt;Consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This impact assessment relates to: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-27"&gt;Consultation for Historic Vehicle MoT Exemption Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.ukconsultations/dft-2011-27"&gt;Consultation: Historic vehicles MOT exemption review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/statistics/series/vehicle-mot-testing/"&gt;Vehicle MOT testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20111103b"&gt;Press Release: Cut red tape MOT for classic cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/penning-20111103/"&gt;Statement by the Minister for Transport: Historic vehicles MOT exemption review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10172</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T21:00:48+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T21:00:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-actions-for-improving-business-opportunities-for-small-and-medium-enterprises"/>
    <title>Department for Transport actions for improving business opportunities for small and medium enterprises</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An action plan to show the activity the Department for Transport is undertaking to improve business opportunities for small and medium enterprises (SMEs). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To contact the department about improving business opportunities for SMEs please contact 020 7944 8288&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10176</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T20:58:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T20:58:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/information-charter"/>
    <title>Information charter</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The department with its agencies holds personal data on the majority of the UK adult population:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency holds records on 42 million drivers and 36 million vehicle keepers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Driving Standards Agency holds details of 3.7 million tests conducted each year and 90,000 registrations for Approved and Potential Driving Instructors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Vehicle and Operator Services Agency holds 103,000 records on goods and passenger vehicle operators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Maritime and Coastguard Agency holds records on seafarers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is very likely that at least one part of our department will hold personal information about you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know how important it is to protect your privacy and to comply with the Data Protection Act 1998. If we ask for your personal information we will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let you know why we need it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only ask for what we need, and not collect excessive or irrelevant information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure nobody has access to it who shouldn’t&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;let you know if we share it with other organisations to give you better public services, and whether you can say no&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only keep it for as long as we need to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not make it available for commercial use (such as marketing) without your permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In dealing with your personal information, we will also:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;value the personal information entrusted to us and make sure we respect that trust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abide by the law when it comes to handling personal information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider the privacy risks when we are planning to use or hold personal information in new ways, such as introducing new systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide training to staff who handle personal information and respond appropriately if personal information is not used or protected properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In return, to help us keep your information reliable and up to date, we ask you to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give us accurate information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tell us as soon as possible of any changes, such as a change of address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-find-out-what-personal-information-we-hold-about-you"&gt;How to find out what personal information we hold about you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about the personal information we process by looking at the privacy policies for our agencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/privacy"&gt;Department for Transport privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/dvla/privacy.aspx"&gt;Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-privacy"&gt;Driving Standards Agency privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/aboutus/2301.aspx"&gt;Highways Agency privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/mcga07-home/mcga-footerpages/privacy_cookies.htm"&gt;Maritime and Coastguard Agency privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/vosa"&gt;Vehicle and Operator Services Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/vca/privacy-and-cookies.asp"&gt;Vehicle Certification Agency privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out whether any of our agencies, or the central department, hold any personal information about you, you can make a subject access request to them under the Data Protection Act 1998. If they do hold information about you they will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give you a description of it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tell you why they are holding it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tell you who it could be disclosed to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and let you have a copy of the information in an intelligible form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In making a subject access request to any part of the department, please be as specific as you can about the information you want, and, if it isn’t obvious, explain why you expect us to hold your personal information. To make a subject access request contact the department or the relevant agency:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/about/contact/"&gt;Departmental and agency contacts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidance for each of the agencies will explain whether it is their policy to charge a £10 fee, as allowed under the Data Protection Act 1998.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="when-we-share-information"&gt;When we share information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to providing the best and most efficient service to our customers. We may share personal information within our organisation or with other bodies where it would be compatible with the purpose for which we collected it, and/or where we are required or permitted to do so by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some cases where we can pass on your information without telling you, for example to prevent and detect crime or to produce anonymised statistics. In all cases - whether data is shared internally or externally - the Department will act in accordance with the DPA and other relevant legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/dft-sharing-information/"&gt;Who we share information with and why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-training-and-guidance-we-give-to-our-staff"&gt;The training and guidance we give to our staff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of our staff are trained in the importance of protecting personal and other sensitive information. Those that work in areas that handle large volumes of personal data, such as DVLA, DSA and VOSA, receive more in depth training and take refresher training each year. Managers who have formal responsibilities for large datasets receive further training still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wide range of guidance is available to staff on compliance with the Data Protection Act 1998 and information security policies, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/data-protection-act/"&gt;Notes for guidance on complying with the Data Protection Act 1998&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-make-a-complaint"&gt;How to make a complaint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unhappy with the way we have handled your personal information and wish to make a complaint, please write to the Data Protection Officer at the relevant agency or the central department. We will acknowledge your complaint within five working days and let you have a full response within 20 working days. If it is not possible to respond fully within this timescale, we will write and let you know why and say when you should receive a full response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="data-protection-contacts"&gt;Data protection contacts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="department-for-transport"&gt;Department for Transport:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Protection Officer&lt;br&gt;
Department for Transport&lt;br&gt;
Information Management Directorate&lt;br&gt;
Ashdown House&lt;br&gt;
Sedlescombe Road North&lt;br&gt;
St Leonards on Sea&lt;br&gt;
East Sussex, TN37 7GA&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:informationhandling@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;informationhandling@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="driving-standards-agency"&gt;Driving Standards Agency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Protection Officer&lt;br&gt;
Driving Standards Agency&lt;br&gt;
Knowledge and Information Management&lt;br&gt;
The Axis Building&lt;br&gt;
112 Upper Parliament Street&lt;br&gt;
Nottingham, NG1 6LP&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:dataprotection@dsa.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;dataprotection@dsa.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-commissioner"&gt;Information Commissioner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For independent advice about data protection, privacy and data sharing issues, contact the Information Commissioner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information Commissioner&lt;br&gt;
Wycliffe House&lt;br&gt;
Water Lane&lt;br&gt;
Wilmslow&lt;br&gt;
Cheshire, SK9 5AF&lt;br&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ico.gov.uk"&gt;www.ico.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Phone: 08456 306 060 or 01625 524 510&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
