<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-19T23:00:23+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8224</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T23:00:23+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T23:00:23+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/regulation-of-aviation-security--4"/>
    <title>Regulation of aviation security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a summary of responses to the government’s consultation on better regulation for aviation security, and announcing the government’s decision on taking forward the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document &lt;a rel="external" href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-21/dft-2011-21-consultation.pdf"&gt;Better regulation for aviation security&lt;/a&gt; set out proposals to modernise the regulatory regime for aviation security to bring it into line with better regulation principles, promote innovation and efficiency and ensure the best possible passenger experience. It proposed a move to an Outcome Focused Risk Based (&lt;abbr title="Outcome Focused Risk Based"&gt;OFRB&lt;/abbr&gt;) approach which would give operators the flexibility and responsibility to design security processes that deliver specified security outcomes, perhaps more focussed towards the needs of their passengers, rather than requiring them, as at present, to comply with prescriptive security requirements. It builds on the successful and similar approach that now applies in aviation safety regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move to an &lt;abbr title="Outcome Focused Risk Based"&gt;OFRB&lt;/abbr&gt; approach would be managed through the introduction of a Security Management System (&lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt;) developed and operated by each responsible organisation. A &lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt; is an organised, systematic approach to managing security which embeds security management into the day-to-day activities of the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will begin with a series of &lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt; pilots, starting at London City Airport once the Olympics have finished, in which industry operators will develop the &lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt; approach and in so doing enhance their internal security cultures. The pilot at London City Airport will be concerned only with the organisation and governance of security at the airport, not with the security checks themselves, which will continue to be managed and delivered in the current way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once these pilots have been concluded, and we are satisfied that the &lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt; process is sufficiently robust and will deliver its intended benefits, we shall look to roll it out generally across the industry. This will provide a sound basis for the development and piloting of the &lt;abbr title="Outcome Focused Risk Based"&gt;OFRB&lt;/abbr&gt; approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation ran from 14 July until 7 November 2011. Some 116 responses were received, from a range of organisations and individuals in the aviation industry as well as from interested bodies. I am grateful to them for the time they took in responding and for their informed and constructive comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to say that there was overwhelming support for the proposed new approach. In publishing the consultation the government acknowledged that these are complex proposals which require further development. The responses have been helpful in clarifying some of the issues involved, including importantly the proposed timetable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation proposed that the new arrangements should be phased in over three years starting in April 2013. The Civil Aviation Bill, which is currently before parliament, provides for various aviation security functions that are currently performed by the Department for Transport to be conferred on the Civil Aviation Authority (&lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt;). Subject to the date of royal assent, we are preparing for the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; to take on those functions from April 2014. The &lt;abbr title="Outcome Focused Risk Based"&gt;OFRB&lt;/abbr&gt; proposals would represent a significant change in the approach to the regulation of aviation security. We have therefore decided that development and roll-out of &lt;abbr title="Security Management System"&gt;SeMS&lt;/abbr&gt; is the right first step to take towards the roll-out of the &lt;abbr title="Outcome Focused Risk Based"&gt;OFRB&lt;/abbr&gt; approach. The &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; has been consulted and supports this decision. The conferring of functions on the &lt;abbr title="Civil Aviation Authority"&gt;CAA&lt;/abbr&gt; does not depend on this development being completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary report, with further information about our plans for implementing the new approach, will be available in the libraries of both houses and on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-21/"&gt;Better regulation for aviation security consultation, 14 July 2011, updated 26 June 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8153</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T22:44:24+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T22:44:24+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/airport-security-scanners"/>
    <title>Airport security scanners</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Christmas Day 2009 an attempted attack on Northwest flight 253 from Amsterdam Schiphol to Detroit was made using an explosive device concealed in the underwear of a passenger. The device had been constructed with the aim of making detection by existing screening methods extremely difficult and had not been picked up by airport security at any point throughout the passenger’s journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous government’s response to this threat included introducing security scanners at UK airports. Security scanners were deployed at Heathrow and Manchester airports in February 2010. They were deployed at Gatwick airport a few months later, meaning that today scanners are in operation at three of the largest UK airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A public &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/2010-23"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt;on an interim code of practice for the use of security scanners began just before the general election. After the election, my predecessor, Philip Hammond, extended the consultation to allow more time for people to respond. The consultation closed on 19 July 2010 and over 6,000 responses were received. These have been analysed and I can now announce how we intend to deploy security scanners in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overwhelming feedback from airports is that nearly all passengers accept the use of security scanners and find the process quick and convenient. Out of over a million scans the Government is aware of only twelve refusals. However, I recognise that some passengers have concerns about the use of security scanners and these concerns were reflected in the responses to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways in which security scanners can be deployed have been restricted by European legislation. My predecessor asked the Transport Commissioner to bring forward proposals which relax these restrictions, and allow scanners to be used more flexibly. An outline package which would achieve this was presented to the European Aviation Security Committee in July and has now been agreed by the European Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most responses to the consultation expressed discomfort with the idea of having an image of their body captured for analysis, and they indicated that - if selected for a security scan - they would prefer to opt for an alternative method of screening. I have considered this carefully. However, I have decided against it, on security, operational and privacy grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I do not believe that a ‘pat down’ search is equivalent in security terms to a security scan. The purpose of introducing security scanners in the first place was to protect the travelling public better against sophisticated terrorist threats: these threats still exist and the required level of security is not achieved by permitting passengers to choose a less effective alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have considered carefully whether there are alternative screening methods which might deliver equivalent levels of security to a security scan. A full private search - involving the loosening and/or removal of clothing in the presence of security staff in a private room - would deliver a reasonable level of assurance. However, I believe that this is likely to represent a greater intrusion of privacy than a security scan, and that nearly all passengers, if they fully understand the procedures, would be unlikely to opt for this alternative. It is also likely to be operationally disruptive to airports and other passengers. Appropriately trained security staff would need to be diverted from the main search area to undertake these searches, leading to increased costs and longer queues for everyone else. I do not, therefore, believe that this represents a viable way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that the proposals recently agreed by the European Parliament include the right for passengers to request an opt out from scanning. The UK did not support these proposals when they were presented to the Aviation Security Committee. Given the security arguments against permitting such an opt-out, and the threat level that exists in the UK, the Government intends to use its powers under the Aviation Security Act to maintain the current position. Those passengers selected for scanning will therefore not be able to fly if they are not willing to be scanned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also asked people whether they had any health concerns relating to the small doses of ionising radiation produced by some security scanners. Only a limited number of responses were received on this issue, but I recognise that it has continued to be a contentious issue. Last year, experts from the Health Protection Agency (&lt;abbr title="Health Protection Agency"&gt;HPA&lt;/abbr&gt;) conducted an official assessment of the x-ray backscatter scanner in use at some UK airports. The &lt;abbr title="Health Protection Agency"&gt;HPA&lt;/abbr&gt; found that the dose of ionising radiation received from deployed backscatter scanners is the equivalent to that received naturally through just two minutes of flying at high altitude.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Commission has called for further expert consideration of the potential health risks from security scanners and has asked the European Scientific Committee on Emerging and Newly Identified Health Risks to review the evidence. I look forward to the Committee’s report and will consider it carefully before making decisions about which technologies should be deployed at UK airports in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is right that the Government does what it can to address people’s concerns wherever that is possible without compromising security. Therefore I can announce today that the Government intends to make further improvements to the privacy and data safeguards already in place for security scanners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software which automatically analyses images is currently in development. Where this technology has developed to a stage at which it passes rigorous Government testing, airports will be expected to deploy it when they renew or replace their equipment. This will mean that in the future images will no longer be seen by human reviewers. In addition, airports will also be required to undertake routine testing of hardware and software to ensure that they remain unable to copy, save, or otherwise transmit images. This will be verified by the Department’s transport security inspectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been considering whether security scanners should be rolled out more widely at UK airports. In principle, I believe that they should. My officials will work with the aviation industry to agree a risk-based approach to further deployments. However, I want to make sure that this is done in conjunction with the availability of enhanced screening technology with better privacy safeguards. The precise timing of further deployments will therefore be dependent on how quickly the new generation of security scanners is developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have placed a copy of this statement, and the revised regulations on the use of security scanners at UK airports, in the libraries of both houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/information-on-the-implementation-of-security-scanners/"&gt;Information on the implementation of security scanners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8049</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:57:32+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:57:32+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-investment--4"/>
    <title>Rail Investment</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statement sets out the government’s plans for investment in rail infrastructure and rolling stock. It builds on the announcement by the Chancellor of the Exchequer of the outcome of the spending review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next four years, we will provide £14 billion of funding to Network Rail to support capital maintenance and infrastructure investment; and £750 million for high speed rail. We will also fund the Crossrail project, the Tube upgrade programme, light rail projects in Birmingham, Tyneside, Nottingham and Sheffield; and provide additional funding to franchisees for extra rolling stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I can confirm we will fund and deliver the Thameslink programme in its entirety, virtually doubling the number of north-south trains running through central London at peak times. But the original programme for the rebuilding of London Bridge was always ambitious, with substantial risks around delivery, and operation of existing services, during construction. To reduce these risks, we have re-profiled the delivery of the programme to achieve completion in 2018. This will enable Network Rail to make further efficiencies to their design and delivery programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Thameslink programme, we will procure a new fleet of trains - up to 1,200 new carriages. This is in addition to around 600 new carriages which will be provided for the Crossrail project. The new Thameslink and Crossrail rolling stock will enable the redeployment of hundreds of serviceable electric carriages currently used on Thameslink services. These carriages belong to rolling-stock leasing companies, but we expect they will be available at competitive leasing prices for re-use elsewhere, thus justifying further electrification of our network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a first step, Network Rail will electrify the commuter services on the Great Western Main Line from London to Didcot, Oxford and Newbury over the next six years. Electric trains will speed up journeys, improve reliability and reduce the impact on the environment. Network Rail will also electrify the lines between Liverpool, Manchester, Preston and Blackpool - an investment of up to £300 million. Work is expected to begin next year and to be finished in 2016. As with Thameslink, we expect Network Rail to keep a tight rein on costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redeployment of electric rolling stock to these routes will, in turn, free up hundreds of diesel units which will be available to train operators to lease as they become available in the period after 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also today confirm that an additional 650 carriages will have been delivered to the network between 6 May 2010 and March 2014. This is in addition to the Thameslink and Crossrail carriages I have already mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have funding confirmed for developments at Reading, Birmingham, London Kings Cross and Gatwick Airport. In addition, investments on the East Coast Main Line and Midland Main Line and improvements in Yorkshire, on trans pennine routes, around Manchester and in South Wales will improve line speed, reliability and capacity of services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond these investments in the commuter railway, there are far-reaching decisions to be made about intercity services. The Intercity Express Programme, launched by the previous government, identified the Agility Trains consortium as preferred bidder to build a new fleet of intercity trains. This February, my predecessors invited Sir Andrew Foster, to provide an independent assessment of the programme. Sir Andrew recommended work on the Agility Trains proposal and a detailed study of the alternatives. Following this work, the four options Sir Andrew identified, have been narrowed down to two. I have ruled out the option of requiring passengers to interchange from electric to diesel trains, recognising the value to passengers of preserving through-journeys. I have also ruled out the option of a wholesale refurbishment of the existing diesel ‘Intercity 125’ fleet, some of which dates back to the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining options are, on the one hand a revised, lower cost Agility Trains proposal, which envisages a mixed fleet: some all-electric trains, and some electric trains which are also equipped with underfloor diesel engines. And on the other, a fleet of new all-electric trains which could be coupled to new diesel locomotives where the overhead electric power lines end. Both these options would allow us to preserve through-journeys between London and parts of the rail network which are not electrified. Both of them would deliver faster journey times. For example, we expect to see a time saving of at least 15 minutes, for the journey between Cardiff and London bringing it below 2 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a major decision which will affect intercity rail travel for decades, and we must get it right. To address outstanding issues on choice of train type and further electrification on the Great Western Main Line, additional work will be required within the Department, with Agility Trains, and with the Welsh Assembly Government on the business case for electrification into Wales. I expect to announce a final decision on IEP, and on further Great Western electrification, in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This package I have announced today has only been possible because this government has been prepared to take the tough decisions to protect investment in Britain’s future. I will make a further oral statement to the House on the issues raised in this statement later today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8061</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:54:01+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:54:01+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/high-speed-rail--14"/>
    <title>High Speed Rail</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With permission, Mr Speaker, I wish to make a statement on the government’s plans for the development of a national high speed rail network, and on the proposed route that we will put forward next year for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the coalition’s main objectives is to build an economy which is more balanced both sectorally and geographically, that will deliver sustainable economic growth while delivering on our climate change targets. Investment in infrastructure, and transport infrastructure in particular, will be a key part of that approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deliver economic growth and carbon reduction we must provide attractive alternatives to short-haul aviation, while addressing the issue of scarce rail capacity between the city centres. Network Rail has calculated that by 2024 the West Coast Main Line will effectively be full, with no further enhancements that could reasonably be made to meet future demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that the best long-term solution to these challenges is the development of a national high-speed rail network. Our proposed strategy is for a Y-shaped network, to be delivered in two phases: the first a line from London to the West Midlands, and the second the onward legs to Manchester and Leeds with connections to points further north via the East and West coast mainlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our proposals would provide an unprecedented increase in capacity on the key north-south routes out of London, through a combination of new infrastructure and released capacity on existing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliability would be improved and journey times between major cities would be slashed. Central Birmingham would be brought within 49 minutes of London - potentially less for non-stopping trains - and within 1 hour 5 minutes of Leeds. The released capacity on the West Coast Mainline would offer the possibility of commuter frequency fast services to London from places like Coventry and Milton Keynes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By running trains seamlessly onto existing inter-city routes, our proposed network would also bring Glasgow and Edinburgh to within three-and-a-half hours of London - fast enough to induce a major shift of passengers from domestic aviation. In the longer-term, we will also explore with the Scottish government the options for further reducing journey times to Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of a high speed rail network has been a key factor in our decision on additional runways at London’s airports, and that is why we have said from the outset that any such network must be linked to our principal gateway airport and integrated with the European high speed network via HS1. In June, I asked HS2 Ltd to carry out additional work on such links. I have studied that work and the recommendations of Lord Mawhinney’s review. I have also examined Arup’s proposals for a transport hub near Iver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded that a spur to the airport, running on the surface close to the M25 for part of its length, is the best option. It is lower-cost than the other options considered by HS2 Ltd, keeps journey times between London and Birmingham to a minimum, and retains the flexibility to be extended into a loop in future. In order to deliver the best possible value for taxpayers’ money, I propose that a spur be constructed as part of the second phase of the network, opening at the same time as the routes to Manchester and Leeds. I have today asked HS2 Ltd, to carry out further work on such a spur route, with a view to public consultation later in this Parliament alongside the routes to Manchester and Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the period prior to the opening of that second phase, high speed rail travellers to the airport would be able to change to fast Heathrow Express services at Old Oak Common, where there would also be a direct interchange with Crossrail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to a link to HS1, HS2 Ltd’s report identifies that a connection can be made via a new tunnel from Old Oak Common to the North London Line near Chalk Farm, from where existing infrastructure can be used to reach the HS1 line north of St Pancras. This proposal is significantly cheaper than any other option for a direct link, and would enable direct trains to run from the midlands and the north to Europe, without affecting existing service levels on the North London Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a tunnel can only be constructed before the Old Oak Common interchange comes into operation, so this link will be included in the phase one scheme put forward for consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, the government believes that the construction of a high speed rail network will support economic growth and the rebalancing of the UK economy. But we recognise that the proposed line will have significant local impacts on the areas it passes through. And that we have a duty to do everything practically possible to mitigate those impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, since my appointment as Secretary of State, I have reviewed the proposals of the previous administration. I have looked at the case for High Speed Rail, at the corridor options for a north-south route, at the different route options put forward by HS2 Ltd and in detail at the route option recommended in its March report. I have reached the conclusion, as the previous administration did, that the route option recommended in March represents the most appropriate general alignment for the High Speed Railway between London and the West Midlands. However before finalising the detailed route that I am publishing today for consultation, I travelled the length of it and talked directly to local authorities, property owners, many of the protest groups and their Members of Parliament, as well as commissioning additional work on the options for improving the proposed alignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, significant amendments have been made to both the vertical and horizontal alignment, and to the proposed mitigation measures. In total, around 50% of the preferred route proposal published in March has been amended in some respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that solutions have now been found which can significantly mitigate the impacts of the railway at local level which, when properly understood, will reassure many of those who have been understandably apprehensive about the potential impact on their lives and their property values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, in Primrose Hill, work to identify the most appropriate locations for the necessary vent shafts has shifted the proposed tunnel, and thus also the vent shafts themselves, to the north, away from the most sensitive areas of this part of London, locating them alongside the existing railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between Amersham and Wendover, opportunities to cover section of the proposed cutting to create a ‘green bridge’ and longer ‘green tunnel’ have been incorporated into the route design to reduce its visual impact and avoid severance of public rights of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Hartwell House, by moving the alignment away from this historic property, HS2 Ltd have been able to ensure that the line would not be visible from the House itself and that additional earthworks and planting can be undertaken to further reduce visual and noise impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the most northerly section of the route, an improved alignment has been identified which would move the line further from Lichfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, Mr Speaker, despite our best efforts at mitigation, we will not be able to avoid all impacts on property values. Where a project which is in the national interest imposes significant financial loss on individuals, I believe it is right and proper that they should be compensated fairly for that loss. So I have asked my officials to prepare a range of options for a scheme to assist those whose properties would not be required for the construction of the railway, but who would nonetheless see a significant diminution of value as a result of the construction of the line. The forthcoming consultation will include proposals for such a scheme, which will sit alongside the statutory blight regime which covers those whose properties would need to be taken to build the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am publishing today on my department’s website and placing in the library of the House, a set of reports by HS2 Ltd which set out for each route section the options considered and the changes proposed, together with detailed maps showing the revised preferred route from London to the West Midlands in full.  This route will form the basis for the public consultation, which I expect to begin in February next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the consultation is launched, I will also publish a revised business case; a full appraisal of sustainability; noise contour maps; and route visualisations; all of which can only be completed now that the final preferred route for consultation has been determined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear, the consultation will encompass the government’s strategy for a national high speed rail network, the choice of corridor and the detailed line of route that I have outlined for the initial London to West Midlands phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the consultation process, roadshows will be held along the length of the preferred route from London to the West Midlands to ensure that local people have the opportunity to find out more about the project and to discuss specific concerns with those involved in developing the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, it is my view that a high speed rail network would deliver a transformational change to the way Britain works and competes in the 21st century,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would allow the economies of the Midlands and the North to benefit much more directly from the economic engine of London, tackling the North-South divide more effectively than half a century of regional policy has done, expanding labour markets and bringing our major conurbations closer together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation exercise we will launch in the New Year will be one of the biggest and most wide-ranging ever undertaken by government and I urge all Hon. Members with an interest to participate and to encourage their constituents to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These proposals have the support of political and business leaders from all parts of the United Kingdom, and I hope they will gain cross-party support in this House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8042</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:44:39+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:44:39+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--13"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first Transport Council of the Belgian Presidency will take place in Luxembourg on 15 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be asked to reach a political agreement on the Directive amending Directive 1999/62 on charging of heavy goods vehicles (the Eurovignette Directive). The Directive governs the taxation of lorries, including rules for the charging of access to road infrastructure where member states choose to do this. The proposed amendments include the removal of references to mandatory hypothecation of revenues and proposals to allow charges to be set flexibly within the overall cap to reflect externalities in areas and at times when there is congestion. We strongly support the former and believe the latter represents an acceptable approach to dealing with congestion. The amendments will also include proposals to allow member states discretion not to include goods vehicles weighing less than 12 tonnes in charging schemes - reflecting the fact that few such vehicles are involved in international traffic - and some limitation of the Commission’s powers to propose amendments to minimum and maximum rates using delegated acts. In particular the Commission’s power to increase the minimum rates of lorry circulation taxes, such as goods vehicle &lt;abbr title="Vehicle Excise Duty"&gt;VED&lt;/abbr&gt;, has been removed. We support both of these proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We remain concerned that this Directive, which impacts on national charging regimes and hence on tax, rests on a transport legal base and will continue to press our position that these issues should be agreed by unanimity. We will also continue to press the case for increasing maximum daily rates for time-based charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be an exchange of views on Strategy and the Future of Transport 2010-2020. This will give ministers an opportunity to set out their position on issues expected to be covered in the European Commission’s forthcoming white paper on transport policy, prior to the more detailed analysis which will follow publication. I will reiterate the UK’s commitment to climate change mitigation measures in transport and to better regulation across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be asked to adopt a mandate authorising the Commission to open negotiations with Brazil on a comprehensive air transport agreement. The government supports the opening of negotiations on such an agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;abbr title="Any Other Business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt; the Commission will present their recent legislative proposal to recast the first rail package. There will be no substantive discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among items for adoption without debate (‘A points’) the Council is expected to adopt conclusions on applications of the European Global Navigation Satellite Systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8130</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:27:21+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:27:21+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/regulation-of-aviation-security--3"/>
    <title>Regulation of aviation security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am launching a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-21"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; on the government’s proposals to modernise the way we regulate aviation security. Better regulation for aviation security proposes a new outcome focused, risk-based approach to regulation which builds on the successful and similar approach to aviation safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the UK is recognised internationally as having one of the most effective aviation security regimes in the world, we also face a continuing threat from international and domestic terrorism. The government’s recent Strategic Defence and Security Review set out its proposals for securing Britain in an age of uncertainty and included a commitment to improve aviation security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this consultation offer a new approach to the regulation of aviation security. Our current system can place significant financial burdens on the aviation industry along with inconvenience to passengers, and could be more consistent with the government’s better regulation principles. I think we can do better - with a new regime which maintains and improves security standards but in a more efficient and passenger-friendly way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I therefore propose that the government should move from prescribing security processes to setting security outcomes. This will give airports and airlines greater flexibility to deliver high standards of security in ways that that are better integrated with their day-to-day business and designed around the needs of the passenger. It will allow them to adopt appropriate new technology as it become available. I want to move away from the current, highly prescriptive, one-size-fits-all approach where all operators run the same regime to one where industry takes a more proactive and more innovative and tailored approach to security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach will also enable the regulator to operate a system of ‘earned autonomy’ - rewarding those operators with the most robust systems of aviation security with greater trust in how they deliver the specified outcomes. Conversely, the level of scrutiny by the regulator will increase proportionately where any concerns arise about the delivery of the required outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The safety and security of passengers will remain of paramount importance to the government, and so the new arrangements will have robust oversight procedures in place to ensure security standards are not compromised. To do this, I am proposing to require all industry operators to develop a security management system. This would demonstrate a clear commitment to providing an overall high level of security and set out how security outcomes specified by the UK Regulator and EU requirements will be delivered. Integral to this will be robust internal quality assurance and auditing arrangements which will complement the regulator’s own assurance and compliance processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also proposes new reporting arrangements whereby industry will regularly report to the regulator on performance and occurrences (including the rectification measures to be taken). This gives the regulator a fuller picture on which to base decisions and direct regulatory effort. I also propose to introduce a system that allows staff to report on a confidential basis any concerns relating to aviation security. These proposed arrangements will provide an additional layer of assurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach offers a new partnership between government and the industry, one that is dedicated to maintaining the highest standards in aviation security whilst also improving the passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are complex proposals, which require further development in consultation with the aviation industry and other interested parties. The Department for Transport will be making extensive efforts to engage industry during the consultation process to explain the proposals further and to seek input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the end of the consultation, the government will then consider all responses and produce a summary report along with next steps. I will make a further statement to the House at that point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8158</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:20:18+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:20:18+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/search-and-rescue-helicopters--3"/>
    <title>Search and rescue helicopters</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform the House of the government’s intentions for the future of the search and rescue helicopter service in the UK. Following the cancellation of the SAR-H Private Finance Initiative in February, the Department for Transport will today publish a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/uk-sar-helicopter-services"&gt;notice&lt;/a&gt; in the Official Journal of the European Union to commence procurement for a new UK wide service contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Rt. Hon Friend the Defence Secretary has agreed that the new contract will provide a search and rescue capability provided by civilian crews, enabling our armed forces to focus activity on their front line operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy and the Royal Air Force crews have shown great dedication and professionalism in delivering an exemplary search and rescue service for many years, and we owe them all great thanks for this. Looking forward, we are confident that, building on nearly 30 years of civilian service provided under contract to the Maritime and Coastguard Agency (&lt;abbr title="Maritime and Coastguard Agency"&gt;MCA&lt;/abbr&gt;), a fully civilian service will be able to maintain the same standards in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This competition will procure a contracted search and rescue helicopter service for the whole of the UK, for a period of approximately 10 years. The Royal Air Force and Royal Navy will continue to provide search and rescue coverage until the replacement for this capability is in place, and it is my intention that the contract I let will require this to be the first part of the new service to become operational. This will ensure that the Ministry of Defence is able to meet its previously announced intention to withdraw from service and retire its fleet of Sea King helicopters by March 2016. The replacement for the capability currently provided by the &lt;abbr title="Maritime and Coastguard Agency"&gt;MCA&lt;/abbr&gt; will follow on from this. This transition will ensure continuity of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bidders for the future service will be able to put forward options which will utilise a mixed fleet of modern helicopters based on the capabilities required at each of the bases (such as range, carrying capacity and endurance). The services will be capable of delivery by different contractors providing complementary services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of a modern fleet of fast, reliable helicopters will lead to major improvements in the capability available from the present mix of helicopters. Modern helicopters operating from 10 full-time bases can not only continue to meet all current service requirements but also provide faster flying times to a large part of the UK search and rescue region, as well as providing a more reliable service. This will therefore be reflected in the new contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my intention that search and rescue operations will cease at RAF Boulmer in 2015 and at &lt;abbr title="Maritime and Coastguard Agency"&gt;MCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Portland when the interim arrangements that were announced in July expire. Other operations at RAF Boulmer will be unaffected by this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the complexity of the issues that need to be considered by bidders during the procurement, I intend that this procurement will be undertaken using the competitive dialogue procedure. As far as is practicable however, I intend to run the competition using lean procurement principles during some stages of the procurement. This will, I hope, both expedite and simplify some stages of the procurement that would ordinarily be time consuming and costly for industry to participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect to award a contract in early 2013 to give the future service provider time to mobilise the new capability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8040</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:16:59+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:16:59+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/consultation-on-revising-the-strategic-national-transport-corridors--5"/>
    <title>Consultation on revising the Strategic National Transport Corridors</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am publishing today, the 16 September, a consultation paper on proposals to amend the criteria defining Strategic National Corridors (&lt;abbr title="Strategic National Corridors"&gt;SNCs&lt;/abbr&gt;). This will result in the identification of roads, including the A1 between Newcastle and the Scottish border as being of national significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic National Corridors were established in 2009 to define the network over which the largest proportion of strategic traffic - that is traffic travelling between the ten largest urban areas, ten busiest ports and seven busiest airports in England moves around the country. The original definition also provided for connectivity between the four nations of the United Kingdom, but there was no specific provision for connecting capital cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that the routes linking Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast to the nearest urban strategic destination should be recognised for the strategic connectivity that they provide.  For this reason I am today launching a consultation on proposals to change the definition, to explicitly include links with our capital cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this change we believe that two routes would be identified as having national significance: namely the A1 between its junction with the A19 north of Newcastle, and the Scottish Border, providing a defined link to Edinburgh; and a route between Bootle and the Twelve Quays Ferry Terminal in Birkenhead, providing connectivity with Belfast. We have also set out information about alternatives to these routes which I invite consultees to consider. Routes linking the network with Cardiff were identified in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation does not include any specific proposals to increase the capacity of these routes. However, the department is considering the nature of the problems on the A1 north of Newcastle so that, as part of the spending review, ministers will be in a position to consider these alongside other priorities in identifying those schemes and programmes that it will be proceeding with, consistent with resources available and the government’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that the consultation will run for a period of twelve weeks, and invite everybody with an interest in the roads potentially affected to take part. A consultation document and instructions for responding can be found on the department’s website and a copy has been placed in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8085</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:15:10+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:15:10+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/olympic-airspace--3"/>
    <title>Olympic airspace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the commitment to deliver a safe and secure Olympic and Paralympic Games, the government is today announcing its plans for temporary airspace control measures that will apply over London and the South East during the Games period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures comprise an inner prohibited airspace zone and an outer restricted zone, approximately 60 nautical miles across, centred on the Olympic Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only certain categories of aircraft - those operating commercial services and subject to full security procedures - will normally be permitted to operate within the prohibited zone. Certain aircraft involved in, for example, Police, Medevac and Olympic Broadcast operations will be exempted. Other operations at airports within this zone may also be considered for exemption subject to strict conditions, which will be assessed on a case-by-case basis. Similarly, we are working with Battersea Heliport to agree a basis on which operations there may be allowed to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All types of aircraft will be permitted to operate in the wider restricted zone provided that they can satisfy certain requirements designed to ensure that all aircraft within the zone can be readily identified and monitored by air traffic control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is envisaged that the measures will be in place from 13 July to 12 September 2012, to cover the period of both the Olympic and Paralympic Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These measures have been designed to help to protect key Games locations from potential airborne threats. It is normal practice to implement airspace restrictions during large-scale events such as major sporting events, and similar measures have been put in place for previous Olympic and Paralympic Games. The measures have been developed to be proportionate and to minimise the impact on the aviation community during the summer of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not expected that any airports will need to close as a result of the measures. There should be no impact on scheduled air services, and limited impact on most other types of operation outside the prohibited zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government, the Civil Aviation Authority and &lt;abbr title="National Air Traffic Services"&gt;NATS&lt;/abbr&gt; will now work with airspace users and others to ensure that the planned measures, and their potential impacts, are fully understood and discussed before the regulations to implement them under the Air Navigation Order 2009 are made later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Options for airspace controls over other Olympics venues outside the South East are still being considered and plans for these will be announced later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copies of a leaflet entitled ‘London 2012 Airspace’, aimed at the general aviation community, showing the coverage of the zones and setting out in more detail the restrictions that will apply within them, have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8237</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T15:12:17+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:12:17+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-bus-and-coach-passenger-rights"/>
    <title>EU Bus and Coach Passenger Rights</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will be publishing a consultation on Wednesday 18 July which puts forward the government’s plans for applying the EU Regulation on bus and coach passenger rights. This aims to ensure bus and coach passengers have rights similar to those using other modes of transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation, which mainly applies to bus and coach journeys over 155 miles (250km), lays out the responsibilities of operators and terminal owners in the case of delays, cancellations, accidents and other issues affecting passengers, including disabled passengers and passengers with reduced mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public consultation will offer the chance for those affected by this EU Regulation to put forward their opinions on domestic enforcement measures, the use of available exemptions and the designation of terminals served by long-distance services where specific assistance has to be provided to disabled people and people with reduced mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the approach outlined in the consultation strikes the right balance between passenger protection and operator competitiveness. I look forward to receiving responses from interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
