<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-23T16:50:57+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7650</id>
    <published>2011-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:50:57+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dsa-yn-adnewyddu-contract-cyhoeddi-gyda-r-llyfrfa"/>
    <title>DSA yn adnewyddu contract cyhoeddi gyda’r Llyfrfa</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dewiswyd Y Llyfrfa (&lt;abbr title="Dewiswyd Y Llyfrfa"&gt;TSO&lt;/abbr&gt;), rhan o Grŵp Williams Lea, i gyhoeddi adnoddau addysg i yrwyr a reidwyr yr Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru (&lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) am y tair blynedd nesaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mae’r symudiad yn dilyn cystadleuaeth lem am y contract i gyhoeddi ystod o
feddalwedd, llyfrau a DVDs y &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, gan gynnwys The &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; Guide to Learning to Drive a Rheolau’r Ffordd Fawr. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meddai Jane Phillips, cyfarwyddwr Ymgysylltu a Gweithredu’r &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Roedd cystadleuaeth lem am y contract pwysig hwn a roddodd gyfle i ni gael y gwerth gorau posibl am arian i’r asiantaeth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mae hwn yn amser cyffrous yn y byd cyhoeddi gyda rhaglenni ffôn, e-ddysgu ac e-lyfrau yn datblygu’n gyflym ac edrychwn ymlaen at weithio gyda &lt;abbr title="Dewiswyd Y Llyfrfa"&gt;TSO&lt;/abbr&gt; i ddatblygu cynnwys, fformatau a chyfryngau newydd i wneud ein deunyddiau mor hygyrch â phosibl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Dewiswyd Y Llyfrfa"&gt;TSO&lt;/abbr&gt; yw partner cyhoeddi swyddogol presennol &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7654</id>
    <published>2011-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:47:10+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/streic-arholwyr-gyrru-ymgeiswyr-i-fynychu-profion"/>
    <title>Streic arholwyr gyrru – ymgeiswyr i fynychu profion</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mae’r Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru yn annog pob ymgeisydd prawf gyrru sydd wedi bwcio i gymryd prawf ar Ddydd Iau 30 Mehefin i fynychu fel arfer er gaethaf y bygythiad o weithredu diwydiannol gan arholwyr sy’n aelodau o’r undeb Gwasanaethau Cyhoeddus a Masnachol (&lt;abbr title="Gwasanaethau Cyhoeddus a Masnachol"&gt;PCS&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meddai prif weithredwr yr Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru, Rosemary Thew: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nid yw pob arholwr yn aelod o undeb y Gwasanaethau Cyhoeddus a Masnachol(&lt;abbr title="Gwasanaethau Cyhoeddus a Masnachol"&gt;PCS&lt;/abbr&gt;) a hyd yn oed os ydynt, ni allwn fod yn sicr na fyddant yn dod i’r gwaith. Felly rydym am i ymgeiswyr fynychu er mwyn gallu cyflawni profion ymarferol os yn bosibl. Nid yw profion theori wedi eu heffeithio a byddant yn digwydd fel y cynlluniwyd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ni fydd rhaid i ymgeiswyr sy’n cyrraedd ond yn methu cymryd eu prawf oherwydd gweithredu diwydiannol gysylltu a’r &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; i drefnu dyddiad arall. Dylent glywed gennym gyda dyddiad newydd o fewn pump i 10 niwrnod gwaith. Ymddiheurwn am yr anghyfleustra fydd hyn yn achosi a byddwn yn gwneud popeth y gallwn i leihau’r aflonyddwch i’n cwsmeriaid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Os nad oes arholwr ar gael ar gyfer prawf, bydd dyddiad newydd yn cael ei drefnu yn awtomatig gan y &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; ac fe anfonir manylion y prawf newydd at yr ymgeisydd. Os bydd ymgeiswyr yn methu mynychu, ni fyddant yn gallu hawlio treuliau parod os yw eu profion yn cael eu canslo a bydd angen iddynt aildrefnu eu profion eu hunain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Efallai y bydd canolfan gwasanaeth cwsmeriaid y &lt;abbr title="Asiantaeth Safonau Gyrru"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; ar gyfer profion ymarferol hefyd wedi ei effeithio gan y gweithredu diwydiannol. Bydd cwsmeriaid sydd am drefnu prawf ymarferol yn dal i allu defnyddio ein gwasanaeth archebu ar y rhyngrwyd yn &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/drivingtest"&gt;direct.gov.uk/drivingtest.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mae manylion hawlio treuliau parod ar gael o &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/drivingtestexpenses"&gt;direct.gov.uk/drivingtestexpenses.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8273</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T16:18:56+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:18:56+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/british-transport-police-federation-annual-conference"/>
    <title>British Transport Police Federation annual conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many thanks for that introduction and for inviting me to address your national conference. I’m sorry I couldn’t be with you for your awards ceremony but I want to take this opportunity to congratulate all of the winners. Your bravery awards are always a timely reminder of the debt of gratitude this country owes to the British Transport Police (&lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;). Day in, and day out, the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s police officers work tirelessly to protect the travelling public, to make our railways, tubes and trams safe and secure ways to travel, putting your own safety on the line to do this. So, as a Rail Minister and a rail passenger, I would like to put my tribute on public record and to thank you for all you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every few years it seems that a proposal crops up to subsume you into one or other of the Home Office forces. And I welcome the fact that every time that debate resurfaces, the case is successfully made for retaining a specialist railway police force. With the robust leadership provided by Andy Trotter, I’m certain you’ll continue to fend off these take-over attempts. I would like to acknowledge the great work Andy is doing as your chief constable. In taking over from Sir Ian Johnston, he had a tough act to follow and I believe the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; has been very lucky in the exceptional calibre of both its current and its previous chief constables. And I’d also like to praise the work of the British Transport Police Federation and its chairman, Alex Robertson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You face a host of operational demands, some of which your chairman outlined in his excellent speech kicking off the conference today. At one end of the spectrum vandalism, drunkenness, mobile phone theft and a host of other crimes this country has already witnessed in the murderous 7/7 attacks. At the other, we’ve seen the Mumbai killings illustrate another set of risks that could materialise on our rail network. All of this is a reminder, if it were needed, of the pivotal security and anti-terrorism role of the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;. The Olympics will bring a new set of exacting challenges and your key role in delivering a successful games, is one I fully recognise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="public-finances"&gt;Public finances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the work this Federation does, the priorities you campaign on, the issues which matter most to your members, all of these things must be set against the backdrop of the crisis in the public finances and the scale of the deficit the coalition inherited from our Labour predecessors. This government’s most urgent priority is to tackle that deficit. From our first days in office, through our Emergency Budget to the Spending Review, we’ve been taking the difficult decisions needed to control spending and put the public finances back on the path to recovery. And let’s be clear, painful though some of the spending reductions will be, the consequences of not dealing with the deficit are far worse. We’d be facing spiralling interest rates and the risk of an Irish style budget crisis and bail out. Left untackled the debt we inherited, the largest in British peacetime history, would be costing the country £70 billion a year in interest payments alone by the end of this Parliament. That’s more than we’re spending on policing our streets and defending our country. And there are some things that public finance problems have in common, with a credit card bill, the simple truth is the longer you it leave it the worse it gets. The restoration of fiscal discipline is vital if we are to put this country back on its feet again and deliver the economic stability we need for jobs and growth. But we also recognise the crucial importance of modernising our transport infrastructure to make it an engine of economic growth and a gateway to a better quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why the Chancellor has placed a priority on transport projects, committing more than  £30 billion of capital investment over the next four years, including, pretty much the biggest programme of rail upgrades in modern history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mcnulty-and-efficiency"&gt;McNulty and efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fact is that the cost of running the railways has escalated dramatically over recent years. If we’re going to continue to deliver improved services and additional capacity that passengers want, the cost of running the railways has to come down. For the sake of both taxpayers and fare payers, it’s imperative that we achieve that goal. So drawing on the work being done by the McNulty Review, we’ll be challenging the rail industry to cut its costs. And I’m afraid it would be difficult to justify exempting the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; from those efforts. I very much welcome the efforts you are already making to drive down costs and improve efficiency and I accept that the Olympics is a special case which requires separate consideration but I’m certain that the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police Authority"&gt;BTPA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the rail industry will rightly want to press for savings over the years to come. And given the amount of public money supporting the train operators, Network Rail and the London Underground, the cost of the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; does have a direct bearing on the public finances, even though your funding structure is different from your Home Office counterparts. I’m confident that the innovation and dedication your force has always demonstrated will enable you to meet this new challenge successfully and to find ways to deliver top class policing outcomes within a the tighter funding environment which I’m afraid the crisis in the public finances makes inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pay-and-pensions"&gt;Pay and pensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech, your chairman touched on the Winsor Review. Of course I fully understand your anxiety about what the outcome might be. This will be the most comprehensive independent review of police pay and conditions in more than 30 years. Working alongside police officers and their representatives, Tom Winsor’s key objective is to ensure that chief constables can deliver the frontline services people want, while securing value for money. And as Tom has made clear, his over-riding principle while conducting this review is fairness - “fairness to police officers and fairness to the taxpayer”. Your chairman also referred to the Hutton Review and the indirect impact it might potentially have on the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; pension fund, separate though that is, from the public sector schemes which Lord Hutton is considering. Pensions reform is a massive challenge. Successive governments have put this issue in the ‘too difficult’ box. Well, the state of the public finances means that is no longer a viable option. But we have already made it clear that this is not a race to the bottom. We have decisively rejected this option. Lord Hutton’s remit is to come up with reforms that put public sector pensions on a more sustainable financial footing but do so in a way which is fair both to the workforce and to taxpayers. We want to see public service pensions as a gold standard, once again providing a benchmark for the private sector to aspire towards. Staying with pensions for a moment, in his speech, Alex expressed concern about the costs of the Pension Protection Fund. I understand why this matters to your members. So, officials from my department have been talking to the &lt;abbr title="Pension Protection Fund"&gt;PPF&lt;/abbr&gt; on this issue to see if we can find a way to address some of your concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are a number of other ways in which the Department for Transport is engaged on matters raised with us by the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;. For example, we’re giving very active consideration to the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s request for an armed unit. I welcome the progress being made on this issue. I know also that you have long argued that the football authorities and football clubs should take more responsibility for the costs they impose on police forces in general and the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; in particular. Well, there are no simple solutions on that issue but I have taken it up with my colleagues at the Home Office and &lt;abbr title="Department for Culture Media and Sport"&gt;DCMS&lt;/abbr&gt; to explore whether change might be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rising-to-the-challenge"&gt;Rising to the challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond question these are testing times. But if anyone has what it takes to meet the challenge then it’s the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;. By way of proof Alex pointed to some very impressive improvements in crime and detection stats from the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s annual performance figures. In fact, over the past 6 years, crime on Britain’s railways is down a remarkable 25%, while the detection rate has improved by 18 points over the same period. It now stands at its highest level ever. These results speak far more eloquently than I ever could about the courage, commitment and dedication of all those who work for the British Transport Police. For example, your Safer Stations, Safer Journeys programme has helped reduce crime through high-visibility patrolling of stations and trains. You have also provided invaluable support to officials in my department on initiatives like the Secure Stations Scheme which can have a real impact on quality of life for millions of commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I fully recognise the value of the work the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; is doing to combat cable theft. Metal thieves targeting the railway are causing misery to thousands of passengers and freight users, because of the major disruption they cause. Network Rail anticipates that by the end of 2011, around 500,000 minutes of delay will have been caused by cable theft. I welcome the joint work being done by the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Home Office and Network Rail to tackle this crime, not least by trying to make it much more difficult for thieves to get cash for stolen metal. But perhaps the aspect of your working practices that I admire the most is the approach you take to getting the railway up and running again as quickly as possible after an incident on the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leadership and officers of the &lt;abbr title="British Transport Police"&gt;BTP&lt;/abbr&gt; demonstrate a real awareness of the damaging economic consequences of prolonged railway shutdowns, not to mention the inconvenience and frustration for passengers. I think there are lessons here for the way we deal with incidents on the road and motorway network. I’ve repeatedly expressed enthusiasm for spreading best practice from rail to road in this context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion, for some 2 centuries, the men and women who tackle crime on our railways have been at the forefront of policing. I’m certain that the British Transport Police will continue to play a pivotal role in the success of this country’s railways. And that’s because your members and the unique police force in which they serve, are the people who day after day risk their own personal safety in keeping railways safe for others. In so doing, they are, as your chairman said in his speech, part of the bedrock of democracy. So I thank you once again for what you do to protect the travelling public and I thank you for listening to what I’ve had to say today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7657</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:14:15+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-tests-set-to-return-to-the-trowbridge-area"/>
    <title>Driving tests set to return to the Trowbridge area</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving test candidates in Wiltshire could benefit from a more local service as the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) carries out a trial exploring a new approach to test delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of seven trials to provide practical car tests in selected areas that do not currently have a local test centre but still have a significant demand for tests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s test centres in Wiltshire, at Trowbridge, closed in 2008, with tests moving to the neighbouring centre in Chippenham. However, the trial will explore whether tests can now be provided more locally, including in the Trowbridge area, and possibly using alternative venues such as local authority buildings, hotels or leisure centres. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want us to be more flexible and innovative in delivering driving tests to make sure that we are offering people the best service possible wherever they live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to provide a more local service that is both convenient for candidates and cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working to identify suitable test routes in the area and find a venue that offers the right level of service for candidates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plans for trials across England, Scotland and Wales. Each trial will be closely monitored to assess any impact on levels of customer service and the cost of delivery, and to make sure the integrity of the test is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will then decide whether the scheme can be rolled out to other areas without a local test centre where there is a significant demand, as well as suitable routes and venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial will involve only practical car tests; theory test centres will not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7655</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:07:11+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/dumbarton-leads-the-way-in-trial-to-bring-driving-tests-closer-to-candidates"/>
    <title>Dumbarton leads the way in trial to bring driving tests closer to candidates</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving tests in Dumbarton are being evaluated as part of a national trial that aims to provide a more local service for driving test candidates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as using conventional driving test centres, the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) wants to explore how it can also use other venues to deliver tests, such as hotels or local authority buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former driving test centre in Dumbarton closed earlier this year, but &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; has since been delivering practical driving tests from the Burgh Hall in Dumbarton town centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is now planning similar trials in six other locations across England, Scotland and Wales that do not currently have a local test centre but still have a significant demand for tests. The aim is to provide a service for the local community and ensure that candidates are able to take their test at a convenient location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want us to be more flexible and innovative in delivering driving tests to make sure that we are offering people the best service possible wherever they live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to provide a more local service that is both convenient for candidates and cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trials will be monitored to assess any impact on levels of customer service and the cost of delivery, and to make sure the integrity of the test is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will then decide whether the trials can be rolled out to other areas without a local test centre where there is a significant demand, as well as suitable test routes and venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial will only involve practical car tests; theory test centres will not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7660</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:03:19+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ashford-leads-the-way-in-trial-to-bring-driving-tests-closer-to-candidates"/>
    <title>Ashford leads the way in trial to bring driving tests closer to candidates</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving tests in Ashford are being evaluated as part of a national trial that aims to provide a more local service for candidates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as using conventional driving test centres, the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) wants to explore how it can also use other venues to deliver tests, such as local authority buildings, leisure centres or hotels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former driving test centre in Ashford closed earlier this year when &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s occupancy agreement came to an end, but since then &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; has been delivering practical driving tests from the Holiday Inn on Canterbury Road. In the coming weeks testing will move to Ashford Borough Council’s Civic Centre on Tannery Lane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want us to be more flexible and innovative in delivering driving tests to make sure that we are offering people the best service possible wherever they live. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to provide a more local service that is both convenient for candidates and cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is now planning similar trials in six other locations across England, Scotland and Wales that do not currently have a local test centre but still have a significant demand for tests. The aim is to provide a service for the local community and ensure that candidates can take their test at a convenient location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trials will be monitored to assess any impact on levels of customer service and the cost of delivery, as well as making sure the integrity of the test is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will then decide whether the trials can be rolled out to other areas without a local test centre where there is a significant demand, as well as suitable test routes and venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trials will only involve practical car tests; theory test centres will not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8271</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T16:00:46+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:00:46+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/chamber-of-shipping-annual-dinner"/>
    <title>Chamber of Shipping annual dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that kind introduction Jan. This country’s shipping industry is, and always will be, fundamental to our prosperity and our security. I am incredibly proud to be the Maritime Minister, and I want to be here, a constructive friend to the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move forward together, I can already see that positive steps are being taken and real progress is being made. We have already made significant steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On light dues, I’ve recently confirmed a move to full funding of Irish Lights from Irish domestic sources by 2015 or 2016&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On ship to ship transfers, I have suspended legislation that would have pushed ships 12.1 miles out from our coast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But there are challenges. On the issue of equality of pay, I will have to introduce some legislation following infraction proceedings. These will be the minimum provisions though and I will do all I can to make a level playing field across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. Turning to piracy, a huge challenge and concern for our industry - I know that in reality many UK flagged ships are already employing armed guards to protect themselves. If shipping companies choose to have them, I don’t want cowboys on ships - I want properly trained security companies. That is why I am looking at our guidance on this issue to give the industry support and advice if they choose to go down this route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the broader economic front, this government is tackling our inherited debt so as to create the conditions that will help private businesses, just like those you represent, to thrive. Yes, the challenges we face mean we are navigating our way through some choppy economic seas. But cutting the deficit is the best way to spark demand, spur job creation and strengthen our economy, and that’s why we must stick to the course we have set out. This need for growth is one of the reasons that I want to look very closely at all the trust ports round the UK to make sure that they have the right commercial ambitions to grow. The other way we will grow is to invest in our young people. That is why we have protected the &lt;abbr title="Support for Maritime Training"&gt;SMART&lt;/abbr&gt; budget this year and want to work together with you as part of our review to find the most effective way of supporting our young trainees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to offshore renewables, I warmly welcome the co-operation being provided by the shipping and ports industries. It is possible to realise the full potential of this new source of clean energy in a way that does not compromise the economic viability of our shipping our ports industries, nor compromise navigational safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to protect our seas as well so that we can have a renaissance in coastal shipping. We are an island nation and we need to transport more goods by sea. Working together, I truly believe that we can build that successful and sustainable future. That’s what excites me about my job and that’s why I am incredibly proud to be your champion in government. It’s also the reason, as I said at the start of my speech, that I am totally committed to partnership working. You have a minister who is on your side and in your corner. Now, does that mean that we will always agree on every last dot and comma of shipping policy? Of course it doesn’t. But I know that we stand on common ground and share a common cause. And that’s why I also know that, as well as having a history of which it can be proud, Britain’s shipping industry also has a future of which it can be confident. So I thank you for your hospitality, I thank you for listening and I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/7659</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T16:00:24+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-tests-set-to-return-to-warrington"/>
    <title>Driving tests set to return to Warrington</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving test candidates in the Warrington area could benefit from a more local service as the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) carries out a trial exploring a new approach to test delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of seven trials to provide practical car tests in selected areas that do not currently have a local test centre but still have a significant demand for tests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test centre in Warrington closed in March 2008 when a new multi-purpose test centre opened in St Helens. This trial will not replace the multi-purpose test centre, but will explore whether tests can also be provided more locally, possibly using alternative venues such as local authority buildings, hotels or leisure centres. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want us to be more flexible and innovative in delivering driving tests to make sure that we are offering people the best service possible wherever they live. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to provide a more local service that is both convenient for candidates and cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is working to identify suitable test routes in the Warrington area and find a venue that offers the right level of service for candidates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plans for trials across England, Scotland and Wales. Each trial will be closely monitored to assess any impact on levels of customer service and the cost of delivery, as well as making sure the integrity of the test is maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; will then decide whether the trials can be rolled out to other areas without a local test centre where there is a significant demand, as well as suitable routes and venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial will involve only practical car tests; theory test centres will not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuide/8605</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T12:25:25+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T15:58:21+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/fish-and-shellfish-farm-authorisation-and-registration"/>
    <title>Fish and shellfish farm authorisation and registration</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All fish, shellfish and crustacean farms are legally required to be authorised by the Fish Health Inspectorate (&lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;) under the Aquatic Animal Health (England and Wales) Regulations 2009. Before setting up a new fish, shellfish or crustacean farm, or before starting any related development, you must apply to the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; to have it authorised. Once you have met all of the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s requirements and have an approved and documented biosecurity measures plan in place, you will be issued with a certificate of authorisation, and be able to stock and trade from your farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are conditions of authorisation that your farm will have to observe, such as keeping records of all movements in the prescribed format and following good hygiene practice. The &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; can suspend or revoke your authorisation if they believe you aren’t complying with the conditions of your authorisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide explains how to apply for authorisation for your farm. It also sets out your legal responsibilities and tells you how to make changes to your authorisation if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fish-and-shellfish-farm-authorisation"&gt;Fish and shellfish farm authorisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Aquatic Animal Health (England and Wales) Regulations 2009, all fish, shellfish and crustacean farms - known as aquaculture production businesses - must be authorised by the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply-for-authorisation"&gt;How to apply for authorisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before setting up a new fish farm or beginning any development, you must apply for authorisation. To apply for authorisation, complete form AW1 and return it to the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your application is for a new farm, you should only fill in sections 1, 4 and 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the details that you provide about your farm will form part of your authorisation. This includes the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;species farmed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number and type of holding facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ordnance Survey grid reference showing the location of your farm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So it is very important that you include all of these when you fill in section 4 of form AW1. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/files/Form-AW1.pdf"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form AW1 to apply for authorisation from the Aquatic Animal Health and Movements (&lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt;) website (PDF, 65KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-happens-after-you-apply"&gt;What happens after you apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; has received your application form, they will confirm they have received it and inform you that an inspector will visit your site. They will also give you guidance on developing a biosecurity measures plan (&lt;abbr title="biosecurity measures plan"&gt;BMP&lt;/abbr&gt;). The &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; will consult with other government bodies regarding the species you’re intending to farm and the facilities that will be developed and included in the authorisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fish health inspector who is responsible for the area where your farm is situated will contact you directly to make arrangements to visit. During the visit the inspector will discuss and document your farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the visit the inspector will pass their report and the data they collect to an authorisation officer. The authorisation officer will act on their recommendations, which will result in one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;authorisation being granted because your site is complete and has an approved &lt;abbr title="biosecurity measures plan"&gt;BMP&lt;/abbr&gt; in place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorisation in principle being granted: This may be because your site is complete but your draft &lt;abbr title="biosecurity measures plan"&gt;BMP&lt;/abbr&gt; has not yet been submitted for approval. Once this happens authorisation will be granted. Or it may be because yours is a new site in the ‘paper’ planning stage. Once a consultation with other government bodies has taken place and the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; has approved your plans, your site will be granted authorisation in principle. Full authorisation will only be granted after a full site and &lt;abbr title="biosecurity measures plan"&gt;BMP&lt;/abbr&gt; assessment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;authorisation is not granted: It may be that it is more appropriate to register your site as a fishery or aquatic animal holding - see the page in this guide on registering a fishery - or it may be that your proposed plans or species are not permitted under current legislation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your application for authorisation will be handled according to &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; standards of customer service. For guidance on what standards to expect when you apply for authorisation, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cefas.defra.gov.uk/media/510230/fish-health-inspectorate-cc.pdf"&gt;download the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; citizen’s charter from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 51KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="what-happens-if-your-application-is-unsuccessful"&gt;What happens if your application is unsuccessful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; turns down your application they will tell you the reasons why, and how you can appeal against their decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="requirements-for-authorised-fish-and-shellfish-farms"&gt;Requirements for authorised fish and shellfish farms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish, shellfish and crustacean farms need to be authorised to prevent infectious diseases being introduced and spread within the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, as a condition of authorisation you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep movement records in the prescribed format&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;follow good hygiene practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;comply with any surveillance requirement requested by the Fish Health Inspectorate (&lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;comply with the procedures specified in your site’s approved biosecurity measures plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Details of your farm will be kept in a public register of authorised businesses maintained by the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="record-keeping-requirements"&gt;Record keeping requirements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owners and operators of authorised fish, shellfish and crustacean farms are required to keep certain records in a format specified by the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;. The records that you must keep are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;details of movements of any aquaculture animal, or aquaculture animal product, into or out of your premises - see the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/moving-fish-and-shellfish"&gt;moving fish and shellfish&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of any aquaculture animals that have died in each of your units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the results of any surveillance you carry out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the results of any surveillance carried out by the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; which you are notified about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="changes-to-an-existing-authorisation"&gt;Changes to an existing authorisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are already operating an existing aquaculture production business (&lt;abbr title="aquaculture production business"&gt;APB&lt;/abbr&gt;) there may be certain occasions when your authorisation needs to be changed. This might be because you need to make changes to the way your farm operates, such as the species farmed or the facilities used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply-to-make-changes-to-your-details"&gt;How to apply to make changes to your details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must tell the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; in advance if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the owner or operator of the farm changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the farm is no longer operational and your authorisation needs to end&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the species being farmed changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of tanks, ponds or other holding facilities changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To apply to make the required changes, you must complete Section 2 or 3 of form AW1 as appropriate and send it to the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/files/Form-AW1.pdf"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form AW1 to make changes to your authorisation details from the Aquatic Animal Health and Movements (&lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt;) website (PDF, 65KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fhi-enforcement-of-non-compliance-by-an-apb"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; enforcement of non-compliance by an &lt;abbr title="aquaculture production business"&gt;APB&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; will, in the first instance, issue an enforcement notice to sites that have not complied with a condition of authorisation and will agree the appropriate follow up action. For continued non-compliance the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; can suspend or revoke an authorisation if they believe that a farm has not complied with either the conditions of authorisation or another legal requirement. The &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; will send a written notice of suspension or revocation with details of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reason for the suspension or revocation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the date that the suspension or revocation starts, and its duration if they are issuing a suspension&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your right to appeal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-register-a-fishery"&gt;How to register a fishery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Aquatic Animal Health (England and Wales) Regulations 2009, all stocked and cropped waters - apart from rivers and canals - must be registered with the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt;. Until your fishery or cropping water is registered, you will not get consent from the Environment Agency to stock your waters or remove fish from them. See the guide on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/moving-fish-and-shellfish"&gt;moving fish and shellfish&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="registration-requirements"&gt;Registration requirements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of registering a fishery requires a single named person to take responsibility for the waters. This could be the owner, lease holder, operator or manager. The person responsible must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; all reasonable help and access in the event of fish mortality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;report any suspicion of a notifiable disease&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply-to-register-your-waters"&gt;How to apply to register your waters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of registration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fisheries registration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aquatic animal holdings registration (cropping waters)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To register a stocked and cropped fishery, you must use form RW1. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/forms/forms-list/"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form RW1 to register your fishery from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 184KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To register an aquatic animal holding, you must use form RW2. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/files/Form-RW2.pdf"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form RW2 to register your aquatic animal holding from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 98KB)&lt;/a&gt;. Registration of aquatic animal holdings is the minimum required under the legislation and applies only to low risk cropping and harvesting waters, not fisheries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you fill in the application form, you must include a map of your waters. You must use one application form for each complex of waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; has received your application, they will register your waters and provide you with your registration number on a registration document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fhi-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;01305 206 700&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/files/Form-AW1.pdf"&gt;Download form AW1 to authorise your fish or shellfish farm from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 65KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/forms/forms-list/"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form RW1 to register your fishery from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 184KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/aahm/files/Form-RW2.pdf"&gt;Download &lt;abbr title="Fish Health Inspectorate"&gt;FHI&lt;/abbr&gt; form RW2 to register your aquatic animal holding from the &lt;abbr title="Aquatic Animal Heatlh and Movements"&gt;AAHM&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF, 98KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8161</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T15:52:23+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T15:52:23+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/update-on-business-plan"/>
    <title>Update on Business Plan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s Business plan says that, following the consultation on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/high-speed-rail/"&gt;high speed rail&lt;/a&gt; which was held earlier this year, we would complete the analysis of consultation responses and announce our subsequent decisions to Parliament in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since taking up office in October I have been considering the issues, raised as part of the consultation and additionally have listened to the views of honourable members. In order to ensure that my decision is based on a careful consideration of all relevant factors, I have concluded that I should allow myself until early in 2012 to announce my decisions. I am therefore notifying the House that I will not be making a further statement on the subject of high speed rail this year, but I expect to announce my decisions in January.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
