<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-31T16:00:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/6982</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T16:00:47+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T16:00:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/strengthening-uk-relationships-in-asia-latin-america-and-africa-to-support-uk-prosperity-and-security"/>
    <title>Strengthening UK relationships in Asia, Latin America and Africa to support UK prosperity and security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political weight is shifting east and south. This means that fast-growing economies in Asia, Latin America and Africa are essential to our interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wants to increase Britain’s prosperity and security by improving links with the economic and political powers of tomorrow. The government is helping these markets grow so UK business can enjoy the mutual benefits of trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has shifted resources to boost the UK’s presence in the fastest-growing parts of the world. Ministers across government are planning their overseas travel strategically to meet influential politicians, business and community leaders in the fastest-growing parts of the world, and are hosting them when they visit the UK. On these visits building links, including trade and investment, are the main part of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emerging Powers Fund launched in autumn 2012, supporting projects to the value of £1.8m over three years to build links with the fastest-growing parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prosperity Fund was launched in April 2011 so that the UK can create the conditions for sustainable global growth and development. In its first year the Fund gave £19.4 million to 248 projects in 14 countries and regions to build links with the fastest-growing parts of the world. In 2012-2013, the Fund is allocating £19 million in 15 countries and regions. The Fund’s aim is achieving long-term policy changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment’s (&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;) new strategy, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/item/148300.html"&gt;Britain open for business&lt;/a&gt;, launched in May 2011, sets out plans to provide practical support to exporters and inward investors over five years, including winning high-value overseas opportunities for UK businesses. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/global-issues/prosperity/business-charter"&gt;Business Charter&lt;/a&gt; launched alongside the &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strategy, shows how the government supports UK business abroad, including in the fastest-growing parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Border Agency have expanded premium visa services, which are now offered in more than 25 countries including fast-growing economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countries with dedicated Prosperity Fund programmes are: Brazil, China, Colombia, India, Indonesia, Japan, Mexico, Russia, South Africa, South Korea and Turkey. We also operate regional funds in the Gulf, Latin America and South East Asia to widen our global reach, and work with the International Energy Agency and the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development through our delegation in Paris.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In every overseas post, &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; staff undertake press and communications work, which includes building relations with local media, and communicating the advantages of investing in and trading with the UK. A small London-based team works with the 1,700 London-based international media to ensure they understand the UK’s economic strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office"&gt;FCO&lt;/abbr&gt; operates websites in 53 local languages around the world, which attract 10 million visitors every year. These platforms are used to champion the UK’s reputation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/8885</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T15:44:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T15:44:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-british-interests-in-the-european-union-a-review-of-the-balance-of-competences"/>
    <title>Promoting British interests in the European Union: a review of the Balance of Competences</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those across Europe saying that they had a positive image of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; dropped from 52% in 2007 to 31% in 2011. It is important that the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; addresses the legitimate demands for its greater accountability, transparency, efficiency and probity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; continues to develop we need to be clear when it is best to take decisions at the national or local level, closer to the people affected, and in other cases when it is best to take action at the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; or global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is carrying out a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/pdf/publications/eu-balance-of-competences-review.pdf"&gt;review of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s competences&lt;/a&gt; (the power to act in particular areas conferred on it by the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Treaties).The review of the balance of competences will look at the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s competences, how they are used, and what that means for Britain and our national interest.
Government departments are reporting on areas of competence and their findings will be published during the course of the review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government departments are also consulting Parliament and its committees, business, the devolved administrations, and civil society to look in depth at how the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s competences work in particular areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our European partners and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; institutions will be contributing evidence to the review, and it will examine issues that are of interest across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, seeking to improve understanding and engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/12/pdfs/ukpga_20110012_en.pdf"&gt;European Union Act 2011&lt;/a&gt; lets the British public have its say on proposed transfers of powers and competences from the UK to the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. Any future proposal to transfer powers or competences from the UK to the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; will need to be approved by Act of Parliament and by the British people in a referendum before the UK can agree to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="preserving-the-citys-global-competitiveness"&gt;Preserving the City’s global competitiveness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is protecting the UK’s economic interests. First, by ensuring that the Eurozone crisis does not undermine efforts to reduce our deficit. Second, by making sure that the single market works fairly for the benefit of all 27 members, including the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;passed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/bills/cbill/2012-2013/0057/13057.pdf"&gt;European Union (Approval of Treaty Amendment Decision)&lt;/a&gt;, which ends the UK’s liability to the Eurozone crisis through the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helped &lt;a href="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pages/about/what/international/pdf/crd%20%28pl%29.pdf"&gt;introduce &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; legislation&lt;/a&gt; that provides a safer and stronger banking system in Europe, protecting the taxpayer and providing a basis for European countries to implement the global agreement on banking standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secured a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/finances/docs/committees/reform/20120912-com-2012-510_en.pdf"&gt;commitment&lt;/a&gt; that as Eurozone countries move towards designing a full banking union, which will not involve the UK, the integrity of the single market for all 27 members of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; will be preserved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;refused to allow a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201213/cmselect/cmfaff/writev/futunion/m22.htm"&gt;Fiscal Compact&lt;/a&gt; to be written into Treaty law without adequate safeguards for the single market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Competence” is about everything deriving from &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; law that affects what happens in the UK. That means examining all the areas where the Treaties give the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; competence to act, including the provisions in the Treaties giving the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; institutions the power to legislate, to adopt non-legislative acts, or to take any other sort of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means examining areas where the Treaties apply directly to the member states, without needing any further action by the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; institutions – for instance, the provisions on state aids and free movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s competences was launched on 12 July 2012 and will conclude by the end of 2014. A final decision will be taken closer to the time on how to draw together the analysis produced during the review, in the light of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s rapidly changing situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progress of the review, including evidence submitted to it, will be transparent. Our European partners and the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; institutions will also be invited to contribute evidence to the review, and it will examine issues that are of interest across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, seeking to improve understanding and engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review will be broken down into a number of individual reports covering specific areas of &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; competence. The review will be structured around four semesters: autumn 2012 – spring 2013, spring 2013 – autumn 2013, autumn 2013 – spring 2014, spring 2014 – autumn 2014. A ‘tranche’ of reports will be prepared and subsequently published each semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; is a single market of 500 million people, with a combined GDP of £11 trillion, in which British citizens can trade, travel and work freely. It is a key reason for Britain’s attractiveness as a global business hub and place to invest. It is the basis for cooperation with our closest partners on challenges that by their nature cross borders, such as climate change, international development, migration and transnational crime. And it amplifies the UK’s voice and helps advance our values of democracy, open markets and individual rights in the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London is one of the biggest and most dynamic urban areas in the world. According to the international ranking of city competitiveness produced by the Economist Intelligence Unit (2012), London is the second most attractive city in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_GlobalCompetitivenessReport_2012-13.pdf"&gt;World Economic Forum Global Competitiveness Report&lt;/a&gt; indicates that UK employment regulation is perceived as significantly better than in other major European economies, and on a par with the USA and Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Policy/6976</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-31T15:34:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-single-market-more-effective"/>
    <title>Making the Single Market More Effective</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="issue"&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/policy/from-6-to-27-members/index_en.htm"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Enlargement in 2004&lt;/a&gt;, UK business has seen exports to new member states rise by almost 100%, more than double the rate for the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; as a whole. However, The European Commission says that without reform, Europe could grow at just 1.5% a year for the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and job creation depend on healthy, well-connected markets, where competition and consumer access stimulate business and innovation. By reducing barriers to trade between the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; and other dynamic markets, the UK’s trade and exports will increase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s prospects are closely tied to the prosperity of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; as a whole. Higher growth and increased employment depends on action by all Member States and by the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; institutions. The UK therefore welcomes the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/120296.pdf"&gt;European Commission’s Annual Growth Survey&lt;/a&gt; which sets out ten priorities for faster growth and higher employment, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2011:217:0015:0017:EN:PDF"&gt;European Council’s commitment&lt;/a&gt; to “give priority to restoring sound budgets and fiscal sustainability, reducing unemployment through labour market reforms and making new efforts to enhance growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/letter-to-european-council-on-european-growth/"&gt;letter of 18 March 2011&lt;/a&gt;, co-signed by eight other &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; prime ministers, urged the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to improve the Single Market, focusing on sectors with the highest growth potential such as services, digital and energy; and called for European and global markets to improve trade, and support business and enterprise by removing regulatory burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is Europe’s largest and most advanced e-commerce market. The per capita, per annum spend on e-commerce in the UK is the highest anywhere in the world. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/newsroom/cf/pillar.cfm?pillar_id=43&amp;amp;pillar=Digital%20Single%20Market"&gt;Digital Agenda&lt;/a&gt; will update &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Single Market rules by boosting the music download business, establishing a single area for online payments, and further protecting &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; consumers in cyberspace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that a strong Single Market benefits all Member States and operating at its full capacity it offers growth and job creation. The European Commission adopted an &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/e-commerce/communication_2012_en.htm"&gt;e-Commerce Communication&lt;/a&gt; on 11 January 2012 with 16 actions aiming to double the volume of e-commerce in Europe by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234bn, went to the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. On 13 July 2010 the Council adopted a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:189:0001:0008:EN:PDF"&gt;Directive setting out new VAT rules for e-invoicing&lt;/a&gt;. EInvoices can be processed more quickly and cheaply as there are no postal delays or costs. The mass adoption of e-Invoicing within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; could generate savings of around € 240 billion over a six-year period. Member States are obliged to implement this into their national law by the beginning of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/october/tradoc_148303.pdf"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;-South Korea Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 1 July 2011, unlocking a huge range of opportunities for UK companies. South Korea is the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s fourth largest export market outside Europe. Based on current trading patterns, this agreement is expected to increase the UK’s Gross Domestic Product by £500m and result in £1.4 billion savings in duties annually for &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/d/junebudget_complete.pdf"&gt;June Budget 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/sr2010_completereport.pdf"&gt;October 2010 Spending Review&lt;/a&gt; announced action to support private sector growth and investment while reducing public debt by 2014-15. The government took this action to boost the UK’s long-term economic potential and help create new jobs. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_complete.pdf"&gt;2011 Budget&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt; set out in March 2011 how the UK would rebalance the economy and create a new model of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Single Market adds €600 billion a year to the European economy. Further liberalisation of services and the creation of a digital single market could add €800 billion more. This is the equivalent of making the average European household almost €4,200 better off each year. The European Policy Centre has found that development of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.epc.eu/dsm/6/Policy_recommendations.pdf"&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; by 2020 could result in a 4% increase in GDP in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Single Market gives UK businesses access to the world’s largest trading bloc with 500 million people and 21 million companies generating £11 trillion in economic activity. Since 1992, the UK’s bilateral trade with &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states has more than trebled. Trade with Europe accounts for roughly 3.5m jobs in the UK, around 11% of the workforce. In 2011, 47% of UK exports, worth £234bn, went to the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having initially started as six countries (Belgium, France, Germany, Italy, Luxembourg and the Netherlands), the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; is now the world’s largest international single market. Following the expansion of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; in May 2004 (the A8 countries - Czech Republic, Estonia, Hungary, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia, Slovenia -  as well as Cyprus and Malta) and in January 2007 (Bulgaria and Romania), the Single Market is now made up of 27 Member States. With almost 500 million people generating €12 trillion in economic activity, the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; is a bigger trading area than the US and Japan combined and accounts for over half of all UK trade in goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch on 1 January 1993, the Single Market has brought major benefits to UK business, consumers and employees. Member States trade twice as much with each other as they would do if the Single Market were not in place. The single market has also contributed increased growth of at least 1.85% and the creation of 2.75 million new jobs across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standards have been harmonised for hundreds of products, creating parity for manufacturers across the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. And ‘mutual recognition’ of goods by all Member States means that if a product is good enough to be sold in one country, it cannot be excluded from sale in another. The overall effect has been to turn the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; into a “domestic” market for both businesses and consumers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8726</id>
    <published>2012-10-30T18:25:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-30T18:25:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/driving-instructor-suspension-compensation-scheme"/>
    <title>Driving instructor suspension: compensation scheme</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is about introducing a compensation scheme in connection with The Driving Instruction (Suspension And Exemption Powers) Act 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act introduces a power for the Driving Standards Agency to suspend the approval of driving instructors in rare situations where they pose a danger to the public. This will usually be where the instructor is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;convicted of a serious violent or sexual offence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delivering tuition of a dangerously low level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the suspension power can be used, a compensation scheme must be in place for instructors whose approval to instruct is suspended but not subsequently removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals are about the system for making a claim for compensation and how compensation will be worked out. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8138</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:39:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:39:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/sale-of-trust-ports--4"/>
    <title>Sale of Trust Ports</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 3 August 2011, I announced the criteria that the government will consider particularly relevant to the appropriateness of the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales under the Ports Act 1991. This followed the consultation that I announced on 16 May 2011 and which closed on 27 June. I regret that it was not possible to announce this first by written ministerial statement to the House, but I did not wish to delay consideration of the application by Dover Harbour Board for a transfer scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that Dover Harbour Board has now considered the criteria, intends to proceed with its application for a transfer scheme under the Ports Act 1991, and proposes to submit a new set of documents containing a further elaboration of its scheme for decision by the Minister of State under the new criteria. If interested parties would find it useful and seek my department’s assistance, we would be happy to consider ways in which properly to facilitate discussions on all the options before the Dover Harbour Board submits its elaborated proposal. I should make clear that the decision minister would take no part in such discussions and would continue to perform her statutory functions in an objective, impartial manner whatever the outcome of any such discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following paragraphs set out the revised policy which the Secretary of State expects to follow when considering an application under the Ports Act 1991 for the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales. This covers the consideration of any proposal for a transfer scheme submitted under section 9 or 10 of the 1991 Act, together with the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions in respect of the subsequent sale of the port to which the scheme relates. The Secretary of State also intends to have particular regard to the policy considerations set out below before making a transfer scheme himself under section 12 of the 1991 Act or subsequently approving the sale of a port to which such a scheme relates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="essential-criteria"&gt;1. Essential criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation - the Secretary of State will not approve an application for the sale of a trust port under the 1991 Act unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an enduring and significant level of community participation in the port. Such participation could take a variety of forms, but must include the ability to influence the port’s long term development and may include the right to receive a share in the profits of the port, or the future increase in its value. It does not necessarily require a community role in the operation of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future investment in, and development of, the port - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an ownership model with the capability and access to capital to meet future investment needs and to exploit development potential of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair price - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to represent good value for money, having regard not only to Exchequer proceeds and market conditions, but also to other benefits including those to the community and the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair competition - the Secretary of State will not approve an application that is likely to deliver an ownership model which results in unsatisfactory levels of competition in the relevant sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="highly-desirable-criteria"&gt;2. Highly desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport networks- It is highly desirable for an application to be likely to deliver an ownership model which will cause the port to be operated so as to contribute to reliable, resilient and efficient transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sale process - It is highly desirable that the sale should be conducted in such a way as to give all bona fide prospective purchasers a fair and equitable opportunity to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desirable-criteria"&gt;3. Desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employee involvement - It is desirable for an application to be likely to deliver port employee participation in the ownership of the port, such as the right to receive equity shares or a share in its future success*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*This is without prejudice to the Ports Act 1991 section 5(3) requirement to have particular regard to the desirability of encouraging the disposal of the whole or a substantial part of the equity share capital of the successor company to managers or other persons employed by the port company etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20110516"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110516i/"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports in England and Wales - Consultation on revised criteria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8171</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:25:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:25:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--36"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the second Transport Council of the Polish Presidency in Brussels on 12 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council reached political agreement on a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council establishing a single European railway area (Recast). At its first reading of the proposal on 16 November the European Parliament made amendments which differed significantly from the council’s general approach adopted at the June Transport Council. However, the political agreement text only incorporates those amendments that do not alter the general approach, and are acceptable to the UK. The commission hopes a 2nd reading deal can be struck with the European Parliament under the Danish presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council agreed a partial general approach on a draft regulation amending regulation 3821/85 on recording equipment in road transport. This proposal would amend the specification for tachographs, which measure hours spent at the wheel by commercial lorry and bus drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council also agreed a general approach on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council amending Directive 2008/106/EC of the European Parliament and of the council on the minimum level of training of seafarers to bring the extant directive into line with the latest International Maritime Organization rules; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the accelerated phasing-in of double-hull or equivalent design requirements for single-hull oil tankers (Recast). The amendments reflect changes to the international regime for tankers adopted at the International Maritime Organization between 2002 and 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The council noted a progress report on a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on union guidelines for the development of the Trans-European Transport Network. This item generated substantial discussion. I intervened to acknowledge the importance of good cross-border infrastructure for the single market, but expressed concern about binding obligations proposed and the financial and administrative burdens they would place on member states at a time when fiscal constraints are substantial and also stressed the need for member states’ to retain their responsibility for planning decisions, processes and implementation. On the proposed increase to the TEN-T budget I said budgetary restraint must be the priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the commission presented its new proposals on a ‘better airport package’ which cover a recast of the slot allocation regulation, and revisions to the current directives on ground handling and noise which are intended to address issues of capacity, growth, environmental concerns and competitiveness. The proposals on ground handling and noise have been recast as (directly applicable) regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission reported on the European aviation safety management system and air cargo security action plan. I intervened in strong support of the European aviation safety management system and to request that the commission report back on progress at a future transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission, at the request of Finland, reported on the current state of play with regards to the aviation EU emissions trading system. There had been three main developments since the June Transport Council: the US House of Representatives had approved a Bill that would prohibit US airlines from complying with &lt;abbr title="emissions trading system"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;; there had been political messages against &lt;abbr title="emissions trading system"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt; emerging from the International Civil Aviation Organization council in November; and President Obama had specifically raised the issue at the EU/US summit on 28 November, noting the need to avoid confrontation. The commission’s assessment was that while international opposition was strong, so was the EU response. The commission acknowledged there still could be a challenge in &lt;abbr title="International Civil Aviation Organization"&gt;ICAO&lt;/abbr&gt; under the Chicago Convention, and that it was important to understand what forms retaliatory action could take. Following a legal challenge from the US Air Transport Association and 3 US airlines the European Court of Justice will deliver its judgement on the case on 21 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antonio Tajani, commissioner responsible for industry and entrepreneurship, updated ministers on recent developments within the Galileo programme and indicated that since the successful launch of the first two satellites in October the system was now up and running with real momentum behind it. The commission also presented their proposed regulation on Galileo governance and exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the council, I met ministers from Finland, and Ireland, the German State Secretary, and the Northern Irish Transport Minister to discuss items on the Transport Council agenda, in particular TEN-T. In a separate discussion after Transport Council, I exchanged views on TEN-T and better regulation with the Siim Kallas, the Transport Commissioner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK did not participate in the vote on one item on the A point list, namely Article 81 based council decision authorising the EU to accede to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention relating to the carriage of passengers and their luggage by sea. The UK has however subsequently notified its intention to opt-in to the council decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish delegation presented the work programme of their forthcoming presidency of the EU. The incoming Danish presidency’s overarching aim in the transport sector will be ‘green growth’ and they will take forward work on current Council dossiers. For example, they will be seeking to reach a 2nd reading agreement with the European Parliament on the recast of the first railway package. They will also commence work on proposals included in the recently published commission work programme such as the airport package and the proposals on driving licences and the satellite navigation programmes as well as on an expected proposal on enforcement of the maritime labour convention. Their main priorities are the TEN-T guidelines and the airport package, especially ground handling and noise reduction proposals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8721</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:04:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:04:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-draft-ports-national-policy-statement-and-associated-documents"/>
    <title>The draft ports national policy statement and associated documents</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport published this consultation document on 9 November 2009 in order to invite views on the draft National Policy Statement for ports and the accompanying documents listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation document explained the context of the &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and set out the key policies. The consultation period for the draft National Policy Statement closed on 15 February 2010. The responses are now being carefully considered and the department will publish a summary of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; has been under parliamentary scrutiny and the Transport Select Committee published a report to the House in March (HC 217).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will lay a response before Parliament in due course, as required by s.9(5) Planning Act 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decisions"&gt;Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24 October 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/national-policy-statement-for-ports/"&gt;National Policy Statement for Ports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="consultation-documents"&gt;Consultation documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110131091024/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/consultation.pdf"&gt;Developing a Ports National Policy Statement consultation document (PDF - 510 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173318/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/consultation-welsh.pdf"&gt;Developing a Ports National Policy Statement consultation document - Welsh language (PDF - 142 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/cardiff-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Event Cardiff 7/12/09 (PDF - 41 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/leeds-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Event Leeds 10/12/09 (PDF - 40 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/london-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; event London 14/1/10 (PDF - 58 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/npsports.pdf"&gt;Draft National Policy Statement for Ports (PDF - 871 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp1.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 1 Scoping Report (PDF - 565 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp2.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 2 - AoS Phase 1 Assessment (PDF - 342 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp-3.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 3 - AoS Phase 2 Assessment (PDF - 397 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp4.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 4 - AoS Phase 3 Assessment (PDF - 331 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp5.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 5 - AoS Phase 4 Assessment (PDF - 491 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/appropriateassessment.pdf"&gt;Appropriate Assessment (PDF - 2048 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8779</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-transposition-of-directive-2008-57ec-on-the-interoperability-of-the-rail-system"/>
    <title>The transposition of Directive 2008/57EC on the interoperability of the rail system</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents set out the government’s final proposals for implementing Directive 2008/57RC on the interoperability of the rail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents seek stakeholder’s views on how we implement the requirements of the Directive including proposed draft Regulations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:191:0001:0045:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G1 - EC Directive 2008-57-EC (Interoperability Recast)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:108:0004:0019:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G2 - EC Regulation 352-2009 (CSM Risk Assessment)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:273:0012:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G3 - EC Directive 2009-131 (Interoperability Annex VII)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:341:0001:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G4 - EC Decision 965-20095 (Amenments to Annex V11)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:326:0011:0024:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G5- EC Decision 1158-2010 (CSM Safety Certificate)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:327:0013:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G6 - EU Decision 1169-2010 (CSM Safety Authorisation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:043:0033:0054:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G7 - EU Decision 107-2011 (Common Specification for NVR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0008:0009:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G8 - EC Regulation 201-2011 (Declaration of Conformity)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0021:0028:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G9 - EU Directive 18-2011 (Amending Annexes 11,V &amp;amp; V1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:063:0022:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G10 - EC Decision 155-2011(Reference Document)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:256:FULL:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G11 - EC Decision 633-2011 (Specification for infrastructure register)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:095:0001:0029:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex H - EC recommendation 217-2011 Authorisation for placing into srervice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8121</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:24:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:24:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--35"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the second Transport Council of the Hungarian Presidency in Luxembourg on 16 June 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council reached a general approach on a directive which recasts the 2001 first rail package. The 2001 legislation set the initial framework for a single European rail market, setting out principles for charging and access to the network. The present draft directive modifies the three 2001 directives. The presidency tabled a compromise text which was slightly amended at the council. The presidency then concluded that there was a qualified majority for a general approach. The text of the general approach is acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council also reached a general approach on the draft regulation amending regulation 1406/2002, which established the European Maritime Safety Agency. This amending regulation modifies and extends the tasks of the agency to bring them in line with recent international and EU developments in the maritime safety field. I set out the UK’s opposition to any staff or administrative cost increases for the agency, and was able to accept revised wording on agency resources, which addressed our concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council debated the European Commission’s recent white paper, ‘Roadmap to a single European transport area - towards a competitive and resource efficient transport system’, which was issued in March. The council debate centred on a number of questions put by the presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The white paper aims to increase the sustainability and competitiveness of the sector while moving towards a fully integrated transport network. In doing so, the commission aims to cut carbon emissions from transport by 60% by 2050 (compared to 1990 levels). Member states broadly agreed that the transport sector has to make an adequate contribution to the achievement of the medium and long-term climate change targets. I explained that, while supporting the broad thrust of the ten goals in the white paper, the UK has some concerns on the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not in favour of having targets for their own sake, and do not think that it is practical or desirable to have a multiplicity of goals and targets. Furthermore, we do not support sector specific targets, which would constrain our progress on carbon reduction within the economy as a whole. Wherever targets are set, we believe that they must be realistic and supported by robust evidence and cost impact analysis. I also joined others in proposing that we work internationally to negotiate similar commitments with all of the global partners, in the framework of international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stressed that the EU should focus on actions that need to be undertaken at EU level, and where there was no such case, it should be left to Member States and local authorities to act. I also welcomed, with support from some other ministers, the commission’s commitment to undertake thorough impact assessments for any actions. I urged the commission to consider the importance of reducing the overall burden of regulation, to help our businesses and the budgetary constraints that we all face, as it takes forward the white paper proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Council conclusions were adopted on EU inland waterway transport, inviting the commission to launch a project to continue support for an existing inland waterway programme, which is designed to encourage modal shift of freight from road to inland waterways, and to bring forward proposals for a follow-on programme. The conclusions are acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted a decision on the signing and conclusion of an agreement with the intergovernmental organisation for International Carriage by Rail on the EU accession to the convention concerning international carriage by rail of 9 May 1980, as amended by the Vilnius Protocol of 3 June 1999. The decision is acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted two decisions in the area of aviation external relations, both of which were acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first decision authorised the commission to open negotiations with Moldova on a comprehensive air transport agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was a decision on the signature of an air transport agreement between the EU and Brazil. Ministers pre-signed the agreement in the margins of the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among any other business items, the commission reported on air cargo security work which has been carried out in pursuit of the action plan endorsed by ministers at the December 2010 justice and home affairs and transport councils. They were disappointed that a proposal to strengthen EU inbound air cargo security had been narrowly defeated in the June Regulatory Committee, and called on ministers from member states which voted against or abstained to rethink their position. I joined Germany in expressing strong support for the commission, and called for work to continue on the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under any other business, the commission reported on work to deal with the impact of volcanic ash on the EU aviation sector and on recent developments in implementing the Single European Sky. On volcanic ash, I underlined the importance of developing the existing methodology and modelling, and increasing pressure on equipment manufacturers for engine tolerance levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the margins of the council, I met ministers from France, Germany, Ireland and the Netherlands to discuss the work on volcanic ash. In a separate discussion, I exchanged views on better regulation with the Netherlands minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK abstained on one item on the A point list, namely the adoption of a council decision on the conclusion of a memorandum of cooperation between the EU and the International Civil Aviation Organisation. This reflects our general need to be vigilant regarding the balance between member states’ and EU competence in United Nation bodies and other international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8762</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/amending-regulation-8-of-the-local-authorities-traffic-orders-exemptions-for-disabled-persons-england-regulations-2000"/>
    <title>Amending Regulation 8 of the Local Authorities' Traffic Orders (Exemptions for Disabled Persons) (England) Regulations 2000</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on amending one aspect of the legislation which covers the Blue Badge parking concessions. The amendment seeks to put beyond doubt the fact that local authorities are not required to allow Blue Badge holders to park in loading bays or on yellow lines when there is a ban on loading or unloading in force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
