<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-01T22:00:21+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10341</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T22:00:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T22:00:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/secure-stations-scheme-guidelines"/>
    <title>Secure Stations Scheme guidelines</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction-to-the-secure-stations-scheme"&gt;Introduction to the Secure Stations Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secure Stations Scheme represents a national standard for passenger safety and security on Britain’s railway stations. Launched in 1998, the scheme was independently reviewed in 2003 and subsequently revised in order to simplify some procedures and encourage more operators to take part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These resource materials have been prepared to assist operators in making improvements to stations for the security of staff and passengers. They contain information which may be useful in improving the physical environment and management of any station - from a busy, major, urban interchange to one in a small, quiet, rural community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For stations that fall short of the scheme’s accreditation standard there is a new category of ‘working towards accreditation’. This category recognises the efforts that are being made by some operators to get such stations to meet the standard, and provides them with the guidance and support to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme guidance pack includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-1-overview-of-the-secure-stations-scheme"&gt;Guideline 1 overview of the Secure Stations Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overview of the scheme, including an explanation of the criteria for accreditation, costs and benefits to the operator, and the assessment process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-2-design-and-crime"&gt;Guideline 2 design and crime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines for design and management to reduce opportunities for crime and provide reassurance for passengers, including specifically those design and management features that will be assessed for accreditation under the scheme;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-3-managing-a-secure-station"&gt;Guideline 3 managing a secure station&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A design and management audit by which operators can make their own early assessment of whether they comply with the design and management requirements of the scheme, or where there is need for improvement, and which will require endorsement by the British Transport Police Crime Reduction Officer (CRO);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-4-recording-and-monitoring-of-crimes-and-other-incidents"&gt;Guideline 4 recording and monitoring of crimes and other incidents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedure for obtaining recorded crime data from the British Transport Police. For accreditation under the scheme, operators will need to supply crime data expressed in the context of passenger throughput figures;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-5-passenger-perceptions"&gt;Guideline 5 passenger perceptions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The procedure for obtaining passenger views about the station. This has been revised, subsequent to the review, to enable operators to make greater use of the results of the National Passenger Survey (NPS). The NPS provides independent, reliable and consistent data that enables national comparisons to be made, and its use will reduce costs for operators;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-6-the-whole-journey-involving-other-organisations"&gt;Guideline 6 the whole journey: involving other organisations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines for working in partnership with other agencies, including other public transport operators, local authorities, the police and Crime and Disorder Reduction Partnerships, to address issues relating to the security of passengers across the whole journey;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-7-working-towards-accreditation"&gt;Guideline 7 working towards accreditation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A procedure for working towards accreditation by which operators who manage stations that do not meet the accreditation standard can get support and recognition for their efforts to make the necessary improvements to them;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="guideline-8-tackling-crime-at-stations-in-high-crime-and-socially-excluded-areas-perceptions"&gt;Guideline 8 tackling crime at stations in high crime and socially excluded areas perceptions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines for tackling crime at stations in high crime and socially excluded areas to see what actions have been undertaken at similar stations to reduce crime and improve personal security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is a record sheet to record your passenger survey results and crime data, and an application form to be signed off by you, your local British Transport Police Crime Reduction Officer and the British Transport Police Independent Accreditor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/secure-station-scheme-accredited-stations"&gt;Secure Stations scheme list of accredited stations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/secure-station-scheme-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;Secure Station scheme frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/public-transport/crime#sss"&gt;Secure Station scheme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10289</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T21:20:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T21:20:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/first-capital-connect"/>
    <title>First Capital Connect</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that the public register of franchise agreements is updated on a quarterly basis and that the data held on the website may not be necessarily be the most current information held by the department. If you cannot find the information that you need, please contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications?tag=public-register-of-franchise-agreements"&gt;Public Register of Franchise Agreements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10345</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T21:07:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T21:07:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/shrewsbury-kingsland-bridge-toll-review--3"/>
    <title>Shrewsbury (Kingsland) bridge toll review</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Order allows the Shrewsbury &amp;amp; (Kingsland) bridge company to raise toll charges for cars and all other vehicles - except for motorcycles, from 10p to 20p. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="shrewsbury-kingsland-bridge-decision-letter"&gt;Shrewsbury (Kingsland) bridge decision letter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tc-20120123/"&gt;Shrewsbury (Kingsland) bridge decision letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This publication is available in hard-copy from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/shrewsbury-kingsland-bridge-toll-review/"&gt;The Stationery Office.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10413</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:57:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:57:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/traffic-signs-manual"/>
    <title>Traffic signs manual</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traffic signs manual gives guidance on the use of traffic signs and road markings prescribed by the Traffic Signs Regulations and covers England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland. Revised editions of the manual will be published here as they are released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapters may be purchased in hard copy from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tso.co.uk/bookshop"&gt;The Stationery Office&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-introduction-isbn-9780115505591"&gt;Chapter 1 introduction (ISBN 9780115505591)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduction and an outline of the historical, functional and design aspects of signs. The chapter includes sections dealing with the positioning and mounting of signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-in-draft-informatory-signs"&gt;Chapter 2 (in draft) informatory signs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2 is currently a work in progress. It will contain advice on the design and use of directional signs, and also other informatory signs such as home zone signs. Due to the amount of work required to complete chapter 2, it is intended that interim advice on individual topics will be made available as and when completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current advice on the design and use of directional informatory signs is published in Local Transport Note (LTN) 1/94. Also available is the latest list of primary destinations in England, which supersedes the information in LTN 1/94, and guidance on the calculation of x-heights which is site-specific and more accurate than the table in LTN 1/94.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-regulatory-signs-isbn-9780115529252"&gt;Chapter 3 regulatory signs (ISBN 9780115529252)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidelines on the correct use of regulatory signs prescribed by the traffic signs regulations. These include prohibited turns, waiting and loading restrictions, bus and cycle lanes etc. There is also a comprehensive section dealing with the signing of speed limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-warning-signs-isbn-9780115524110"&gt;Chapter 4 warning signs (ISBN 9780115524110)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning signs are used to alert drivers to potential danger ahead. They indicate a need for special caution by road users and may require a reduction in speed or some other manoeuvre. This reprinted edition includes four minor amendments and addition of Appendix A, note 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-road-markings-isbn-9780115524790"&gt;Chapter 5 road markings (ISBN 9780115524790)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road markings serve a very important function in conveying to road users information and requirements which might not be possible using upright signs. They have the advantage that they can often be seen when a verge-mounted sign is obscured, and, unlike such signs, they can provide a continuing message. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-the-design-of-traffic-signs-isbn-9780115524806"&gt;Chapter 7 the design of traffic signs (ISBN 9780115524806)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How sign faces are designed. This chapter does not include the various methods by which signs are constructed and mounted. It supersedes Local Transport Note ‘2/94 directional informatory signs interim design notes’, which was withdrawn in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-part-1-road-works-and-temporary-situations---design-isbn-9780115530517"&gt;Chapter 8 (part 1) road works and temporary situations - design (ISBN 9780115530517)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance for the design of temporary traffic management arrangements which should be implemented to facilitate maintenance activities or in response to temporary situations. For enquiries and comments regarding this chapter, please email &lt;a href="mailto:chapter8@highways.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;chapter8@highways.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-part-2-road-works-and-temporary-situations---operations-isbn-9780115530524"&gt;Chapter 8 (part 2) road works and temporary situations - operations (ISBN 9780115530524)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance for planning, managing, and participating in operations to implement, maintain and remove temporary traffic management arrangements. For enquiries and comments regarding this chapter, please email &lt;a href="mailto:chapter8@highways.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;chapter8@highways.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/local-transport-notes"&gt;Local transport notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rsta-uk.org/publications.htm"&gt;RSDA/CSS code of practice for signing at surface dressing sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/tal"&gt;Traffic advisory leaflets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/tpm/"&gt;Traffic and parking management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/trafficsignsimages/"&gt;Traffic signs image database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/traffic-sign-working-drawings"&gt;Working drawings for traffic signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10337</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:44:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:44:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/sale-of-trust-ports-criteria-statement"/>
    <title>Sale of trust ports criteria statement</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document sets out the revised policy which the Secretary of State expects to follow when considering an application under the Ports Act 1991 for the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales. This covers the consideration of any proposal for a transfer scheme submitted under section 9 or 10 of the 1991 Act, together with the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions in respect of the subsequent sale of the port to which the scheme relates. The Secretary of State also intends to have particular regard to the policy considerations set out below before making a transfer scheme himself under section 12 of the 1991 Act or subsequently approving the sale of a port to which such a scheme relates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10438</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:31:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:31:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-twitter-policy"/>
    <title>Department for Transport Twitter policy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-twitter-policy"&gt;DfT Twitter policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The departments twitter channel (&lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/transportgovuk"&gt;@transportgovuk&lt;/a&gt;) is managed by the Digital Engagement Team, on behalf of colleagues across the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not use automation tools e.g. &lt;abbr title="Really Simple Syndication"&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feeds to generate tweets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow us, you can expect between two to ten tweets a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweets will include alerts about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;announcements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;press releases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new content published on our website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new content uploaded to other digital channels e.g. YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marketing campaign messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invitations to consult&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information from our Ministerial team about what they’re doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;occasional live coverage of events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="following"&gt;Following&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow us on Twitter we may follow you back. Being followed by us does not imply endorsement of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="availability"&gt;Availability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will update and monitor our Twitter account during office hours, Monday to Friday. Twitter may occasionally be unavailable and we accept no responsibility for lack of service due to Twitter downtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="replies-and-direct-messages"&gt;@Replies and Direct Messages&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome feedback, ideas and engagement from all our followers, and endeavour to join the conversation where possible. However, we are not able to reply individually to all the messages we receive via Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Engagement Team read all @replies and Direct Messages and ensures that any emerging themes or helpful suggestions are passed to the relevant colleagues in the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot engage on issues of party politics or answer questions which break the rules of our general comments policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual ways of contacting us for official correspondence are detailed in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/about/contact"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; section of our website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="driving-standards-agency-dsa-twitter-policy"&gt;Driving Standards Agency (DSA) twitter policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSA’s Twitter feed &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/dsagovuk"&gt;@dsagovuk&lt;/a&gt; will be updated with the latest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;news stories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;press releases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invitations to consult&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new content uploaded to our web channels and YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="why-use-twitter-to-follow-dsa"&gt;Why use Twitter to follow DSA?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of benefits of choosing to follow DSA on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you’ll be one of the first to find out about latest DSA news&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can follow other government organisations all in one place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can access Twitter on your mobile/ smart phone/ tablet, so even if you’re not at your computer you can stay up to date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can subscribe to DSA’s Twitter &lt;abbr title="Really Simple Syndication"&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed - you can use this to have our latest messages appear in your web browser, email application or even onto your desktop if you have installed an &lt;abbr title="Really Simple Syndication"&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; reader; you won’t even need to remember to check for new messages!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you have your own website you can include your own latest ‘tweets’ on your homepage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can ‘retweet’ messages of the people you’re following so your followers can read them too&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4 id="retweeting-by-dsa"&gt;Retweeting by DSA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, DSA’s twitter accounts receive requests from followers to retweet their messages. Being retweeted by DSA does not imply endorsement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSA will retweet if the request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is to publicise an event or activity the follower is undertaking for charity purposes (such as Sport Relief, Children in Need or a local charity)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is to publicise a message of congratulation on a follower’s pupil (or family member if the follower isn’t an ADI) successfully passing their driving test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;DSA may also retweet (without being requested) those tweets whose messages are considered relevant to DSA’s mission of safe driving or riding for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSA will not retweet if the request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;asks for endorsement of an activity for commercial gain (such as an event or meeting which charges an entry fee over £5.00)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is considered to cause potential embarrassment to DSA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="availability-1"&gt;Availability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will update and monitor our Twitter account during office hours, Monday to Friday. Twitter may occasionally be unavailable and we accept no responsibility for lack of service due to Twitter downtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="need-help"&gt;Need help?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry if you’re new to Twitter! If you need help with getting started and want to get a feel for the basics go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://help.twitter.com"&gt;help.twitter.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12103</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:30:56+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:30:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a57-m1-to-todwick-crossroads-inspectors-report"/>
    <title>A57 - M1 to Todwick crossroads inspectors report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purposes of ‘the scheme’ are to promote and improve safety for all road users by reducing the number of fatal and serious injury accidents within the section of the A57. Reduce levels of delay and congestion, particularly at the A57/B6463 Todwick crossroads junction. Provide support to economic regeneration, in particular the Dinnington regeneration area. Improve access to employment in the area. Provide environmental improvements in terms of reduced carbon emissions, enhanced accessibility and improved facilities for pedestrians, cyclists and equestrians&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-authority-orders-decision-letter"&gt;Local authority orders decision letter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/publications/lao-20120229/"&gt;Local authority orders decision letter for the A57 - M1 to Todwick crossroads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10042</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:25:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:25:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/aviation-industry-notifications"/>
    <title>Aviation industry notifications</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="information-for-the-aviation-industry"&gt;Information for the aviation industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document below is a list of Aviation industry notifications issued by the Department for Transport and Surefax. If you have not received a listed Surefax please ensure that you fall within the specified audience for receipt before contacting your relevant Department for Transport divisional contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the onus remains upon the nominated recipient to ensure that they keep the Department for Transport notified of any change in circumstances relating to contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12104</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:22:35+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:22:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/transport-for-greater-manchester-light-rapid-transit-system"/>
    <title>Transport for Greater Manchester: light rapid transit system</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order will give transport for Greater Manchester statutory authority for the continuation, maintenance and operation of a 130 metre segregated tramway at Mumps in Oldham and make other provisions on the operation of the Manchester metrolink system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/10082</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T20:22:22+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T20:22:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/drug-driving-expert-panel-terms-of-reference-and-membership"/>
    <title>Drug driving expert panel terms of reference and membership</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following downloads contain details of the terms of reference and membership for a new drug driving expert panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120509a/"&gt;Drug driving press release, 9 May 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/drug-driving-faqs/%20"&gt;FAQs - Drug driving offence and drug screening devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
