<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-25T23:01:25+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuide/8892</id>
    <published>2012-09-14T15:24:52+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T23:01:25+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/investing-in-aquaculture"/>
    <title>European Fisheries Fund: investing in aquaculture</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to invest in an aquaculture project (the farming of aquatic organisms such as fish, crustaceans, molluscs and aquatic plants), you may be eligible for a grant from the European Fisheries Fund (&lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-can-apply"&gt;Who can apply?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, as the applicant, must sign the application form, even if you had help completing it as you will be responsible for making sure that all of the terms and conditions of the grant are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grants can only be awarded to micro, small or medium-sized enterprises in the private sector or those that have fewer than 750 employees and a turnover of less than €200 million (according to latest exchange rates). You can establish the size of your business by using the following table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="table-showing-the-criteria-for-establishing-the-size-of-your-business"&gt;Table showing the criteria for establishing the size of your business&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th width="25%"&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width="25%"&gt;Number of employees&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width="25%"&gt;Turnover&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width="25%"&gt;Balance sheet total&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Medium&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 250&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Less than or equal to €50 million&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Less than or equal to €43 million&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Small&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Less than or equal to €10 million&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Less than or equal to €10 million &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Micro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Less than or equal to €2 million&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Less than or equal to €2 million&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must respect the number of employees threshold when you are determining the size of your enterprise but you may choose to meet either the turnover or balance sheet total maximum. You could exceed one of them without losing your status.
Further information is available in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sme/files/sme_definition/sme_user_guide_en.pdf"&gt;‘The new SME definition: User guide and model declaration’ on the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF 1.2MB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-things-may-be-eligible-for-a-grant"&gt;What things may be eligible for a grant?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; may support investments in constructing, extending, equipping or modernising production installations, especially when:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving working conditions, hygiene, human or aninal health and product quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing negative impact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enhancing positive effects on the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All investments must contribute to one or more of the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diversifying towards new species (those that have low or non-existent production in England) and production of species with good market prospects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;putting into practice methods that substantially reduce negative impact or enhance positive effects on the environment when compared with normal practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting traditional activities important for preserving and developing the economic and social structure and the environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting the purchase of equipment that protect aquaculture farms from wild predators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving the working and safety conditions of aquaculture workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/forms/eff/ax2-pia001_guidance.pdf"&gt;Read more about eligible and not eligible projects in guidance notes on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF 146 KB)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-much-grant-will-i-get"&gt;How much grant will I get?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; programme is competitive, and only projects that most effectively meet its aims will be awarded a grant. You will receive a percentage of the total eligible cost of your project if you are successful. The minimum grant is £400 and the maximum is £250,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="table-showing-the-maximum-level-of-grant-available-to-different-types-of-project"&gt;Table showing the maximum level of grant available to different types of project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th width="60%"&gt;Project type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width="40%"&gt; Maximum level of grant available as a percentage of eligible costs&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Small, micro and medium-sized enterprises and projects which deliver very high environmental contributions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Other applicants and projects&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2 id="how-to-apply-for-funding"&gt;How to apply for funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should submit the Axis 2 application form to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_axis2.htm"&gt;Find out more about Axis 2 and download the application form from the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your application must include a detailed business case that shows that your project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has quantified outputs and clear and attainable targets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will provide an additional and sustainable benefit to the fishing industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has a justified need for grant will provide good value for money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should also include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a full description of your project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information on the economic viability of investments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information on any needed consents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the benefits of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financial, environmental and other benefits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a cost-benefit analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an analysis of quotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an environmental impact assessment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the results you expect from the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will publicise the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will monitor the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you will manage risks to delivery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information about your business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how your project will affect the local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For advice on applying to the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;, you should contact the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-in-the-offer-letter"&gt;What is in the offer letter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offer letter sets out details of the conditions of the grant and any agreed performance targets and outputs for the project. You must comply with the conditions along with details of eligible expenditure to allow us to pay your grant claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#more-like-this"&gt;More information from European Fisheries Fund  overview guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-to-claim-funding-from-the-eff"&gt;How to claim funding from the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are eligible for funding under the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt;, you can claim your grant by submitting a claim form by the date specified in your offer letter to the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; at the following address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Relations Team&lt;br&gt;
Marine Management Organisation&lt;br&gt;
Lancaster House&lt;br&gt;
Hampshire Court&lt;br&gt;
Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;br&gt;
NE4 7YH&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_success.htm"&gt;Download the &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; claim form and guidance from the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should normally submit a single full and final claim by the date specified in your offer letter. You may be allowed to submit one or more interim claims but the final claim must still be submitted by the date specified in the offer letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; aims to pay the grant within 8 weeks once all the necessary information to consider your claim is received. The &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; accept no liability in respect of loss attributable to any delay in the payment of claims or to any suspension, reduction or cancellation of grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The payment will be made electronically into your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#more-like-this"&gt;More information on completing the claim form, supporting documentation, changing your project and how to manage your project from European Fisheries Fund overview guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For advice, you can call the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team on 0191 376 2505 or email them at &lt;a href="mailto:eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk"&gt;eff.projects@marinemanagement.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="mmo-business-relations-team"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; Business Relations Team&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0191 376 2694 or 0191 376 2676&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/eff_eff_axis2.htm"&gt;Axis 2 information and application forms on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marinemanagement.org.uk/fisheries/funding/forms/eff/conditions.pdf"&gt;Read the general conditions of &lt;abbr title="European Fisheries Fund"&gt;EFF&lt;/abbr&gt; grant for projects in England on the &lt;abbr title="Marine Management Organisation"&gt;MMO&lt;/abbr&gt; website (PDF 93KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:DetailedGuide/8873</id>
    <published>2012-09-10T15:08:37+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T21:53:02+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/the-single-payment-scheme"/>
    <title>The Single Payment Scheme</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Single Payment Scheme (&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;) - part of the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) - is the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s main agricultural subsidy scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a farmer in England who meets the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; rules, you can apply to the Rural Payments Agency (&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;) for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments. These payments are not linked to production, giving you flexibility in how you run your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide gives an overview of the scheme and explains how to apply for payment. It covers the Cross Compliance requirements, including farmers’ obligations to keep land in good agricultural and environmental condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide also explains how deductions from &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments - known as ‘modulation’ - help fund rural development schemes for farmers, such as England’s Environmental Stewardship schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-sps"&gt;What is the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; is the main agricultural subsidy scheme in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme requires you to adhere to Cross Compliance requirements in order to receive the payments in full. These requirements reflect existing English and European law, or basic good agricultural practice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In England, the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; is run by the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;, while the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt;) takes the lead on &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; policy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each part of the UK has different &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; arrangements. This guide covers England only. For information about the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; in Scotland, Wales or Northern Ireland, you should contact the relevant agriculture department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-does-the-sps-work"&gt;How does the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be eligible for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments, you must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be a farmer, as defined by the European Union&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have eligible land at your disposal on the prescribed date in May of the scheme year - this land must be eligible for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; for the entire calendar year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hold payment entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;meet the minimum claim size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must also meet the cross compliance rules. You can browse the index to &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Cross Compliance guidance on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/293a8949ec0ba26d80256f65003bc4f7/21c99ddaeb3232a9802573aa004efa3e!OpenDocument"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also meet the application deadlines set each year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eligible-land"&gt;Eligible land&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligible land is defined as any area of your holding taken up by arable land and permanent pasture, except for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;forested areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;areas used for non-agricultural activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exceptions do apply to non-agricultural activities which are divided into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A - permitted without restriction, eg walking, bird watching, fishing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B - permitted up to a 28 day limit, eg shooting, car boot sales, festivals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C - inconsistent with the land being considered as remaining in agricultural use, eg golf course, airstrip, game rearing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="applications-and-key-dates-for-the-sps"&gt;Applications and key dates for the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments in England are made through the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;. The deadline for receipt of applications is usually the 15 May of the scheme year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;’s payment window for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments runs from 1 December of the scheme year, to the following 30 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read frequently asked questions on &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; registration on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/293a8949ec0ba26d80256f65003bc4f7/158501c0ecb81268802572c600349816!OpenDocument"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="key-2013-dates"&gt;Key 2013 dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 April - last date for &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; to receive your request to transfer entitlements for it to take effect by 15 May 2013, and in time for the 2013 scheme year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;15 May - the date on which you must have land at your disposal to be eligible for the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;. It is also the final date for receipt of applications without penalty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;31 May - last date for submitting any amendments arising from &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s response to your &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; 2013 application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9 June - any &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; 2013 applications and/or written amendments received by &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; after this date will be rejected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="sps-onlinehttpswwwgovuksingle-payment-scheme-online---how-to-apply-electronically"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/single-payment-scheme-online"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online&lt;/a&gt; - how to apply electronically&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online is the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s free web-based service which allows you to submit your &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; application electronically. You can also track the progress of your claim and view claim or entitlements statements issued to you for the 2009 scheme year onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not yet registered for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online, you will need a Personal Identification Number (PIN). You should have received this in late February/early March 2012. If you have not previously applied electronically and need a pin, you should call the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; Customer Service Centre on Tel 0845 603 7777.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 2012 scheme year over 37,000 applications were submitted using the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online Make a Claim service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online also enables you to track claims and view statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-make-a-claim"&gt;How to make a claim&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can submit your &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; application electronically during each scheme year application period. You can access and amend your &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; data, check your application for common errors and correct them before you submit. It will then provide you with an instant on-screen acknowledgement that the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; has received your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the scheme year application period ends you can still access the make a claim service to view claims previously submitted via &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online or a farm software package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-track-claims"&gt;How to track claims&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This service allows you to see the status of &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; applications you have submitted from the 2009 scheme year onwards. With track claims you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check the progress of your claim at any time without needing to contact the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;track the progress of your claim from start to finish regardless of whether you submitted the application electronically (using &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online or a farm software package) or on the paper SP5 form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;find out if you need to submit more information to progress your claim and reply to the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; electronically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-to-view-statements"&gt;How to view statements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This service allows you to view claim and entitlements statements issued from the 2009 scheme year onwards. With view statements you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;view online a PDF version of all claim and entitlements statements that the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; have sent to you for the 2009 scheme year onwards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;save the PDF to another application or print it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have used &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online or a farm software package to apply for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, you will not receive paper applications forms or claim and entitlements statements from &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; in future. These will be available to view online.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sps-entitlements"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, entitlements are used as the basis for subsidy payments. An entitlement gives a farmer the right to a payment, provided it is supported by a hectare of eligible land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments are based on entitlements, which were allocated to farmers in 2005. If you do not have any entitlements, or wish to obtain more, you may be able to purchase or lease some from another farmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each entitlement you choose to claim payment on, you must have at least one hectare of eligible land. Your total claim must be at least one hectare. If you hold special entitlements, your claim will only be valid if the value of your claim is at least €200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="value-of-entitlements-under-the-sps"&gt;Value of entitlements under the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of the scheme in 2005, &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements were valued on two elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a flat rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an addition - based on any historic reference amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until 2012 the value of entitlements changed from scheme year to scheme year. During this period, the flat rate element gradually increased and the historic element decreased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="entitlement-rates-2005---2012"&gt;Entitlement rates 2005 - 2012&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following tables provide information on the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; flat-rate entitlement values for 2005 to 2012 for the Severely Disadvantaged Areas (SDAs), non-SDAs and SDA moorland. Figures include a reduction factor for historic entitlement, the conversion rate that was applied - from euros to sterling - and, for 2006 onwards, the sugar tonnage rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates"&gt;2005 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (10% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€28.20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£19.23&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8578711&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€23.59&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£16.08&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8578711&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€3.36&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£2.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8578711&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2005 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.68195&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-1"&gt;2006 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (15% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€45.92&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£31.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.9362356601&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€38.02&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£25.76&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.9372378661&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€6.48&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£4.39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.9217465831&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2006 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.67770&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2006 sugar tonnage rate was €9.710&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-2"&gt;2007 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (30% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€95.13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£66.28&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8224050932&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€76.98&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£53.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8217647726&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€13.40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£9.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8188342677&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2007 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.69680&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2007 sugar tonnage rate was €9.50331&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-3"&gt;2008 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (45% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€141.93&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£112.17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7875675861&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€116.21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£91.84&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7835710360&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€20.53&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£16.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7786558592&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2008 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.79030&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 sugar tonnage rate was €10.376042&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-4"&gt;2009 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (60% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€190.47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£173.19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7234699423&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€156.09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£141.93&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7229429055&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€27.37&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£24.89&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7273821633&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2009 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.90930 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 sugar tonnage rate was €10.256098&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-5"&gt;2010 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (75% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€241.14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£207.37&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.6293490704&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€194.78&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£167.50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.6266152534&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€34.15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£29.36&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.6266538333&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2010 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.85995&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010 sugar tonnage rate was €3.526882&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-flat-rates-6"&gt;2011 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement flat rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Flat rate (90% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reduction factor for historic entitlement&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€289.94&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£251.28&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3977943979&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€233.95&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£202.75&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3989093934&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€40.82&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£35.38&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.4047346028&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2011 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.86665 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2011 sugar tonnage rate was €1.411122&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sps-entitlement-rates"&gt;2012 &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement rates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(100% figure)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Rounded sterling value)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Non-SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€323.91&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£258.50&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€260.29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£207.72&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SDA Moorland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;€45.47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;£36.29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2012 exchange rate applied was €1 = £0.79805&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any payments that the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; makes will be reduced for European and national modulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2012, the value of all entitlements is based on a flat rate, with a single value being established for all entitlements in each of the three English areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, England is divided into three regions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-Severely Disadvantaged Area - England outside the upland Severely Disadvantaged Area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Severely Disadvantaged Area - English upland SDA other than moorland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Severely Disadvantaged Area Moorland - English moorland within the upland SDA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within each region, there are two types of entitlement - normal and special. Land in a specific region can only be used to support entitlements in that same region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="types-of-sps-entitlement"&gt;Types of &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements fall into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;normal entitlement - code NML&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;special entitlement - code SPE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="activating-sps-entitlements"&gt;Activating &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your entitlements can be activated for payment - ie claimed - in each year you apply under the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To activate all your entitlements, you must have sufficient land at your disposal on 15 May (unless that falls on a weekend). The land must be eligible for the whole calendar year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="usage-rule-for-sps-entitlements"&gt;Usage rule for &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not claim an entitlement for two years it will be taken away from you and put into the National Reserve - except in exceptional circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can rotate entitlements to make sure they are used at least once in any two-year period but can only use them in the area of England where they were established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sps-entitlements-subject-to-special-conditions"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements subject to special conditions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had no eligible land, or entitlements over a certain value in 2005, then you were able to apply for entitlements subject to special conditions. These conditions related to the number of livestock on a holding in the year of claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To activate special entitlements for payment, a farmer must maintain at least 50 per cent of the level of agricultural activity, expressed in Livestock Units kept during the reference period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conversion-of-special-sps-entitlements-into-normal-sps-entitlements"&gt;Conversion of special &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements into normal &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special entitlements will be permanently converted into normal entitlements if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you do not confirm on the application form that you wish your entitlements to retain their special status&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when completing your field data sheet, you declare more eligible land for the activation of entitlements than is needed to activate your normal entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you transfer out special entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of Livestock Units needed to activate any remaining special entitlements for payments will be reduced pro rata to take account of the conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-sps-entitlements-statement"&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements statement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entitlement statement for the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; shows the number of English entitlements that you held on the application deadline date for a specific scheme year. The statement also shows the new value in euros of each entitlement but does not show any entitlements transferred in or out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is recommended that you keep your entitlements statement for your records and refer to it when you complete subsequent &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; application forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download guidance on &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements from the &lt;a href="rpa.defra.gov.uk/entitlements"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transfer-of-entitlements-under-the-sps"&gt;Transfer of entitlements under the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmers can transfer &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements at any time of the year. Since 1 January 2009, there is no longer a requirement for the transferor - the person making a transfer - to be a farmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entitlement transfers can be made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by sale or gift - with or without land &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by lease with land &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through inheritance &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through merger or scission - ie splitting - of a business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-to-transfer-sps-entitlements"&gt;How to transfer &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To transfer &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlements, you must complete and return an RLE 1 application form. You can request this form by calling the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline on Tel 0845 603 7777. Alternatively you can print out a form from the [&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website] (http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rle1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should use the RLE 1 form to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transfer entitlements - with or without land&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transfer entitlements by lease with land &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;surrender entitlements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transfer land and/or make a permanent boundary change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To request the right amount of RLE 1 forms you will need the following information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single Business Identifier (SBI) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;primary business address &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the reason you are requesting the RLE 1 form &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of businesses to which you are transferring entitlements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of land parcels you wish to transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Usually, the RLE 1 form will already contain as much detail as possible relevant to your specific transfer. Where it is not possible to send you a pre-populated RLE 1, a blank form will be issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must notify the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; at least six weeks before a transfer of entitlements is due to take place. If you fail to do this, the transfer will take effect six weeks from the date that &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; receives the form. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-the-environment-with-cross-compliance"&gt;Protecting the environment with Cross Compliance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to receive the full &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payment - and certain Rural Development scheme payments - you must comply with a set of Statutory Management Requirements. These relate to areas of public, animal and plant health, environment and animal welfare. You must also demonstrate that you are keeping your land in good agricultural and environmental condition. This is known as ‘Cross Compliance’. All agricultural activities are covered by Cross Compliance and you must comply with the requirements across the whole agricultural area of your holding, regardless of the amount of land you entered into the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These standards are based on existing European and domestic legal requirements, or basic good agricultural practice that you should already be following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For technical advice and queries you can call the Cross Compliance Helpline on 0845 345 1302.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cross Compliance standards also apply to anyone claiming certain Rural Development schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-advice-on-cross-compliance"&gt;Further advice on Cross Compliance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find up-to-date guidance for farmers on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rpa.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/293a8949ec0ba26d80256f65003bc4f7/21c99ddaeb3232a9802573aa004efa3e!OpenDocument"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must also complete an annual template for Cross Compliance soil protection purposes. You can complete your Soil Protection Review 2012 template manually or electronically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-the-sps-helps-fund-rural-development"&gt;How the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; helps fund rural development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Modulation’ is a levy on CAP direct payments - in England this is the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; - to support rural development, such as the agri-environment schemes.
There are two types of modulation levy - European and national. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="modulation-levy-rates"&gt;Modulation levy rates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rates of modulation are set at &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; and national levels, as a percentage of direct payments made to farmers. In England, total modulation, including &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; and national modulation, is 19 per cent. &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; modulation deductions do not apply to the first €5,000 of direct payments. This exemption does not apply to national modulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the proceeds from &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; modulation are shared out among the original 15 &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states, but most of the funds are kept within the originating member state. All the proceeds from national modulation are kept by the originating member state.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Separate arrangements for national modulation apply in the devolved administrations of Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="benefits-to-businesses"&gt;Benefits to businesses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In England, modulation payments help pay for the Rural Development Programme for England. This includes the Entry Level Stewardship agri-environment scheme, for which all farmers are eligible to apply and which is designed to deliver environmental benefits over and above Cross Compliance requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modulation attracts matched funding from the &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt; budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-funding-for-farmers"&gt;Other funding for farmers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, there are other types of support available through the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; Common Agricultural Policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you receive &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; payments or certain other Rural Development Scheme payments, you must meet Cross Compliance requirements. These requirements apply across all farming activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For detailed information see &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/cross-compliance-the-basics"&gt;Cross Compliance: an overview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-rural-development-programme-for-england-rdpe"&gt;The Rural Development Programme for England (&lt;abbr title="Rural Development Programme for England"&gt;RDPE&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt;, Natural England and the Forestry Commission are responsible for awarding funding from the &lt;abbr title="Rural Development Programme for England"&gt;RDPE&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt; manages the &lt;abbr title="Rural Development Programme for England"&gt;RDPE&lt;/abbr&gt; socio-economic elements (Axis 1 and 3 and the management of the Axis 4 Leader approach).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out about the &lt;abbr title="Rural Development Programme for England"&gt;RDPE&lt;/abbr&gt; on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ww2.defra.gov.uk/rural/rdpe/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt; website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read about grants and funding on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.naturalengland.org.uk/grantsfunding/default.aspx"&gt;Natural England website.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read about timber industry and woodland grants and funding on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.forestry.gov.uk/website/fchomepages.nsf/hp/GBIGL"&gt;Forestry Commission website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also available is the English Woodland Grant Scheme. Download a guide to the English Woodland Grant Scheme from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.forestry.gov.uk/pdf/ewgs1-guide.pdf/%24FILE/ewgs1-guide.pdf"&gt;Forestry Commission website (PDF, 526KB).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-natural-england-energy-crops-scheme"&gt;The Natural England Energy Crops Scheme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Energy Crops Scheme run by Natural England continues to offer grants to farmers to establish miscanthus and short rotation coppice in certain parts of England. You can find details and application forms for the Energy Crops Scheme on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.naturalengland.org.uk/ourwork/farming/funding/ecs/default.aspx"&gt;Natural England website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial help is also available to exporters of certain crops. For more information, see &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/agriculture-horticulture-and-fisheries-import-and-export"&gt;Agriculture, horticulture and fisheries: import and export.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cross-compliance-helpline"&gt;Cross Compliance Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0845 345 1302&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="natural-england-enquiry-service"&gt;Natural England Enquiry Service&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0845 600 3078&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="defra-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs"&gt;Defra&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;08459 33 55 77&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rpa-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0845 603 7777&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="ewgs-hotline"&gt;EWGS Hotline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;01223 346 004&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="rpa-sps-helpline"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Helpline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0845 603 7777&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/single-payment-scheme-online"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://spsonline.rpa.gov.uk/RPARegAndEnrol/registerAndEnrol!requestPINReg.action"&gt;Request a new PIN on the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/UIMenu/D18B1A94A6AE8F0C8025734B0033818B"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Online and farm software packages guidance on the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/293a8949ec0ba26d80256f65003bc4f7/21c99ddaeb3232a9802573aa004efa3e!OpenDocument"&gt;Index to &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Cross Compliance guidance on the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/rpa/index.nsf/293a8949ec0ba26d80256f65003bc4f7/e5b20880d03465a3802573aa0050128c!OpenDocument"&gt;Key Soil Protection Review (SPR) (GAEC 1) measures on the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rpa.defra.gov.uk/entitlements"&gt;Download the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s SP19 on understanding your &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; entitlement statement from the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/sps2011"&gt;Download the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Handbook for England 2011-2012 from the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://rpa.defra.gov.uk/sps2012"&gt;Download the &lt;abbr title="Single Payment Scheme"&gt;SPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Handbook for England Suupplement 2012 from the &lt;abbr title="Rural Payments Agency"&gt;RPA&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/30034?category=45001"&gt;ELS scheme guidance on the Natural England website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.naturalengland.gov.uk/ourwork/farming/funding/es/default.aspx"&gt;Environmental Stewardship scheme information on the Natural England website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.forestry.gov.uk/pdf/ewgs1-guide.pdf/%24FILE/ewgs1-guide.pdf"&gt;Download a guide to the EWGS from the Forestry Commission website (PDF, 526K)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8792</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:40:27+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:40:27+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/charging-heavy-goods-vehicles-consultation"/>
    <title>Charging heavy goods vehicles consultation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals for levying a charge on heavy goods vehicles using roads in the UK. It sets out the proposals being examined and requests your views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/hgvroaduserlevy/documents.html"&gt;Bill and explanatory note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20121023a/"&gt;HGV Road User Levy, written statement by the Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Transport, 23 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8730</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:37:06+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:37:06+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/code-of-practice-for-the-acceptable-use-of-advanced-imaging-technology-security-scanners-in-an-aviation-security-environment"/>
    <title>Code of practice for the acceptable use of advanced imaging technology (security scanners) in an aviation security environment.</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper invites responses from stakeholders on the Government’s interim code of practice for the acceptable use of advanced imaging technology (body scanners) in an aviation security environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//publications/information-on-the-implementation-of-security-scanners"&gt;Information on the implementation of security scanners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8903</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:34:59+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:34:59+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/future-of-urban-transport-discussion-document"/>
    <title>Future of urban transport discussion document</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this discussion paper is to encourage debate on the issues around the future transport needs of our cities and urban communities and to invite comments on the plans for a new Urban Challenge Fund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8734</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:31:48+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:31:48+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/amending-driving-licence-standards-for-vision-diabetes-and-epilepsy"/>
    <title>Amending driving licence standards for vision, diabetes and epilepsy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is being issued for comments on changes to the minimum standards for vision, diabetes and epilepsy in relation to driving. Driver licensing in Great Britain is carried out by Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA) and in Northern Ireland by the Driver and Vehicle Agency (DVA). This document relates to licensing standards across the United Kingdom; any reference to DVLA applies to DVA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document seeks views on changes to the medical standards for vision, diabetes and epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/dvla/consultations.aspx"&gt;DVLA consultation &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8811</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:30:11+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:30:11+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-abolition-of-the-disabled-persons-transport-committee-dptac"/>
    <title>The abolition of the Disabled Persons Transport Committee (DPTAC)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultation about what successor arrangements should be put in place if Disabled Persons Transport Advisory Committee (DPTAC) is abolished. We are seeking to ensure that any successor arrangement will continue to provide the Department with consensual, pan-disability advice in a flexible way, and that any arrangement represents value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cross-government review of Non Department Public Bodies carried out in October 2010 concluded that reform was needed to increase accountability, reduce duplication of activity, improve transparency and discontinue obsolete activities. In line with the goals of this review, the department needs to ensure it continues to have access to specialist advice on the practical issues facing disabled people using the transport network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has developed a number of options for securing specialist advice on disability transport issues should the department make an order to abolish DPTAC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8733</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:28:47+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:28:47+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-proposed-designation-order-for-the-port-of-belfast-security-authority"/>
    <title>Consultation on the proposed designation order for the Port of Belfast security authority</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A consultation paper on the proposed Designation Order to define the boundary of the Port of Belfast for the purposes of the Port Security Regulations 2009 and designate the Port of Belfast Security Authority as the relevant Port Security Authority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8735</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:25:44+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:25:44+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposal-to-discontinue-passenger-services-at-mosley-street-metrolink-station-manchester"/>
    <title>Proposal to discontinue passenger services at Mosley Street Metrolink station- Manchester</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport for Greater Manchester (previously Greater Manchester Passenger Transport Executive) wished to discontinue passenger services at Mosley St station on the Metrolink light rail system in central Manchester. Under the provisions of the Railways Act 2005, GMPTE conducted an assessment of the effects of the proposed closure and DfT conducted a public consultation earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation was completed in February 2011 and a request was submitted to ORR to ratify the closure of the station. ORR have now completed their ratification procedure and are content for the station closure to go ahead. The ratification notice and other papers can be viewed at the link below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decisions"&gt;Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk/server/show/nav.1478"&gt;Office of Rail Regulation (ORR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation-responses"&gt;Consultation responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110509101621/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/2010-35/responses.pdf"&gt;Responses Summary (PDF - 25 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 24 May 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="consultation-documents"&gt;Consultation documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110509101621/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/2010-35/consultation.pdf"&gt;Proposal to discontinue passenger services at Mosely Street station, Manchester (PDF - 36 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 23 November 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110509101621/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/2010-35/annexa.pdf"&gt;Annex A - Location of Mosley Street station (PDF - 2048 MB)&lt;/a&gt;, 23 November 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110509101621/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/2010-35/annexb"&gt;Annex B - Code of Practice on Consultation&lt;/a&gt;,23 November 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="impact-assessments"&gt;Impact assessments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110509101621/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/2010-35/closureassessment.pdf"&gt;Mosley Street Metrolink Station Closure Assessment (PDF - 463 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 24 May 2011&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8737</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T16:12:20+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T16:12:20+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-closure-of-passenger-services-at-woodlands-road-metrolink-station-manchester"/>
    <title>Proposed closure of passenger services at Woodlands Road Metrolink station, Manchester</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Greater Manchester Passenger Transport Executive wishes to close passenger services at Woodlands Road station on the Manchester metrolink light rail network. In accordance with the Railways Act 2005, the Department is conducting a public consultation on the proposed closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-documents"&gt;Download documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//consultations/closed/2010-37/woodlandsroad.pdf"&gt;Proposed closure of passenger services at Woodlands Road Metrolink station, Manchester (PDF - 32 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 December 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//consultations/closed/2010-37/annexa.pdf"&gt;Annex A Woodlands Road map (PDF - 180 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 December 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//consultations/closed/2010-37/annexb.pdf"&gt;Annex B Code of Practice on Consultation(PDF - 16 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 December 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
