<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-22T16:35:47+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8303</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T16:35:47+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T16:35:47+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/low-carbon-vehicle-partnership-lowcvp-conference"/>
    <title>Low Carbon Vehicle Partnership (LowCVP) Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Neville for that introduction (Prof. Neville Jackson - Chair LowCVP)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also for asking me along, I’m delighted to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="history-tells-a-different-story"&gt;History tells a different story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s often a tendency to talk about ultra low emission vehicles in the language of the future - “the next generation, the cars of tomorrow”, you know the sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, looking back, interestingly, history tells a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the mid 19th to the early 20th century, the electric vehicle (&lt;abbr title="electric vehicle"&gt;EV&lt;/abbr&gt;) was actually the king of the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to their petrol contemporaries EVs were much easier to drive and much cheaper to buy, run and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, not only were they more comfortable and more reliable than petrol cars, they were far more popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right up until the early 1920’s cities like New York had an electric taxi fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Europe and the States, major haulage firms were using electric trucks to transport their goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some countries even set up exchangeable battery services to help motorists drive longer and further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="three-key-reasons"&gt;Three key reasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then things changed. So I think we have to ask, what happened? How was the electric vehicle overtaken in the race to shape and dominate motoring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view there are three key reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A century ago we started to see major advances in the design and technology of internal combustion engines which then began to dominate the market.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mass production pushed down the price of petrol and diesel vehicles, while the plentiful supply of oil kept prices at the pumps low. The end result was that a different type of motor car entered the market with much greater affordability for customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And, last but not least, there was a radical improvement in access to supporting infrastructure. By working together, governments and private sector companies at the time ensured there were more and better roads, as well as increasing numbers of nationwide filling stations that were easy to find and quick to use. This led to an explosion in the number of petrol cars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="converging-coming-together"&gt;Converging, coming together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that those three points - technology, affordability and access - are just beginning to transform the fortunes of low carbon vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly but surely they’re converging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, we’re seeing a big and rapid leap forward in the design and technology of low carbon vehicles. There was a slow start but the pace is now picking up and is making low carbon vehicles a reliable and viable choice for consumers in terms of their motoring needs today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, earlier on my way here today I saw a number of adverts for the Vauxhall Ampera, crowned 2012 European Car of the Year, and I am looking forward to taking a test drive in one later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing that’s happening is a welcome shift from prototypes to mass production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nissan predicts it will sell 1.5 million zero emission cars by 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While, according to recent research by Deloitte, eco-friendly vehicles could account for one in ten of all new global car sales within a decade. The fact that some of these cars are produced in the UK is another reason why the switch to low emission is so important for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History shows that mass production means greater affordability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a Government perspective, greener motoring is also being made more affordable through consumer incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/topics/sustainable/olev/plug-in-car-grant/"&gt;Government’s Plug in Car Grant&lt;/a&gt; is one example - a 25% subsidy up to a maximum of £5,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve launched a &lt;a href="/topics/sustainable/olev/plug-in-van-grant/"&gt;Plug-in Van Grant&lt;/a&gt; too, which again gives 25% of the purchase price, up to a maximum of £8000, bringing these vans into an affordable range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably there’s a chicken and egg situation in the development of the low emission vehicle market - we have limited infrastructure because we have few electric vehicles, and we have few electric vehicles because we have limited infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new area - we are trying to dramatically change consumer behaviours in a market used to one type of vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s important for us to understand how the market segments; about different types of business and leisure users, all of which will have their different success stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Plug In grants, our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120607094602/http://dft.gov.uk/topics/sustainable/olev/recharging-electric-vehicles/"&gt;Plugged-In-Places Programme&lt;/a&gt; is another important piece of the picture, triggering vital investment in infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also set out a comprehensive strategy around incentives and investment in infrastructure; one that identifies how recharging infrastructure will develop in a way that is targeted, convenient and safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say the lead we’re giving in this area is paying real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s encouraging private sector companies to fund and build networks of thousands of recharging points at locations around Britain, including motorway service stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a blend of supportive Government and private enterprise, we can really improve access to a new low carbon transport network where plug-in vehicles are a commonplace feature of the motoring landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="not-just-the-cars--vans-we-drive"&gt;Not just the cars &amp;amp; vans we drive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the point I’m making is this: the factors that led to the rise and dominance of petrol powered vehicles are now starting to open the road for low carbon driving all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when you look at consumer and business take-up, it’s been a predictable adoption curve. Now we are moving along that curve and a shift to low emission vehicles is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been slow-burn, but it’s been steady, and I believe it will start to pick up speed over the next 12-24 months and gain real traction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s also important to recognise the way manufactures are reducing the emissions and improving the efficiency of conventional vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, average new car fuel efficiency has improved 30% in the last ten years; while, on average, a new car bought today is 23% cleaner than a car designed and built in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there is brilliant work being done here. But I still think, to meet our carbon targets, we will need to harness new types of motoring technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked about Plug In grants and Plugged-In Places, but this Government is clear that we will be technology neutral. We want to ensure that consumers have real choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should also remember that decarbonising road transport is not just about the cars and vans we drive. Nor indeed is it just about electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about the public transport, haulage, and even the sustainability of the fuels we produce - and the DfT has been keen not to lose sight of these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re backing a revolution in bus travel with a multi-million pound Green Bus Fund - a scheme that has helped to deliver more than 500 low carbon buses on routes across England. And, notably, much of this work has been done by UK companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we recently launched a low carbon truck demonstration trial - £9.5 million worth of funding to encourage, and assist, UK road-haulage operators to buy, and use, low carbon medium and heavy-goods vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also why, through our new Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation legislation, we only reward genuinely sustainable bio-fuels - those that deliver greenhouse gas savings but do not cause undesirable environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-status-quo-is-not-an-option"&gt;The status quo is not an option&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, I believe we are making real progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m also convinced that for this important agenda, that the status quo is not an option. And let me explain why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s a lot cheaper to plug in and re-charge than fill-up at the garage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, it’s been estimated that a small electric van will typically cost £100 less in fuel for every thousand miles driven compared to a diesel equivalent. And look at the Nisan Leaf - it costs £3 to go a hundred miles - dramatically cheaper than a conventional car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So making the switch to ultra-low emission makes sound financial sense - whether you’re running a business or just an ordinary motorist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a much wider economic dimension too. One that is absolutely crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the global market for low carbon goods and services is currently worth a staggering £3 trillion a year. And that market is forecast to grow to well over £4 trillion during the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are very exciting times. We are witnessing the transition from oil-based mobility to other, lower carbon sources of energy. This is not just good for consumers and the environment - it’s good for UK plc. We want to see our country at the forefront of R &amp;amp; D in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have to seize the moment and grab a share of the green growth and those green collar jobs - which is why we’re positioning this country to be a global leader in the design, production and use of electric and ultra-low emission cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s already working. Nissan is building a plant to manufacture its electric vehicles and batteries in the North East. With policies that mean Britain is very definitely open for business, I believe that other investors will follow that lead. Working alongside BIS, I am determined to make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need to bear in mind that oil is a finite fossil fuel - one that’s getting harder to find and, as we are all discovering every time we fill up our vehicles, more expensive to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important for the public, as well as industry and jobs. And, if we want to make sure that we aren’t constantly at the mercy of fluctuating world oil prices, then a brighter and cheaper motoring future is surely a low carbon motoring future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driving from A to B and cutting emissions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting public transport and helping the motorist.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reducing dependency on oil and developing sustainable bio-fuels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boosting our economy and safeguarding our environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;None of these ambitions are contradictory - they are complimentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re not mutually exclusive - they’re actually two sides of the same transport coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off this speech by arguing that, once upon a time, the future looked as though it belonged to low carbon vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to end it by arguing that history is turning full circle - that, just like the champions of the internal combustion engine a century ago, our generation has a golden opportunity to change the world and change motoring once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may not be easy. And I appreciate that these early days may have felt like slow days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is happening, it can be done and I’ll be right behind you - so let’s go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8302</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T16:18:15+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T16:18:15+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/lep-network-annual-conference"/>
    <title>LEP Network Annual Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction David (David Frost &lt;abbr title="Local Enterprise Partnerships"&gt;LEP&lt;/abbr&gt; Network Chair)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also for asking me along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an important conference focused on important issues… and so I’m delighted to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one brief glance at the Conference Programme is proof enough that you have a packed schedule and busy day. So I promise not to take up too much of your valuable time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, when it comes to making speeches, I’m always conscious of the wise words of the 19th century politician Lord Reading whose sage advice to public speakers was “Always be shorter than anybody dared to hope”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-matters"&gt;Local Matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in my job for some six months now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, one of the things that’s really struck me is the extent to which the transport debate can be dominated by “the national”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big-ticket items and large-scale infrastructure; the policies and projects; those pieces of the transport jig-saw with a genuine nationwide significance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I suppose that’s only to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, something like HS2 - a rail modernisation that will transform Britain’s social and economic geography - is bound to generate headlines and grab people’s attention from one end of the country to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the other thing you quickly learn in this job is that “local” matters hugely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It matters because nearly all journeys start, or end, on local transport networks. And those journeys can shape your entire day, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only takes a late bus, a packed train or a congested road and a short commute becomes an endurance test and a good day turns into a bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, there is a direct relationship between the quality of local transport and the quality of our individual lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also has a wider impact on us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because an effective and efficient local transport system is the bedrock of a successful and sustainable local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s getting products into our shops and onto the shelves, or connecting businesses with the market-place and employees with the work-place, local buses, trains and roads are essential economic ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="getting-local-transport-right"&gt;Getting local transport right&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does all that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it means this Government has a laser focus on getting local transport right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in it, reforming and modernising it. From day one in office these have been first order priorities for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me walk you through just a few of the things we’ve been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our £560 million Local Sustainable Transport Fund will give communities more power to design and deliver local transport schemes; while our £770 million Growing Places Fund will help to help kick-start infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Autumn Statement the Chancellor announced 20 local authority major transport schemes. And, just before Christmas, I gave the green light for a further 21 local majors. That’s an investment package worth £854 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in this year’s Budget, the Chancellor again announced investments designed to improve local transport links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ranged from £15 million for Cycle Safety in London, to supporting Network Rail to invest a further £130 million in the Northern Hub rail schemes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve reformed as well, simplifying funding by cutting the number of separate local transport grant streams from 26 to just four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re cutting red tape too. For example, by freeing up local councils so they can remove expensive and unsightly clutter from our roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a “win-win” reform that will save money and improve the local environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also looking at ways to devolve more responsibility for commissioning local and regional rail services - a move that could increase transparency, strengthen accountability and improve the passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms to benefit bus passengers as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seventy million pounds of new funding to improve bus services, another thirty million pounds for green buses and an extra fifteen million pounds to support the roll out of smart ticketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New regulations to ensure healthy competition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for local authorities, empowering them to deliver innovative public transport solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measures that will encourage more people to hop on a bus - changes that will help cut carbon emissions, ease congestion and improve the quality of services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="local-enterprise-partnerships-leps--proposed-reforms"&gt;Local Enterprise Partnerships (LEPs) &amp;amp; proposed reforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So from game-changing reforms to major investments, we are advancing on a number of fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as your network and this event demonstrate, it cannot stop there… because we also see a pivotal role for Local Enterprise Partnerships (LEPs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have 39 LEPs established across England - full national coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, when it comes to transport, it is you, the LEPs, who really understand the crucial importance of good transport links to your businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re the ones who know the local challenges and opportunities. The ones well placed to devise local solutions - solutions that can help boost economic growth, minimise the environmental impact of travel, improve public health and tackle social exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, that local power and knowledge, that potential, has too often been blunted by centralised funding and bidding processes that, as you know, can be time consuming and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our challenge, one in which we want you to play a central role, is to localise decision making. To speed it up, but to also ensure it remains rigorous, evidence based and backed up by a proper evaluation of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely why we have just consulted on reforms designed to devolve decisions on capital funding for local schemes to democratically accountable local transport bodies from 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these proposed reforms we are seeking to give communities real power to deliver real improvements on everything from local roads and public transport schemes, to better pedestrian routes and new rail stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think the advantages of such a system are clear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Targeting funding more effectively and getting the best return on every penny spent and every pound invested&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making decisions that place higher weight on local priorities and needs, while generating maximum economic growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And saving a huge amount of time and effort that was previously wasted meeting central requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have made it clear that we want LEPs to be key players in the devolved process - something that’s been broadly welcomed by the majority of those responding to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not for us at the centre to tell you precisely how these arrangements should work in every area. What we’ve done is simply open a door. It’s up to you to walk through and take the steps needed to work effectively in partnership with local authorities, recognising the enhanced role for businesses and, of course, maintaining democratic accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re especially keen to see a strong role for LEPs when it comes to things like investment finance, ensuring best value, or making those tough trade-offs between competing priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m convinced our reforms have the potential to make a positive difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None the less, I think it’s important to recognise that achieving devolution like this is no simple task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, there will obviously be a need for assurances on key areas - effective governance, financial management, accountability and the achievement of value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, then, these are matters which businesses, local authorities and LEPs deal with every day. So I am confident that, together, we can make these reforms work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration between my Department and the new transport bodies will also be important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, this is a major change and we stand ready to give help and assistance to the local bodies as they approach this transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That process of transition will mean a managed hand-over to transport bodies when they are ready. But let me assure you, the end game is one in which Central Government’s role is light touch, rather than heavy handed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, we’ll be there as good partners if and when you need us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am clear that our main function is to support you. To help you adapt to, and work in, a truly decentralised decision-making system so that you can meet the challenges and maximises the opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="end-to-end-travel"&gt;End to end travel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the big opportunities out there is the potential to improve end to end trave - locally and nationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if they’re walking and cycling, or they’re travelling by road or rail people today demand, and deserve, a transport system that provides a properly joined-up journey from front door to final destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing that might involve something as simple as providing real time travel information, or taking full advantage of smart ticketing technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, it could mean giving buses priority on roads leading to railway station forecourts and placing bus stops as close as possible to the main station entrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, whatever steps we take, our ambition must be seamless connections, both between different providers and across the different transport modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in my view, if anyone can help make that happen, then it’s LEPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="smart-localism"&gt;Smart Localism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll all be aware that the consultation on our proposed reforms closed at the start of this month, and we intend to produce a report on the key findings in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this we’re planning to publish indicative allocations for major transport scheme funding for local transport bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the changes we propose are important in their own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d argue they are also part of a much bigger reform picture - one that I call “Smart Localism”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart because it recognises that a one size fits all approach cannot work in a modern world where the consumer rules and the customer is king or Queen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And smart because it enables local services, like transport, to be tailored to local needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart Localism is a challenge to the old ways of thinking and working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a rejection of the Big State&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more diktats from above; no more “Whitehall knows best”; no more treating citizens as passive recipients of standardised services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, Smart Localism is a declaration that those days are long gone and that the best government is self government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It understands that people today want something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They want a genuine say over the issues that affect their lives and their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They want bespoke services that reflect their priorities and fit in with their lifestyles, whether it’s their bus routes or their bin collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what they get with Smart Localism. Because decision-making is devolved and power is dispersed to where it can do the most good - to local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially it’s about replacing the straight-jacket of central control with the freedom of civic activism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for me, Smart Localism is actually about community, in the truest sense of the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I promised at the start to keep things brief, so I think it’s time I brought my speech to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I’ve argued that, when it comes to transport, this Government believes local matters - to our neighbourhoods and our livelihoods… to our quality of life and our future prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s concrete action that counts, not simply good intentions or warm words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, from investments to reforms, I’ve walked you through some of the practical ways in which we’re modernising local transport, making it fit for the demands and challenges of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also talked up the merits of what I call Smart Localism: the way that it can empower and enable: its potential to give people chances and choices because it gives them the power to control and decide - the power to “do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I believe in Smart Localism. But it’s also why I believe in you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I look on you, the Local Enterprise Partnerships, as its standard bearers - the men, the women, the Network helping to spread and embed its values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I wrap things up - and because silent gratitude isn’t much use to anyone - I’d like to pay tribute to the work you do and the difference you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re doing a great a job - so keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening and I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8301</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T16:12:50+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T16:12:50+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/institution-of-mechanical-engineers-imeche"/>
    <title>Institution of Mechanical Engineers (IMECHE)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also for asking me along. This is an important event, debating an important subject, and so I’m delighted to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know you have a packed schedule, so I’ll do my best to keep things brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, what I’d like to do this morning is give you a sense of why I think &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; matters critically for Britain’s future - why this is a project whose time has very definitely come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="section"&gt;1825, 2025, 2026&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ours is the country that gave the world the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if Victorian Britain was the 19th century midwife to rail travel, then it was the mechanical engineer, and former President of this very Institution, George Stephenson who was surely its father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 1825 it was Stephenson - one of the greatest of our Victorian forebears - who built the first steam locomotives. And it was Stephenson who ran them on the first public railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those trains, and that line, covered little more than two dozen miles between Stockton and Darlington, but they started a process that would change our world forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2025 will be the year we celebrate the bicentenary of that incredible achievement - two centuries since the story of rail began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But 2026 will be the year we start writing a new chapter in that story. Because that’s when we aim to have the first trains speeding along &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-different-future"&gt;A different future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Britain, high speed rail will be a transport quantum leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many other countries it’s already a well established form of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it is forty seven years since Japan launched the world’s first commercial high speed rail service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And its famous Bullet Trains proved to be so popular and successful they were carrying a hundred million passengers within three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, high speed networks have sprung up across the Far East and Western Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And new lines are being built in nations as diverse as the United States, Saudi Arabia, and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, set against this international reality, the choices I faced when I took up my job as Transport Secretary were pretty straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we go for growth, or do we settle for stagnation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do we take this once in a generation chance, or do we lose it forever?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And, for me, the facts were crystal clear - self-imposed exile from this global transport revolution made no sense whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do that and it would be our cities, our businesses and our travelling public losing out, and looking on, as others embraced high speed rail - enjoying, and exploiting, its social, economic and environmental benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compete and win in the modern world Britain needs to aim for a different future. So, in January, I gave the green-light to &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering that “should we” “shouldn’t we” question on &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; naturally raises other important questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when will it be up and running? What will it look like? How much of a difference could it make? So let me try to address some of the key strategic issues around the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-network-two-phases"&gt;National network, two phases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to say is that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will be a truly national high speed rail network built in two phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 1 will link London to the West Midlands, plus a direct connection to the Continent through the Channel Tunnel via High Speed 1. And it’s worth noting that more than half of the route will be in cuttings or tunnels to mitigate the visual and noise impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; trains will run directly onto the existing network - which means that, even in this initial phase, it will offer faster journeys to destinations in the North West and Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 2 will provide onward legs to Manchester and Leeds, with intermediate stations in the East Midlands and South Yorkshire, plus a direct connection to our international hub, Heathrow Airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks and months I’ll be considering &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd’s route and station advice for this second phase. I intend to publish that advice in the autumn, together with a Government response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want the whole country to share in &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;’s benefits, which is why I recently went up to Scotland and spoke to the Scottish Government about how high speed rail can work for communities and businesses north of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, the date we’ve set ourselves for completion of Phase 1 is 2026. And, by 2033, we expect Phase 2 to be finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-a-high-speed-britain-could-look-like"&gt;What a high speed Britain could look like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these two phases will add up to a Y-shaped network that’s around 330 miles long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just think about the potential positive impact of that network, about what a high speed Britain could look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious change is that journey times between our cities and regions will have been slashed and connectivity radically improved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London to Birmingham: 45 minutes instead of the current 1 hour 24 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Birmingham to Manchester: just 41 minutes, rather than the hour and a half it takes now. Birmingham to Liverpool down to a hour from 1 hour 34 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And Birmingham to Leeds: a trip of 57 minutes, as opposed to the 2 hours it takes today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;High speed trains will also be high capacity trains - up to 18 an hour in each direction with up to 1,100 seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, not only will &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; mean better connected communities and better served passengers, it will also free up a huge amount of extra space for freight and commuters on the conventional rail network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s a massively important &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; bonus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, yes, in the spending review we committed £18 billion worth of investment to improve our conventional railways - the biggest modernisation programme since Queen Victoria sat on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our scope for squeezing ever-more capacity out of our existing rail infrastructure is diminishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just look at the passenger figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand for long-distance rail travel has doubled over the past 15 years and there are now over 1.4 billion rail journeys on the rail network a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, up-grading existing major North-South lines would only provide a short term fix, and would consign passengers to years of disruption, delays and misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what makes &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; so much more than a way to provide faster and better journeys for those travelling on the high speed network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the capacity it unlocks, it’s actually the key to meeting the demand challenge and transforming rail services for every passenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will also help breathe new life into our towns and cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because high speed rail stations will be at the heart of urban across the country, acting like a catalyst to local development, galvanising businesses, generating innovation and driving forward renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; tens of thousands of jobs - direct and indirect - will have been created and sustained by the building, on-going maintenance and day-to-day running of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think that the construction and operation of Phase 1 alone will support something like 40,000 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will mean much wider job opportunities, not least of all for engineering, technology and infrastructure specialists, and the firms and businesses that make up the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are already helping us deliver Crossrail, Thameslink, electrification and upgrades to major stations like Reading and Birmingham. But even the largest of these schemes will be dwarfed in size by &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to see British companies, with their world-beating skills and expertise - the kind of qualities that &lt;abbr title="Institution of Mechanical Engineers"&gt;IMECHE&lt;/abbr&gt; and its members are famous for - competing for key high speed contracts. Britain’s best helping us deliver &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; on time and on budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, on the way over here this morning I was reminded that &lt;abbr title="Institution of Mechanical Engineers"&gt;IMECHE&lt;/abbr&gt; - along with its virtual next door neighbour the Institution of Civil Engineers - is located right in the heart of Government… a stone’s throw from the Treasury in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s no accident. Your founders chose this spot for their impressive headquarters because they lived in an age when modernising this country’s infrastructure was seen as a top political priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, as &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; shows, under this Government, it is again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will give a huge boost to families and businesses up and down the country - to our individual quality of life and our collective well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters it will enhance social mobility, giving choices and opportunities to millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will also help to re-boot and re-balance our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of Britain will be open for business as companies and entrepreneurs across the regions use &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to exploit new markets, win new customers and attract new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And high speed rail could even be good for the environment, with its potential to encourage a modal shift of people and goods away from long-distance car use and short haul aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="beyond-a-simple-benefit-cost-ratio"&gt;Beyond a simple benefit-cost ratio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; makes sound financial sense too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We estimate the full Y network will cost £32.7 billion to build (in 2011 prices) and that it will generate benefits of up to £47 billion and fare revenues of up to £34 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; sums add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s be clear, the economic case for this project goes way beyond a simple benefit-cost ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there will be a welcome return on the money invested in &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real economic gains will be seen in the way a national high speed rail network helps to support job creation and stimulate the economy, improve connectivity and increase capacity, and make Britain’s competitive edge razor sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plain truth is that the price of not going ahead with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; far outweighs the cost of building it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, high speed rail matters for our country’s success and our children’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From its size and scale, to the positive difference it will make, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a landmark transport project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recognise that this is huge project; a challenge that’s as big as they come; and a genuine test of our energy, commitment and skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when I look at the “wow factor” renovations of stations like St Pancras and Kings Cross; when I see the way in which these railway hubs have been transformed and restored to their Victorian splendour; I know it’s a test we are equal to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that Britain has been here before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the start of my speech, we are the heirs of giants like George Stephenson; the inventors and innovators who gave us the railways; the Victorian forebears whose vision and determination transformed this country’s fortunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, half a century ago jobs, growth and opportunity got a decades’ long shot in the arm when another generation had the vision to plan and construct the motorway network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we can no more turn our backs on the positive potential of high-speed rail than these earlier generations could have opted out of the steam age; or condemned this nation to a slow-lane future without motorways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like them, we cannot simply hope for a better and more prosperous future- like them we must, and we will, build it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8304</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T16:04:11+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T16:04:11+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/armed-guards-to-tackle-piracy"/>
    <title>Armed guards to tackle piracy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secretary-General, President, your Excellencies, Ministers, High Commissioners and Ambassadors, distinguished delegates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to join you for this important debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a major trading nation and a global maritime centre, the UK places great importance on shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Ensign Group is the sixth largest trading fleet in the world, and shipping accounts for over 90 percent of the UK’s visible imports and exports-..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the broader maritime industry supports more than 250,000 UK jobs; and contributes over £13bn to our GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we want to see this industry prosper, we also want to see a safe and prosperous &lt;strong&gt;global&lt;/strong&gt; maritime industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free and safe trading by sea is crucial to world economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything that affects the transport of goods by sea and threatens the safety of seafarers should be a matter of the gravest concern to the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am delighted that the International Maritime Organisation is holding this high level debate into the sensitive issue of privately contracted armed guards on ships, and I’d like to thank Ministers and senior representatives from Governments around the world for giving up their time to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="global-problem-global-response"&gt;Global problem, global response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Prime Minister David Cameron recently described Somali piracy as “a complete stain on our world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was absolutely right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What began 20 years ago as a small scale problem in the coastal waters around the Horn of Africa has - over the past decade - grown into a highly sophisticated and lucrative business… threatening shipping throughout the Western Indian Ocean, and costing the international economy an estimated $7bn a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while governments and the shipping industry feel the financial impact, it’s the human victims of Somali piracy who are paying the biggest price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, thousands of seafarers have been attacked, assaulted, used as human shields, or kept in extended confinement in Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is reported that in the past four years alone, more than 60 have died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And violence against victims is increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their indiscriminate and brutal aggression, the pirates have made clear that any crew member on any vessel is a target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your nationality, faith, or business; and whatever flag your ship is flying, you are seen as fair game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are all in this together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s clear to me that if we want to find an effective and lasting solution to the global threat of Somali piracy, we need a global response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-in-recent-years"&gt;Progress in recent years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the international community and the shipping industry have made substantial progress in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure we all welcome yesterday’s successful operation conducted by the European Naval Forces’ Operation Atalanta to disrupt pirates’ logistical dumps in Somalia. This will increase the pressure on, and disrupt pirates’ efforts to get out to sea to attack merchant shipping and dhows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navies from more than 20 countries are currently patrolling the seas around Somalia and the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many specific initiatives to tackle piracy are also being implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the UK has announced funding for a range of counter-piracy projects. These include supporting regional justice systems and prison capacity building in Mauritius, the Seychelles, Tanzania and Somalia so pirates can be prosecuted and punished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our officials are also working to help Kenya seize pirates’ assets. And together with the Netherlands we are supporting a regional centre in the Seychelles for co-ordinating intelligence and pursuing the leaders and funders of piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to say that many other states are involved in a range of similar initiatives to tackle piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, the IMO is taking important steps to build capacity in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shipping industry has also developed and implemented a wide range of best management practices to deter attacks and boost protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I resolutely believe that we need more than a series of unilateral responses to the problem of piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a global response. And I believe one of the most effective ways we can capitalise on our shared strengths would be to develop an internationally agreed approach to the use of armed guards on ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="armed-guards"&gt;Armed guards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last October the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120607094600/http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20111206a"&gt;British Government announced that we would allow the use of armed guards on British flagged ships in exceptional circumstances&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might apply to vessels crossing the high risk area when best management practices on their own may be considered insufficient to prevent attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many other flag states are taking similar action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision was not one we took lightly. Having armed guards on ships generates risks as well as benefits. But where their use is justified by a full risk assessment, and where professional standards can be achieved and assured, we believe armed guards can provide an effective deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps as a result of all of these actions, the number of successful attacks on shipping actually fell during the second half of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="more-to-do"&gt;More to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome and applaud all the positive measures being taken to tackle this global problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is absolutely no room for complacency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact we need to work together more closely… developing new strategies… using our collective expertise &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; combined focus to their very best effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the progress we’ve made, the pirates still have it too easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Ocean and Gulf of Aden are among the busiest and most valuable shipping routes in the world. 22,000 ships pass through the Gulf each year, and the value of EU bound cargo exposed to Somali piracy, for instance, is $952 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the vast expanse of water in which the pirates operate obviously limits the effectiveness of naval patrols or other security vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although fewer ships may be being taken, last year the number of attacks actually rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive ransoms are still being paid out. Last year they reached a total of $160m - an average of $5m per captured ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And too few pirates are being brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action on land to improve stability remains the ultimate answer but will take time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So until regional stability is assured, and while the profits from hijacking ships outweigh the perceived risks in the minds of the pirates, these gangsters of the sea will pose a continuing threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-priorities"&gt;Key priorities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the UK believes there are two key priorities now for the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, we need to ensure that the protective measures are effective and safe for the seafarer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I therefore welcome the work of the IMO on the development of guidance for shipowners and Flag States on the use of privately employed armed security guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also welcome the interim guidance provided to private maritime security companies by Working Group 3 of the Contact Group on Piracy off the Coast of Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK remains committed to assisting this work as we develop and implement our own national standards for private security companies, and as we keep our guidance to UK flagged ship owners up to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are clear that ultimately we need an international accreditation scheme for PMSCs - so only the highest quality organisations are employed, and so all vessels have guards on board who meet agreed security standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like the new system to be in place as soon as possible, and we believe that the entire process of international accreditation must be open, transparent and inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it must also be practical to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the UK would like to see an internationally co-ordinated and consistent process for embarking and disembarking private security staff and weapons in countries around the region - to ensure the safety of seafarers and vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second key priority is action to undermine the ‘business model’ that currently makes piracy pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome and support the work of the Contact Group in this area which includes disrupting the illicit movements of money associated with piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are delighted that a range of countries have agreed to join the UK led International Piracy Ransoms Taskforce, announced by David Cameron at the London Conference on Somalia in February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This taskforce will consider ways to prevent the flow of cash to pirates. The first meeting of this taskforce will take place at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that tackling these issues will not be easy, and there may be no quick answers, but it remains critical that we work together as an international community to identify the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to conclude, we face a very resolute and aggressive enemy, based in one of the poorest nations on earth, facing some of the greatest challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we know that combating the threat in the coming years will be extremely tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to make the very best use of the strengths and resources we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are at our strongest when we’re together….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United in our commitment to protect shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United in our strategy to improve regional stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And united in our determination to stamp out the menace of piracy for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120607094602/http://dft.gov.uk/publications/measures-to-counter-piracy"&gt;Guidance to UK flagged shipping on measures to counter piracy, armed robbery and other acts of violence against merchant shipping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8300</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:54:22+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:54:22+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/intelligent-mobility-summit"/>
    <title>Intelligent Mobility Summit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that kind introduction - and I’d like to thank the Automotive Council for all the work that you’ve put in to organise this summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real pleasure to see so many experts and distinguished professionals from a wide range of backgrounds and disciplines come together to share ideas on the future of mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a debate with massive implications for the future of our economy, and the future of our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m honoured to be here and to be taking part in today’s event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transport-and-its-impact-on-the-uk"&gt;Transport and its impact on the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nation we are placing seemingly ever-increasing demands on our transport system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because transport is a great enabler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As individuals, it helps us live our lives; enjoy our leisure time; achieve our goals; and expand our horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also key to economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing the arteries through which commerce flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linking commuters with the workplace and goods with the marketplace&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers rightly want transport that is safer, cleaner and greener. They want less congestion and more reliability. And, however they are travelling, they want transport that is seamless, truly integrated and makes the best use of their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Intelligent mobility’ can make this a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not merely by delivering a more dynamic, efficient and integrated transport system… but also by transforming the travel experience, and increasing the value of time spent on the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It offers a huge opportunity to provide a step change in delivering a quality service for customers, by building transport around the user and around the passenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-challenge"&gt;The Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The positive potential of intelligent transport cannot be exaggerated. But neither should we underestimate the challenges ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boosted by continued population growth, a rise in GDP, more prosperous consumers, and more affordable motoring, we estimate that road-user demand will rise by around 35% over the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one sense, this can be seen as a positive because rising demand means our economy is continuing to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, at the same time, sustaining the performance of our road systems will become increasingly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve the economic growth that is so crucial to Britain’s future prosperity, we cannot afford to allow our transport arteries to clog up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must be prepared to accommodate rising demand for road space while hitting our carbon reduction targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to base our strategy around the multi-faceted expectations of the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at a time of limited public resources, we need to explore new and innovative ways of funding improvements to road transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-government-is-doing"&gt;What Government is doing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are clear that Britain needs a modern road network fit for the 21st century - one that drives growth, jobs and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means investing in parts of the infrastructure where we can deliver the best value and benefits to businesses and road users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re already investing over £1 billion to tackle areas of congestion and improve the national road network, and spending £500m on local schemes. That’s on top of the £2.3 billion planned investment in major roads announced in the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my Department is working with the Treasury to look at new ways to fund roads in the longer term - such as attracting more private sector involvement through new ownership and financing models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a fresh approach to investment is only part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need a smarter road network - one that can adapt to future changes in society and technology. A more intelligent system to make better use of capacity, both on roads and public transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, our priority here is not only to improve the way that transport networks are managed, but also to build change around the user, transforming the travel experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New technologies offer enormous opportunities to address both concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also huge gains on offer for UK-based businesses if we get this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already a recognised global leader in developing transport technologies. We have the knowledge, facilities and experience to lead the world in making intelligent mobility come to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take advantage of this capability, we need to foster strong links between different parts of the transport industry with technology providers, academia, and the engineering sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking round this room today, the Automotive Council is an excellent example of how you are working co-operatively to deliver a shared vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I see our role in Government as very clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to free you up to do the job you’re best at - focusing on your customers, understanding their changing needs and innovating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to provide the right support structure for the private sector to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s something we are working on across the Coalition, as highlighted in the recent Budget, where the Chancellor set out plans to make the UK the technology hub of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, by establishing two new Catapult Centres for Transport Systems and Future Cities - which can create a critical mass for research - we will support collaboration between leading UK businesses, innovators and academics to bring new technologies to market, attract inward investment, reduce congestion, and support economic growth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry-leadership"&gt;Industry Leadership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we depend on industry expertise to deliver this work. And I am proud to say that the UK is well-placed to drive forward the Automotive Council’s vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are home to one of the most diverse, efficient, innovative and high-tech motor industries in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud that Ford, General Motors, Toyota, Nissan, Honda, Jaguar Land Rover, and BMW - among others - all have major manufacturing facilities here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also have a thriving motorsport industry; perhaps the most sophisticated fleet sector in the world; and a strong supplier base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our country’s history shows a magnificent motor industry heritage. But the real strength of Britain’s modern motor industry is that it’s looking forward, not back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that gives me confidence that we here in the UK can lead a global revolution in smarter transport and intelligent mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry is already stepping up to the challenge in many ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the way traffic is managed - and we’re already using some of this technology as part of our Olympics transport programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bringing low carbon passenger and commercial vehicles to market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And exploiting the opportunities offered by digital technologies to change the way you communicate and interact with the consumer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just consider the extraordinary range of services that an organisation like Transport for London is able to offer through its website and smart-phone apps today compared with a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travellers in the capital can access live traffic and Tube information; top up their Oyster Smartcards; check their Boris Bike availability; pay for the Congestion Charge; get directions to the nearest parking space; book a taxi; and - perhaps best of all - find out when their next bus is arriving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail users can now get a first app with real time train journey information down to each station and even each platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few years, web-based technologies will increasingly give individuals the ability to start tailoring their journeys as they like. That’s going to change the way that transport providers see the market and deliver their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And actually, that’s something we’ve seen in other areas of the business world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take an early innovation that has become routine - the Tesco Club Card… an idea that has changed shopping and supermarkets for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece of simple but effective technology empowered the shopper. But, by allowing Tesco to analyse shopping behaviour, it also enabled them to develop strategies that could best exploit customer segmentation. In other words, it worked for the business too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good example of industry taking the lead was the SatNav summit - run by ITS (UK) and ADEPT - which the DfT hosted in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the SatNav has transformed the way we navigate around towns and cities, there is clearly potential to further improve the flow of information to customers over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, as we become increasingly reliant on SatNavs and smartphones to find our way around, so the consequences of any glitch in the technology, or in the information fed into the system, become more serious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the information going into SatNavs must be accurate and up to date. But the places they help us navigate to, our towns and cities, are not places that never change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New retail and housing developments alter the street network. New traffic lights are built. New weight and height restrictions come into force on a road. So the information needs to be supplied as quickly and seamlessly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reputations of the SatNav supplier, or even the car manufacturer, can’t help but be linked to the flow of information provided by a wide range of sources… from local councils to the Highways Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are SatNav user groups who also have a critical interest in the debate… freight companies, for example, taxi firms, and fleets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here again, collaboration between different public and private sector organisations is absolutely key to improving the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the most of the opportunities that technology can offer, industry cannot deliver this vision alone. You need to work in partnership with Government if you’re to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can open up new sources of data, and that’s exactly what we are doing with our transparency agenda - from providing information on MoTs to streetworks and road accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also create incentives, such as the £30 million Plugged-in Places programme, offering match-funding to consortia to encourage the development of plug-in vehicle recharging infrastructure across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can improve access to European Research Funding, and work to lift the burdens of red tape on business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="roads-strategy"&gt;Roads strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a timely debate, because the Department has recently started work on a new Roads Strategy, to be published towards the end of the year, as recommended by Alan Cook’s independent review of the Strategic Road Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective is to set clear, long-term goals for the network and help deliver a ‘horizon shift’ in our aspirations for such a key, significant national asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our focus will be on maintaining performance to support economic growth; to reduce environmental impacts; and to support the safety and security of road users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology will influence and sometimes transform the way we approach each of these issues, and will therefore be of critical importance in the development of the new strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your thinking on this will be invaluable, and we hope that over the coming months you will engage with the Department and help us shape our plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is a perfect opportunity to start thinking about this. So before I finish I’d like to suggest three challenges that I hope will help focus your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - in terms of challenge and opportunities, what are the long-term outcomes that we want to achieve? Where are users and consumers going to be? It’s not just about capacity, as you know, it’s about the quality of journeys and provision too. what are those needs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - looking at the range of solutions, what are the technologies that will drive economic growth and help make the most of capacity, but deliver the best experience too on our transport network and how can we better understand their benefits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally - how can we take forward momentum from today’s event, to improve collaboration and actually deliver meaningful results?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="looking-ahead"&gt;Looking ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can sum up, together, government and industry have made great progress towards addressing problems of safety, pollution and fuel consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have helped make Britain’s roads among the safest in the world. And we are on the cusp of a further transformation in road safety with the development of virtually un-crashable cars by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re making great headway on the environmental impact of road transport. Improvements in fuel efficiency and the development of hybrid and electric vehicles mean that, despite an increase in traffic, CO2 emissions are set to fall significantly over the next 25 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps our biggest challenge, given its economic, environmental and social cost, is making sure we tackle congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we all need to focus on solutions - be they managing demand, enabling travellers to make more informed decisions about their journeys, and making the best use of existing networks and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the complexity and size of the task ahead, I’m convinced that we are on the road to an exciting future - one in which innovative solutions can make a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when technology is changing so rapidly - perhaps faster than at any time since the invention of the internal combustion engine - we have a tremendous opportunity to develop a more intelligent road transport strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To grasp this opportunity, we have to exploit our shared know-how and experience. We have to invest in areas that offer the biggest potential benefits. And we have to put the customer at the heart of our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow these principles and I’m convinced that we can meet our shared objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8299</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:52:59+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:52:59+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/transport-times-aviation-conference"/>
    <title>Transport Times Aviation Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you David. This is a key conference at a crucial time for Britain’s aviation sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know how difficult the past few years have been for many in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With challenges like rising oil prices, a turbulent global economy, and a ruthlessly competitive marketplace have all taken their toll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But paradoxically, the economic downturn has also made us appreciate, even more than before, the immense contribution that aviation makes to our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure it’s a familiar figure to many when I say, the sector generates around £9bn of output each year and of course plays a crucial role in providing our gateway to the global marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the year of the Olympic Games and the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, we are reminded of the critical role that aviation plays in supporting tourism, and making London such a popular destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the very success of our aviation sector also presents us with a series of key challenges, these centre around:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… how to accommodate growth while meeting our environmental commitments and addressing the quality of life impact of aircraft noise…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… how to improve our airports and the passenger experience…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and how to protect Britain’s position as one of the best connected countries in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, the debate on the future of our airports must be grounded in reality and based on the facts. The reality is that Britain has an extensive and highly successful global aviation network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, London is the most well connected city in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has five highly successful and busy airports… six if you include Southend and some would also like to see Manston to play a role in meeting our aviation capacity needs as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The London airport network provides direct links to around 350 international destinations, including most of the world’s greatest commercial centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heathrow delivers over 9000 flights every year to New York making the UK the market leader in Europe, on this route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2500 to Singapore and New Delhi make us market leaders here too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of the Westminster village… I’ve read on the escalators at Westminster tube station that we’re lagging behind in this important market…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… lagging behind unless, that is, we include the 3000 flights every year to Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do that… it’s clear that in this market too, we lead with Heathrow delivering more services to China than any of its continental rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And frankly I don’t think my colleagues in the Foreign Office would thank me if I started acting on the assumption, as some people seem to, that Hong Kong &lt;strong&gt;wasn’t&lt;/strong&gt; a part of China!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while it is true that Heathrow is pretty much full and Gatwick too is approaching capacity… it’s simply not the case that London’s connectivity is falling off a cliff edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But good government is not just about tackling the problems of today… it is also about planning for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way that we are not prepared to leave future generations with a fiscal deficit, neither should we leave them with an infrastructure deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is right that we have the debate about our capacity and connectivity needs over the years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Chancellor announced in his Autumn statement that we would explore all the options for maintaining the UK’s aviation hub status with the exception of a third runway at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition has always been clear that it does not support a third runway at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of its very first acts as a Government was to confirm this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heathrow is unique in Europe in terms of the magnitude of the noise impact it has on densely populated areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The airport accounts for approximately 70 per cent of people in the UK exposed to average noise from airports above 55 decibels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than one in four people exposed to this level of noise around European airports lives near Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands live on a daily basis with a plane overhead every 90 seconds… not to mention the flights that wake them up at 4.30am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of life impact of a third runway, with up to 220,000 more flights over London every year, would be massive and there is no technological solution in sight to ensure planes become quiet enough quickly enough to make this burden in any way tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need another solution… and last year we kicked off the process to decide what that will be with the publication of our scoping document on a sustainable future for aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responses came from a wide range of industry and environmental stakeholders, members of the public and community and campaigning groups. I’d like to thank those who took part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using them to inform the drafting of our consultation document on a sustainable future for aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also developing a call for evidence on maintaining the UK’s hub airport capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two documents will be published in the Summer… a little later than planned… but we remain committed to finalising policy framework by next spring as we originally promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some would like us to go faster but this decision is a crucial one which requires an objective, thorough and evidence based analysis of our connectivity needs and how best to meet them in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thorough assessment of the environmental impact of potential solutions will also, of course, be crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Coalition has said from the start… we want aviation to grow… but growth at any price and without regard for the environmental consequences would not be in the nation’s best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviation needs to play its part in meeting our carbon commitments and protecting the quality of life of local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as asking the right environmental questions… we need to ask the right economic ones as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that &lt;strong&gt;connectivity&lt;/strong&gt; is the crucial outcome we want to secure and that connectivity and capacity aren’t always synonymous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the last time capacity was increased at Heathrow was when the Terminal 5 planning consent raised the movement cap to 480,000 flights per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when capacity went up, the number of destinations actually fell because of an increasing emphasis on trans-Atlantic routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely… while additional capacity &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; certainly improve connectivity… it is not the only means of doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to make better use of the airports we have by using them more efficiently and by seeking to focus our hub capacity on the routes that are of the greatest importance to the economy as a whole and which will contribute most to the continuing success of Heathrow as one of the world’s most popular hub airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do acknowledge that the DfT’s latest published demand forecasts do indicate that airports in the south east are likely to be full by around 2030 with increasingly significant crowding pressure by the mid 2020s… even if regional airports start to shoulder more of the load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how long it takes to deliver new capacity… we do need to start preparing now for those longer term challenges… though it should be acknowledged that demand forecasts are presented as a range and can change as key assumptions about economic growth and oil prices are varied. So there is an element of uncertainty here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor… I’m afraid… would it be right for me to stand here and pre-judge the outcome of the detailed and evidence-based decision-making process we started on with our scoping document and which we will continue with the documents we’re publishing in the Summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of the last Government shows what a tangled web you can weave if you start out with one outcome in mind and seek to reverse engineer the evidence to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whichever solution is ultimately chosen… delivery is likely to span across more than one Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Secretary of State and her predecessor have both expressed an interest and willingness to seek cross-party consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that the degree of cross-party support which has been established for HS2 is making the high speed rail project easier to deliver than it otherwise would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In taking the process forward to determine the right solution to the UK’s long term aviation connectivity needs… we’ll consider very carefully how we can take the politics out of the debate and seek common ground with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I would emphasise that our focus on the longer term is not distracting us from the action we’re taking to improve our airports right now and make the best possible use of our current capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legislation is going through Parliament to deliver a new system of economic regulation that will put the passenger interest firmly at the heart of the regulatory system and create the right incentives for investment in the improvements that customers want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The licence based approach we are proposing will help the CAA intervene more quickly and more effectively if an airport is failing its customers than waiting for a 5 yearly price review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also pressing ahead with measures that emerged from our South East Airports Taskforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include reform of the aviation security regime… moving it away from the prescriptive approach of today towards what we have called “an outcome-focused, risk-based” system. Which I think would bring significant improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re now consulting on those changes, which would give airport operators more flexibility on how to meet security standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are confident that the new approach can deliver the same high standards as today… or possibly higher… but will enable these outcomes to be delivered in a more passenger friendly and efficient way by harnessing the ideas and expertise of the airport operators who actually deliver these services on the front line and enabling them to integrate more seamlessly into operations at the airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further important initiative that emerged from the work of the taskforce is the tactical use of greater operational freedoms at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trial of these measures commenced in November and they include the use of both runways for arrivals in certain prescribed circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe these freedoms could potentially deliver operational benefits by improving punctuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could also provide environmental benefits by reducing the number of late running night-flights and reducing aircraft stacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the trial will provide a sound factual basis on which to assess the impacts and benefits of theses operational freedoms being trialled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full consultation with local communities will take place after the end of phase 2 of the trial to enable us to decide whether any of these new operational freedoms should go beyond the trial stage to become long term changes to the way Heathrow operates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fourth key initiative for improving our airports is harnessing the latest technology to modernise airspace management through the CAA’s Future Airspace Strategy and the Single European Sky programme run by the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a priority for the Government and one which is starting to make some real progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental part of the SES programme is the establishment of functional airspace blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By running airspace in bigger blocks which combine a number of countries, we can increase capacity, reduce fuel consumption, mitigate noise and improve safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Irish functional airspace block was the first to start operations and is already delivering practical benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifthly and lastly - we are delivering a step change in the quality of the surface access links to a number of our busiest airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester airport is going to be linked up to the Metrolink tram network for the first time and funding has been secured for a new Airport Link Road connecting with the M56 and A6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thameslink will significantly improve rail connectivity to Luton and Gatwick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase one of HS2 will provide a top class interchange with Birmingham airport and phase two to Manchester and Leeds will bring the airport within an hour’s travel time for the majority of the UK population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase two will also give millions of people in the Midlands and the North a direct high speed rail route to Heathrow for the first time. The long awaited tube upgrade will improve London Underground services to Heathrow and a quarter of a century after the project was first mooted.. Crossrail construction is now underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two huge tunnel boring machines will soon be starting their journey under central London, delivering that crucial direct link between Heathrow and the global financial powerhouse in the City and Canary Wharf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ladies and gentlemen… we’re taking a range of actions right now to ensure our airports continue to provide top class international gateways to the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re also carrying out the process needed to determine our future connectivity needs and how we meet them in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an immensely important debate and I would urge all of you to take part when the call for evidence and consultation documents are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank for taking time to listen to what I’ve had to say on these key issues for our economy, our environment and our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8298</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:42:59+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:42:59+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/good-transport-equals-good-economics"/>
    <title>Good transport equals good economics</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James, many thanks for that introduction (James Hanratty).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you also to the Club and its members for asking me to share your evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a real pleasure to be here - and for two main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is because, as a Cabinet Minister, my office is usually filled with Civil Service officials offering me advice on transport policy, media interviews. In fact, on almost every subject under the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So frankly, any chance I get to speak for longer than two minutes uninterrupted is one that I grab with both hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason I’m so pleased to be here is because I get the opportunity to engage with an audience that is expert, informed and distinguished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, that’s pretty much par for the course at the Athenaeum Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, yours is an institution that can open up its two hundred year old membership books and see names like Charles Dickens and Rudyard Kipling, Charles Darwin and Barnes Wallis, Lord Palmerston and Winston Churchill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that even the Duke of Wellington was a Club member at one time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was the Iron Duke himself who gave this unforgettable advice about public speaking - “Don’t quote Latin, say what you have to say and then sit down.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while doing my best to stick to Wellington’s advice - especially the bit about quoting Latin - tonight I’ll be speaking about “equations”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, to be accurate, one equation in particular. I can see a few raised eyebrows. Don’t panic, I promise that you won’t have to sit through a mathematics’ lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, the equation I want to talk about is one that drives my policy approach at the DfT, and it’s this - good transport equals good economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-race-to-win-the-future"&gt;A race to win the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the Athenaeum has been down the decades, Britain is home to inventors and innovators, builders and creators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurs opening businesses, creating jobs and spreading prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers analysing problems and devising solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers pushing the limits of design, scientists pushing the boundaries of discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And companies turning out some of the best products on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all vital components of our national capital and they are the equal of any in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while all of this should give us hope about Britain’s future, it should not give us rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the modern global economy there is a race to win the future and complacency will mean we end up being left behind in the starting blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like they say, if you snooze, you lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this Government deliberately set itself the task of building a Britain that is ready and able to go up against the global competition, and win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="re-booting-re-energising--re-balancing-the-economy"&gt;Re-booting, re-energising &amp;amp; re-balancing the economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, right from day one in office, we understood that you can’t build a better future on the quick sands of inherited debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you need to sink your foundations into the rock-solid ground of fiscal discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re sticking to our deficit reduction plan. Paying down the inherited debt, winning credibility in the markets and keeping interest rates low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also have a laser focus on making this the best place in the world to start, finance and grow a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re removing the shackles that hold our entrepreneurs and wealth creators back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freeing them up, giving them room to succeed by reforming employment laws and modernising the planning regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re knocking down the barriers of rules of out-dated and unnecessary rules too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to see better regulation, not more regulation, which is why I back a “one in, one out” rule and the “Red Tape Challenge”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re easing access to credit and bringing down the costs of borrowing for small businesses with our National Loan Guarantee Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, we’re cutting Corporation Tax as well… down from 26 per cent to 24 per cent this month, to 23 per cent in April 2013 and then down to 22 per cent by April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re putting in place the conditions of long-term stability by re-booting and re-energising our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re working hard to re-balance the economy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes of course, we recognise and value Britain’s role as the world’s leading financial centre - a role we’re committed to safeguarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these islands were once the workshop of the world and it’s time to be a nation of manufacturers, innovators and exporters once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more products around the world stamped with the words “Made in Britain” that’s our ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shifting UK Plc from a “spend and borrow” past to a “make and sell” future, that’s our goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-straightforward-equation"&gt;A straightforward equation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong and stable economy is an essential ingredient for Britain’s future success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as the Prime Minster recently argued, the infrastructure deficit we inherited is as serious as the budget deficit that was left to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And infrastructure matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the thread that makes possible our journeys to work, delivers light when we flick the switch and provides the connections that made the communications revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In believe that if this country is to out-produce, out-innovate and out-compete the rest of the world, then it also needs infrastructure fit for the 21st century. And that includes the transport networks that are so crucial to our economic future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s not just my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Chambers of Commerce say that “infrastructure is the lifeblood of British business”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CBI say “there are large amounts of business capital waiting to be unlocked if the government achieves a step-change on transport”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Institute of Directors say it is “essential to provide more and better transport infrastructure in order to sustain the UK’s competitiveness”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t agree more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cutting congestion and speeding up journey times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving people and products faster and more reliably&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And making sure Britain is plugged into the global market place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s how you power up the recovery and put people back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot afford to sit back and look on while other countries invest in world class transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the emerging economies of Asia and Latin America, in the Middle East and Africa - even in the United States and the European Union - nation after nation is upgrading and expanding their infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bridge they repair, every road they improve and every rail track they lay drives their growth and increases their prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today over-stretched and outmoded infrastructure just won’t cut it. They cost British businesses and British families time and money, it’s as simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the start, for me it’s a straightforward equation - good transport equals good economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we too must invest in and modernise our transport networks. And that’s precisely what this Government is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-different-choice"&gt;A different choice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, to be honest, the easy choice faced with the debt and deficit we inherited, would have been to cut capital spending and major infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we made a different choice. A deliberate decision to invest in our transport infrastructure - from huge multi-billion projects like Crossrail, to small interventions that make a big difference, like encouraging more people to cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last year’s Spending Review - over £30 billion for road, rail and local transport across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up the £560 million Local Sustainable Transport Fund, giving local communities more power to design and deliver local transport schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year’s Autumn Statement unveiled a multi-billion pound investment package in which transport took centre-stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in this year’s Budget, the Chancellor again announced investments designed to improve our country’s transport links. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£150 million for our Growing Places Fund to boost economic growth, jobs and house-building;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£15 million for Cycle Safety Infrastructure for TfL to reduce the rate of collisions and encourage an increase in cycling in London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And £11 million for Low Carbon Buses to help build a cleaner and greener Britain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Budget we also announced our support for Network Rail to invest a further £130 million in the Northern Hub rail schemes - funding that means passengers in the great counties of Yorkshire and Lancashire will enjoy better connections, faster services and more seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="hs2-decision"&gt;HS2 decision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government made a different choice about transport investment because we were looking well beyond the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking decisions to improve our national well-being, not just for the next four or five years, but for the next four or five decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not in spite of the economic challenges we face, but as a means to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that same long-term national interest which motivated my recent decision to give the go-ahead to HS2 - a national high speed rail network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2 will slash journey times, shrink our country and radically improve the connections between our cities and regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will help to create jobs and generate growth, promote social mobility and spread prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want the whole country to share in those HS2 benefits. Which is why I recently went up to Scotland and spoke to the Scottish Government about how speed rail can work for communities and businesses north of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="were-doing-more-much-more"&gt;We’re doing more… much more&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work to update and upgrade Britain’s transport infrastructure doesn’t begin and end with high speed rail. We’re doing more, much more, to get Britain moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re investing in our conventional railways - from new stations and new rolling stock, to electrifying more lines it all adds up to the biggest modernisation programme since Victorian times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, hand-in-hand with extra resources for our railways goes reform of our railways. So I’ve just published a Rail Command Paper setting set out our vision for an efficient, effective and value for money rail industry. Reforms that will put the customer first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re investing in our roads too, improving these arteries of trade and freight, whether it’s by unlocking extra capacity through our managed motorway schemes, or it’s through easing congestion by widening the Kettering Bypass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We won’t improve our roads through individual projects alone - as important as they are. So we’re developing a comprehensive national roads strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also carry out a feasibility study into new ownership and financing models for the national road network and report progress in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be looking at where we can learn lessons from other industries, and building on the proposals in Alan Cook’s report on the Highways Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving our quality of life and enhancing our economic prospects also means modernising transport at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all journeys start, or end, on local transport networks. And those journeys can shape your entire day, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only takes a late bus, a packed train or a congested road and a short commute becomes an endurance test and a good day turns into a bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when it comes to transport, local matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, because it matters so much, I’ve unblocked overdue major road schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, just before Christmas I gave the green light to a further 21 projects, all together adding up to an investment in our road network worth £854 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="island-nation-trading-nation"&gt;Island nation, trading nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is not just an island nation - we are a trading nation. So our ports must be world class global gateways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re backing major container port developments like Liverpool, Bathside Bay, Felixstowe South, London Gateway, Teesport and the Port of Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also why we want to see a successful and sustainable future for that other crucial global gateway, our aviation industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should remember that our country and our capital are right up there with the very best when it comes to international connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only China and the USA have aviation networks more extensive than ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not France. Not Germany. Not South Korea. Not any of our main economic competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are directly connected to 356 international destinations. And no European country can match our connections to the world’s great commercial centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over nine thousand flights every year to New York, three thousand to Hong Kong, two thousand five hundred to Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To each of these important destinations, and many others, Britain is the market leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, right now, this country is very definitely in aviation’s global premier league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None-the-less, if we are to maintain that high flying status then we have to take on the tough challenges facing the industry - whether it’s improving the passenger experience, or it’s enhancing capacity and connectivity while tackling the industry’s impacts on climate change and the local environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve been working on a call for evidence on the options for maintaining the UK’s status as an international hub for aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document, alongside our overarching aviation framework, will help define the future of UK aviation for decades to come and it is crucial that we get this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We remain committed to having a final policy in place by next spring at the latest, but we have taken the decision to wait until both documents are ready and intend to publish them in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, tonight I have argued that good transport equals good economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise that, as an equation, it is certainly uncomplicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also believe that it is absolutely undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite simply, an economy built for success requires transport networks built to last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time-warp transport would leave us a time-warp Britain - a country stuck in the past, rooted in the global slow lane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we need to invest in our transport networks… renew, rebuild and reform to make them the best that they can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, while I’m Transport Secretary, that’s exactly what we’ll continue to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I think it’s high time I brought my contribution to the proceedings to a close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’d like to sign off with an announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something that not too many people know, and it’s this… I’m a committed and unashamed Marxist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, before that shocking revelation reaches the Chief Whip, let me point out that I’m actually a Groucho Marxist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as only he could, Groucho Marx once joked - “I have had a perfectly wonderful evening… but this wasn’t it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I too have had a perfectly wonderful evening and this WAS it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it just remains for me to say a big thank-you - for inviting me along, for listening to what I had to say and for making me feel so welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;END&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8297</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:39:09+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:39:09+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/plug-in-van-grant-breakfast-event"/>
    <title>Plug-In Van Grant breakfast event</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that, today, we’ve got manufacturers here - and thank you for bringing your plug-in vans along… can’t wait to see them up close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got people who already own low carbon vans and some who are thinking of buying them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may even have one or two sceptics - those yet to be persuaded of the merits of these new and exciting vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, whatever your motive for being here this morning, I want to thank you all for making the time and taking the trouble to come along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, while I have the chance, I’d also like to say a very personal thank you to Pete (Waterman), for providing the soundtrack to my youth and, of course, for letting us use this venue today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pete has been a solid supporter of what’s cutting edge in transport - particularly on the rail side - and it’s great that he is able to be here to lend his support today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-motorist--pro-environment"&gt;A motorist &amp;amp; pro-environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cars and vans are absolutely central to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s how most of us get around and for many journeys they are, and will remain, the only practical and convenient travel choice -  not a luxury but an essential means of getting from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, climate change is a global challenge we simply have to meet head on. It cannot be ignored or side-stepped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is everyone’s business and anyone who is serious about tackling this challenge must also be serious about reducing the environmental impact of motor vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what marks this new grant out because, for me, it demonstrates that you can be a motorist and be pro-environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="good-for-the-environment-good-for-business"&gt;Good for the environment, good for business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new grant is good for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric vans will produce less air pollution and less noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, by helping to cut CO2 emissions, they will also help the UK meet our climate change targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the plug-in van grant is good for business too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses that run electric vans can benefit from reduced refuelling costs, get exemption from the van benefit charge, and attract capital allowance concessions, not to mention the 100% discount for the congestion charge in the capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But best of all, it’s been estimated that a small electric van will typically cost £100 less in fuel for every thousand miles driven compared to a diesel equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see just how well plug-in vehicles can fit into fleets - and just how much commercial sense they make - I recommend a read of the Climate Group’s report on Plugged in Fleets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s published today so, if you get the chance, pick up a copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="plug-in-van-grant"&gt;Plug-In Van Grant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about our new Plug-in Van Grant, and let me tell you why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It offers a 20% discount when you buy a new, eligible, ultra-low emission van…meaning up to £8000 off the purchase price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is available to both private individuals and business buyers across the UK&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It runs alongside our continuing “&lt;em&gt;Plug-In Car Grant”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And it is designed to build on, and complement, our existing “&lt;em&gt;Plugged in Places”&lt;/em&gt; recharging infrastructure programme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also think this type of low emission vehicles initiative is ideally suited for vans, especially if you look at the way they’re driven and used in business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vans often have a predictable range&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They make frequent stops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And many of them return to an overnight base where they can be easily recharged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might want to talk to some of the guests here today who have already taken the plunge and purchased plug-in vans.
I would particularly like to mention British Gas’s ambitions with hundreds of electric vans scheduled to be introduced into their fleets over the next few years - a move that will significantly add to the numbers of plug-in vehicles on the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would strongly encourage those of you who haven’t yet made the switch to plug-in vehicles to seriously consider it - not only for the environmental benefits but for what it could do for your own business’s bank balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-with-the-grain"&gt;Working with the grain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m convinced that the way to deliver real change is to work with, rather than against, the grain of human nature and every-day reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And&lt;/strong&gt;, by giving consumers motoring options that are reliable and affordable, as well as cleaner and greener, that’s precisely what these new grants are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the potential to create a virtuous circle by further stimulating investment in the mass production of ultra-low emission vehicles which, in turn, could bring down costs and further boost demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supported by a growing charging infrastructure, these developments can help make plug-in cars and vans an everyday part of life for British motorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks---take-a-look-at-the-future"&gt;Concluding remarks - take a look at the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, today is really all about setting out the path for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe these vans are going to make a real and positive difference - to communities and businesses, to how we live, drive and work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think you should just take my word for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why don’t we finish up here, go outside and take a look at the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/topics/sustainable/olev/plug-in-car-grant/"&gt;Plug-in Car Grant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120221/"&gt;Press release: Cash boost for electric van man - 21 February 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8292</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:37:17+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:37:17+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/aoa-conference"/>
    <title>AOA Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that warm welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you Ed [Ed Anderson Chairman of the AOA] - both for the kind words wishing me well in my new job and for inviting me along, it’s a real pleasure to be with you all today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks also to Andrew for playing his part in the proceedings as Conference Moderator [Andrew Neil]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the next 20 minutes or so will be a rare and treasured moment for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because I’ll be able to speak safe in the knowledge that, just for once, Andrew can’t interrupt me before I’m finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great honour for me to be speaking to such a distinguished and expert audience as the new Transport Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve certainly had a whirlwind two weeks since taking up my job. Getting to grips with my new brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting out and about too. Nobody ever learned anything stuck to a chair in Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s very much part and parcel of who I am and the way I want to do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to events like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engaging with, and listening to, people across our transport sectors and networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, like any politician, I hate to disappoint an audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as tempting as it may be, at this stage it’s probably a bit early to be laying out my entire transport blueprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I will at least make this iron-clad commitment: my focus in the coming weeks and months will be on making sure that transport remains right where it should be - at the top of this Government’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-successful-aviation-sector-a-growing-economy"&gt;A successful aviation sector, a growing economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I’m especially pleased my first keynote conference speech is to an aviation audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is because I had the pleasure of working with many of you during my time as Economic Secretary to the Treasury - and I can see some familiar faces in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the second reason is that I recognise, and value, your crucial contribution to UK plc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The members of the AOA, the people in this audience and the range of aviation companies you represent… you are all key players in a key sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in his speech, Ed rightly underlined the massive difference that sector makes to all of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not least, the jobs it creates and supports&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way it gives British business a gateway to the global marketplace&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes - the taxes it pays to the public purse that keep our public services going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no exaggeration to say that a successful aviation sector goes hand-in-hand with a growing UK economy. For me, they really are two sides of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="heathrow---time-to-turn-the-page-and-write-the-next-chapter"&gt;Heathrow - time to turn the page and write the next chapter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about our shared challenges I couldn’t put it any better than the theme of your conference - these are &lt;em&gt;“tough economic times”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our task as a Government is to do everything we can to ensure that businesses take root, people find good jobs and Britain’s competitive edge is razor sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as I’ve said, I’m with Ed and the AOA on this one - aviation has a front and centre role in helping us deliver those key economic objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that some people might say &lt;em&gt;“well what about expansion at Heathrow?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I accept that the Government’s decision on Heathrow’s third runway has had its share of critics - not least among this audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to be honest with ourselves - because all sides in this debate inhabit the same world of political reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the political reality is that the runway decision has been made, it’s done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to emphasise that the decision we took does not mean we are anti-aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Transport Secretary and this Government are anything but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know just how many people rely on an efficient, effective and successful Heathrow - for work and for travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get just how crucial aviation is to our national well being - economically, socially and environmentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I recognise that the industry needs certainty and decision making in the long-term national interest - not chopping and changing for reasons of short-term political advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would simply say this to you - it’s time to turn the page and write a new chapter in the story of aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prominent in that new chapter will be a credible, workable aviation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the industry is absolutely right to stress just how much strategy matters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes it’s easy to fall into the trap of thinking that strategy is all about dealing with single issues, such as capacity for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe our aviation strategy for our country has to be far broader-based than just the capacity question, though I recognise the importance of that question.
Actually, the best strategies cover all the bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re focused on the short term and the long term; the economic and the environmental; the local and the global; the needs of the sector and the needs of the passenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in what remains of my speech, I want to walk you through what we’re doing already, as well as talk about where I want to get to as we move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-were-doing-already---improving-the-passenger-experience"&gt;What we’re doing already - improving the passenger experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are we doing right here and now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the AOA has been working closely with my Ministerial colleague Theresa Villiers, as part of the South East Airports Task Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with your help and input, we are already engaged in the process of improving our airports and, by doing so, improving the passenger experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that passenger experience has to inform everything we do. Satisfied customers - as I know from my time in industry, before becoming an MP - are the life-blood of every successful business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re working with the UK Borders Agency to reduce queues at border checks, while maintaining the highest levels of security. Let me be clear that passenger safety and security will always be a top priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To also benefit passengers, we’re reforming ATOL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updating it. Bringing it into the 21st century in a way that enhances consumer protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AOA will know better than anyone that we’ve been cracking on with the business of modernising the 25-year-old framework for the economic regulation of our main airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in the spring of next year, we will legislate for a new regime to boost the quality of service that airlines and passengers receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also developing a new regulatory system on aviation security - one where Government will set the security outcomes to be achieved, freeing up operators to devise best ways of delivering them. Tailored better to the security needs of airports to maintain and enhance passenger safety and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-were-doing-already----improving-resilience"&gt;What we’re doing already -  improving resilience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another immediate step we’re taking is to trial the use of operational freedoms at Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this starts tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s an innovation that could help reduce the number of late departures, particularly unscheduled night flights, and allow the airport to recover more effectively on days when poor weather, or other problems, disrupt flights and delay passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, it could help to improve resilience. However, it’s a pilot and we’ll make sure we find out how it works with practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenges with “ash clouds” and “snow falls” are reminders of just how importance improving resilience is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that lessons have been learned, work undertaken, investments made and resilience measures put in place since we all experienced the disruption caused by erupting volcanoes and freezing winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do need to be prepared. The better the preparation, the better resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I’m ready to work with the industry to make sure that prepared is exactly what we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined to invest both time and effort where I can help make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I am pleased that Colin Matthews welcomed my suggestion that I visit Heathrow to hear directly from their Leadership Group about the steps they’ve taken to improve their winter resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I didn’t suggest an early trip to Heathrow because other operators aren’t on my resilience radar. They are, and I, of course, want to engage with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, ultimately, I recognise Heathrow is our busiest airport and a vital international hub, whether you are a passenger or a business operator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their preparations are crucial to the economic interests of our country-not to mention the travel plans of passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So naturally, I am keen to hear about the progress they are making and whether there is best practice that can be more widely shared and adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="moving-forward---sustainability-the-environmental-challenge"&gt;Moving Forward - sustainability (the environmental challenge)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s just some of what we’re doing already, where is it that I would like us to get to as we move forward?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, in a nutshell, the long-term vision is for an aviation sector that is successful because it is sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, an aviation sector that can grow and help our economy to grow too. But also an aviation sector that achieves these goals while addressing its local and global environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed himself spoke about environmental sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he reminded us of the real progress being made to cut emissions and combat the industry’s contribution to our carbon foot print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New technologies and new designs, lightweight materials and new fuel efficient aircraft - all making a positive difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much welcome that progress. And I understand that maintaining it, pushing on, isn’t always easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I also believe there’s something that aviation has in common with every other sector of our economy: namely that, just like the resilience challenge, the environmental challenge is one we simply have to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every industry, every business faces that self-same challenge. As does the Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we ask no more of one sector than we do of another. The journey towards a cleaner, greener future is one we all ultimately have to go along together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="moving-forward---new-framework"&gt;Moving Forward - New Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help us move forward strategically we have taken a fresh look at the structure of aviation policy with our Sustainable Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’d like to thank the AOA, and the many others gathered here today, for submitting their response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Framework - and the process of engagement that accompanied it - was a recognition that the Government does not claim to have a monopoly of wisdom about the best way to build a successful future for aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted, we needed, your input and your views. Your answers to a range of questions on key issues - from the economic benefits of aviation and the role of a UK hub airport, to how we accommodate growth in a genuinely sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming out of this exercise I honestly believe that we can - and I think we have to - leave behind the polarised opinions that have dominated the discussion in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think we can develop a common sense path forward and some common ground. This is vital to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="moving-forward---strategy-is-a-two-way-street"&gt;Moving Forward - Strategy is a two-way Street&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings me to the final point I want to make about moving forward and where I want us to get to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, for me, the way we’ve gone about the Sustainable Framework demonstrates an inescapable truth- that strategy is a two way street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes of course, Government has a responsibility to map out a route to a successful and sustainable aviation future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the industry itself must also step up to the plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you want to move forward?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your ideas for change and progress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you think we can meet the challenges that are out there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all those of you who worked with me in the Treasury, you will know that I am open and willing to listen to the views of industry - and I will have exactly the same approach here in Transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in this industry more than most, different players have a very different view of what “good” looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I am convinced that the best solutions emerge when all sides are fully engaged and properly involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, that doesn’t mean setting up a talking shop. Many people would say there’s enough hot air in the world, we don’t need to add to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it means both sides committing themselves to a can-do process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better way to do strategy. One that empowers us to develop real world solutions to the real world challenges facing aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an approach I adopted at the Treasury, working successfully with the oil industry to deliver investment in North Sea exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, building on our work with the Sustainable Framework, it’s an approach I intend to maintain now that I am Transport Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what I want is engagement that is organised and structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must also be regular. That’s essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting down together. Meeting on regular occasions throughout the entire year - spring and summer, autumn and winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that will be my approach to working with the industry - a structured and constructive approach so you know what our timeframes are for looking at the key issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I conclude, I want to briefly return to those key words in to your conference theme - that these are tough times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inherited debt and the state of the global economy perhaps means they are the most testing for a generation or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yes, I know that the task we have set ourselves - to ensure the long-term success and sustainability of aviation against this economic backdrop - that task is incredibly hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help and partnership of people like you - the members of the AOA, indeed all the women, men and companies of our aviation sector - I believe it can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I conclude, if there’s one message I’d really like you to take away today then it is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if the Government and the aviation industry come together and act together then, not only will we be better placed to see the challenges coming,  we’ll be ready, and able, to meet them head-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I thank you for your time and your hospitality and I look forward to working incredibly closely with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the Minister.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8291</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T15:33:41+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-22T15:33:41+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/asem-ministerial-meeting"/>
    <title>ASEM Ministerial meeting</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers, distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an honour to represent the United Kingdom at this important occasion. As a global trading nation, it is vital for the UK that transport links with Asia are fostered and expanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are keen for our companies to participate in Asian markets, and we welcome investments by Asian companies in the UK - not just those from advanced economies in the region, but also from countries that are still developing and expanding their horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have long historical connections with Asia and the Asia-pacific region. Of course, there are sister countries of the UK in the British Commonwealth, and her Majesty Queen Elizabeth is already in Australia for the Commonwealth heads of Government meeting. The Commonwealth is a force for peace and prosperity, and holds a special place in British hearts for its traditions and spirit of harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also have long-held contacts with other countries in Asia, great and small. The English language, so widely spoken, is one of our key assets and one of our gifts to the world - even if so often spoken with an American accent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The themes of our meeting are sustainability, safety and efficiency. Each of these is critically important for the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to a green transport future is a major goal for us. We need to revitalize our economy after the shocks of recent times, but growth that ignores environmental responsibility is not, ultimately, sustainable. That is why we are investing heavily in such policies as the de-carbonisation of road transport through advance technologies, and pushing for stringent measures to control emissions from aviation and shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also tackling our remaining air pollution hot spots - a problem which particularly affects rapidly growing cities in Asia, and which harms the health of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety is also a primary concern. For many years the UK has been a world leader in road safety. Our roads are the safest in the world, alongside Sweden and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday I shall have the privilege of visiting the Tangyuan middle school in Chengdu, which was re-built after the terrible earthquake with money given by one of our famous British companies, BP. I shall talk to the students about British road safety practices and philosophy - my own small contribution to helping prevent deaths and injuries from traffic accidents in Chengdu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I should also pay tribute to the unbreakable spirit of people in Asia in the face of Natural Disasters. The British people have been moved by the resilience of Asian communities - in China, Japan, Pakistan and elsewhere - when disaster strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and final theme of our meeting is the promotion of seamless travel, both for goods and people. This is another shared goal for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just about advanced technologies and systems, It is also about reducing barriers and allowing free and fair competition. I would love to see my government’s new ‘Red Tape challenge’, which is identifying hundreds of outdated or burdensome regulations for the scrap heap, being replicated around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainability, safety and efficiency. Three concepts which my country supports fully. We look forward to working with our European and Asian partners, both public and private sector, in our quest to make these concepts a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
