<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recently updated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-29T13:39:54+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8138</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:39:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:39:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/sale-of-trust-ports--4"/>
    <title>Sale of Trust Ports</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 3 August 2011, I announced the criteria that the government will consider particularly relevant to the appropriateness of the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales under the Ports Act 1991. This followed the consultation that I announced on 16 May 2011 and which closed on 27 June. I regret that it was not possible to announce this first by written ministerial statement to the House, but I did not wish to delay consideration of the application by Dover Harbour Board for a transfer scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware that Dover Harbour Board has now considered the criteria, intends to proceed with its application for a transfer scheme under the Ports Act 1991, and proposes to submit a new set of documents containing a further elaboration of its scheme for decision by the Minister of State under the new criteria. If interested parties would find it useful and seek my department’s assistance, we would be happy to consider ways in which properly to facilitate discussions on all the options before the Dover Harbour Board submits its elaborated proposal. I should make clear that the decision minister would take no part in such discussions and would continue to perform her statutory functions in an objective, impartial manner whatever the outcome of any such discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following paragraphs set out the revised policy which the Secretary of State expects to follow when considering an application under the Ports Act 1991 for the sale of a major trust port in England or Wales. This covers the consideration of any proposal for a transfer scheme submitted under section 9 or 10 of the 1991 Act, together with the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions in respect of the subsequent sale of the port to which the scheme relates. The Secretary of State also intends to have particular regard to the policy considerations set out below before making a transfer scheme himself under section 12 of the 1991 Act or subsequently approving the sale of a port to which such a scheme relates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="essential-criteria"&gt;1. Essential criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation - the Secretary of State will not approve an application for the sale of a trust port under the 1991 Act unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an enduring and significant level of community participation in the port. Such participation could take a variety of forms, but must include the ability to influence the port’s long term development and may include the right to receive a share in the profits of the port, or the future increase in its value. It does not necessarily require a community role in the operation of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future investment in, and development of, the port - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to deliver an ownership model with the capability and access to capital to meet future investment needs and to exploit development potential of the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair price - the Secretary of State will not approve an application unless the sale is considered likely to represent good value for money, having regard not only to Exchequer proceeds and market conditions, but also to other benefits including those to the community and the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair competition - the Secretary of State will not approve an application that is likely to deliver an ownership model which results in unsatisfactory levels of competition in the relevant sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="highly-desirable-criteria"&gt;2. Highly desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport networks- It is highly desirable for an application to be likely to deliver an ownership model which will cause the port to be operated so as to contribute to reliable, resilient and efficient transport networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sale process - It is highly desirable that the sale should be conducted in such a way as to give all bona fide prospective purchasers a fair and equitable opportunity to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="desirable-criteria"&gt;3. Desirable criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employee involvement - It is desirable for an application to be likely to deliver port employee participation in the ownership of the port, such as the right to receive equity shares or a share in its future success*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*This is without prejudice to the Ports Act 1991 section 5(3) requirement to have particular regard to the desirability of encouraging the disposal of the whole or a substantial part of the equity share capital of the successor company to managers or other persons employed by the port company etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/hammond-20110516"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-20110516i/"&gt;Sale of Trust Ports in England and Wales - Consultation on revised criteria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8171</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:25:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:25:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--36"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the second Transport Council of the Polish Presidency in Brussels on 12 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council reached political agreement on a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council establishing a single European railway area (Recast). At its first reading of the proposal on 16 November the European Parliament made amendments which differed significantly from the council’s general approach adopted at the June Transport Council. However, the political agreement text only incorporates those amendments that do not alter the general approach, and are acceptable to the UK. The commission hopes a 2nd reading deal can be struck with the European Parliament under the Danish presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council agreed a partial general approach on a draft regulation amending regulation 3821/85 on recording equipment in road transport. This proposal would amend the specification for tachographs, which measure hours spent at the wheel by commercial lorry and bus drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council also agreed a general approach on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council amending Directive 2008/106/EC of the European Parliament and of the council on the minimum level of training of seafarers to bring the extant directive into line with the latest International Maritime Organization rules; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the accelerated phasing-in of double-hull or equivalent design requirements for single-hull oil tankers (Recast). The amendments reflect changes to the international regime for tankers adopted at the International Maritime Organization between 2002 and 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The council noted a progress report on a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on union guidelines for the development of the Trans-European Transport Network. This item generated substantial discussion. I intervened to acknowledge the importance of good cross-border infrastructure for the single market, but expressed concern about binding obligations proposed and the financial and administrative burdens they would place on member states at a time when fiscal constraints are substantial and also stressed the need for member states’ to retain their responsibility for planning decisions, processes and implementation. On the proposed increase to the TEN-T budget I said budgetary restraint must be the priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under any other business, the commission presented its new proposals on a ‘better airport package’ which cover a recast of the slot allocation regulation, and revisions to the current directives on ground handling and noise which are intended to address issues of capacity, growth, environmental concerns and competitiveness. The proposals on ground handling and noise have been recast as (directly applicable) regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission reported on the European aviation safety management system and air cargo security action plan. I intervened in strong support of the European aviation safety management system and to request that the commission report back on progress at a future transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commission, at the request of Finland, reported on the current state of play with regards to the aviation EU emissions trading system. There had been three main developments since the June Transport Council: the US House of Representatives had approved a Bill that would prohibit US airlines from complying with &lt;abbr title="emissions trading system"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt;; there had been political messages against &lt;abbr title="emissions trading system"&gt;ETS&lt;/abbr&gt; emerging from the International Civil Aviation Organization council in November; and President Obama had specifically raised the issue at the EU/US summit on 28 November, noting the need to avoid confrontation. The commission’s assessment was that while international opposition was strong, so was the EU response. The commission acknowledged there still could be a challenge in &lt;abbr title="International Civil Aviation Organization"&gt;ICAO&lt;/abbr&gt; under the Chicago Convention, and that it was important to understand what forms retaliatory action could take. Following a legal challenge from the US Air Transport Association and 3 US airlines the European Court of Justice will deliver its judgement on the case on 21 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antonio Tajani, commissioner responsible for industry and entrepreneurship, updated ministers on recent developments within the Galileo programme and indicated that since the successful launch of the first two satellites in October the system was now up and running with real momentum behind it. The commission also presented their proposed regulation on Galileo governance and exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the council, I met ministers from Finland, and Ireland, the German State Secretary, and the Northern Irish Transport Minister to discuss items on the Transport Council agenda, in particular TEN-T. In a separate discussion after Transport Council, I exchanged views on TEN-T and better regulation with the Siim Kallas, the Transport Commissioner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK did not participate in the vote on one item on the A point list, namely Article 81 based council decision authorising the EU to accede to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention relating to the carriage of passengers and their luggage by sea. The UK has however subsequently notified its intention to opt-in to the council decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish delegation presented the work programme of their forthcoming presidency of the EU. The incoming Danish presidency’s overarching aim in the transport sector will be ‘green growth’ and they will take forward work on current Council dossiers. For example, they will be seeking to reach a 2nd reading agreement with the European Parliament on the recast of the first railway package. They will also commence work on proposals included in the recently published commission work programme such as the airport package and the proposals on driving licences and the satellite navigation programmes as well as on an expected proposal on enforcement of the maritime labour convention. Their main priorities are the TEN-T guidelines and the airport package, especially ground handling and noise reduction proposals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8721</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T13:04:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T13:04:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-draft-ports-national-policy-statement-and-associated-documents"/>
    <title>The draft ports national policy statement and associated documents</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport published this consultation document on 9 November 2009 in order to invite views on the draft National Policy Statement for ports and the accompanying documents listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation document explained the context of the &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and set out the key policies. The consultation period for the draft National Policy Statement closed on 15 February 2010. The responses are now being carefully considered and the department will publish a summary of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; has been under parliamentary scrutiny and the Transport Select Committee published a report to the House in March (HC 217).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State will lay a response before Parliament in due course, as required by s.9(5) Planning Act 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decisions"&gt;Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24 October 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/national-policy-statement-for-ports/"&gt;National Policy Statement for Ports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="consultation-documents"&gt;Consultation documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110131091024/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/consultation.pdf"&gt;Developing a Ports National Policy Statement consultation document (PDF - 510 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173318/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/consultation-welsh.pdf"&gt;Developing a Ports National Policy Statement consultation document - Welsh language (PDF - 142 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background-documents"&gt;Background documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/cardiff-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Event Cardiff 7/12/09 (PDF - 41 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/leeds-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Event Leeds 10/12/09 (PDF - 40 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/london-nps.pdf"&gt;Ports &lt;abbr title="National Policy Statement"&gt;NPS&lt;/abbr&gt; event London 14/1/10 (PDF - 58 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 22 March 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/npsports.pdf"&gt;Draft National Policy Statement for Ports (PDF - 871 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp1.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 1 Scoping Report (PDF - 565 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp2.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 2 - AoS Phase 1 Assessment (PDF - 342 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp-3.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 3 - AoS Phase 2 Assessment (PDF - 397 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp4.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 4 - AoS Phase 3 Assessment (PDF - 331 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/aosapp5.pdf"&gt;Appraisal of Sustainability (AoS) - Appendix 5 - AoS Phase 4 Assessment (PDF - 491 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110203173348/http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/closed/portsnps/appropriateassessment.pdf"&gt;Appropriate Assessment (PDF - 2048 KB)&lt;/a&gt;, 9 November 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8779</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-transposition-of-directive-2008-57ec-on-the-interoperability-of-the-rail-system"/>
    <title>The transposition of Directive 2008/57EC on the interoperability of the rail system</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents set out the government’s final proposals for implementing Directive 2008/57RC on the interoperability of the rail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents seek stakeholder’s views on how we implement the requirements of the Directive including proposed draft Regulations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:191:0001:0045:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G1 - EC Directive 2008-57-EC (Interoperability Recast)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:108:0004:0019:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G2 - EC Regulation 352-2009 (CSM Risk Assessment)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:273:0012:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G3 - EC Directive 2009-131 (Interoperability Annex VII)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:341:0001:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G4 - EC Decision 965-20095 (Amenments to Annex V11)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:326:0011:0024:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G5- EC Decision 1158-2010 (CSM Safety Certificate)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:327:0013:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G6 - EU Decision 1169-2010 (CSM Safety Authorisation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:043:0033:0054:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G7 - EU Decision 107-2011 (Common Specification for NVR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0008:0009:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G8 - EC Regulation 201-2011 (Declaration of Conformity)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0021:0028:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G9 - EU Directive 18-2011 (Amending Annexes 11,V &amp;amp; V1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:063:0022:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G10 - EC Decision 155-2011(Reference Document)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:256:FULL:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G11 - EC Decision 633-2011 (Specification for infrastructure register)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:095:0001:0029:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex H - EC recommendation 217-2011 Authorisation for placing into srervice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8121</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:24:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:24:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--35"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the second Transport Council of the Hungarian Presidency in Luxembourg on 16 June 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council reached a general approach on a directive which recasts the 2001 first rail package. The 2001 legislation set the initial framework for a single European rail market, setting out principles for charging and access to the network. The present draft directive modifies the three 2001 directives. The presidency tabled a compromise text which was slightly amended at the council. The presidency then concluded that there was a qualified majority for a general approach. The text of the general approach is acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council also reached a general approach on the draft regulation amending regulation 1406/2002, which established the European Maritime Safety Agency. This amending regulation modifies and extends the tasks of the agency to bring them in line with recent international and EU developments in the maritime safety field. I set out the UK’s opposition to any staff or administrative cost increases for the agency, and was able to accept revised wording on agency resources, which addressed our concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council debated the European Commission’s recent white paper, ‘Roadmap to a single European transport area - towards a competitive and resource efficient transport system’, which was issued in March. The council debate centred on a number of questions put by the presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The white paper aims to increase the sustainability and competitiveness of the sector while moving towards a fully integrated transport network. In doing so, the commission aims to cut carbon emissions from transport by 60% by 2050 (compared to 1990 levels). Member states broadly agreed that the transport sector has to make an adequate contribution to the achievement of the medium and long-term climate change targets. I explained that, while supporting the broad thrust of the ten goals in the white paper, the UK has some concerns on the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not in favour of having targets for their own sake, and do not think that it is practical or desirable to have a multiplicity of goals and targets. Furthermore, we do not support sector specific targets, which would constrain our progress on carbon reduction within the economy as a whole. Wherever targets are set, we believe that they must be realistic and supported by robust evidence and cost impact analysis. I also joined others in proposing that we work internationally to negotiate similar commitments with all of the global partners, in the framework of international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stressed that the EU should focus on actions that need to be undertaken at EU level, and where there was no such case, it should be left to Member States and local authorities to act. I also welcomed, with support from some other ministers, the commission’s commitment to undertake thorough impact assessments for any actions. I urged the commission to consider the importance of reducing the overall burden of regulation, to help our businesses and the budgetary constraints that we all face, as it takes forward the white paper proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Council conclusions were adopted on EU inland waterway transport, inviting the commission to launch a project to continue support for an existing inland waterway programme, which is designed to encourage modal shift of freight from road to inland waterways, and to bring forward proposals for a follow-on programme. The conclusions are acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted a decision on the signing and conclusion of an agreement with the intergovernmental organisation for International Carriage by Rail on the EU accession to the convention concerning international carriage by rail of 9 May 1980, as amended by the Vilnius Protocol of 3 June 1999. The decision is acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council adopted two decisions in the area of aviation external relations, both of which were acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first decision authorised the commission to open negotiations with Moldova on a comprehensive air transport agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was a decision on the signature of an air transport agreement between the EU and Brazil. Ministers pre-signed the agreement in the margins of the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among any other business items, the commission reported on air cargo security work which has been carried out in pursuit of the action plan endorsed by ministers at the December 2010 justice and home affairs and transport councils. They were disappointed that a proposal to strengthen EU inbound air cargo security had been narrowly defeated in the June Regulatory Committee, and called on ministers from member states which voted against or abstained to rethink their position. I joined Germany in expressing strong support for the commission, and called for work to continue on the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under any other business, the commission reported on work to deal with the impact of volcanic ash on the EU aviation sector and on recent developments in implementing the Single European Sky. On volcanic ash, I underlined the importance of developing the existing methodology and modelling, and increasing pressure on equipment manufacturers for engine tolerance levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the margins of the council, I met ministers from France, Germany, Ireland and the Netherlands to discuss the work on volcanic ash. In a separate discussion, I exchanged views on better regulation with the Netherlands minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK abstained on one item on the A point list, namely the adoption of a council decision on the conclusion of a memorandum of cooperation between the EU and the International Civil Aviation Organisation. This reflects our general need to be vigilant regarding the balance between member states’ and EU competence in United Nation bodies and other international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8762</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:17:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/amending-regulation-8-of-the-local-authorities-traffic-orders-exemptions-for-disabled-persons-england-regulations-2000"/>
    <title>Amending Regulation 8 of the Local Authorities' Traffic Orders (Exemptions for Disabled Persons) (England) Regulations 2000</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on amending one aspect of the legislation which covers the Blue Badge parking concessions. The amendment seeks to put beyond doubt the fact that local authorities are not required to allow Blue Badge holders to park in loading bays or on yellow lines when there is a ban on loading or unloading in force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/8951</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-the-transport-elements-of-the-renewable-energy-directive"/>
    <title>Implementation of the transport elements of the Renewable Energy Directive</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Energy Directive (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Energy Directive"&gt;RED&lt;/abbr&gt;) requires the UK to ensure that 10% of the energy used in transport is from renewable sources in 2020, as well as requiring the introduction of mandatory sustainability criteria for biofuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of responses we received to the consultation on the government’s proposals to implement the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Energy Directive"&gt;RED&lt;/abbr&gt; through making amendments to the Renewable Transport Fuels Obligation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//news/statements/baker-20111107"&gt;Statement: Responding to the consultation on the Renewable Energy Directive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//topics/sustainable/biofuels/"&gt;Biofuels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//consultations/?tag=biofuel"&gt;Biofuel consultations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//publications/?tag=biofuel"&gt;Biofuel publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk//topics/sustainable/biofuels/rtfo/"&gt;Renewable Transport Fuels Obligation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8164</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:13:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:13:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--34"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the second Transport Council of the Polish presidency which will take place in Brussels on 12 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presidency will be seeking a political agreement on a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council establishing a single European railway area (recast). The European Parliament had its first reading of this proposal on 16 November. Many of the Parliament’s amendments differed significantly from the council’s general approach text. Following discussion at the one council working group meeting that took place following the first reading it is expected the presidency will seek a political agreement, which incorporates only those amendments that do not alter the general approach, and thus will be acceptable to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council will be asked to reach a partial general approach on a draft regulation amending Regulation 3821/85 on recording equipment in road transport and amending regulation 561/2006. The UK supports elements of the proposal that aim to reduce burdens on business. I will want to resist provisions that might impose unnecessary burdens or additional costs on government or Industry, including the proposal to ban operators from installing and calibrating tachographs in their own vehicles. I will be seeking to minimise the risks of increases in costs and burdens via future decisions taken by the European commission (‘the commission’) under a delegated or implementing act, by pressing for clearly specified constraints on the scope of proposed action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council will be asked to reach a general approach on a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the council amending Directive 2008/106/EC of the European Parliament and of the council on the minimum level of training of seafarers. Although we would question the merit of a European database of seafarer certification, we have negotiated important changes which would require the anonymisation of seafarer personal data to be a mandatory pre-condition of the obligation to transfer data. We have also negotiated changes to align the text more closely with the deadline for the implementation of the amendments to the International Convention on Standards of Training, Certification and Watchkeeping for Seafarers to avoid placing additional burdens on EU member states which would put our flags at a competitive disadvantage with other countries’ flags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council will be asked to reach a general approach on a proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on the accelerated phasing-in of double-hull or equivalent design requirements for single-hull oil tankers (Recast). The UK is in favour of the general approach proposed for the draft recast of these regulations which brings European law in line with amendments agreed at the International Maritime Organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be a progress report on a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the council on union guidelines for the development of the Trans-European Transport Network. The UK recognises that the TEN-T Network should be focused on projects that carry clear EU-added value and should be supported by guidelines on projects seeking EU funding. We do not support standards and requirements being expanded to the wider TEN-T Network on a mandatory basis. We believe that decisions on national projects to be prioritised for development and investment should remain with the member states and the transport operators concerned. Furthermore, the UK is keen to ensure that this proposal does not impose any additional financial or administrative burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main items under any other business include the commission’s presentation on its proposal for an airport package, the implementation and exploitation of European satellite navigation systems and the connecting Europe facility. The commission will also provide information on the European aviation safety management system and air cargo security action plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Polish presidency will provide information on the ministerial conference on Eastern Partnership held in Krakow on 24-25 October 2011 and on the high level conference on the implementation of the single European sky and its extension to third countries held in Warsaw on 28 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish delegation will also provide information on the work programme of their forthcoming Presidency of the EU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8207</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T11:57:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T11:57:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/high-speed-rail--33"/>
    <title>High Speed Rail</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of this month I will receive HS2 Ltd’s route and station advice for high speed rail lines to Leeds, Manchester and Heathrow. This is an important next step in our aspiration for a truly national high speed network, as set out in our programme for government. Phase 2 of High Speed Two will spread the benefits of high speed rail further across the country, increasing capacity and enhancing connectivity by extending high speed rail lines to Leeds and Manchester and connecting other major conurbations in the North and in Scotland through seamless transition onto the existing network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fulfilment of its remit, HS2 Ltd’s advice will include options for stations in Manchester, Leeds, South Yorkshire, the East Midlands and at Heathrow Airport, as well as advice on the case and potential locations for additional stations. It will also cover the impact of Phase 2 of the network in releasing capacity on the Midland and East Coast main lines, as well as further extending the benefits of released capacity within the west coast corridor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will consider this advice objectively and in detail over the coming months, and I intend to publish it in the autumn together with a government response setting out initial preferred route and station options. An important part of this process will be to consider the views of delivery partners in the cities where HS2 stations may be located, including any underpinning evidence which they have identified. Understanding local desires and plans for development will be crucial in helping me reach initial preferences for station locations. I am particularly keen to ensure that the network best supports the economic potential of the cities and regions it serves, through well-integrated station locations that build on local and regional plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimising the risk of blight is a serious consideration, and it is for this reason that I expect to publish HS2 Ltd’s advice once I have reached a view on routes and station options. Publishing a detailed range of possible options without an indication of the government’s preferences would generate unnecessary and harmful blight across areas that ultimately might never be affected by the lines. I will be working with national environmental stakeholders to discuss key sustainability issues and how best to consult on lines of route going forward to help meet the needs of different stakeholders and the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following publication, the input of interested parties, including MPs and their constituents, will be valuable to help further develop the proposals that will go forward for subsequent formal public consultation. Only once a full public consultation has been launched and completed will any decisions be reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When preferred route options are published in the autumn we will consult on and introduce an exceptional hardship scheme to assist property owners impacted by the proposals. Further, in order to reduce uncertainty for those affected by the proposals, and to ensure that the benefits for passengers and business of a national high speed rail network are realised as soon as possible, I have asked my officials to explore options for bringing forward formal public consultation on Phase 2 of High Speed 2 to 2013, and I will set out my proposed timetable later this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/8094</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T11:53:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T11:53:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council--32"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the first Transport Council of the Hungarian Presidency, which will take place in Brussels on 31 March 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a progress report and policy debate on the draft regulation amending regulation 1406/2002, which established the European Maritime Safety Agency. The proposed amendment gives the agency several new, largely technical, tasks. In principle, the United Kingdom would be able to support the proposals, subject to the commission delivering the additional funding required through a programme of reprioritisation of the current European Union budget. It is also important for the UK to ensure that the extension of the agency’s marine pollution response capabilities to cover offshore oil and gas installations is at the request of an affected state only, and that any involvement in the analysis of the safety of these installations explicitly excludes activities or requirements related to the exploration or exploitation of mineral resources by means of a well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be two agenda items on global navigation satellite systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a progress report and the council will be asked to reach a general approach on a decision on rules for access to the public regulated service of the Galileo system. I believe the text to be tabled for general approach addresses the UK’s earlier concerns covering costs, the framework for the manufacture of PRS receivers and associated material, and security standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a policy debate and the council will be asked to agree conclusions following the commission’s recent mid-term review of the European programmes. The government is deeply disappointed and concerned that the full Galileo programme cannot now be delivered within the budget or timescale agreed in 2007. A robust assessment of all options is needed in light of this. The government considers that the programme should respect the 2007 budget by reducing its level of ambition. The draft council conclusions do not prejudice the forthcoming negotiations on the next multi-annual financial framework for the EU and urge the commission to continue its cost analysis in order to identify options for cost reduction. They go on to underline the council’s wish that the cost analysis should result in cost savings. Accordingly, I expect to be able to agree to the conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council will be asked to adopt two decisions in the area of aviation external relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a decision on the signature and provisional application of a memorandum of cooperation between the community and the International Civil Aviation Organisation.  I intend to abstain on this proposal as I consider that it is necessary to put down a marker that the UK is concerned about the principle of member state sovereignty in international organisations and cautious about any proposals which could have the effect of enhancing the role of the EU at the expense of member states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is a decision authorising the commission to negotiate with Switzerland on an amendment to the existing air transport agreement. This will further remove barriers to market access on the basis of full application by Switzerland of the EU regulatory framework. The UK is supportive of the proposed negotiating mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council may be asked to adopt a position on a decision concerning the accession of the EU to the protocol of 2002 to the Athens Convention relating to the carriage of passengers and their luggage by sea, 1974. A number of issues still need to be resolved. I will report to the House on this matter if it is considered at the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be raising two issues under any other business. The first is the importance of ensuring that the forthcoming review of European air quality legislation takes full account of transport issues The second is the need to make swift progress in delivering an enhanced regulatory regime for air cargo security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, as expected, the commission’s new white paper on transport policy is published before the council, the commission will give a presentation on it under &lt;abbr title="Any Other Business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt;. A debate on the white paper will follow at a later council, when member states have given full consideration to it. Also under &lt;abbr title="Any Other Business"&gt;AOB&lt;/abbr&gt;, the commission will report on the follow-up to the volcanic ash crisis of 2010, looking at the wider scope of crisis management and EU methodology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
