<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/publications</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent publications</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T18:44:36+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15719</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:44:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:44:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/firefighters-pension-scheme-employee-contributions"/>
    <title>Firefighters' pension scheme: employee contributions</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes to the firefighters’ pension schemes in England are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased levels of employee contribution rates, effective from 1 April 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the introduction of tiered contribution levels, so that higher earners will pay a higher rate of contribution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;different levels of increase for the firefighters’ pension scheme (1992) and new firefighters’ pension scheme (2006)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the specific handling of contributions for retained and part-time firefighters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15764</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:38:32+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/draft-national-planning-policy-framework"/>
    <title>Draft National Planning Policy Framework</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft National Planning Policy Framework was published for consultation. This is a key part of the government’s reforms to make the planning system less complex and more accessible, and to promote sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15850</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:27:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:27:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementing-the-mobile-homes-act-1983-on-local-authority-gypsy-and-traveller-sites"/>
    <title>Implementing the Mobile Homes Act 1983 on local authority Gypsy and Traveller sites</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Housing and Regeneration Act 2008 will apply the Mobile Homes Act 1983 to local authority Gypsy and Traveller sites. This consultation document sought views on a number of issues around implementing the 1983 Act on these sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15804</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:23:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/development-rights-for-small-scale-renewable-and-low-carbon-energy-technologies-and-electric-vehicle-charging-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Development rights for small-scale renewable and low-carbon energy technologies and electric vehicle charging infrastructure</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sought views on government proposals to introduce permitted development rights for small scale renewable and low carbon technologies in domestic and non-domestic settings. It also sought views on introducing permitted development rights and deemed advertisement consent in relation to electric vehicle charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/12712</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/offering-suitable-housing-to-homeless-people"/>
    <title>Offering suitable housing to homeless people</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 enables local authorities to end the main homelessness duty by arranging an offer of suitable accommodation in the private rented sector, without requiring the applicant’s agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed draft Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012 sets out those circumstances in which accommodation used for the private rented sector offer to end the main homelessness duty is not to be regarded as suitable.  It also looks at how best to strengthen requirements in relation to location and suitability, when local authorities secure accommodation for the use of households owed duties under the homelessness legislation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15700</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T17:18:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T17:18:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/what-can-a-mayor-do-for-your-city--3"/>
    <title>What can a mayor do for your city?</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to creating directly elected mayors in the 12 largest English cities, subject to confirmatory referendums and full scrutiny by elected councillors. This consultation paper sought views on the government’s proposed approach for giving powers to mayors elected in the 12 cities following the referendums held in May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15362</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-traveller-sites"/>
    <title>Planning for traveller sites</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation on the government’s draft planning policy for traveller sites ended on 3 August, and a new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be published as soon as possible, following due consideration of the consultation responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also consulting on the draft &lt;em&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/em&gt; until 17 October. As part of this consultation, we welcome views on the consistency of the draft Framework with the draft planning policy for traveller sites, and any other comments about the government’s plans to incorporate planning policy on traveller sites into the final National Planning Policy Framework. The new planning policy statement for traveller sites will be reviewed in the light of all comments received and incorporated into the final National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the consultation on the National Planning Policy Framework, the government would welcome responses to the following question:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/15361</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/business-rates-retention-technical-details"/>
    <title>Business rates retention: technical details</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This technical consultation builds on the proposals in the government response to consultation published in December 2011, and on the statements of intent published on 17 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seeks views on a range of detailed technical issues concerning practical implementation of those proposals, particularly focusing on how the Government proposes to calculate local authority start-up funding allocations, baseline funding levels as well as other parameters which are required for the setup and operation of the business rates retention scheme. As such, it will be of particular interest to local authority finance departments responsible for implementing and running the new scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 2 focuses on establishing baseline funding levels for each local authority, as well as the methodology for allocating Revenue Support Grant which will be paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The December 2011 consultation response stated that, in the interests of maintaining as much stability as possible, these would be calculated on the basis of the 2012/13 formula grant process with updated data sets and some limited technical updates. This section details proposals for making those calculations and includes exemplifications of the proposed options. It also covers transfers and adjustments to the local government spending controls total and includes proposed methodologies for incorporating those separate grant funding streams being included in the business rates retention scheme from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 3 outlines other parameters which need to be determined when setting up the business rates retention system - particularly in relation to establishing individual local authority business rate baselines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 4 details proposals on how the system will operate once it has been set up. It is arranged chronologically, to give local authorities the best idea of how the scheme will operate year-by-year. The calculation of levy and safety net payments is set out in this section. The safety net will fall within the 7.5%-10% range and funded by a 1:1 levy as already announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 5 covers the proposed approach to closing the 2012-13 national non domestic rating account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has published a number of documents to supplement the technical consultation on business rates retention. These documents set out the proposed approach for the London share of business rates and an alternative option for funding the New Homes Bonus. In addition, the Department has published supplementary information on proportionate shares as well as population data. These documents can be found below. Responses to additional consultation questions should be sent as part of the responses to the technical consultation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13413</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/making-it-easier-to-set-up-new-town-and-parish-councils-discussion-paper"/>
    <title>Making it easier to set up new town and parish councils: discussion paper</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government wants to make it easier to set up new town and parish councils. This discussion paper presents a range of proposals that would help achieve this. We would like your views on these, as well as any other comments or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13411</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/business-rates-retention-draft-regulations"/>
    <title>Business rates retention draft regulations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation invites comments on drafts of the main regulations that will underpin the business rates retention scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of these regulations in draft is intended to give local authorities and interested parties further clarity about the detailed implementation of the scheme, and the opportunity to comment on the draft regulations to help ensure they work as intended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13412</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/improving-local-government-transparency"/>
    <title>Improving local government transparency</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the publication of the ‘Code of recommended practice for local authorities on Data Transparency’ in September 2011, ministers would now like to make the code a legal requirement via regulations, subject to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has the power to enforce the code through regulations via the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1980/65/contents" title="Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980"&gt;Local Government Planning and Land Act 1980&lt;/a&gt;, Section 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers wish to hear from all those local authorities listed in paragraph 4 of the code. They would also like to hear from relevant bodies, open data experts, developers, citizen activists and other interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13410</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-east-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the East Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the East Midlands Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the East Midlands Regional Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13408</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-south-east-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the South East regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the South East Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the South East Plan which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the South East Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices. This includes whether or not to retain the Oxfordshire structure plan policy H2, covering development at Upper Heyford, until a revised plan is adopted by the relevant local planning authority (Cherwell District Council).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13407</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:13+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/amendments-to-the-new-firefighters-pension-scheme-2006-automatic-enrolment"/>
    <title>Amendments to the new firefighters' pension scheme 2006: automatic enrolment</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation covers amendments to the new firefighters’ pension scheme (England), as set out in the Firefighters’ Pension Scheme (England) Order 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so that fire and rescue authorities can comply with their duties for automatic enrolment under workplace pension reform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13406</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13405</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-when-dwellings-should-not-be-liable-to-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: when dwellings should not be liable to the empty homes premium</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Local Government Finance Bill includes provisions that will allow a billing authority to charge an empty homes premium to provide a stronger incentive to get homes back into productive use and remove the blight of such properties on local neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premium was subject to a consultation, ‘Technical Reforms to Council Tax’, which ended on 29 December 2011. The government published its response on 28 May 2012, which confirmed its intention to proceed with the premium and stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will not be payable until a dwelling has been empty and unfurnished for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the maximum premium that an authority will be able to charge will be 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the government’s proposals on exceptions to the premium: dwellings which may otherwise be liable for the premium, but which are subject to circumstances that mean that it would not be appropriate for it to apply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13403</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/protocol-on-government-intervention-action-on-fire-and-rescue-authorities-in-england"/>
    <title>Protocol on government intervention action on fire and rescue authorities in England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultation on guidance on statements of assurance for fire and rescue authorities in England and Protocol on Government intervention action for fire and rescue authorities in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on the revision of the protocol on Government intervention action and applies to fire and rescue authorities in England only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13404</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-yorkshire-and-the-humber-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the Yorkshire and the Humber regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revoking the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the previous environmental report for the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Regional Strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a standalone document that is intended to give reader an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the Yorkshire and Humber Plan and the Regional Economic Strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a compact disc. Please email requests to the &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;Environmental Assessment Team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13402</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/guidance-on-statements-of-assurance-for-fire-and-rescue-authorities-in-england"/>
    <title>Guidance on statements of assurance for fire and rescue authorities in England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultation on guidance on statements of assurance for fire and rescue authorities in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on ‘light-touch’ guidance on statements of assurance for fire and rescue authorities in England&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/13401</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-reforms-to-council-tax-caluclating-the-council-tax-base-with-the-empty-homes-premium"/>
    <title>Technical reforms to Council Tax: caluclating the Council Tax base with the empty homes premium</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation sets out the government’s proposals on how the Council Tax empty homes premium is to be included in the calculation of the Council Tax base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
