<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/publications</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent publications</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16388</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T12:28:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-west-midlands-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the West Midlands regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919194311/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationwmrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the West Midlands regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the West Midlands Plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16651</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/business-rates-retention-policy-statement"/>
    <title>Business rates retention: policy statement</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This policy statement provides early confirmation of the government’s policy decisions on the business rates retention scheme following the technical consultation that took place in the summer, and ahead of the provisional local government finance settlement which will constitute the government’s formal response to consultation. This policy statement, which includes an updated step-by-step guide to the scheme’s workings, will support local authorities in their preparations for smooth implementation of the business rates retention scheme from April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16632</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decision-letter-greater-manchester-light-rapid-transit-system"/>
    <title>Decision letter - Greater Manchester (Light Rapid Transit System) </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decision letter to authorise a modification to the route of an extension of the Metrolink system near Oldham Town Centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16627</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/contact-telephone-numbers-for-crosscountry-rail"/>
    <title>Contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry rail</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information request regarding geographical contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16458</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-port-security-regulations-2009-at-certain-ports"/>
    <title>Implementation of Port Security Regulations 2009 at certain ports</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Directive 2005/65/EC is to enhance security coordination in the wider area at certain ports. The directive requires the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designation of a port security authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointment of a port security officer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a port security risk assessment to be conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a port security plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft designation orders which we are are consulting on here append plan(s) outlining the area which the port security authority will have responsibility over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16495</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-statistics-contacts"/>
    <title>Department for Transport Statistics Contacts</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="general-enquiries"&gt;General enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

UK Department for Transport
&lt;br&gt;Transport Statistics
&lt;br&gt;Zone 2/27, Great Minster House
&lt;br&gt;33 Horseferry Road
&lt;br&gt;London
&lt;br&gt;SW1P 4DR
&lt;br&gt;Phone: 0300 330 3000
&lt;br&gt;Fax: +44 (0)20 7944 2165
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:publicationgeneral.enq@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;publicationgeneral.enq@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aviation-statistics"&gt;Aviation statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Aviation and airport statistics, International Passenger Survey, origins and destinations of international freight traffic, Transport Indicators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:aviation.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;aviation.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3088&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bus-and-coach-statistics"&gt;Bus and coach statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Bus and coach statistics, light rail and tram statistics, taxi statistics, parking and disabled parking (blue) badge statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:bus.statistics@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;bus.statistics@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3094&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="international-comparisons"&gt;International comparisons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Transport statistics for EU and other international bodies, international comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:inter.transport.comparisons@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;inter.transport.comparisons@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3088&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="maritime-statistics"&gt;Maritime statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Maritime statistics, Merchant Fleet statistics, Sea passenger statistics, Port traffic, coastwise and inland waterways freight statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 4131&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-rail-travel-survey"&gt;National Rail Travel Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on the National Rail Travel Survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 8874&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on National Travel Survey, other personal travel data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;national.travelsurvey@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 6594&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="public-attitudes-to-transport"&gt;Public attitudes to transport&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on travel plans and travel awareness campaigns, attitudes towards transport policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:attitudes.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;attitudes.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 4892&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="publications-and-it-unit"&gt;Publications and IT unit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Transport Statistics internet site, statistical publications unit, Transport Statistics Great Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:publicationgeneral.enq@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;publicationgeneral.enq@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 4847&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rail-statistics"&gt;Rail statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk"&gt;The Office of Rail Regulation&lt;/a&gt; has responsibility for general rail statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:rstats@orr.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rstats@orr.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44(0)20 7282 2192/2196&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-accident-statistics"&gt;Road accident statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Road accidents, vehicle speeds, car safety, drink-driving, inter-modal passenger safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:roadacc.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;roadacc.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 6595&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-freight-statistics"&gt;Road freight statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Road freight, Continuing Survey of Road Goods Transport, light goods vehicle survey, survey of International Road Haulage, pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:roadfreight.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;roadfreight.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3093&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-maintenance-statistics"&gt;Road maintenance statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Highways maintenance statistics, National Road Maintenance Condition Survey, investment, highways expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:roadmaintenance.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;roadmaintenance.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 4746&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="road-traffic-statistics"&gt;Road traffic statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Road traffic statistics – production and analysis, manual traffic counts and road lengths surveys. Road traffic statistics – development, automatic traffic counts, weigh-in-motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:roadtraff.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;roadtraff.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3095&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sub-national-data"&gt;Sub-national data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Sub-national data, urban transport, transport employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:subnational.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;subnational.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 4746&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="vehicles-statistics"&gt;Vehicles statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information on Vehicle stock and new registrations, statistical advice to DVLA, VED evasion studies, vehicle taxation and fuel consumption, road track costs, environmental statistic, speed surveys in urban areas and on trunk roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:vehicles.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;vehicles.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone: +44 (0)20 7944 3077&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16489</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/right-to-buy-notice-in-reply-to-a-tenants-claim-rtb2"/>
    <title>Right to Buy: notice in reply to a tenant's claim (RTB2)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a council tenant applies to buy their home through the Right to Buy scheme, the council will send a notice (RTB2) within 4 weeks of receiving the completed application form (RTB1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will confirm if the tenant has the Right to Buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16427</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2012-in-england"/>
    <title>Council Taxbase 2012 in England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2008 to 2012 updating those &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/council-taxbase-2011-in-england"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt; previously issued on 16 November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="number-of-dwellings"&gt;Number of dwellings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In England there were 22.4 million dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list liable for council tax as at 10 September 2012. This is an increase of 1% compared with 2011 and an increase of 3% compared with 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of dwellings on the valuation list that are exempt from council tax increased by 2% compared with 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;35% of all exemptions from council tax are class C (short term vacant dwellings). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A further 27% of all exemptions are class M or N (student related exemptions). Of these, class M exemptions have increased by more than 48% in the period 2008 to 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of class L exemptions (unoccupied dwellings repossessed by a mortgage lender) again fell between September 2011 and September 2012 to 9,400, the four consecutive annual fall. There are now 6,500 (or 41%) fewer class L exemptions than the peak in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7.7 million dwellings were entitled to a discount as a result of being occupied by single adults. This represents 33% of all dwellings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.7 million Band A dwellings (50% of all dwellings liable to Band A council tax) were entitled to a single adults discount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The total number of dwellings on the Valuation Office valuation list in England as at 10 September 2012 was 23.2 million, an increase of 143,000, or 1% compared with 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="empty-properties"&gt;Empty properties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 2011 and 2012 the number of long-term empty dwellings subject to a discount fell by 28,000 (or 22%). In the same period the number of long-term empty dwellings not subject to a discount increased by 8,000 (or 5%). This gives a net reduction of 20,000, or 7%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2011 and 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of long term empty dwellings that were subject to a discount has fallen by 86,000, or 47%, between 2008 and 2012. In the same period the number of long term empty dwellings that do not receive a discount has increased by 18,000 or 13%. This gives a net reduction of 68,000, or 21%, in the total number of long term empty dwellings between 2008 and 2012. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since the introduction of the New Homes Bonus in the summer of 2010 a large number of authorities have taken the opportunity to review the empty properties and second homes in their area. A number have also altered the level of discount awarded with many abolishing the discount for empty properties altogether.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16424</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/national-non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-authorities-in-england-2011-12-update"/>
    <title>National non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England 2011-12 (update)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;An updated statistical release giving details of the national non-domestic rates collected by local authorities in England in 2011-12 was published on 20 November 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provided updated information on figures that were announced on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-domestic-rates-collected-by-local-councils-in-england-2011-to-2012"&gt;15 August 2012&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics release includes data from 2007-08 to 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points from the latest release are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the net rate yield (after allowances for changes in respect of previous years and reliefs) increased by 9.1% to £21 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contribution to the pool (net rate yield after allowances for collection costs including losses) also increased by 9.2% to £20.7 billion in 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;between 2007-08 and 2011-12 the contribution to the pool from the local lists increased by £3.5 billion or 21%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London accounts for 29% of the contribution to the national pool while having only 15% of the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16401</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-blackpool-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Blackpool Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16406</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/improvement-notice-issued-to-walsall-metropolitan-borough-council"/>
    <title>Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improvement notice issued to Walsall Metropolitan Borough Council by the Department for Education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16298</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/street-lighting"/>
    <title>Street lighting</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information response regarding the switching off of street lighting on sections of some roads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16370</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/model-ship-security-plan-templates"/>
    <title>Model ship security plan templates</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These model ship plans will help company and ship security officers to compile a ship security plan (SSP) under the International Ship and Port Facility Security (ISPS) Code, for agreement and verification by the Department for Transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents are cruise ship and ro-ro (roll-on/roll-off) passenger ferry templates. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/mcga07-home/shipsandcargoes/mcga-shipsregsandguidance/mcga_dops_maritimesecurity_mainpage/dops_ms-guidance/mcga_dops_msb_ssp/dops_msb__model_ship_security_plan.htm"&gt;template for use with cargo ships&lt;/a&gt; is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/"&gt;Maritime and Coastguard website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16331</id>
    <published>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/affordable-housing-starts-and-completions-funded-by-the-hca-and-the-gla-april-to-september-2012-13"/>
    <title>Affordable housing starts and completions funded by the HCA and the GLA - April to September 2012-13</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest statistics on affordable housing starts and completions funded by the Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) and the Greater London Authority (GLA) were released on Friday 16 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures show the supply of homes delivered under the accelerated land disposal programme, the 2011-15 affordable homes programme (including the affordable homes programme, empty homes, homelessness change, mortgage rescue and traveller pitch funding), the economic assets programme, firstbuy, the get Britain building programme, the kickstart housing delivery programme, the national affordable housing programme and the property and regeneration programme. Details about these programmes can be found in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/housing-statistics"&gt;HCA Housing statistics release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key points were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 1 April and 30 September 2012, there were 3,735 affordable housing starts on site delivered in England through programmes managed by the HCA and the GLA. This represents an increase of 678 per cent compared to the 480 (revised) started in the same period of the previous year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Between 1 April and 30 September 2012, there were 11,432 affordable housing completions delivered through programmes through programmes managed by the HCA and the GLA. This represents a decrease of 11 per cent compared to the 12,778 completed in the same period in the previous year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on the number of affordable homes delivered under the HCA affordable housing programmes is published twice a year. From April 2012, the Mayor of London has had strategic oversight of housing, regeneration and economic development in London. This means that the HCA no longer publish affordable housing starts and completions for London and this responsibility has been taken over by the GLA. DCLG combines data from the HCA and the GLA to publish six monthly affordable housing starts and completions delivered nationally under the affordable housing programmes of the HCA and GLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the HCA affordable housing statistics, see their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/housing-statistics"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the GLA affordable housing statistics, see their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://data.london.gov.uk/datastore/package/gla-affordable-housing-programme-outturn"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16257</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:56:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/technical-review-of-planning-appeal-procedures"/>
    <title>Technical review of planning appeal procedures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Published: 1 November 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is consulting on a set of proposals to make the planning appeals process faster and more transparent, improve consistency and certainty in decision taking timescales. The proposals will bring cost and time benefits for those appealing decisions and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16093</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/channel-tunnel-transposition-of-railway-safety-and-interoperability-directives"/>
    <title>Channel Tunnel: transposition of railway safety and interoperability directives</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking views on whether to transpose the requirements of 3 European directives on railway safety and interoperability so that these provisions are in force for the Channel Tunnel. In recognition of the Tunnel’s cross-border nature these we would like to incorporate the provisions of these railway safety and interoperability directives by making amendments to the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16258</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/right-to-buy-sales-in-england-2012-to-2013-quarters-1-and-2"/>
    <title>Right to buy sales in England: 2012 to 2013 - quarters 1 and 2</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents official statistics on the number of sales of dwellings under the right to buy scheme, as well as providing statistics on receipts resulting from those sales, and starts on site as part of the one-for-one replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local authorities sold an estimated 444 dwellings under the right to buy scheme in 2012-13 quarter 1. In this quarter local authorities received £24 million from right to buy sales, while 14 dwellings were started on site or acquired.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local authorities sold an estimated 1,043 dwellings under the right to buy scheme in 2012-13 quarter 2. In this quarter local authorities received £62 million from right to buy sales, while 234 dwellings were started on site or acquired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These statistics relate only to sales by local authorities under the right to buy scheme, excluding sales by registered providers under preserved right to buy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16457</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-regulated-agents-and-in-flight-suppliers"/>
    <title>Department for Transport regulated agents and in-flight suppliers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="contact-number-for-all-enquiries"&gt;Contact number for all enquiries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone: 0207 944 6430&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;transec.cargo@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="communication-with-cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Communication with Cargo and In-Flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could all non-urgent communication with inspectors, wherever possible, please be sent to their email addresses (listed below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cargo-and-in-flight-supplies-inspectors"&gt;Cargo and in-flight supplies inspectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christian Whitley, Team Leader Cargo and In-flight Supplies &lt;a href="mailto:Christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;christian.whitley@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daz Salmon &lt;a href="mailto:daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;daz.salmon@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gillian Stephens &lt;a href="mailto:gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;gillian.stephens@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Sidney &lt;a href="mailto:james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;james.sidney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jerry Koster &lt;a href="mailto:jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;jerry.koster@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin Gurney &lt;a href="mailto:martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;martin.gurney@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maurice Stearn &lt;a href="mailto:maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maurice.stearn@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carole Cousins &lt;a href="mailto:carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;carole.cousins@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="validation-and-known-consignors-scheme"&gt;Validation and Known Consignors Scheme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email all enquires to &lt;a href="mailto:current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;current.cargovalidations@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="correspondence"&gt;Correspondence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport  
&lt;br&gt;Transport Security Compliance  
&lt;br&gt;3rd Floor, Fry Building  
&lt;br&gt;2 Marsham Street  
&lt;br&gt;London, SW1P 4DF
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16254</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/social-housing-sales-in-england-2011-to-2012"/>
    <title>Social housing sales in England: 2011 to 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statistical release presents official statistics on the number of sales of existing social housing stock in England for 2011 to 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social housing sales include sales under right to buy, preserved right to buy, right to acquire, social homebuy, other outright or shared equity sales to tenants, and sales of existing stock to the private sector. The figures exclude sales through low cost home ownership schemes where these do not relate to existing social stock, i.e. sales of newly built homes for shared ownership or acquisitions of private sector homes for affordable home ownership. Intra-tenure transfers between social housing providers are also excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the release are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were an estimated 9,670 total social housing sales in England in 2011-12. This is an increase of 15% on 2010-11 but continues the low level of sales seen since 2008-09. The increase was entirely due to an increase in private registered provider sales; local authority sales were virtually unchanged.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were an estimated 3,720 right to buy sales in England in 2011-12 (38% of all sales), a 1% increase from 2010-11. Most (70%) right to buy sales were of local authority properties. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The average market value of a local authority property purchased through right to buy in 2011-12 was £100,040. Average capital receipts were £73,350 and the average discount was £26,690 per property. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registered provider sales in 2011-12 included 140 properties sold through the right to acquire scheme (compared to 200 in 2010-11) and 40 through social homebuy (compared to 110 in 2010-11).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A further 3,320 sales (34% of total sales) were disposals of registered provider properties to the private sector. Other shared equity and outright sales of existing stock accounted for the remaining sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These statistics relate to right to buy sales by local authorities and registered providers. The statistics include sales under the right to buy and preserved right to buy schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/16253</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/driver-certificate-of-professional-competence-cpc-statistics"/>
    <title>Driver Certificate of Professional Competence (CPC) statistics</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="about-these-statistics"&gt;About these statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These operational statistics about Driver Certificate of Professional (&lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt;) modules and training have not been designated as an official statistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics come from data held by the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;), and are compiled and published by staff in &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="information-you-cannot-find"&gt;Information you cannot find&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you cannot find the information you need, it may have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;published in &lt;a href="/government/publications?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;topics%5B%5D=all&amp;amp;departments%5B%5D=driving-standards-agency&amp;amp;publication_type=foi-releases" title="Responses to FOI requests"&gt;response to an Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designated as an &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/driving-tests-and-instructors-statistics" title="Official driving test statistics"&gt;official statistic&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.dft.gov.uk/foi/form/" title="Send an FOI request"&gt;send an &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; request&lt;/a&gt; if you still cannot find the information you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="information-that-cannot-be-released"&gt;Information that cannot be released&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; cannot send you information if it is part of an official statistic that has not yet been published. This is because the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/2998/contents/made" title="Pre-release Access to Official Statistics Order 2008"&gt;Pre-release Access to Official Statistics Order 2008&lt;/a&gt; limits access to official statistics until they are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="downloads"&gt;Downloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These older statistics are available from the The National Archives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2011-12.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2011 to 2012)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2010-11.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2010 to 2011)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2009-10.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2009 to 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa_conducted_module_4_cpc_pass_rate_09-10.pdf"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; module 4 pass rate (2009 to 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa-driver-cpc-statistics-2008-09.csv"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; periodic training, driver qualification cards and centre and course approvals (2008 to 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20121105135246/http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/dsa-practical-test-statistics-driver-cpc/dsa_conducted_module_4_cpc_pass_rate_08-09.pdf"&gt;Driver &lt;abbr title="Certificate of Professional Competence"&gt;CPC&lt;/abbr&gt; module 4 pass rate (2008 to 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
