<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/publications</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government</title>
  <subtitle>Recent publications</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56774</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-ec-392-2009"/>
    <title>Consultation on the implementation of EU Regulation (EC) 392/2009</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the UK’s draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation gives effect, within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention to create parity for the passenger shipping industry and help ensure that UK citizens have access to the same levels of compensation when travelling between two different &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states. Furthermore, it increases the limits of liabilities for death or personal injuries to passengers being carried by sea; requires carriers to have compulsory insurance, and provides claimants with the right of taking direct action against the insurers. The intended effect is to provide an enhanced framework of compensation in the event of death or personal injury to a passenger, or the loss or damage to luggage when travelling on a sea journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation also brings into scope certain domestic passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56767</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/construction-tender-price-indices-tpis-notes-and-definitions"/>
    <title>Construction tender price indices (TPIs) notes and definitions</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tender Price Index of Public Sector Building Non Housing (PUBSEC) measures the movement of prices in tenders for building contracts in the public sector in Great Britain. It does not include contracts for housing, civil engineering, mechanical engineering, electrical engineering, minor alterations projects or for repair and maintenance work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56364</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dclg-statement-of-new-regulation-1-january-to-30-june-2013"/>
    <title>DCLG statement of new regulation - 1 January to 30 June 2013</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The headline figures show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we are introducing 24 measures in this period, 20 of which are deregulatory measures that will reduce the burden on business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;none of these measures will increase the regulatory burden on businesses, as they are all either deregulatory measures that will bring savings to business, or regulatory measures that have no cost to business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Regulatory Policy Committee have evaluated 5 of our measures and estimated that they will reduce the burden on business by £45.36 million per year. We expect this figure to rise considerably as our other measures are validated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56721</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-sonr"/>
    <title>Fifth statement of new regulation (SONR)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides a forward look of all regulations in scope of government’s ‘one-in, two-out’ regime that are scheduled to come into force between 1 January and 30 June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is published every 6 months to give businesses an indication of when regulations affecting them will be coming into effect. The headline figures show that the sum total of Government deregulation by July 2013 is expected to reduce the annual cost to business by around £919 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56725</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"/>
    <title>Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation guidance for suppliers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation (&lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme requires suppliers of road transport fuel to ensure that a certain proportion of it comes from sustainable renewable sources. Guidance has been in place to assist suppliers with compliance since the &lt;abbr title="Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation"&gt;RTFO&lt;/abbr&gt; was first introduced. Obligated suppliers are consulted each year on revisions to the guidance. These have taken into account the latest European and domestic legislative developments and experience in operating the obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"&gt;Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56731</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-fifth-statement-of-new-regulation-regulations-covering-january-to-june-2013"/>
    <title>BIS fifth statement of new regulation: regulations covering January to June 2013</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lists Department of Business, Innovation and Skills (BIS) measures in scope of ‘One In, Two Out’ regulations to come into force from January to June 2013, to show how BIS is removing burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56761</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/quarterly-price-and-cost-indices-commentary-3q-2012"/>
    <title>Quarterly price and cost indices: commentary 3Q 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explains the data published in the three quarterly BIS construction price and cost indices (PCIs): tender price indices (12/P147C), construction resource cost indices (12/P148C), and output price indices (URN 12/P149C).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56763</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/construction-tender-prices-indices-december-2012"/>
    <title>Construction tender prices indices December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A small number of the indices in this release have been revised due to inconsistencies between the indices published on the BIS website and those published on BCIS Online.  Mostly this affects older indices with a few more recent exceptions. BIS apologises for any inconvenience this may have caused.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56765</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/construction-output-price-indices-december-2012"/>
    <title>Construction output price indices - December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of three quarterly BIS construction price and cost indices (PCIs), providing output price indices (OPIs) for construction sectors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57009</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/bis-quarterly-constuction-price-and-cost-indices-3rd-quarter-2012"/>
    <title>BIS quarterly constuction price and cost indices 3rd quarter 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="headline-results"&gt;Headline results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BIS Output Price Index for New Construction (2010): All New Construction (COPI) for 3rd Quarter 2012 rose 0.7% on the previous quarter and by 3.5% on the same quarter a year earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tender Price Index for Public Sector Non-Housing (PUBSEC) for 3rd Quarter 2012 fell 1.1% on the previous quarter and 0.6% on the year from 3rd Quarter 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tender Price Index of Social Housing (TPISH) shows a fall of 0.5% compared with the previous quarter and a rise of 1.1% compared with the same quarter a year earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BIS Tender Price Index of Road Construction (ROADCON) is not available for 3rd Quarter 2012 but the index for the 2nd Quarter 2012 shows prices falling 1.7% compared to the previous quarter and rising 4% in the year from 2nd Quarter 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resource costs indices in 3rd Quarter 2012 show fairly stable prices in the building sectors, housing and non-housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs in the infrastructure both roads and infrastructure generally have fallen slightly (0.4%) compared to the previous quarter but still show increases in the year since 3rd Quarter 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="publication-note"&gt;Publication note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release was published around 40 minutes after 9.30am, in breach of the Code of Practice for Official Statistics. We are currently investigating why this happened, and a report will be submitted to the National Statistician’s Office and published on the UK Statistics Authority’s website in due course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56973</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/jsp-315-sevices-accommodation-code-volume-3"/>
    <title>JSP 315 Sevices Accommodation code: Volume 3</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Volume 3 of Joint Services Publication (JSP) 315: Services Accommodation Code deals with Reserves and Cadet Accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56769</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/construction-resource-cost-indices-december-2012"/>
    <title>Construction resource cost indices - December 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A small number of the indices in this release have been revised due to inconsistencies between the indices published on the BIS website and those published on BCIS Online.  Mostly this affects older indices with a few more recent exceptions. BIS apologises for any inconvenience this may have caused.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56799</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/court-martial-results-from-the-military-court-centres"/>
    <title>Court Martial Results from the Military Court Centres</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In line with the Government’s Transparency and Open Data initiative, the Military Court Service has agreed to provide Court Martial results in respect of the Military Court Centres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56824</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/notice-of-proposed-new-byelaws"/>
    <title>Notice of proposed new Byelaws</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice of proposal for the introduction of new byelaws in respect of the Ministry of Defence site known as RAF Croughton.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56833</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tax-arrangements-for-public-sector-appointees-in-bis-as-of-31-january-2012"/>
    <title>Tax arrangements for public sector appointees in BIS as of 31 January 2012 </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has committed to making clear to the public how it uses taxpayers’ money. All government departments have been asked to publish a wide range of information about how it meets and measures its objectives and the use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56834</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-about-revoking-the-north-west-regional-strategy-environmental-report"/>
    <title>Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the North West regional strategy: environmental report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This environmental report is a consultation document on the likely significant environmental effects of revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy (which together form the regional strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report succeeds the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919154703/http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/revocationnwrss"&gt;previous environmental report&lt;/a&gt; on the revocation of the north west regional strategy which was consulted on between October 2011 and January 2012. It is a stand alone document the intention of which is to provide the reader with an up-to-date comprehensive assessment of the environmental effects of the revocation of the north west plan and the regional economic strategy without the need to refer back to the previous environmental report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the period all consultation responses will be considered, including those already submitted during the earlier response period. Responses are invited on all aspects of the report and proposal including the supporting appendices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: Due to the size of the documents this publication can also be supplied on a CD-ROM. Please email requests to &lt;a href="mailto:SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;SEAConsultation@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="series"&gt;Series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;Strategic Environmental Assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56866</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/defence-focus-magazine-266"/>
    <title>Defence Focus magazine 266</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defence Focus magazine issue 266 - December 2012 - January 2013&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56768</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/construction-resource-cost-indices-notes-and-definitions"/>
    <title>Construction resource cost indices notes and definitions</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Resource Cost Indices give a measure of the notional trend of input costs to a contractor in terms of increases in the cost of labour, materials and plant by application of the Price Adjustment Formulae for Building (Series 3), Specialist Engineering (Series 3) and Civil Engineering (1990 Series) to cost models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/56541</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"/>
    <title>Working with Troubled Families: a guide to evidence and good practice</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a tool to help local authorities and their partners, who have asked for guidance on how best to work with troubled families, and for the evidence about family intervention to be brought together in one place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report looks at academic evidence, local evaluations of practice, what practitioners have told us works in their services and what families tell us makes this work different and successful for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:PublicationesquePresenter/57003</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tallow-review-a-report-on-the-current-animal-fat-market"/>
    <title>Tallow review: a report on the current animal fat market</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport asked Ecofys to produce a report on the current animal fat (tallow) market to assess whether there has been any impact from allowing double counting of biodiesel produced from category 1 tallow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to explain the issue, the risks, and the available data relating to the tallow market to enable the department to set out its approach to monitoring impacts and also seek stakeholder feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/renewable-transport-fuel-obligation-guidance-for-suppliers"&gt;Consultation about the Renewable Transport Fuel Obligation suppliers’ guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
