<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Sustaining a thriving maritime sector"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:28+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/64055</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/general-lighthouse-fund-report-and-accounts-2012"/>
    <title>General Lighthouse Fund: report and accounts 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Report and accounts for the General Lighthouse Fund (year ended 31 March 2012)</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report and accounts of the General Lighthouse Fund (GLF) are prepared pursuant to Section 211(5) of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995. These accounts have been prepared in accordance with the 2011/12 Government Financial Reporting Manual (&lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt;) issued by HM Treasury. The accounting policies contained in the &lt;abbr title="Government Financial Reporting Manual"&gt;FReM&lt;/abbr&gt; follow International Financial Reporting Standards (&lt;abbr title="International Financial Reporting Standards"&gt;IFRS&lt;/abbr&gt;) to the extent that it is meaningful and appropriate to the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61518</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T09:31:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-guide-to-good-practice-on-port-marine-operations"/>
    <title>A guide to good practice on port marine operations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This supplement to the 'Port marine safety code' contains detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document is a supplement to the ‘Port marine safety code’. It contains more detailed guidance on issues relevant to harbour authorities. It is designed to provide general guidance and examples of how a harbour authority can meet its commitments in terms of compliance with the code. The guidance applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide should not be viewed as the only means of complying with the code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"&gt;Port marine safety code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/60034</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T09:07:01+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T09:07:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-port-security-regulations-2009-at-certain-ports"/>
    <title>Implementation of Port Security Regulations 2009 at certain ports</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This is a consultation on draft designation orders implementing Port Security Regulations 2009.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Directive 2005/65/EC is to enhance security co-ordination in the wider area at certain ports. The directive requires the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designation of a port security authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointment of a port security officer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a port security risk assessment to be conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a port security plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft designation orders which we are are consulting on here append plan(s) outlining the area which the port security authority will have responsibility over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60109</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T09:55:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-port-of-dover"/>
    <title>The Port of Dover</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Dover Port transfer scheme decision announced.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In January 2010 Dover Harbour Board (DHB) submitted a voluntary transfer scheme in accordance with section 9 of the Ports Act 1991, which allows a relevant port authority to voluntarily submit a transfer scheme, which, if confirmed by the Secretary of State for Transport, would allow the port to be privatised.  This was followed by a statutory consultation period on Dover’s transfer scheme that ended on 25 March 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 16 May 2011 the then Secretary of State for Transport, The &lt;abbr title="Right Honourable"&gt;Rt Hon&lt;/abbr&gt; Member for Runnymede and Weybridge (Philip Hammond), launched a consultation on the criteria that the government considers relevant when considering the appropriateness of the sale of a major trust port. The revised criteria - Secretary of State for Transport’s guidance note concerning procedure for the sale of trust ports - was published on 3 August 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the revised criteria, DHB submitted more information in June 2012, and there was a further 6-week period for representations which ended on 27 July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took over as decision minister from the &lt;abbr title="Right Honourable"&gt;Rt Hon&lt;/abbr&gt; Member for Chipping Barnet (Theresa Villiers) in September 2012 and wish to announce the decision, on behalf of the Secretary of State, to the House today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided not to confirm DHB’s transfer scheme. I reached my conclusion taking into account the published policy. I concluded that the transfer scheme proposed would not ensure a sufficient level of enduring community participation in the port. I also concluded that so far as the board made the application in order to be able to obtain the additional finance necessary to undertake the proposed redevelopment of the Western Docks, there were other options available to secure that redevelopment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/publications/dover-transfer-scheme-decision-letter"&gt;full decision letter will be available on the department’s website&lt;/a&gt; shortly after this statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My honourable friend, the Parliamentary under Secretary of State, &lt;abbr title="Honourable"&gt;Hon&lt;/abbr&gt; Member for Wimbledon (Stephen Hammond), as Minister for Maritime will now discuss with DHB, their plans for the future of the port.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60118</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T09:42:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dover-transfer-scheme-decision-letter"/>
    <title>Dover transfer scheme decision letter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Announcing the decision on the transfer scheme submitted by Dover Harbour Board in January 2010 and the enhanced scheme of 13 June 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Transport has decided not to confirm the transfer scheme from Dover Harbour Board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the proposed transfer scheme would not ensure a sufficient level of enduring community participation in the port&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there were other options available to secure the redevelopment of the Western Docks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57017</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T09:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-rights-for-maritime-passengers"/>
    <title>New rights for maritime passengers</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new EU regulation is set to give passengers travelling by water improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling by water are set to enjoy improved rights to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures as a new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on maritime passenger rights enters into force today. These passengers will now benefit from similar rights to those travelling by air and rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, which will apply to most cruise and ferry services operating within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, also provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister, Stephen Hammond, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that passengers receive protection across all modes of transport, enabling them to travel with increased peace of mind throughout the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;. While no one enjoys disruption to their travel plans, I am pleased that this new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation will provide passengers with the right to assistance in cases of cancelled or delayed departures. I am also pleased that this new regulation provides disabled persons or those with reduced mobility the same rights and accessibility assistance when travelling by water, as they have in other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most journeys run smoothly. On the rare occasions when things do go wrong, it is important that passenger complaints are taken seriously and dealt with effectively at the appropriate level. So in this respect, I am extremely grateful to all the bodies that have agreed to undertake voluntary complaint handling roles. This demonstrates collaborative working between government and industry at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of implementation, the Passenger Shipping Association has agreed to act as the voluntary complaint handling body for England and Wales, with London TravelWatch retaining responsibility for services operated and licensed by Transport for London. The Consumer Council for Northern Ireland and the Scottish Government have also agreed to take up similar roles in their respective areas.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gibbons, Director of the Passenger Shipping Association, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that the Shipping Minister and the Department for Transport have selected us as the voluntary complaints handling body for Maritime Passenger Rights in England and Wales. Over the past 2 years we have worked very closely with DfT officials together with our member cruise and ferry companies to achieve a successful implementation. We are confident that the industry as a whole will continue to offer customers an excellent service and will deal effectively with any complaints that arise through this new regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government published its public consultation on UK’s implementation of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation on 5 October 2012. The 6 week consultation closed on 16 November 2012.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation applies in respect of passengers travelling:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on ferry services where the port of embarkation is situated outside the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state and the port of disembarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state, provided that the service is operated by a union carrier. (‘union carrier’ means a carrier established within the territory of a member state or offering transport by a ferry service operated to or from the territory of a member state.)    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on a cruise where the port of embarkation is situated in the territory of an &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member state  &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation includes a number of exemptions that are designed to exclude small boats and to protect small businesses. For example, it does not apply to ships certified to carry up to (and including) 12 passengers; on ships which have a crew responsible for the operation of the ship composed of not more than 3 persons; where the distance is less than 500 metres one way and on excursion and sightseeing tours other than cruises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under the new &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation, if an individual has a complaint, they should first raise it with the operator. If it cannot be resolved in this way, the complaint may then be referred to the appropriate complaint handling body. It is expected most complaints will be resolved at one of these 2 stages.  However if this is not possible, the complaint may then be investigated by the national enforcement body, who will consider whether there has been a breach of the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; regulation. The Maritime and Coastguard Agency (MCA) will operate as the national enforcement body for the whole of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T16:28:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-marine-safety-code"/>
    <title>Port marine safety code</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Safety code for harbour authorities with statutory powers and duties in the UK.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Port marine safety code’ establishes a national standard for every aspect of port marine safety and aims to enhance safety for those who use or work in ports, their ships, passengers and the environment. The code applies to all harbour authorities in the UK that have statutory powers and duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/a-guide-to-good-practice-on-port-marine-operations"&gt;Guide to good practice on port marine operations: a supplement to the ‘Port marine safety code’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/56774</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T09:33:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-ec-392-2009"/>
    <title>Consultation on the implementation of EU Regulation (EC) 392/2009</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>This consultation seeks views on the UK's draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the UK’s draft Statutory Instrument that transposes Regulation (EC) 392/2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation gives effect, within the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt;, to the 2002 Protocol to the Athens Convention to create parity for the passenger shipping industry and help ensure that UK citizens have access to the same levels of compensation when travelling between two different &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; member states. Furthermore, it increases the limits of liabilities for death or personal injuries to passengers being carried by sea; requires carriers to have compulsory insurance, and provides claimants with the right of taking direct action against the insurers. The intended effect is to provide an enhanced framework of compensation in the event of death or personal injury to a passenger, or the loss or damage to luggage when travelling on a sea journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulation also brings into scope certain domestic passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55824</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T09:34:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:34:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-statistics-13-december-2012"/>
    <title>Transport statistics 13 December 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Several sets of figures including quarterly bus usage, port freight and vehicle licensing.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) has published the following transport statistics: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/transport-statistics-great-britain-2012"&gt;transport statistics Great Britain: 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/quarterly-bus-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;quarterly bus statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/vehicle-licensing-statistics-quarter-3-2012"&gt;vehicle licensing statistics: quarter 3 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/national-travel-survey-2011"&gt;national travel survey: 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/reliability-of-journeys-on-the-highways-agencys-motorway-and-a-road-network-october-2012"&gt;reliability of journeys on the Highways Agencys motorway and ‘A’ road network: October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;See statistics at &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; for details on all &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport/about/statistics"&gt;recent transport statistics releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These official statistics are published according to arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16746</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T09:30:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/port-freight-statistics-quarter-3-2012"/>
    <title>Port freight statistics: quarter 3 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This publication presents provisional summary statistics on freight handled by major UK ports, updated quarterly. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This publication presents provisional summary statistics on freight handled by major UK ports, updated quarterly. Provisional annual statistics are updated in June and detailed final annual statistics are published in September. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total port traffic (tonnage) in the year ending quarter 3 2012 (497 million tonnes) was down 2% on the year ending quarter 3 2011 (509 million tonnes). &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of units of all types handled in the year ending quarter 3 2012  (20.8 million units) was down 3% compared with the year ending quarter 3 2011 (21.4 million units).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tonnage in quarter 3 of 2012 (124 million tonnes) was down 3% compared with quarter 3 2011 (127 million tonnes).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of units of all types handled in quarter 3 2012 (5.98 million units) was down 4% compared with quarter 3 2011 (6.21 million units). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="technical-information"&gt;Technical information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on port freight statistics, including the pre-release access list, and related technical documentation &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/technical-guidance-for-transport-stats#Port-statistics"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maritime.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone: 020 7944 4131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
