<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/sustaining-a-thriving-maritime-sector/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Sustaining a thriving maritime sector"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16736</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T12:53:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-major-ports-group-annual-parliamentary-reception"/>
    <title>UK Major Ports Group annual parliamentary reception</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Charles (Charles Hammond – Chairman UK Major Ports Group/UKMPG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along - I’m delighted to have this chance to meet with you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facts are stubborn things&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Adams, second President of the United States, said, “Facts are stubborn things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me, the stubborn facts prove that Britain’s ports are a national asset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every year more than 500 million tonnes of freight and well over 20 million international passengers pass through our ports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they account for over 95% of our imports and exports by volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and they employ around a hundred and thirty thousand people and contribute close to £7 billion to &lt;abbr title="Gross Domestic Product"&gt;GDP&lt;/abbr&gt; (Oxford Economics Report 2011)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="our-ports-matter-more-than-ever"&gt;Our ports matter more than ever&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, our ports matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with Britain facing the most serious economic challenge in a generation, they matter more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you create wealth, jobs and growth right here at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that contribution is absolutely vital to the health of our national economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But your economic importance doesn’t start and finish at our borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because you connect our country and our companies to new markets and new customers overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody has more experience, or more expertise, in accessing the global economy - seizing its opportunities, maximising its potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working day and night so that Britain is always open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure we’re a top trading nation, as well as a leading maritime nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s who you are. It’s what you do - better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why you are key players. The people and the firms who can help Britain out-compete and out-produce the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-evangelist-for-the-ports-industry"&gt;An evangelist for the ports industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I have a tough act to follow in my predecessor Mike Penning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this audience will agree that Mike was a vocal and effective champion for this country’s ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I’m determined to pick up where Mike left off by being an evangelist for your industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So be in no doubt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trust port or private company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small, medium or large enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;north, south, east or west&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will be on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name on the ministerial door may be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our strategy and our policy for the maritime sector remains exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-right-environment-to-grow-and-succeed"&gt;The right environment to grow and succeed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m looking forward to visiting many of the ports you represent, to see for myself how they are coping in what remains a difficult trading climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know these are tough and testing times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as always, your members have been equal to them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the fact that UK ports increased their total traffic by 1.5 percent last year is a huge achievement when set against the backdrop of continuing worldwide economic difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that suggests your members are well placed to benefit as the economy picks up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, with interest rates at their lowest for generations, now is a good time for stable, profitable businesses to invest for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this government knows that we must play our part too.  And there are two main strands to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creating an environment in which ports and maritime-related  business of all kinds can succeed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making sure that the infrastructure for which Government has direct responsibility complements and supports the work you do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re supporting major container port developments like those already under construction at Felixstowe, London Gateway and Southampton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is crucial if these ports are to welcome the largest container vessels which are coming into service.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ships have the choice not to call in Britain at all if the infrastructure isn’t there.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these investments will help make sure that as many deep-sea boxes as possible are delivered directly to this country.  And that the country is ready for recovery and growth in trade in manufactured goods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which UK port will they come?  That’s up to you. I’ll be as interested as anyone to see how the competition in this sector plays out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And others will follow. Liverpool, Bristol, Dover and Teesport also have the necessary consents to expand their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond the container sector, it’s imperative that every port is able to pursue a vision for the future - whether that’s responding to the opportunities brought by offshore energy, or it’s tapping into the potential of the tourism and leisure market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of the business model or maritime market your members choose, I want to make sure the Government creates the right environment for them to grow and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="better-infrastructure-less-regulation"&gt;Better infrastructure, less regulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create that environment we’re absolutely committed to investing in the strategic roads and rail infrastructure that serves UK ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes far-reaching improvements to the rail freight network…as part of a £9.4 billion rail investment package announced this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the new initiatives is a high capacity ‘electric rail spine’ running from the South Coast ports to the West Midlands and Yorkshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at ways to relieve the congestion on road routes to and from ports&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, we’ve set out a major scheme to boost the capacity of the A14 linking Felixstowe with the Midlands and the North,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most crucial arteries for goods coming into the country and -  together with measures to boost rail freight - this modernisation will help ease the flow of traffic around one of our biggest ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also removing the barriers you face so you can do your job efficiently and profitably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being responsible for ports and shipping, I also have the title ‘Minister for Better Regulation’ within the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I want you to know that I also regard myself as ‘Minister for Less Regulation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So believe me, if I find suffocating red tape that’s getting in your way and slowing you down, I will cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where there are regulations which add no value, I will scrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while we’ve already run through the Red Tape Challenge formalities, here’s a challenge that remains open to you: let me know where there is still any redundant regulation and I will try to get rid of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the case I’ve put this evening is that our ports have a front and centre role in the life of our nation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boosting jobs and growth in Britain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acting as international gateways for trade and travel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping us transform our economic prospects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But then you have always been fundamental to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yours is the industry that helped turn a small island nation into a major global player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industry with a proud story to tell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also an industry with a great future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it’s a pleasure to be here this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16458</id>
    <published>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T09:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/implementation-of-port-security-regulations-2009-at-certain-ports"/>
    <title>Implementation of Port Security Regulations 2009 at certain ports</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Directive 2005/65/EC is to enhance security coordination in the wider area at certain ports. The directive requires the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;designation of a port security authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appointment of a port security officer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a port security risk assessment to be conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a port security plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft designation orders which we are are consulting on here append plan(s) outlining the area which the port security authority will have responsibility over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16370</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T11:01:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/model-ship-security-plan-templates"/>
    <title>Model ship security plan templates</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These model ship plans will help company and ship security officers to compile a ship security plan (SSP) under the International Ship and Port Facility Security (ISPS) Code, for agreement and verification by the Department for Transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents are cruise ship and ro-ro (roll-on/roll-off) passenger ferry templates. A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/mcga07-home/shipsandcargoes/mcga-shipsregsandguidance/mcga_dops_maritimesecurity_mainpage/dops_ms-guidance/mcga_dops_msb_ssp/dops_msb__model_ship_security_plan.htm"&gt;template for use with cargo ships&lt;/a&gt; is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/mca/"&gt;Maritime and Coastguard website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/14151</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-10T22:55:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/maritime-statistics-directive-reporting-guidance"/>
    <title>Maritime Statistics Directive reporting guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help for shipping lines, their agents and ports to complete statistical returns on maritime freight traffic through ports, as required by the European Commission Maritime Statistics Directive (95/64/EU).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120606215114/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-rules-and-code-lists/"&gt;administrative rules and code lists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120606215114/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-submission-methods/"&gt;submission methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120606215114/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-faqs/"&gt;frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-maritime-statistics-directive"&gt;What is the Maritime Statistics Directive?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maritime Statistics Directive is a piece of European Union legislation passed in December 1995 &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexplus!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;amp;lg=EN&amp;amp;numdoc=31995L0064"&gt;Council Directive 96/64/EC&lt;/a&gt; which requires Member States to supply to the Statistical Office of the European Communities (Eurostat) information relating to maritime traffic through its’ ports. The UK has been required to report data under the Directive since 1 January 2000. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:141:0029:0047:EN:PDF"&gt;directive was ‘recast’&lt;/a&gt; in 2009, bringing together the original directive and various subsequent amendments in one document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="is-the-provision-of-data-obligatory"&gt;Is the provision of data obligatory?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. The directive requires the government to make collection obligatory in the United Kingdom. The legal powers in the UK are by means of a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/1997/2330/contents/made"&gt;statutory instrument&lt;/a&gt; under section 2(2) of the European Communities Act 1972. The statutory instrument (number 2330 of 1997) obliges all relevant bodies in the transport industry to provide data to &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; for onward transmission to Eurostat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-has-to-provide-the-data"&gt;Who has to provide the data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the statutory instrument requires all relevant transport organisations to provide the data, the detailed data has to be provided by the shipping lines or their agents for freight movements through major UK ports (i.e. those handling more than one million tonnes of freight per annum). In addition, port authorities at major ports have to provide quarterly aggregated data to confirm the completeness of the data collected from shipping lines/agents.
At minor ports (those handling less than 1 million tonnes) only annual aggregate figures are required from port authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-are-the-data-collected"&gt;Why are the data collected?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data collected under the directive are used by the European Commission to assist in policy development at a European level and to monitor the impact of European policy measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the UK government has collected statistics on port traffic in the UK since longer before the Directive came in. These have been used by government, business and the wider public in developing and debating maritime transport policy and in planning operations and new ventures. The effect of the Directive was to change the detail of what was already collected in the UK and introduce much more consistency in European port statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="who-is-responsible-for-ensuring-collection-of-data-in-the-uk"&gt;Who is responsible for ensuring collection of data in the UK?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government department with overall responsibility for the data collection is the Department for Transport, (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;). It employs a collection agent, BMT Reliability consultants, to carry out the day-to-day operation of the data collection activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-can-i-find-the-results-from-the-data-collected"&gt;Where can I find the results from the data collected?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport publishes UK data. Eurostat publishes &lt;a rel="external" href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/eurostat/home"&gt;Europe-wide data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-data-has-to-be-collected-and-how-often"&gt;What data has to be collected and how often?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Directive requires the collection of statistics on freight traffic, vessels and passenger traffic through ports throughout the European Union. The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; has the means to collect data on vessels and passenger traffic separately, so the system described here relates to the requirements for freight traffic only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data relating to freight traffic is only being collected in detail for UK ports handling more than one million tonnes of freight per annum (‘major ports’). This detailed data includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reporting port;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Lloyds Register Number (or IMO Number) for the vessel (or name, flag and deadweight);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the direction of movement (inwards or outwards);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;port of loading for inwards cargo or unloading for outwards cargo;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for unitised traffic the type of units (container, accompanied trailer, unaccompanied trailer etc.);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whether they are loaded or empty units;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of units and the freight tonnage;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for other traffic, the broad product group and freight tonnage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This data has to be provided at least quarterly and is being collected primarily from shipping lines or their agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the ‘major’ port authorities (where traffic exceeds one million tonnes per annum) are providing the following information on a ‘retrospective’ quarterly basis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the names of all shipping lines and agents using their port;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the identity of all vessels using their port; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the gross weight and number of units of goods in and out of their port.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data for other ports, handling less than one million tonnes a year, is being provided only annually in summary form by port authorities. 
For more see &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-rules-and-code-lists/"&gt;administrative rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-are-the-data-collected-in-the-uk"&gt;How are the data collected in the UK?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These range of options are available by which data providers can supply the data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by sending the data automatically via a Port Community System&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by entering the data through web based forms (iSDES)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by submitting ASCII data files in a &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; approved format&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by completing paper forms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The collection agency provide a central database to collect and store the data received by these methods, ready for transmission to &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details see &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-submission-methods/"&gt;submission methods&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/ecmsd-rules-and-code-lists/"&gt;administrative rules&lt;/a&gt;.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-can-i-get-further-information"&gt;How can I get further information?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can obtain further information from the contacts listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="contact-us"&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For enquiries about statistical results or general data collection policy please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport.
&lt;br&gt;Maritime Statistics Help Desk
&lt;br&gt;Maritime Statistics Collection Agency
&lt;br&gt;BMT Reliability Consultants Limited
&lt;br&gt;12 Little Park Farm Road
&lt;br&gt;Fareham
&lt;br&gt;Hampshire
&lt;br&gt;PO15 5SU
&lt;br&gt;Tel: 01489 553290
&lt;br&gt;Fax: 01489 553291
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ask questions/send messages to the help desk:
&lt;a href="help@maritimestatistics.co.uk"&gt;help@maritimestatistics.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For help with providing data please contact the Maritime Statistics Help Desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To submit data:
&lt;a href="data@maritimestatistics.co.uk"&gt;data@maritimestatistics.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="address"&gt;&lt;div class="adr org fn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Department for Transport
&lt;br&gt;Maritime Statistics Branch
&lt;br&gt;Department for Transport
&lt;br&gt;Zone 2/19
&lt;br&gt;Great Minster House
&lt;br&gt;76 Marsham Street
&lt;br&gt;London
&lt;br&gt;SW1P 4DR
&lt;br&gt;Tel: 020 7944 3087
&lt;br&gt;Fax: 020 7944 2165
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="maritime.statistics@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;maritime.statistics@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12812</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T16:32:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/details-of-passenger-ship-fires-in-2010"/>
    <title>Passenger ship fires in 2010</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport’s (&lt;abbr title="The Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s) response to Freedom of Information (&lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt;) request F0007151: Passenger ship fires in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13238</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T21:27:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/consent-letter-under-section-24-of-the-merchant-shipping-act-1853"/>
    <title>Consent letter under section 24 of the Merchant Shipping Act 1853</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This letter gives consent to the mortgaging or charging of dues on ships under section 24 of the Merchant Shipping Act 1853. The letter concerns the harbour authorities of Birkenhead Port Limited, Heysham Port Limited, The Manchester Ship Canal Company Limited, The Mersey Docks and Harbour Company Limited and Port of Sheerness Limited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13195</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T22:17:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/eu-transport-council-29-october-2012"/>
    <title>EU Transport Council 29 October 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will attend the first Transport Council of the Cypriot Presidency (the Presidency) in Luxembourg on Monday 29 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency hopes to achieve general approach on 3 proposals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on common rules for the allocation of slots, repealing Council Directive 95/93/EC. The proposed regulation has been subject to intense official-level scrutiny by Council Working Groups and these discussions are ongoing. Progress to date has been mixed, but the proposition remains acceptable from a UK perspective. I believe that the resulting regulation could help promote the most effective use of airport slots and build on the existing transparent, market-based approach to encourage the more efficient use of scarce capacity at congested airports, while minimising administrative and financial burdens for industry. However, at this stage, it remains unclear whether or not it will be possible to seek a general approach at the October Council.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second is a proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the enforcement of certain provisions of the Maritime Labour Convention by flag states. The proposed general approach represents a satisfactory outcome for the UK and I will support it as it allows appropriate flexibility to member states, and will not require the UK to make any substantive changes to its proposed implementation of the provisions of the Maritime Labour Convention on flag state responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The third is a proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Directive 2009/16/EC on port state control. I will support the proposal which will not require the UK to make any substantive changes to its proposed implementation of the provisions of the Maritime Labour Convention on port state responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;An orientation debate will be held on a proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on roadworthiness testing for motor vehicles and their trailers (first reading). The UK strongly supports the ongoing roadworthiness testing of vehicles as a worthwhile contribution to road safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the UK is very concerned by the potential cost burden of the European Commission’s proposal as it is currently framed. The UK alone has identified costs of over €1 billion without any discernable benefit in road safety. We have also identified significant administrative burdens embedded in the proposal that similarly would produce no road safety benefit. In the current economic climate the UK does not wish to see any additional cost to European citizens, businesses or governments unless clearly justified by road safety benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presidency will be seeking a political agreement on the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Regulation (EEC) No 3821/85 on recording equipment in road transport and amending Regulation (EC) No 561/2006 of the European Parliament and the Council (first reading). The UK supports the proposal which strikes a sensible balance between improving the security of the tachograph whilst ensuring that additional burdens on industry and enforcement authorities are minimised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council will be expected to adopt a proposal for a Council decision on the signing, on behalf of the European Union, and provisional application of the agreement providing a general framework for enhanced cooperation between the European Union and the European Organisation for the Safety of Air Navigation (Eurocontrol). The UK supports the proposed agreement. It is important that the significant work Eurocontrol performs on behalf of the European Union is put on a sound contractual and financial basis to help ensure value for money from the proposed €40 million expenditure over 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13237</id>
    <published>2012-10-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/marine-navigation-no-2-bill"/>
    <title>Marine Navigation (No.2) Bill</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impact assessment for the Marine Navigation (No.2) Bill, a private member’s bill promoted by Sheryll Murray MP to reduce burdens on the ports and shipping industry and improve maritime safety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/15702</id>
    <published>2012-10-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-05T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-on-the-implementation-of-eu-regulation-1177-2010"/>
    <title>Consultation on on the implementation of EU Regulation 1177/2010</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the Department for Transport’s draft regulations that facilitate implementation of EU Regulation No 1177/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 concerning the rights of passengers when travelling by sea and inland waterways and amending Regulation (EC) No 2006/2004 into UK law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/draft-guidance-sea-passenger/"&gt;Draft guidance notes relating to Regulation (EU) No. 1177/2010, 5 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13219</id>
    <published>2012-10-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:41:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/draft-guidance-notes-relating-to-regulation-eu-no-1177-2010"/>
    <title>Draft guidance notes relating to Regulation (EU) No. 1177/2010</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These seven guidance documents are intended to provide general information on those provisions within EU Regulation 1177/2010 (“EU Regulation”) concerning the rights of passengers when travelling by sea and inland waterway. The guidelines specifically relate to the obligations of carriers (ie cruise and ferry operators) and port terminal operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department welcomes feedback from stakeholders on these documents up to 18 December 2012. Comments should be clearly marked and sent to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damian de Niese
Draft Guidance on EU Regulation 1177/2010
Department for Transport - Zone 2/29
Great Minster House
33 Horseferry Road
London
SW1P 4DR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href="mailto:damian.de_niese@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;damian.de_niese@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
