<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving communities more power in planning local development"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/13406</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12779</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-for-schools-development"/>
    <title>Planning for schools development</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation document invites views on the government’s proposals to make changes to the general permitted development order to give a permitted development right for change of use planning permission for schools development. The purpose of the proposals set out in this document is to support the Department for Education’s policy on new free schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12774</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:49+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/planning-application-fees"/>
    <title>Planning application fees</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation paper seeks views on proposed changes to the planning application fees regime which would decentralise responsibility for setting fees to local planning authorities. We also propose to allow authorities to charge for resubmitted applications and to set higher fees for retrospective applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals will help to reduce the subsidising of planning applications by local taxpayers. If accepted and approved by Parliament, the changes would be implemented from April 2011, with a 6-month transition period until October 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12757</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/local-planning-regulations"/>
    <title>Local planning regulations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to reforms in the Localism Bill, the government is revising the regulations which govern the process by which local councils prepare their development plans. This consultation seeks views on whether the revised regulations are fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12748</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:40+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"/>
    <title>Community infrastructure levy</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on the detailed implementation of the government’s proposals to the community infrastructure levy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13422</id>
    <published>2012-10-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-right-to-bid-non-statutory-advice-note-for-local-authorities"/>
    <title>Community Right to Bid: non-statutory advice note for local authorities</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This non-statutory advice note provides a legislative overview of Part 5 Chapter 3 of the Localism Act and the Assets of Community Value Regulations 2012 which introduce the Community Right to Bid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14689</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-communties-supporting-neighbourhood-planning"/>
    <title>Cash boost for communties supporting neighbourhood planning</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New funding to help communities bring jobs and homes to their neighbourhood using improved planning powers was announced today by Planning Minister Greg Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go and the type and design of development that can be granted automatic planning permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £10 million fund is now available to help councils ensure their communities are able to finalise people’s plans for homes, businesses and facilities in their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 200 communities are already using the new planning powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans that can, for example, decide the location of new homes and decide the green spaces communities are keen to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils are today invited to apply for grants of up to £30,000 for each scheme to help pay for the costs of getting plans in place. Payments will be paid to councils to help them support and advise groups taking forward neighbourhood plans and to pay towards the examination of plans and a local referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We have seen enormous enthusiasm from communities around England, jumping at the chance to be in the driving seat of deciding the future vision of their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This fund will give councils and community groups working on plans a big boost in getting their vision in place as soon as possible to ensure people can enjoy the benefits sooner rather then later.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Neighbourhood planning is making sure local residents are, for the first time, centre stage in helping decide their neighbourhood’s future. It is giving people the chance to plan positively and will help deliver the homes and jobs their communities need to thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eden-valleys-plan-a-step-closer"&gt;Eden Valley’s plan a step closer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Upper Eden Community Plan Group has their plan well underway after the enthusiasm of residents to be at the centre of decision making ensured they were one of the first areas to use these new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area covering 17 parishes in and around Kirkby Stephen in Cumbria has already been designated a neighbourhood plan area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan that focuses on how and where to provide new housing, affordable housing for older people and better broadband connectivity has now been passed to the Eden District Council for a formal consultation. Local people and businesses will be invited to comment before a final referendum is held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Payments will be made in two payments. The first, of £5,000 will be made once a neighbourhood area has been designated. The second payment of £25,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning independent examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the Upper Eden Community Plan can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uecp.org.uk/"&gt;www.uecp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11807</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/food-growing-case-studies"/>
    <title>Food growing: case studies</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The projects included in this document showcase best practice and the varied approaches that community groups have taken to getting land to use for their food growing projects. From space on housing estates now being run as a mini social enterprise, to derelict allotment land, every project shows that where community groups work together with their local authorities or other local landowners, great achievements can follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11292</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/openness-and-transparency-on-personal-interests-guidance-for-councillors"/>
    <title>Openness and transparency on personal interests: guidance for councillors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide gives basic practical information to councillors about how to be open and transparent about their personal interests. It is designed to help councillors, including parish councillors, now that new standards arrangements have been introduced by the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
