<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving communities more power in planning local development"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles has announced a new multi-million pound cash boost to help more communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56622</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/guidance-will-help-support-development-and-get-infrastructure-built"/>
    <title>Guidance will help support development and get infrastructure built</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Updated guidance will ensure the Community Infrastructure Levy is effective in supporting development and getting key infrastructure built. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance has been revised with the active participation of councils and developers to provide certainty on key issues. It has been updated to reflect reforms to the planning system and will help councils looking to introduce the levy, as well as providing clarity to those paying the levy about how it works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; ensures there is no double charging to developers by clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance reflects existing best practice and ensures councils in the process of developing proposals do not need to start their levy setting process from the beginning. Support will be available to councils who choose to review their levy as a result of the new guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ensures a robust evidence base is used for assessing levy rates and provides advice on the 2012 regulations that improve the operation of the levy. The guidance also makes clear that there is no obligation for councils to charge the levy, and that they can set a low or zero rate if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Government has worked actively with councils and developers to get this guidance right and make clear how we expect the levy to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The guidance ensures that councils who have already adopted their levy will not need to do anything new and only councils developing levy rates will need to consider this new guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will continue to listen to issues being raised, such as the need for greater clarity at an earlier stage on how the levy will be spent. We will also be considering the suggestion to move the 2014 date when councils will be limited in their use of pooled Section 106 planning obligations for infrastructure that can be funded by the levy. The government expects to consult on further regulatory changes in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy has the potential to raise an estimated £1 billion a year of funding by 2016 to support growth locally. It gives councils more choice and flexibility in how they fund the infrastructure that their communities want and need, and provides developers with much more ‘up front’ certainty about the amount of money they will be expected to contribute for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Peace from the British Property Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development industry has raised a number of concerns about the Community Infrastructure Levy. We have been closely involved in the development of this document and are pleased that it clearly sets out what local authorities must do when they are looking to charge the levy. These revisions should help support development by ensuring the levy is being implemented effectively. We look forward to continuing our work with the department on other Community Infrastructure Levy issues next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Mike Jones, Leader, Cheshire West and Chester Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils are keen to continue work with the development industry in a positive and productive way that enables much needed development to take place in a way that is fair and equitable to developers and to local people. Discussions on the Community Infrastructure Levy have been conducted in this spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Builders Federation Executive Chairman Stewart Baseley said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been closely involved in the process to improve the Community Infrastructure Levy guidance. We are pleased that it assists in clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations and sets out the importance of robust evidence and transparency when deciding on levy rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recently introduced changes to ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged the Community Infrastructure Levy. Applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents (via a Section 73 planning application) without having to pay another levy on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/56590</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:03:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"/>
    <title>Community Infrastructure Levy guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Guidance setting out the main procedures local authorities need to follow when introducing and operating the Community Infrastructure Levy.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guidance is issued by the Secretary of State under section 221 of the Planning Act 2008 and replaces the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance-charges"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy Guidance: charge setting and charging schedules procedure&lt;/a&gt;’ published in March 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles has announced a major milestone in the transfer of power to local communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/39682</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary>Consultation about transferring some planning functions from the Homes and Communities Agency to Milton Keynes Council.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Don Foster welcomed a huge response from neighbourhood groups interested in using new powers to save local assets or take over services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act which was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. Download &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate" title="A Plain English Guide to the Localism Act"&gt;A Plain English Guide to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently the Community Right to Bid came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/" title="my community rights"&gt;Community Rights&lt;/a&gt; website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16517</id>
    <published>2012-10-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-right-to-bid-non-statutory-advice-note-for-local-authorities"/>
    <title>Community Right to Bid: non-statutory advice note for local authorities</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This non-statutory advice note provides a legislative overview of Part 5 Chapter 3 of the Localism Act and the Assets of Community Value Regulations 2012 which introduce the Community Right to Bid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14689</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-communties-supporting-neighbourhood-planning"/>
    <title>Cash boost for communties supporting neighbourhood planning</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New funding to help communities bring jobs and homes to their neighbourhood using improved planning powers was announced today by Planning Minister Greg Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go and the type and design of development that can be granted automatic planning permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £10 million fund is now available to help councils ensure their communities are able to finalise people’s plans for homes, businesses and facilities in their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 200 communities are already using the new planning powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans that can, for example, decide the location of new homes and decide the green spaces communities are keen to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils are today invited to apply for grants of up to £30,000 for each scheme to help pay for the costs of getting plans in place. Payments will be paid to councils to help them support and advise groups taking forward neighbourhood plans and to pay towards the examination of plans and a local referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen enormous enthusiasm from communities around England, jumping at the chance to be in the driving seat of deciding the future vision of their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This fund will give councils and community groups working on plans a big boost in getting their vision in place as soon as possible to ensure people can enjoy the benefits sooner rather then later.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is making sure local residents are, for the first time, centre stage in helping decide their neighbourhood’s future. It is giving people the chance to plan positively and will help deliver the homes and jobs their communities need to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eden-valleys-plan-a-step-closer"&gt;Eden Valley’s plan a step closer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Upper Eden Community Plan Group has their plan well underway after the enthusiasm of residents to be at the centre of decision making ensured they were one of the first areas to use these new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area covering 17 parishes in and around Kirkby Stephen in Cumbria has already been designated a neighbourhood plan area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan that focuses on how and where to provide new housing, affordable housing for older people and better broadband connectivity has now been passed to the Eden District Council for a formal consultation. Local people and businesses will be invited to comment before a final referendum is held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Payments will be made in two payments. The first, of £5,000 will be made once a neighbourhood area has been designated. The second payment of £25,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning independent examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the Upper Eden Community Plan can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uecp.org.uk/"&gt;www.uecp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11807</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/food-growing-case-studies"/>
    <title>Food growing: case studies</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The projects included in this document showcase best practice and the varied approaches that community groups have taken to getting land to use for their food growing projects. From space on housing estates now being run as a mini social enterprise, to derelict allotment land, every project shows that where community groups work together with their local authorities or other local landowners, great achievements can follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11292</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/openness-and-transparency-on-personal-interests-guidance-for-councillors"/>
    <title>Openness and transparency on personal interests: guidance for councillors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide gives basic practical information to councillors about how to be open and transparent about their personal interests. It is designed to help councillors, including parish councillors, now that new standards arrangements have been introduced by the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
