<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Giving communities more power in planning local development"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/39682</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T18:39:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/proposed-transfer-of-homes-and-communities-agency-functions-and-assets-to-milton-keynes-council"/>
    <title>Proposed transfer of Homes and Communities Agency functions and assets to Milton Keynes Council</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a request by Milton Keynes Council to take greater strategic control of growth and delivery in their area, they asked to acquire full control of planning functions. Currently the Homes and Community Agency is responsible for considering certain types of planning applications for specific areas of Milton Keynes (mainly the areas designated as ‘expansion areas’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many strands to this transfer package, this document seeks views on the transfer of those planning functions back to Milton Keynes Council only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16517</id>
    <published>2012-10-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:39:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-right-to-bid-non-statutory-advice-note-for-local-authorities"/>
    <title>Community Right to Bid: non-statutory advice note for local authorities</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This non-statutory advice note provides a legislative overview of Part 5 Chapter 3 of the Localism Act and the Assets of Community Value Regulations 2012 which introduce the Community Right to Bid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14689</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-communties-supporting-neighbourhood-planning"/>
    <title>Cash boost for communties supporting neighbourhood planning</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New funding to help communities bring jobs and homes to their neighbourhood using improved planning powers was announced today by Planning Minister Greg Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go and the type and design of development that can be granted automatic planning permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £10 million fund is now available to help councils ensure their communities are able to finalise people’s plans for homes, businesses and facilities in their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 200 communities are already using the new planning powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans that can, for example, decide the location of new homes and decide the green spaces communities are keen to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils are today invited to apply for grants of up to £30,000 for each scheme to help pay for the costs of getting plans in place. Payments will be paid to councils to help them support and advise groups taking forward neighbourhood plans and to pay towards the examination of plans and a local referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen enormous enthusiasm from communities around England, jumping at the chance to be in the driving seat of deciding the future vision of their neighbourhood.
&amp;gt; “This fund will give councils and community groups working on plans a big boost in getting their vision in place as soon as possible to ensure people can enjoy the benefits sooner rather then later.
&amp;gt; “Neighbourhood planning is making sure local residents are, for the first time, centre stage in helping decide their neighbourhood’s future. It is giving people the chance to plan positively and will help deliver the homes and jobs their communities need to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eden-valleys-plan-a-step-closer"&gt;Eden Valley’s plan a step closer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Upper Eden Community Plan Group has their plan well underway after the enthusiasm of residents to be at the centre of decision making ensured they were one of the first areas to use these new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area covering 17 parishes in and around Kirkby Stephen in Cumbria has already been designated a neighbourhood plan area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan that focuses on how and where to provide new housing, affordable housing for older people and better broadband connectivity has now been passed to the Eden District Council for a formal consultation. Local people and businesses will be invited to comment before a final referendum is held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Payments will be made in two payments. The first, of £5,000 will be made once a neighbourhood area has been designated. The second payment of £25,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning independent examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the Upper Eden Community Plan can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uecp.org.uk/"&gt;www.uecp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11807</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/food-growing-case-studies"/>
    <title>Food growing: case studies</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The projects included in this document showcase best practice and the varied approaches that community groups have taken to getting land to use for their food growing projects. From space on housing estates now being run as a mini social enterprise, to derelict allotment land, every project shows that where community groups work together with their local authorities or other local landowners, great achievements can follow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11292</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/openness-and-transparency-on-personal-interests-guidance-for-councillors"/>
    <title>Openness and transparency on personal interests: guidance for councillors</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guide gives basic practical information to councillors about how to be open and transparent about their personal interests. It is designed to help councillors, including parish councillors, now that new standards arrangements have been introduced by the Localism Act 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11309</id>
    <published>2012-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:31:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-right-to-challenge-statutory-guidance"/>
    <title>Community Right to Challenge: statutory guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This guidance provides further explanation of the legislative framework for the Community Right to Challenge. This is contained in Part 5, Chapter 2 of the Localism Act 2011, The Community Right to Challenge (Expressions of Interest and Excluded Services) (England) Regulations 2012, and The Community Right to Challenge (Fire and Rescue Authorities and Rejection of Expressions of Interest) (England) Regulations 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act was enacted on 15 November 2011. The Community Right to Challenge was commenced on 27 June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This replaces the draft guidance published on 21 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14598</id>
    <published>2012-05-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-permission-powers-firmly-in-the-hands-of-communities"/>
    <title>Planning permission powers firmly in the hands of communities</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Right to Build cuts the red tape to get projects off the ground&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A radical new Right to Build will today put the power to grant planning permission firmly in the hands of communities, Housing Minister Grant Shapps will say today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will make £17million available to help local people get their building projects off the drawing board - with an ‘early bird bonus’ for those that move quickly and get their plans in early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a new support hub launched today will offer the help and advice they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="control-in-the-hands-of-communities"&gt;Control in the hands of communities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new Community Right to Build, communities will be able to approve new local developments without the need to go through the normal planning application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as the proposals meet certain criteria and there is the backing of more than 50 per cent of voters in a local referendum, these projects will get the go-ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Right to Build can be used for whatever communities need to make their neighbourhoods prosper and can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family houses to sell or rent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;community halls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;homes designed specifically to meet the needs of older people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;children playgrounds; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shops and business facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps will today offer a share of £17million to areas looking to start their own building projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will also pledge an ‘early bird bonus’ of up to £2,000 to those that move quickly and get their plans in by the end of March next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those looking for advice and support, community charity Locality will launch a new website, phone line, seminars and detailed one-to-one mentoring for those looking to use their Right to Build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For too long communities have had to use their energy fighting development they didn’t want rather then putting it to use bringing about the homes, shops and facilities they did. The Community Right to Build completely changes that and puts communities in the driving seat by ensuring they can bring about the development their neighbourhood needs.
&amp;gt; “The funding and advice service being offered will provide a big boost to those communities eager to take up their Right and bring about change to their area. I would urge all communities to make use of this support to ensure they have the best chance to thrive in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief executive of Locality, Steve Wyler, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Locality fought hard to shape the Localism Act. We believe in self-reliance and community ownership. The new Community Right to Build presents incredible opportunities for people to have a greater stake in their area. If you can see the potential of new buildings for community benefit we’re here to help, support you through the process and make things happen, enhancing local pride and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund will be run by the Homes and Communities Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief executive of the agency, Pat Ritchie, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Build is an innovative new way of empowering local communities, enabling them to play a more active role in shaping their area according to their needs and aspirations.
&amp;gt; “The funding will support those local groups who want to take forward locally-backed development which will ultimately benefit the whole of their community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Application guidance and full details of how to apply for support funding can be found on the Homes and Communities Agency website at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/community-right-to-build"&gt;www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/community-right-to-build&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The advice service run by Locality is available to all communities. Further details can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-build/"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-build&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £17million fund will be available over the next three years (2012 to 2015). The funding is not intended to cover the cost of building, land acquisition or other costs associated with the development itself. The funding is available to communities through England with the exception of London. Separate arrangements for London will be announced shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Locality-led advice support programme, run in partnership with Urban Forum and HACT, is being funded by the Department for Communities and Local Government for three-years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Build forms part of the neighbourhood planning provisions contained in the Localism Act 2011 and became law on 6 April 2012 as part of the Neighbourhood Planning (General) Regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to use the Right members of the community will need to set themselves up as a corporate body with the purpose of furthering the interests of the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once established the community organisation will have to have their development proposal independently examined and have agreement from more than 50 per cent of people voting in a community referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The funding must be used towards the costs of preparing a submission for a Community Right to Build Order - a new route for obtaining planning permission. This could include consulting in the local area or developing the proposal and business case for a community-led scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/9319</id>
    <published>2012-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-pays-tribute-to-best-of-british-pubs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles pays tribute to 'best of British' pubs</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister outlines government support ahead of summer of celebration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today paid tribute to the ‘Great British pub’ in a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/speeches/newsroom/appgbeerawards2012"&gt;speech&lt;/a&gt; that highlighted the Government’s continued support to the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the All Party Parliamentary Beer Groups’ annual awards, Mr Pickles encouraged the industry to recognise the opportunities ahead. He emphasised the Government support helping pubs get in ‘the shape of their life’ in anticipation of  ‘a triple whammy’ of festivity this summer, bringing punters new and old down to the local to share in the celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pubs make a huge contribution to communities and the country, not just to our heritage, and social lives but to the economy. Pubs collectively add £19 billion to the national economy and provide 900,000 jobs. With the Diamond Jubilee, Olympics and European Championships fast approaching the Minister highlighted how the Great British pub can expect even more opportunities to get business booming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government are determined to help support community pubs to thrive in the long-term making sure that they can continue to play a fundamental role in communities for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Communities Secretary made clear the Government’s continued commitment to cutting restrictive red tape and knocking down bureaucratic barriers that have held back community pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nothing says Britain more than our Great British pubs and our Great British beer. Pubs and brewing are part of our social and cultural heritage but they are also playing a fundamental role in our present.
&amp;gt; “Just as pubs are at the heart of communities we are giving communities the chance to get involved at the very heart of their local, enabling them to make their bids to ensure that these social and economic hubs continue to thrive.
&amp;gt; “We are determined to give our community pubs the support to help get them in the shape of their lives to get business booming not just in this summer of celebration but in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already introduced a series of measures to support thriving community pubs including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;doubling small business rate relief from £6,000 to £12,000 until March 2013 and ensuring rural rate relief is available to public houses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;enabling councils to introduce further business rates discounts to support local businesses, through powers handed to them in the Localism Act&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;introducing a minimum unit price preventing supermarkets from unfair sales of alcohol below cost-price and put an end to the so-called cider-tax&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;through the Community Right to Buy, the Department is giving residents the power to save struggling local pubs by taking them over rather than seeing them empty and derelict&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;making it easier for pubs to have live music, taking away the usual licensing rules from performances where the audience numbers 200 or fewer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11505</id>
    <published>2012-05-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:33:15+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accelerating-the-release-of-surplus-public-sector-land-progress-report"/>
    <title>Accelerating the release of surplus public sector land: progress report</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This report sets out the progress made in the past year to accelerate the release of surplus public land to support housing. It also describes the support mechanisms that have been put in place to help departments dispose of land and the next steps for the programme in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As set out in Budget 2012 sufficient land has been identified to meet the government’s ambition to dispose of land with the capacity to build over 100,000 homes by April 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
