<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Expanding and improving the rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16141</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-views-multi-billion-pound-plans-for-the-north-west"/>
    <title>Minister views multi-billion pound plans for the north west</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major upgrade to rail links which will bring over £4 billion of economic benefits to the north west is progressing well, said Transport Minister Simon Burns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister visited Manchester and Liverpool today to see for himself work on the Northern Hub and plans for the electrification of rail lines – both projects could bring up to 30,000 jobs to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Hub will see a new rail link being built (the Ordsall Chord), stations extended and journey times improved while the electrification programme will enable faster, more reliable and greener trains to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport provides the crucial links that allow individuals and communities to prosper and that is why this investment is so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Commuters and businesses in the region will be big winners thanks to quicker and greener trains and more services across Manchester. But these improvements will also benefit the UK as a whole due the crucial role the north west plays in the country’s transport system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This investment demonstrates that the government is delivering on its commitment not only to improve the transport system but also to use it as an engine to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the minister toured Manchester Airport and Manchester Airport railway station where he viewed plans for a 4th railway platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new platform will increase capacity by enabling the station to accommodate longer and more trains. He also visited Piccadilly station which will have extra platforms as part of the Northern Hub project and toured Tuebrook Sidings, in Liverpool, which is 1 of 13 compounds which will be used to store materials during the second phase of the north west electrification scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Northern Hub is a series of proposed projects to boost economic growth through better train services across northern England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The individual projects were identified in a study published by Network Rail in February 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In July 2012 the government announced it was backing the full scheme. The full package of enhancements is set to be in place by 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s electrification programme will also see rail lines on the Great Western Main Line electrified all the way to the South Wales Valleys. The Midland Main Line between Bedford and Sheffield will also be electrified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A study by Network Rail estimates the investment will bring over £4 billion of wider economic benefits to the north west resulting in 30,000 new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16093</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/channel-tunnel-transposition-of-railway-safety-and-interoperability-directives"/>
    <title>Channel Tunnel: transposition of railway safety and interoperability directives</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking views on whether to transpose the requirements of 3 European directives on railway safety and interoperability so that these provisions are in force for the Channel Tunnel. In recognition of the Tunnel’s cross-border nature these we would like to incorporate the provisions of these railway safety and interoperability directives by making amendments to the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16063</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boxing-day-boost-for-bargain-hungry-passengers"/>
    <title>Boxing day boost for bargain-hungry passengers</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra rail services – which will make it easier for shoppers to access retail hubs in central London, Stratford and Kent – are being provided thanks to an agreement between the Department for Transport, Southeastern, and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have devised a unique agreement to enable Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; to make it easier for their passengers to get to the sales following Christmas, which will provide more services at no cost to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Southeastern ran some very successful services on High Speed 1 during the Olympics and the train operator has shown there is sufficient demand for these services so we were happy to consider allowing them to adjust their timetables. This is an excellent example of the government, infrastructure owners and train operators working innovatively together to improve services for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern’s managing director, Charles Horton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to offer this trial Boxing Day service for our passengers thanks to the collaboration with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our high speed Javelin service will transport people from Ashford to St Pancras International in just 37 minutes, and 19 minutes from Ebbsfleet. We’re also pleased to offer free parking at these 2 stations for Boxing Day so everyone has a little bit extra to spend in the sales!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Ruse, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, the company that owns High Speed 1 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Demand for high speed rail travel is rising all the time and this welcome example of teamwork on the railways means we can offer high speed rail customers a service that will prove hugely popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The half hourly service will run between Ashford International, Ebbsfleet International, Stratford International and St Pancras International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd ran a special timetable through the Olympics and Paralympics with extra high speed services to carry spectators to and from Stratford International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timetables and ticket information can be viewed online at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/"&gt;nationalrail.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16218</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/nuneaton-north-chord-event"/>
    <title>Nuneaton North Chord event</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for asking me along today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely delighted to be here because what you’ve achieved with this new chord really matters. And let me tell you why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, today we earn our living in a global marketplace - one where what we sell in Boston or Shanghai is just as important as what we make in Bristol or Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that rail freight is more important than it’s ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving products and raw materials quickly and reliably - that’s how you power up the recovery and grow the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-sense-environmental-sense"&gt;Economic sense, environmental sense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although this new chord isn’t massive in scale like Crossrail or &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, it’s certainly a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment worth more than £25 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that will allow freight traffic to travel through Nuneaton station, without affecting passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that means better and faster links between the global gateway of Felixstowe and the Midlands, the north west and Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this new chord makes sound economic sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you consider the chord’s potential to cut carbon emissions and ease traffic congestion by attracting freight from road to rail, then it soon becomes obvious that it makes environmental sense too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions---right-investment-right-project-right-reasons"&gt;Conclusions - right investment, right project, right reasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add all that up and what you have is the right investment, in the right project, for the right reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I finish I just want to say a big thank you to everyone who made this possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have done a terrific job of work and, if I had a hat, I’d take it off to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on that note it is now my absolute pleasure to declare the Nuneaton North Chord officially open (minister unveils plaque).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16224</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:50:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/peterborough-station-makeover-official-opening"/>
    <title>Peterborough Station makeover – official opening</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also for asking me along. It’s a genuine pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my officials first asked me if I was interested in a makeover, I thought they meant for me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for my self-esteem the officials in my private office eventually put me straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The makeover is right here at Peterborough Station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, looking around, I can see that every penny of that £3 million was well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-makeover-that-really-delivers"&gt;A makeover that really delivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a new station front, a bigger main concourse and a much brighter interior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a new information point, as well as a new customer waiting area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People using the station will feel safer and more secure thanks to improved &lt;abbr title="Closed Circuit Television"&gt;CCTV&lt;/abbr&gt; coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated ticket machines mean less hassle and more convenience for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, talking of convenience, even the toilets have been refurbished.
Looked at from any angle, this is a makeover that really delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to say it doesn’t stop there. Because I understand there’s more to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be new lifts and footbridges, as well extra and longer platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all the work is due to be completed by the end of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bigger-picture"&gt;Bigger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, the passenger friendly changes we see here are part of a much bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’re actually engaged in a massive rail modernisation effort:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new services and extra carriages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more seats and faster journeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transforming conventional rail and backing rail high speed rail &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;From massive, multi-billion pound projects like Crossrail, to smaller multi-million pound projects like Peterborough, we’re renewing and rebuilding Britain’s railways and making them truly fit for the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="team-effort"&gt;Team effort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that it takes a real team effort to pull off something like this - from back office to building site, from accountants to architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as far as I’m concerned, it doesn’t matter if you were sat in front of a computer or you wore a hard hat, or whether you’re from Network Rail or part of East Coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were involved in modernising this station then you should feel very proud of yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why I’d like to take this opportunity to applaud you for an absolutely fantastic job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common interests and a common purpose….coming together and working together to achieve this station improving, passenger friendly end result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a big thank-you for all of your hard graft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks--cutting-ribbonplaque-unveiling"&gt;Concluding remarks – cutting ribbon/plaque unveiling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience “I wish they’d gone on longer” is rarely a tribute paid to a public speaker, especially a politician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, without any further ado, it’s an honour and a privilege to declare this station open.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14868</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:50:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-headquarters-for-rail-accident-investigators"/>
    <title>New headquarters for rail accident investigators</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today officially opened the new premises of the Rail Accident Investigation Branch (&lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt;), the independent investigators working to make the railways safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southern team of the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is now based at Cullen House, near Aldershot, Hampshire, on the same site as the Air Accident Investigation Branch (AAIB). Previously the team were based in Woking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail is significantly safer now than in previous years because the industry has ensured safety issues have been identified and safeguards introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is helping to ensure that our safety record continues to improve by carrying out thorough investigations when something goes wrong and identifying what needs to change to prevent it happening again. The new premises at Cullen House give the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; an excellent base from which to carry out their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Inspector Carolyn Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cullen House provides a continuing presence for the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; in the south east which together with its northern team in Derby provides a balanced coverage for the geographical territory we investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To date since becoming operational in 2005 we have completed 196 investigations The industry has implemented 95% of recommendations from those investigations, bringing about real changes that improve safety for passengers and those who work on the railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cullen House, Patrick McLoughlin met &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and unveiled a plaque marking the official opening of the new premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new premises are named after Lord Cullen who in 2000 led a public enquiry into the Ladbroke Grove rail crash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sole purpose of &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; investigations is to prevent future accidents and incidents and improve railway safety - the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; does not establish blame, liability or carry out prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For media enquiries, please call 020 7944 3248&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3248  &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12799</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T15:58:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/additional-car-parking-at-bedwyn-station"/>
    <title>Additional car parking at Bedwyn station</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Freedom of Information response letter and supporting material concern additional car parking at Bedwyn station.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15227</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T15:43:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/rail-interoperability-derogations"/>
    <title>Rail interoperability derogations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interoperability regime provides for the possibility of an exemption to be granted to allow a specific project not to comply with particular standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 provide for derogations to be granted, at the discretion of the Secretary of State, for projects to introduce new, upgraded or renewed subsystems but these are only available in limited circumstances which can be summarised as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;projects at an advanced stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gauge or energy incompatibility issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network separation or isolation by sea or geography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;economic viability issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accident or natural disaster recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some circumstances, other factors can allow exemptions for upgrade and renewal work, and in all cases, the Secretary of State must notify the European Commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="list-of-derogations"&gt;List of Derogations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/a-list-of-rail-interoperability-derogations-applied-for-by-the-united-kingdom"&gt;A list of derogations applied for by the United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15321</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T12:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/help-notes-for-the-railways-interoperability-regulations-2011"/>
    <title>Help notes for the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These help notes are for the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 (RIR 2011) which apply to all of the United Kingdom including the British half of the Channel Tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These help notes are published by the Department for Transport (DfT) to assist industry and others who are affected by the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 to fulfil their statutory obligations. They do not cover every circumstance and users should consider seeking further advice from the appropriate safety authority (Office of Rail Regulation, Intergovernmental Commission and Department for Regional Development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These help notes are produced in line with the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills guide to code of practice on guidance which is available at:  &lt;a href="http://www.betterregulation.gov.uk"&gt;www.betterregulation.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reader will find that the process-based parts of help notes variously use the two terms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“must” and “shall”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“should” or “may”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Must” or “shall” indicates that a statutory duty needs to be fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Should” or “may” indicates a recommendation to achieve the best outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments, queries or suggestions on existing or further help notes, please e-mail &lt;a href="mailto:mailto:interoperability@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;interoperability@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16242</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T22:57:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/all-party-parliamentary-rail-in-the-north-group-reception"/>
    <title>All party parliamentary rail in the north group reception</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introductory-remarks"&gt;Introductory remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Julie (Julie Hilling - Chair of &lt;abbr title="All Party Parliamentary Group"&gt;APPG&lt;/abbr&gt;). And many thanks for asking me along today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reputation of this group and its members as rail champions for the north really does go before you, so I’m genuinely delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to kick things off with a promise - always a hostage to fortune for a politician I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, here it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you all have packed diaries and busy schedules - so I promise to try and keep my speech short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was going to say keep it “brief”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, since becoming a minister, I’ve discovered that Whitehall is the only place on earth where, without a trace of irony, the term “brief” is used to describe a ten thousand word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern enough, connected enough, fast enough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I have a pretty straightforward view about Britain’s rail network, and it’s this - out-dated and over-burdened railways just won’t cut it in today’s global economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cost hard working families and hard pressed businesses time and money. And, in these testing economic times, you can be sure they are anything but an engine for powering up the recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t do our environment too many favours either. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest, relying on creaking and crumbling rail infrastructure is no way to shrink transport’s carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it doesn’t matter if it’s a regional link or a national network - Britain needs railways that are modern enough, connected enough and fast enough:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern enough to support economic growth and spur job creation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected enough to spread prosperity and open up life-changing chances for people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And fast enough to attract passengers and freight away from less eco-friendly alternatives like long-distance road travel and short-haul flying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="rolling-up-our-sleeves"&gt;Rolling up our sleeves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely convinced that a good rail system can do great things - socially, economically and environmentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we all know, the good and the great don’t come about simply because politicians are very keen on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, you only get concrete results by rolling up your sleeves and getting on with it. And that’s precisely what this government’s been doing on rail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£18 billion invested in our railways during this Spending Review period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A massively ambitious programme of rail modernisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And a range of groundbreaking reforms…. …from driving down costs and driving up efficiencies to devolving decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, on the second of those reforms, devolution, I know that there was a big response from people and organisations in the north to our rail decentralisation consultation…so I want to thank everyone who took the trouble to have their say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No community left out, no region left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a government that believes in top quality railways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that belief is underpinned by a rock-solid principle. Namely that no community should be left out, no region should be left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned, if we want all of Britain to be open for business then we can’t afford for any part of Britain to be isolated or disconnected from the country’s wider transport system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local, and actually national success, demands that north, south, east and west are plugged in and joined up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-the-performance-and-prospects-of-rail-in-the-north"&gt;Transforming the performance and prospects of rail in the north&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the very reason that transforming the performance and the prospects of rail in the north is a first order priority for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when it comes to one particular component of rail services in the north, I’ll admit that the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; hasn’t enjoyed its best media coverage lately. I’m of course talking about the west coast mainline bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t for one minute seek to carp or complain about that coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serious matters tend to generate serious headlines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also demand a serious response…which is why we are facing up to what went wrong and putting things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None-the less, I genuinely hope that none of the recent coverage obscures the bigger, and more positive, picture about what’s happening to rail in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take our recent approval of a £4.5 billion contract to build a new generation of intercity trains at a purpose-built factory in County Durham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that passengers will be speeding along the tracks onboard new high-tech, high-spec trains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s also a welcome employment bonus, with the creation of 730 skilled jobs, as well as another 200 jobs during construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget our &lt;abbr title="High level output specification"&gt;HLOS&lt;/abbr&gt; announcement - a £9.4 billion investment programme that will uplift rail capacity and improve rail connections right across the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also pleased to say that work is well underway on the north-west electrification scheme….improving travel between Manchester and Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re not stopping there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we also intend building a brand new electric passenger and freight corridor - a rail spine linking the towns, cities and economies of the North, with the towns, cities and economies of the Midlands and south of England such as Sheffield, Nottingham, Reading and Southampton. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electric trains that run on these lines will be cleaner and cheaper to run than diesels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll have better acceleration and shift greater loads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’ll carry more passengers with fewer delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain English our investment is good for passengers, good for business and good for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also tell you that funding worth some £240 million will mean that rail users in the North enjoy more seats, quicker journeys and better services on the East Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, the communities and companies of the region are set to be big winners from the backing the government is giving to the northern hub.&lt;br&gt;
And let me say this - the Northern Hub is about the transforming the rail experience across the whole North, from Newcastle in the north-east to Liverpool in the north-west. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in terms of travel benefits this is a genuine landmark enterprise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s even better news&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because Network Rail estimate the northern hub will also bring over £4 billion worth of wider economic benefits to the region and potentially as many twenty to thirty thousand new jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ll forgive the unintended pun, looking down the track there is another game-changing rail modernisation heading towards the North - &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This national high speed rail network will slash journey times and deliver a step change in capacity on routes between Leeds, Sheffield, Birmingham, London and Manchester - and possibly to Edinburgh and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firms in the north will be able to use &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to exploit new markets and attract new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the region’s communities will have better access to jobs and essential services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a core component of the government’s long-term transport strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, for the sake of every region, it’s a project we’re determined to push across the finishing line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I think it’s time I kept the promise I made right at the start of this speech by winding up my remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s be frank, nobody ever complained that a politician’s’ speech was too short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if I may, I’d like to finish with a quote by one of America’s founding fathers, Benjamin Franklin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I grant you that’s a less than orthodox way to end a rail speech. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, for me, this quote sums up our approach to rail modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the 18th century Ben Franklin argued that, when it came to governing, “well done is better than well said.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me, that’s a yardstick which still stands the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m equally sure that, judged against it, the way this government is renewing, rebuilding and reforming our railways proves that, just like the great man said - actions really do speak louder than words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
