<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Expanding and improving the rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/65304</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"/>
    <title>Government's rail strategy receives independent endorsement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent review of the government’s rail franchising strategy, following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition, has backed the overall policy while delivering advice for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Richard Brown, Chairman of Eurostar, to conduct a thorough investigation into how the government should manage its franchising programme following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key conclusions from the Brown review stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the rail industry works, and that there is no credible case for major structural change (paragraph 1.4, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;passenger numbers have grown by 92% since privatisation… punctuality and passenger satisfaction are running at much improved levels… it is highly unlikely that these successes could have been delivered if franchising was fundamentally flawed (paragraph 1.5, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have now had nearly two decades’ experience of franchising and therefore a good idea as to what has worked and what still needs to be addressed (paragraph 1.6, p4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown’s report, published by the department today, recommends that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the department’s capability should be strengthened to manage future franchising programmes (paragraph 1.12, p8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise should be strengthened and simplified (paragraph 3.13, p23)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans should be put in place to devolve more English franchises to the relevant authorities (paragraph 5.5, p37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Brown said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In carrying out this review I have come to the conclusion that the franchising system is not broken, but rather it has made a major contribution to Britain’s increasingly successful rail network. It is therefore essential for both passengers and the wider rail market that the franchising programme is restarted as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To achieve this goal, my review has identified a series of practical proposals and recommendations which, if implemented, will result in a stronger and more effective approach to franchising. In addition, I have provided the department with three broad options for them to consider where a strengthened franchising organisation might be located. As set out in both my review and the Laidlaw Report, the department must look to strengthen its franchising capability as a top priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passengers cannot wait whilst theoretical discussions are held about the structure of railways. It is essential to get on with the franchising programme in order to maintain the momentum of investment in increasing capacity and improving services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The review has confirmed that government’s approach to rail franchising system is still the best way to secure the rail services for tax payers and fare payers alike. It has identified a number of detailed improvements, which I will carefully consider before publishing a further statement regarding the government’s franchising policy in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any delays to the franchising programme will not affect services for rail passengers and they will continue to receive the services they depend upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brown review was launched by the Department for Transport in October and follows work conducted by Sam Laidlaw, Chief Executive of Centrica and a non-executive DfT board member into what went wrong with the West Coast competition directly. His report was published in December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has recommended that by February the government should publish its plans for the Essex Thameside; Great Western; and the Thameslink, Southern and Great Northern franchise competitions which were put on hold last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government considers that, until those plans had been agreed, it would be inappropriate to publish the specific recommendations about these three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is planning to set out a programme for future franchise competitions in the spring alongside a further statement of franchising policy in light of the Brown Review and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"&gt;Rail franchising written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;br&gt;
Brown inquiry team press enquiries: 07584 115 270 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/65306</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:03:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I took the decision last October to cancel the competition for the InterCity West Coast rail franchise and to put the wider franchising process on hold, I commissioned two independent reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am today laying before the House the second of these, by Richard Brown, the Chairman of Eurostar and a highly respected industry figure. His report sets out his recommendations on how best to get the franchising programme back on course. I welcome this report, and am grateful to Mr Brown and his team for their swift and thorough consideration of the issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown concludes that franchising is a fundamentally sound approach for securing the passenger railway services on which so many people rely.  He has identified a number of detailed recommendations for improving the way that franchises are specified and franchise competitions are run. The issues he has identified deserve, and will get, very careful consideration. His recommendations include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that the franchising programme should be restarted as soon as possible, but at a pace that both the department and the industry can sustain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that franchise term should be determined by the circumstances and size of each individual franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals to strengthen and simplify the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals for the financial and contractual structure of future franchises, including in relation to risk allocation and capital requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that the government should plan to devolve responsibility for further English franchises to the relevant authorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also makes recommendations on how to strengthen my department’s capability to manage the future franchising programme, echoing the findings of Sam Laidlaw’s independent inquiry into the lessons to be learnt from the InterCity West Coast competition.  My department has already published a response to Mr Laidlaw’s report, setting out a series of actions that will allow it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible.  The Permanent Secretary has now appointed a single director-general with responsibility for rail, including franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review recommends that the government should determine, by February, our plans for the three franchise competitions which I put on hold last October.  I accept that recommendation, and I will update the House when I have determined those plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, however, I consider that it would be inappropriate to publish Mr Brown’s specific recommendations about these three franchise competitions because of their stock market sensitivity, and so I have redacted the relevant paragraphs from the version of the report I have published today.  I will publish the redacted paragraphs once I have decided the way forward for those three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also recommends that we should set out a clear programme for future franchise competitions.  I will do so in the Spring, alongside a further statement of the government’s rail franchising policy in light of Mr Brown’s recommendations and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020&lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"&gt;Government’s rail strategy receives independent endorsement press notice, 10 January 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/letter-from-the-secretary-of-state-to-richard-brown"&gt;Letter from the Secretary of State to Richard Brown, 15 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/west-coast-main-line-franchise-competition-cancelled"&gt;West Coast Main Line franchise competition cancelled press notice, 3 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/statement-on-west-coast-main-line-and-franchising"&gt;West Coast Main Line and franchising oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 29 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/65307</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:03:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"/>
    <title>The Brown review of the rail franchising programme</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the cancellation of the competition to run the InterCity West Coast franchise, the Secretary of State asked Richard Brown, Chairman of Eurostar, to carry out an urgent assessment of the implications of the flaws in the West Coast procurement for the rest of the rail franchising programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his independent report, Mr Brown makes a  number of recommendations for the future of the rail franchising programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"&gt;Government’s rail strategy receives independent endorsement press notice, 10 January 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"&gt;Rail franchising written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/letter-from-the-secretary-of-state-to-richard-brown"&gt;Letter from the Secretary of State to Richard Brown, 15 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/west-coast-main-line-franchise-competition-cancelled"&gt;West Coast Main Line franchise competition cancelled press notice, 3 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/statement-on-west-coast-main-line-and-franchising"&gt;West Coast Main Line and franchising oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 29 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/61023</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T14:08:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/proportion-of-trains-running-on-time"/>
    <title>Proportion of trains running on time</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary></summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-input-indicator"&gt;DfT Business Plan input indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-dft-franchised-train-operators-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: DfT franchised train operators (Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-train-operator"&gt;Information broken down by: Train operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85.3 per cent of trains arrived on time between 11 November 2012 and 8 December 2012 in Great Britain, a decrease from 88.4 per cent for the same period last year (GB total). The GB average headline figure incorporates Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) averages for operators franchised by devolved administrations (Arriva Trains Wales, First Scotrail, London Overground and Merseyrail), and non-franchised operators (Grand Central, Heathrow Express and Hull Trains), however, the following table covers only DfT franchised operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="public-performance-measure-ppm-for-dft-franchised-train-operating-companiessup1sup"&gt;Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) for DfT franchised Train Operating Companies&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Percentage of trains running on time 2011-12 P9 and 2012-13 P9 &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Latest rail period&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Latest rail period&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Train Operating Company&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011-12 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012-13 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011-12 P9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012-13 P9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;c2c&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;95.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;96.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97.3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chiltern Railways&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;94.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;94.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CrossCountry&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;74.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Coast&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;85.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Midlands Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Capital Connect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Great Western&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First TransPennine Express&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Greater Anglia&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;London Midland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;77.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northern Rail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southeastern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South West Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;88.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;83.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virgin Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;85.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;These are provisional statistics and are subject to revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;Period 9 2011/12 ran from 13 November 2011 to 10 December 2011. 
Period 9 2012/13 ran from 11 November 2012 to 8 December 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;Formerly National Express East Anglia. Greater Anglia took over the franchise on 5 February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#02"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 11 November 2012 and 8 December 2012, 95.8 per cent of c2c services arrived on time, the highest figure for any DfT franchised train operator. CrossCountry had the lowest figure with 74.5 per cent of trains on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following restrictions brought in after the Hatfield crash in October 2000, &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; fell sharply across the country, and took nearly a decade to recover to previous levels. Since 2008/09 national &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; has generally been above 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Proportion of trains arriving on time’ Excel file contains a longer time series of &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; figures for each of the DfT franchised train operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Public Performance Measure (&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt;) combines figures for punctuality and reliability into a single performance record. It covers all scheduled franchised passenger services, seven days a week and measures the arrival punctuality of individual trains against their planned timetable. These plans, technically called ‘plan of the day’, are usually the same as the published timetable with amendments reflecting pre-published engineering amendments; however, they may differ from their originally published timetable. The reliability figure records the percentage of services that are cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; represents the percentage of trains which are ‘on time’ compared to the total number of trains planned. A train is defined as on time if it arrives at its destination within five minutes of the scheduled destination arrival time for London and South East and regional operators; or within ten minutes for long-distance operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; can fluctuate widely period-by-period for many reasons, many of which are not within the control of the train operators. For example poor &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; performance can also be caused by other train operators or Network Rail. More information is available from the Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;) and on Network Rail’s and individual operators’ websites. &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; data can be expressed as either for the time period, or as a Moving Annual Average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) which is an average for the most recent 13 four-week reporting periods. &lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt; figures smooth out short-term fluctuations and highlight the annual background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: 4 weekly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: 2 January 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further information about this indicator can be found in the measurement template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; data are published on the Office of Rail Regulation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://dataportal.orr.gov.uk/"&gt;Data Portal.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: &lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60832</id>
    <published>2012-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-27T09:12:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/rail-passenger-count-and-loading-data-released-to-to-individuals-and-organisations"/>
    <title>Rail passenger count and loading data released to to individuals and organisations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Freedom of Information response concerning passenger count and loading data released by the government to individuals and organisations.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Freedom of Information response concerns passenger count and loading data originally provided by train operating companies and then released by the Department for Transport to individuals and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60283</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-for-transports-boost-to-train-builders"/>
    <title>Department for Transport's boost to train builders</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New train carriages procured by Southern Railway. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train builders have received a year-end boost as the government announces its backing for two new train orders, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of government support, Southern Railway has now procured 40 new carriages from Bombardier based in Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 40 carriages, the government is also supporting Southern’s tendering process for 116 new electric carriages with the option for a further 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our support for Southern will not only boost capacity but help secure British jobs. The deal for the 40 new carriages, helped along by my department, demonstrates the government’s ongoing commitment to invest in Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My officials are working with Southern to accelerate their procurement process for up to 256 carriages because our ambitious electrification plans requires additional rolling stock on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2011 Southern Railway, with government support, announced its plans to buy 130 carriages from Bombardier to run on services in south London, Surrey, Sussex and Kent. Southern expects these will be in service by December 2013. As part of this deal Southern had the option to buy the additional 40 carriages at a later stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July the government announced the biggest programme of rail modernisation since the Victorian era. At the heart of the scheme was the electrification of the Midland Main Line, from London to Sheffield, with additional spurs linking it to the Great Western Main Line and the Port of Southampton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Southern progresses with the procurement, these 116 new vehicles, and potentially 140 more, could initially be used on the Thameslink routes. Once the expected new Thameslink trains are operational these carriages will be moved to the newly electrified routes, which could include the Midland Main Line to Corby and North Transpennine Routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60317</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-10T14:37:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/rail-passenger-miles"/>
    <title>Rail passenger miles</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Latest quarterly data on rail passenger miles.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-other-key-data"&gt;DfT Business plan other key data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geographical coverage: Great Britain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information broken down by: Rail sector&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Passengers travelled 9.2 billion miles by rail in the second quarter of 2012-13 (July to September 2012), an increase of 4 per cent when compared to the same quarter in 2011-12.  The second quarter of 2012-13 included the Olympic and Paralympic Games, which will have contributed to this increase in rail travel.  These figures are for franchised operators only, so exclude travel with non-franchised operators, such as Grand Central, Heathrow Express and Hull Trains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last ten years, other than a slight dip in 2009 during the recession, passenger rail usage has increased significantly, continuing the upward trend that has been seen since the mid-1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passenger miles travelled with franchised rail operators&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Quarter&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Quarterly total (billions)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Quarterly moving annual average (&lt;abbr title="Moving Annual Average"&gt;MAA&lt;/abbr&gt;) (billions)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11 Q1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11 Q2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11 Q3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010/11 Q4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12 Q1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12 Q2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12 Q3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011/12 Q4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13 Q1&lt;sup&gt;P&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2012/13 Q2&lt;sup&gt;P&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;P&lt;/sup&gt; Figures are provisional&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#11"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-information"&gt;Background information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail passenger kilometres totals are published quarterly by the Office of Rail Regulation (&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt;). The rail industry’s central ticketing system, LENNON, is the basis for passenger kilometres data. LENNON holds information on the vast majority of national rail tickets purchased in Great Britain and is used to allocate the revenue from ticket sales between train operating companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Office of Rail Regulation"&gt;ORR&lt;/abbr&gt; also receives quarterly non-LENNON kilometres data from train operators. Non-LENNON data are information not recorded within the LENNON system such as operator specific tickets and Passenger Transport Executive (&lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executive"&gt;PTE&lt;/abbr&gt;) multi-modal tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics are converted from kilometres to miles by DfT for the purposes of this publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data supplied in the table and the charts refer to financial rather than calendar years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: quarterly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: 7 March 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://dataportal.orr.gov.uk/"&gt;Rail passenger kilometres statistics are published on the Office of Rail Regulation Data Portal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/tsgb-2011-public-transport"&gt;Annual passenger kilometres data for rail and other modes of public transport are published in Transport Statistics Great Britain (&lt;abbr title="Transport Statistics Great Britain"&gt;TSGB&lt;/abbr&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: &lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/60319</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-02T14:46:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/cost-of-running-the-rail-network"/>
    <title>Cost of running the rail network</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>The costs of running the passenger rail network by DfT franchised train operating companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="dft-business-plan-input-indicator"&gt;DfT Business Plan input indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="geographical-coverage-dft-franchised-train-operators-great-britain"&gt;Geographical coverage: DfT franchised train operators (Great Britain)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id="information-broken-down-by-dft-franchised-train-operator"&gt;Information broken down by: DfT franchised train operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="latest-data"&gt;Latest data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total cost of operating the rail network for train operators franchised by the Department for Transport (DfT) in 2010/11 was £9.3 billion. This consisted of £6.3 billion of train operator operating costs, and £3.0 billion of Network Grant paid to Network Rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The costs of running the passenger rail network by DfT franchised train operating companies are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://charts.dft.gov.uk/dft-business-plan/indicators/#09"&gt;Click here to view this data in an interactive chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cost by franchise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Operator&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total Operating Cost (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Allocated Network Grant (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total (£m)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;c2c&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;98.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;42.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chiltern Railways&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;125.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;200.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CrossCountry&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;407.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;291.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;698.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Coast&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;454.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;191.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;645.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;East Midlands Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;292.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;183.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;476.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Capital Connect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;334.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;117.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;452.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First Great Western&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;629.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;317.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;946.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First TransPennine Express&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;220.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;116.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;336.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;London Midland&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;322.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;137.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;459.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;National Express East Anglia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;420.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;211.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;631.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Northern Rail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;522.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;359.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;882.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southeastern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;694.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;244.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;938.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Southern&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;549.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;191.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;740.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South West Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;559.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;259.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;818.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virgin Trains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;639.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;297.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;937.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total DfT franchised operators&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6,269.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3,036.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9,305.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source: Train operating companies, DfT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The operating costs relate to the financial year 2010/11.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="change-in-methodology-in-sourcing-cost-of-running-the-rail-network-figures"&gt;Change in Methodology in sourcing Cost of Running the Rail Network figures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication last year used data from operators’ statutory accounts.  This year the data are based on management accounts; this ensures that the time period to which the data applies is consistent across operators, and allows comparisons to be made over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="operating-costs"&gt;Operating costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) These data are based on the ORR study “Costs and Revenues of Franchised Passenger Train Operators in the UK”, which in turn sourced data from the operators’ management accounts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any figures relating to premia or associated payments to the Department for Transport or Passenger Transport Executives are excluded. Within this total are payments made by operators to Network Rail for access to the rail network which contribute towards infrastructure costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Operators may not treat all aspects of operating costs in the same way in their accounts, and so care should be taken when using these figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="network-grant"&gt;Network Grant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(c) This is calculated by taking the total Network Grant paid to Network Rail by DfT in 2010-11, and allocating it to each franchise based on their share of Fixed Track Access Charges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Allocated Network Grant’ column, allocates, to each operator, the grant paid by the Department for Transport to Network Rail in 2010-11. The grant effectively pays the infrastructure costs incurred by Network Rail that are not covered by operators. In the table above, each operator is allocated a share of the grant in proportion to their Fixed Track Access Charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-related-data-and-information"&gt;Other related data and information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train operating companies’ costs are taken from ORR publication &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rail-reg.gov.uk/upload/pdf/toc-benchmarking-report-2012.pdf"&gt;Costs and Revenues of Franchised Passenger Train Operators in the UK&lt;/a&gt;
Further information about this indicator can be found in the measurement template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing schedule: annually&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;last updated: December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next update: Spring 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/department-for-transport-business-plan"&gt;Business Plan 2012-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/input-and-impact-indicators"&gt;Input and impact indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst contact: &lt;a href="mailto:rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.stats@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/60281</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-secures-free-travel-for-london-midland-passengers"/>
    <title>Government secures free travel for London Midland passengers</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A £7 million package of benefits for rail passengers who suffered cancelled services and delays.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers who suffered cancelled services and delays last year will receive free travel passes and cheap tickets thanks to tough action taken by the government, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Midland season ticket holders will be given 5 days worth of free travel passes under a £7 million package of benefits. The government has also secured 500,000 additional cheap advance tickets for passengers on key network routes serving London, Birmingham, Northampton, Crewe and Liverpool and a commitment to invest in infrastructure improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“London Midland has cancelled or delayed hundreds of services in recent months. On repeated occasions, they were not able to provide enough drivers and some services had to be cancelled, with severe delays to services, and they have fallen short both of everyone’s expectations and their franchise obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing these benefits for passengers represents a firm yellow-card for London Midland and some financial benefit for those who have been hardest hit by their poor performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am confident London Midland has now rectified their driver shortage but the company need to be clear that we will continue to monitor their performance closely and take firmer action if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free tickets will be available to all monthly and annual season ticket holders, as well as to weekly ticket holders who have been affected by disruption, while the additional Advance tickets will be available over the next two years to passengers planning to travel on key London Midland routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal that has been struck will also confirm the end date of the franchise as September 2015, ensuring that London Midland is given sufficient time to resolve these problems on a permanent basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Midland will also spend millions of pounds improving the resilience of their trains and will invest at least £2.25 million on a range of measures to benefit passengers - primarily in the West Midlands, where the worst disruption was experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government is taking this action because London Midland were responsible for the cancellation of a high number of services, particularly at weekends and during the half-term period, due to a shortage of drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The free 5-day passes will enable annual and monthly season ticket holders to make additional journeys outside of their regular commute, or as an extension to existing season tickets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 500,000 additional cheaper advance tickets will be issued over and above those issued in the last year and will be for travel during 2013 and 2014. The tickets will be available on key routes including London-Birmingham, London-Crewe, London-Northampton and Birmingham-Liverpool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/60121</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:48:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--14"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Compensation package for passengers agreed with London Midland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would today like to give an update on the situation in relation to franchised train operator London Midland (&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passengers who use &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; trains may be aware that the operator has been experiencing difficulties recently, with a number of services being cancelled due to a shortage of driving staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation has caused inconvenience and disruption, particularly to passengers in the West Midlands, many of whom have expressed their dissatisfaction to me. I very much share their disappointment that they have not had the reliable service that they rightly expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although the recent levels of performance have been extremely disappointing, I am pleased to say that the measures that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; have put in place are beginning to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has implemented increases to driver efficiency to enable drivers to operate an increased number of routes during existing shifts, improved driver training processes, provided additional incentives for drivers to work overtime and put in place new measures that allow for drivers to cover shifts on other parts of the network where there are shortages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in addition to the ongoing training programme that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaking to ensure that new drivers enter productive service as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;’s performance has been of such a level that they are now in breach of their contractual obligations. We have made London Midland aware that they must now take action to compensate passengers for the disruption caused. We have, therefore, agreed with &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; that they will provide a substantial package of passenger benefits by way of compensation for the inconvenience that has been caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has agreed to spend an additional £4 million over the remainder of the franchise to put in place measures to ensure that these problems do not happen again. In addition, the package of passenger benefits includes the issue of 5 free rail day passes to London Midland season ticket holders, with an expected value of up to £3.5 million. We have also agreed that London Midland will invest a further £2.25 million in infrastructure improvement projects. We have required London Midland to discuss with Centro, the West Midlands Passenger Transport Executive, how the majority of this money will be invested for the benefit of those passengers who have experienced the worst disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this consultation, &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has agreed that most of this money should be directed towards measures such as improvements to safety and security at stations and improving the reliability and efficiency of &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we have also agreed with &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; that they must make available an additional 500,000 Advance tickets on key routes on the &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; network, giving a net benefit of around £1.9 million to passengers who will be able to take advantage of these cheaper fares over the next two years of the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; will be able to remain the operator of this franchise for the remainder of its contract - to September 2015. But London Midland will continue to work to challenging performance benchmarks for the remainder of the franchise, and we will take further action (including ending the franchise early and re-tendering it, if appropriate) in the event of any recurrence of performance problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the package of passenger benefits, we have agreed to revise the profile of performance benchmarks for the next year, to include additional measures that can penalise &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; financially in the event of further poor performance. We have also agreed financial measures to ensure that the reduction in revenue as a result of the free and discounted tickets is borne by &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;, and not by the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that this package, on balance, represents a good deal for passengers and taxpayers, and sends a message to the industry that this level of cancellations is unsatisfactory. I hope that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; can now put this period behind it, and continue to operate a good service for its passengers for the remainder of its franchise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
