<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Expanding and improving the rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16979</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/widespread-support-for-greater-rail-devolution"/>
    <title>Widespread support for greater rail devolution</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers and local communities could achieve better rail services and value for money for taxpayers if they have more say on how their railways are run, according to responses to a government consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback published today also reveals widespread support for rail devolution. The consultation asked individuals, regional groups and interested organisations to give their views on how devolution might work and what the benefits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide the best possible rail services for passengers and ensure that we reduce the cost of running our railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring decisions are taken by those best placed to make them – those who live and work in those areas – could make certain not only that services are planned to maximise value for money for taxpayers but that passengers get services they need and want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also revealed enthusiastic expressions of interest in helping to manage the railways from regional groups in London, the West Midlands and the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responses highlighted the success of regions where the operation of rail services has already been devolved, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merseyside, where Merseytravel has been responsible for the management of rail services since 2003&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London, where Transport for London has been responsible for the operation of London Overground services since 2007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland and Wales, where the operation of regional services is managed by the Scottish government and the Welsh Assembly government&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses also showed support for transport models specifically designed for particular regions on the basis of local geography and the structure of local networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A consultation document, ‘Rail decentralisation’, was published on 8 March 2012. Comments were invited by the end of June 2012. This is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport’s response to the rail decentralisation consultation is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government remains committed to seeking to implement an appropriate form of decentralisation in those parts of England where it is sensible to do so. Following the responses to the consultation, &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue informal discussions with those bodies who have submitted proposals or firm expressions of interest. It will consider further a number of issues that need to be resolved in order to proceed with any decentralisation agreement, subject to any changes to franchising policy which may emerge from the Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most train services are specified, procured and funded centrally by the Department for Transport in London. A public consultation has shown broad support for devolving greater responsibility for local rail services to local authorities, Passenger Transport Executives (PTEs) and Transport for London, where conditions are right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposals for decentralisation have been received from the Rail in the North consortium comprising Transport for Greater Manchester, West Yorkshire PTE with York City Council and South Yorkshire PTE; Centro and Transport for London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressions of interest have been received from West of England Partnership (the Greater Bristol area), Devon and Cornwall Councils, Merseytravel, the Association of North East Councils and Cumbria County Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is envisaged that interested bodies will be ready to submit formal proposals in the first half of next year. In the meantime, the Department for Transport will continue informal discussions with these bodies as they prepare and consult on their formal proposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 70% of respondents to the consultation said they supported devolution of powers to manage the railways to regional bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16975</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:45:02+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:45:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"/>
    <title>Rail decentralisation: devolving decision-making on passenger rail services in England</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most train services in England are specified, funded and managed centrally by the Department for Transport based in London. Passenger Transport Executives’ (&lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt;) and local authorities’ influence over the rail services provided in their local area is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with its aspirations for localism, the government is seeking to devolve, where appropriate, more accountability and decision-making related to local rail services to sub-national bodies, such as local authorities and &lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. This consultation explores how this might be done in parts of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="why-we-are-consulting"&gt;Why we are consulting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government wishes to seek views on whether improved outcomes for transport users might be achieved in some cases if more decisions relating to local rail services were made closer to the communities they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also inviting sub-national bodies - &lt;abbr title="Passenger Transport Executives"&gt;PTEs&lt;/abbr&gt; and local authorities - to indicate their interest and come forward with outline proposals for taking on decision-making responsibility for passenger rail services in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation complements the command paper, ‘Reforming our railways’, published today. That sets out the government’s vision for rail and responds to Sir Roy McNulty’s independent report on value for money on the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/reforming-our-railways/"&gt;Command paper: Reforming our railways&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-09/"&gt;Consultation: Rail fares and ticketing review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/greening-20120308a/"&gt;Rail reform command paper oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 8 March 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120308a/"&gt;Ending inflation-busting rail fare rises press release, 8 March 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16877</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T16:47:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/greater-anglia-franchise-specific-agreement"/>
    <title>Greater Anglia franchise specific agreement</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note that the Public Register of Franchise Agreements is updated on a quarterly basis and that the data held on the website may not be necessarily be the most current information held by the department. If you cannot find the information that you need, please contact us at &lt;a href="mailto:rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;rail.publicregister@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications?tag=public-register-of-franchise-agreements"&gt;Public Register of Franchise Agreements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16621</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:33:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/passengers-to-benefit-from-olympic-boost-to-services--2"/>
    <title>Passengers to benefit from Olympic boost to services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Music lovers and sports fans travelling to gigs and games will benefit from more convenient train services under plans to make it easier for operators to offer more flexible timetables, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes, which are being introduced after a successful trial during the London 2012 Games, will mean that on special occasions train operators will be able to adjust a small portion of the timetable to better serve passengers without seeking permission from the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games were a massive success and proved our transport system was able to successfully carry record numbers of passengers. We helped train operators cope with the changing demand by giving them more flexibility to give passengers the services they needed.
&amp;gt;This has proved such an unqualified success that we have decided to permanently cut the red tape involved in adjusting small portions of the timetable. The changes give train companies the opportunity to ensure passengers are able to plan ahead to ensure they make it to their football matches and concerts and back home again on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Roberts, Chief Executive of the Association of Train Operating Companies (&lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is good news for passengers. Train companies have been seeking greater freedom to adapt their timetables to suit the needs of their customers and this move will be a big boost for people wanting to enjoy many special events across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes enable operators in England to adapt their timetables to cater for events in the calendar year when changes in passenger demand are expected to be significantly different – such as during sporting and cultural events or during school holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train operators will be allowed to adjust up to 30% of their timetabled services for special occasions, ensuring that more frequent passengers are still able to enjoy regular services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary will retain discretion over all timetable changes and the new measures and passenger benefits gained will be reviewed within the next 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The General Consent protocol, which enables train operators to adjust a small portion of their timetables for special events, was trialled with Southern Trains from the 17 April – 23 June 2012. This was then extended to all English train operators during the London 2012 Games.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The decision follows the success of the pilots and following consultation with Passenger Focus, London TravelWatch and &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Secretary of State is not responsible for the management of services within Scotland and Wales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/17110</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T08:31:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/decision-letter-greater-manchester-light-rapid-transit-system"/>
    <title>Greater Manchester: light rapid transit system (Oldham, Manchester Street modification) decision letter</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decision letter to authorise a modification to the route of an extension of the Metrolink system near Oldham Town Centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/16627</id>
    <published>2012-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-21T09:30:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/contact-telephone-numbers-for-crosscountry-rail"/>
    <title>Contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry rail</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of Information request regarding geographical contact telephone numbers for Crosscountry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16141</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:04:43+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-views-multi-billion-pound-plans-for-the-north-west"/>
    <title>Minister views multi-billion pound plans for the north west</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major upgrade to rail links which will bring over £4 billion of economic benefits to the north west is progressing well, said Transport Minister Simon Burns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister visited Manchester and Liverpool today to see for himself work on the Northern Hub and plans for the electrification of rail lines – both projects could bring up to 30,000 jobs to the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Hub will see a new rail link being built (the Ordsall Chord), stations extended and journey times improved while the electrification programme will enable faster, more reliable and greener trains to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transport provides the crucial links that allow individuals and communities to prosper and that is why this investment is so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Commuters and businesses in the region will be big winners thanks to quicker and greener trains and more services across Manchester. But these improvements will also benefit the UK as a whole due the crucial role the north west plays in the country’s transport system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This investment demonstrates that the government is delivering on its commitment not only to improve the transport system but also to use it as an engine to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the minister toured Manchester Airport and Manchester Airport railway station where he viewed plans for a 4th railway platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new platform will increase capacity by enabling the station to accommodate longer and more trains. He also visited Piccadilly station which will have extra platforms as part of the Northern Hub project and toured Tuebrook Sidings, in Liverpool, which is 1 of 13 compounds which will be used to store materials during the second phase of the north west electrification scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Northern Hub is a series of proposed projects to boost economic growth through better train services across northern England&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The individual projects were identified in a study published by Network Rail in February 2010&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In July 2012 the government announced it was backing the full scheme. The full package of enhancements is set to be in place by 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s electrification programme will also see rail lines on the Great Western Main Line electrified all the way to the South Wales Valleys. The Midland Main Line between Bedford and Sheffield will also be electrified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A study by Network Rail estimates the investment will bring over £4 billion of wider economic benefits to the north west resulting in 30,000 new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16093</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T09:30:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/channel-tunnel-transposition-of-railway-safety-and-interoperability-directives"/>
    <title>Channel Tunnel: transposition of railway safety and interoperability directives</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking views on whether to transpose the requirements of 3 European directives on railway safety and interoperability so that these provisions are in force for the Channel Tunnel. In recognition of the Tunnel’s cross-border nature these we would like to incorporate the provisions of these railway safety and interoperability directives by making amendments to the Channel Tunnel (Safety) Order 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16063</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boxing-day-boost-for-bargain-hungry-passengers"/>
    <title>Boxing day boost for bargain-hungry passengers</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra rail services – which will make it easier for shoppers to access retail hubs in central London, Stratford and Kent – are being provided thanks to an agreement between the Department for Transport, Southeastern, and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have devised a unique agreement to enable Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; to make it easier for their passengers to get to the sales following Christmas, which will provide more services at no cost to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Southeastern ran some very successful services on High Speed 1 during the Olympics and the train operator has shown there is sufficient demand for these services so we were happy to consider allowing them to adjust their timetables. This is an excellent example of the government, infrastructure owners and train operators working innovatively together to improve services for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern’s managing director, Charles Horton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to offer this trial Boxing Day service for our passengers thanks to the collaboration with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our high speed Javelin service will transport people from Ashford to St Pancras International in just 37 minutes, and 19 minutes from Ebbsfleet. We’re also pleased to offer free parking at these 2 stations for Boxing Day so everyone has a little bit extra to spend in the sales!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Ruse, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, the company that owns High Speed 1 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Demand for high speed rail travel is rising all the time and this welcome example of teamwork on the railways means we can offer high speed rail customers a service that will prove hugely popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The half hourly service will run between Ashford International, Ebbsfleet International, Stratford International and St Pancras International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd ran a special timetable through the Olympics and Paralympics with extra high speed services to carry spectators to and from Stratford International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timetables and ticket information can be viewed online at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/"&gt;nationalrail.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/16218</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T13:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/nuneaton-north-chord-event"/>
    <title>Nuneaton North Chord event</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for asking me along today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely delighted to be here because what you’ve achieved with this new chord really matters. And let me tell you why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, today we earn our living in a global marketplace - one where what we sell in Boston or Shanghai is just as important as what we make in Bristol or Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that rail freight is more important than it’s ever been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving products and raw materials quickly and reliably - that’s how you power up the recovery and grow the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-sense-environmental-sense"&gt;Economic sense, environmental sense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although this new chord isn’t massive in scale like Crossrail or &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, it’s certainly a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment worth more than £25 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that will allow freight traffic to travel through Nuneaton station, without affecting passenger services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An investment that means better and faster links between the global gateway of Felixstowe and the Midlands, the north west and Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this new chord makes sound economic sense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you consider the chord’s potential to cut carbon emissions and ease traffic congestion by attracting freight from road to rail, then it soon becomes obvious that it makes environmental sense too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusions---right-investment-right-project-right-reasons"&gt;Conclusions - right investment, right project, right reasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add all that up and what you have is the right investment, in the right project, for the right reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I finish I just want to say a big thank you to everyone who made this possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have done a terrific job of work and, if I had a hat, I’d take it off to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on that note it is now my absolute pleasure to declare the Nuneaton North Chord officially open (minister unveils plaque).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
