<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Expanding and improving the rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56290</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T10:38:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/industry-launches-new-rail-technical-strategy"/>
    <title>Industry launches new rail technical strategy</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail industry leaders have outlined a 30 year vision for the railway through a new edition of the ‘Rail technical strategy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Rail technical strategy’ describes how technology can help the railway increase capacity, improve reliability, cut carbon emissions and reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy has been developed by the Technical Strategy Leadership Group – a cross-industry expert body with representatives from across the rail industry – and endorsed by the Rail Delivery Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.futurerailway.org"&gt;Read the Rail technical strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Transport  Simon Burns MP welcomed the strategy saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the industry picking up the baton to develop this Rail technical strategy. Technology has a vital role to play in improving the railway’s performance, cutting its costs along with carbon emissions and delivering a better travelling experience for passengers. By setting in place a 30 year vision, the railway is demonstrating that it has a bright and exciting future, and the potential to support our economy and society for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/48843</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T11:07:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/office-of-rail-regulation"/>
    <title>Office of Rail Regulation</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great pleasure to join you today for this important conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here to talk about ‘transparency’ – one of those modern buzzwords that we hear all the time in politics, business, and the media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by giving you my own perspective on transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transparency-for-the-customer"&gt;Transparency for the customer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speak as a rail minister…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a regular user of the rail network…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a Liberal Democrat…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have campaigned for transparency ever since I was first elected in 1997.  The first bill I presented to Parliament was on the release of public records and I was the first person to submit a &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; request of MPs’ expenses, with all the ramifications that led to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you won’t be surprised that I’m a passionate believer in transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something we need to see more of from every powerful institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud of the progress we have made to open up government and the wider public sector in this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I will say this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about building the respect, trust and confidence of the people who use and fund the network - passengers, freight customers, and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true measure of transparency comes not from those who claim to practise it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes from those on the outside who stand to benefit from it… the passengers and the public who provide the patronage and pounds sterling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be a shared agenda, while we have made big strides over the past few years, we still have some way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Laidlaw report&lt;/a&gt; last week made a specific criticism of the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; when it said the department wasn’t transparent enough with bidders about the franchise process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are correcting that and we will be more transparent in future, but you have to do your bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rail-transparency"&gt;Rail transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me put rail transparency in some sort of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.openpublicservices.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Open Public Services White Paper&lt;/a&gt; last year set the scene for the government’s transparency agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was followed this year by another White Paper and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.data.gov.uk/library/dft-open-data-strategy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Open Data Strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental to these programmes are public services which are responsive to the people they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations which can be held to account by citizens and elected representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open data is crucial to this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our rail reform programme highlighted 3 specific areas for transparency: rail finances; network performance and open access to information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so much has already been achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we are now publishing a great deal of performance data, from right time and passenger complaints to statistics on overcrowding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; has set out the costs of supporting the network by &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt;; subsidies per mile; and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail has separated accounts by route. And new information about &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt; finances will be published next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And passengers have much better access to timetables and real time service information than they had in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, data produced by Network Rail is allowing developers to generate phone and computer apps for passengers on how trains are running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a private-sector, not-for-dividend, company limited by guarantee, Network Rail is not currently subject to the Freedom of Information Act. Nonetheless, as a regulated provider of public services, in receipt of public subsidy, the company wisely recognises the demand for more of its information and data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, it began a programme to publish more of its information and data on its website, including an on-line form allowing members of the public to make suggestions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government welcomes these steps, which will improve the organisation’s accountability to passengers and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I welcome the excellent news from the last &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dft-transport-sector-transparency-board"&gt;Transport Transparency Board&lt;/a&gt; that the fares database will be released as open data during the first quarter of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="olympics"&gt;Olympics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these transparency measures are designed for long-term dissemination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Olympic Games earlier this year set the industry a more immediate challenge around the provision of transport data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key part of the programme was to provide businesses and the public with information about the transport network, and which stations were likely to be busiest at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Transport for London"&gt;TfL&lt;/abbr&gt;, Network Rail, &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt; and train operators worked with organisers to produce ‘hotspot’ data which was published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.getaheadofthegames.com/"&gt;Get Ahead of the Games&lt;/a&gt; website – together with journey planners and interactive tools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site had over 16 million page views and 4 million unique users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it played a key role in what was an enormously successful operation to manage transport demand during the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience was invaluable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It showed just what can be achieved by planning ahead and communicating information to users of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was also a lesson in how to deliver data effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information is of little use if it’s too complicated or inaccessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to be carefully managed, targeted and presented to meet the needs and expectations of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely what was achieved by the team who delivered the Olympics transport plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fares-and-ticketing"&gt;Fares and ticketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the government re-shuffle back in September, the new &lt;a href="/government/people/patrick-mcloughlin"&gt;Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; asked me to lead the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/rail-fares-and-ticketing-review"&gt;fares and ticketing review&lt;/a&gt; in the department.  You will appreciate that this is a hugely labyrinthine process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I am concerned, transparency is key to the review.  I want an outcome where the passenger can easily access the right information to enable them to buy the right ticket for their journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while many do, many don’t.  Indeed, there appears to be some confusion even at the highest levels, judging by &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s comments in the metro last week blaming the government for the rise in unregulated fares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now turn to the issue of right-time information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="right-time"&gt;Right-time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will know, I have been pushing for the release of right-time – the number of trains arriving within 59 seconds of the advertised arrival time - for some time now, actually for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first raised this formally at the Performance Delivery Group which I chair on 20 July 2011 and I am to be honest disappointed that it has taken this long to get where we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make it clear that it is not the intention of the government to replace &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; with right-time for performance benchmarking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may together conclude that the correct benchmark is whether a long-distance service arrives within 9 minutes and 59 seconds, but it is close to dishonest to suggest that a train arriving 9 minutes and 59 seconds after its stated arrival time is on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public are entitled to know the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I recognise, and indeed sympathise, that there is a concern within the industry that if this information is published, you will be attacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observe at this point that ScotRail recently released its right-time data and the world has not ended north of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that releasing information to the public can be uncomfortable – just look at the hundreds of &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; requests we have to deal with in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; each month.  But actually the free availability of information is a key tool to driving up performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry will be releasing right-time data by &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt; on 20 December, even if the timing means it won’t be getting much coverage, I will be making a lot of noise about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making comments saying what a good showing this is from the industry.  In terms of both performance and transparency we’re ahead of our European competitors so this staging post is welcome, but we need to go further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commuter on the 6:40 from Aylesbury, the student on the 8:32 to Brighton and the occasional traveller on the 10:15 to Nuneaton have a right to know whether their train is regularly on time or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look fwd to these passengers having the data they need when we make a further right-time release in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This information is held by the ORR and, as such, it is available under the &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; laws.  It is in my view far better for the industry to be on the front-foot with this rather than have it extracted by someone hostile to the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-transport-sectors"&gt;Other transport sectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that the rail industry is doing pretty well in punctuality.  Both in comparisons with other countries, and in this country when compared with other modes.  Why hide your light under a bushel as if there is a guilty secret?  Those of you who have been to my office will have heard me reference the poster in my office which champions the railway against the clogged road network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined the same level of transparency should apply to other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Highways Agency, for example, has released a wide range of statistics about roadworks and real-time traffic conditions, and over 80% local authorities have opened up their roadwork data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working with the Agency to improve reliability data for the motorway network, and hope to publish information on the wider road network next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus industry has released its national database of services across Britain, with access to real time information from all 350,000 bus stops… &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple but enormously effective improvement for passengers, particularly during these winter months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the aviation industry is also embracing transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) is already publishing monthly punctuality data by route and airline for 10 UK airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our Civil Aviation Bill will enshrine further powers to collect and publish data to help the consumer. Specifically, it will require the industry to provide information that the CAA considers appropriate to help passengers understand and compare different services and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Bill has completed its passage through Parliament and now awaits Royal Assent.  We anticipate that this will be before Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s more the aviation industry could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, we would like the airlines to provide clearer information about the ticket price their customers should expect to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in reality, you have a good story to tell.  Some of you, however, are mindlessly trying to cover it up.  This is 1950s thinking and frankly, it won’t wash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me conclude by first of all recognising and congratulating the industry for the strides it has made towards greater transparency in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an industry that received £3 billion of public subsidy in 2010/11, the public has a right to clearer and more open information on costs, performance and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is what you are delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also urge you – wherever possible – to press ahead with further transparency in the future so it becomes embedded in the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe that whatever helps the passenger will ultimately help the railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18821</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T11:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:50:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-coast-main-line-final-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"/>
    <title>West Coast Main Line: Final report of the Laidlaw inquiry</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the cancelled West Coast Main Line franchise competition has concluded that the project failed because of an accumulation of significant errors related to inadequate planning and preparation, complex organisational structure, and a weak governance framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Sam Laidlaw, the chief executive of Centrica and a non-executive &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; board member, to conduct an urgent investigation following the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the procurement process that led to the competition being cancelled on October 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;final report&lt;/a&gt;, published today by the Department for Transport, finds that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; used flawed and inconsistent methodology when guiding bidders on the amount of risk capital (known as the Subordinated Loan Facility) they would need to offer to guarantee their franchise against default (Inquiry report paragraph 4.31, p22)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Subordinated Loan Facility figures resulting from the flawed methodology were then varied in a way that contravened franchise competition rules (3.4, p11)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ministers made the original August 14 provisional contract award without being told about the critical flaws (2.12, p8) and having been given “inaccurate reports” (3.8, p12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the Laidlaw Inquiry also concluded that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the report’s recommendations to strengthen accountability and governance structures “if acted upon quickly and effectively, will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement” (paragraph 8.6, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;while there were inconsistencies in the way First Group and Virgin Trains Ltd were treated during the franchise process, the report finds that there is no evidence of a culture of bias against Virgin at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; (paragraph 2.6, p7)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is nothing in the report to suggest that the flaws discovered in this franchise competition exist in any other &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; procurements (paragraph 8.3, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; is today publishing its formal response to the report which commits the department to implementing swiftly a series of actions that will enable it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring future franchise competitions are delivered at a good pace based on sound planning, a clear timeline, rigorous management, and the right quality assurance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a simpler and clearer structure and governance process for rail franchise competitions, including the appointment of a single director general with responsibility for all rail policy and franchising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring we have the right mix of professional skills, in-house, and where necessary from professional external advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Building upon and confirming the conclusions from my initial findings, the final report provides an in-depth analysis of the events that led to the flaws whereby the InterCity West Coast competition was cancelled. Alongside this I have also made a series of recommendations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have explained in detail the technical nature of certain errors, specifically around modelling flaws and the Subordinated Loan Facility sizing process. In addition, the report outlines an accumulation of contributory causes including a lack of transparency, inadequate planning and preparation, as well as a complex and confusing organisational structure with weak quality assurance and insufficient governance oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While it is clear that a number of serious and regrettable errors have occurred, I believe that if acted upon quickly and effectively, my recommendations will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The final report from the Laidlaw inquiry makes extremely uncomfortable reading for the department. It has identified precisely what went wrong, revealing serious failures, as well as offering us a number of sensible recommendations to put things right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will not allow these mistakes to be made again and the department is determined to ensure all future franchise competitions are conducted on the basis of sound planning, the rigorous identification and oversight of risk, and the right quality assurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw has delivered an uncompromising report that offers us a way to face up to a number of shortcomings and I would like to thank him and his team for producing these findings with such diligence and speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; Permanent Secretary Philip Rutnam said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no question that this has been a serious blow for the department and I am determined that we learn everything we can from this episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will implement all of Mr Laidlaw’s recommendations, and go further, to ensure we have the right set of skills, support and training to ensure failures like this do not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Laidlaw inquiry final report to the Transport Secretary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;department’s response to the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report&lt;/a&gt;, setting out the actions being taken immediately to resolve the report recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laidlaw-inquiry-final-report"&gt;Transport Secretary’s oral statement to the House of Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report is only part of the work the department is doing to review its rail franchising policy. It will also take into account the forthcoming &lt;abbr title="National Audit Office"&gt;NAO&lt;/abbr&gt; report into the lessons from the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise and the conclusions of Richard Brown’s review of the future of the rail franchising programme, due to be submitted to the Secretary of State by the end of December&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Laidlaw inquiry team: 020 7861 2410&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18811</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T11:38:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:38:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/permanent-secretary-concerning-west-coast-main-line"/>
    <title>Permanent Secretary concerning West Coast Main Line</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport Permanent Secretary Philip Rutnam yesterday received the report of the investigation into the role and conduct of officials in the award process for the ICWC franchise process conducted by Bill Stow (a former Director General at Defra). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is now considering the report and decisions on action following this investigation will be made shortly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Secretary decided yesterday to lift the suspensions of three DfT officials imposed on the 3 October. The decision to suspend a member of staff, or to lift that suspension, is separate from the disciplinary process and does not imply any conclusion on culpability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18775</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/virgin-trains-to-run-improved-west-coast-services"/>
    <title>Virgin Trains to run improved west coast services</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers will experience better services including 28,000 more seats a day under an agreement announced today for Virgin Trains to continue operating rail services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise agreement will run for up to 23 months after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It coincides with the early completion of a government-backed deal to roll out 106 new Pendolino carriages, providing passengers with four new 11-carriage trains and lengthening 31 existing trains from nine carriages to 11. A new hourly service between London and Glasgow will also be introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to ensure not only that passengers continue to experience the same levels of service they have in the past, but that services improve. There will be a new hourly service linking Glasgow and London and we will also work with Virgin Trains to explore other service improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also extremely pleased that passengers will benefit from up to 28,000 more seats daily thanks to the delivery of 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line which has happened on budget and ahead of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling on Virgin Trains will also find it easier to claim compensation if their train is severely delayed thanks to plans for Virgin Trains to introduce an improved passenger’s charter incorporating a delay repay scheme from 1 April 2013, subject to agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 23 month franchise will run from 9 December 2012 until 9 November 2014 after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise. The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be able to shorten this period by up to six months if a subsequent franchise can be let on a shorter timescale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The franchise will operate as a management contract with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. In return Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;) will receive a margin of 1% on revenue for operating services. The franchise also makes a provision for the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 106 Pendolino carriages project has been delivered on budget and ahead of schedule and has resulted from a successful collaboration between the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;, Virgin Trains, Alstom, Angel Trains and Network Rail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/28514</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:40:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"/>
    <title>Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport is today publishing its formal response to the report which commits the department to implementing swiftly a series of actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/18789</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T09:32:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/intercity-west-coast-franchise"/>
    <title>InterCity West Coast franchise</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 October 2012 I announced to the House that following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise competition the Department for Transport was commencing negotiations with Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that negotiations have concluded successfully and that Virgin Trains will continue to operate services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After careful consideration I believe taxpayers, rail passengers and the wider rail industry will be better served by moving directly from this agreement with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to a longer term franchise on the West Coast Main Line. Doing so will provide greater certainty for passengers, minimise disruption for all stakeholders and enable us to maximise the benefits for taxpayers and West Coast passengers. For this reason the new franchise with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will be for up to 23 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce that passengers will not only experience the same levels of service they have previously enjoyed but will also benefit from improvements to previous levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition this agreement coincides with the successful completion today, on budget and ahead of schedule, of a project to deliver 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new carriages, which will see up to 28,000 extra seats provided each day, are being introduced with £1.5 billion of government support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new franchise agreement, there will also be a new hourly service between London and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This franchise will operate as a management contract, with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the government. In return &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will receive a margin of 1% on revenue. The contract also makes a provision for the department and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/18813</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:50:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laidlaw-inquiry-final-report"/>
    <title>Laidlaw inquiry final report </title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, with permission I would like to make a statement on what went wrong with the West Coast franchise agreement and what we are doing to put things right.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I will update the House on the Laidlaw inquiry and the decisive action that we are taking in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I will inform the House of the new deal with Virgin Trains, including an enhanced service, that will begin this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dealing with all this, from the start, my approach has been to come to the House to explain the situation openly, quickly and clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is in that spirit that I make my third statement on this subject today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I turn to the Laidlaw inquiry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 3 October I announced the cancellation of the competition to run the Inter-City West Coast franchise because of the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the process run by the Department for Transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained to the House on the 15 October, I launched 2 independent inquiries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the first inquiry, led by Sam Laidlaw, to look into what happened and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing his final report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the second review, led by the Eurostar chairman Richard Brown, to focus on any lessons to be learned for future of rail franchising. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is well advanced. I expect to receive his report by the end of the year. I will publish it after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am placing a copy of Mr Laidlaw’s final report in the Library alongside a copy of my department’s response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not hide from the seriousness of his findings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They make extremely uncomfortable reading for the department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They caused serious problems for bidding firms including First Group who were in no way at fault. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They must – and will – be acted upon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me turn to the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Laidlaw confirms much of what he first touched on in his interim report. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He finds that the department wrongly calculated the amount of risk capital bidders would have to offer to guarantee their franchise proposals against default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he says that these incorrect figures vary in ways that were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significantly, he also states for the first time that ministers made the original 14 August provisional award without being told about the flaws and after being given “inaccurate reports”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Laidlaw also confirms that if his recommendations on strengthening the organisation are acted upon quickly the department will be able to do its job correctly in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing in the report to suggest that the flaws discovered in this franchise competition existed in other procurements in the department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Mr Laidlaw confirms that he has seen no evidence of bias against Virgin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also offers a clear prescription which we are already acting upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will ensure that all future franchise competitions are delivered with a clear timeline, rigorous management and the right quality assurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also create a simpler and clearer structure and governance process for rail franchise competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include the appointment of a single director general with responsibility for all rail policy and franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will ensure that we have the right mix of professional skills inside the department and, where necessary, from professional external advisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank Mr Laidlaw for carrying out such a comprehensive review to such a tight timetable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any specific personnel issues resulting from what has gone on are, and must of course remain, an issue for the Permanent Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, let me turn to the future of the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my actions, I have put the service to the passenger first. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am pleased to tell the House that my department has negotiated terms with Virgin Rail Group to allow Virgin Trains to continue running the West Coast service for up to 23 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our intention is to run a full competition for the longer term franchise to follow on from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms we have negotiated with Virgin secure continued service for passengers at the same levels they enjoy today, and in some cases better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timetable that was already agreed for December 2012 will operate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today, the last of the 106 government-funded Pendelino carriages comes into service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will allow more trains and longer trains on this vital route. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That timetable includes a new hourly service between London and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to see more improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among them, the introduction of new services from London to Blackpool and Shrewsbury. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject to Virgin securing the track access rights to provide these, and to our completing a value for money assessment, I would hope that both of these new services will be introduced from December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, the Laidlaw inquiry has told us that changes to the department’s governance and structure are needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are and will carry them out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have a new deal for the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been extremely serious issue for my department.  But I am determined that we learn the lessons and get on with the job we are here to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with our commitment to High Speed Two and the increase in capital spending on roads announced by my &lt;abbr title="Right Honourable"&gt;RH&lt;/abbr&gt; Friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer this week, this government is committed to improving our transport network and backing our railways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/43742</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:40:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"/>
    <title>Report of the Laidlaw inquiry</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the Department for Transport’s handling of the franchise competition to run the West Coast Main Line has submitted its report to Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin. Mr McLoughlin has today published that report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16979</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T09:46:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/widespread-support-for-greater-rail-devolution"/>
    <title>Widespread support for greater rail devolution</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passengers and local communities could achieve better rail services and value for money for taxpayers if they have more say on how their railways are run, according to responses to a government consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback published today also reveals widespread support for rail devolution. The consultation asked individuals, regional groups and interested organisations to give their views on how devolution might work and what the benefits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rail Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to provide the best possible rail services for passengers and ensure that we reduce the cost of running our railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ensuring decisions are taken by those best placed to make them – those who live and work in those areas – could make certain not only that services are planned to maximise value for money for taxpayers but that passengers get services they need and want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also revealed enthusiastic expressions of interest in helping to manage the railways from regional groups in London, the West Midlands and the north of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responses highlighted the success of regions where the operation of rail services has already been devolved, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merseyside, where Merseytravel has been responsible for the management of rail services since 2003&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London, where Transport for London has been responsible for the operation of London Overground services since 2007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scotland and Wales, where the operation of regional services is managed by the Scottish government and the Welsh Assembly government&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responses also showed support for transport models specifically designed for particular regions on the basis of local geography and the structure of local networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A consultation document, ‘Rail decentralisation’, was published on 8 March 2012. Comments were invited by the end of June 2012. This is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport’s response to the rail decentralisation consultation is available on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/rail-decentralisation-devolving-decision-making-on-passenger-rail-services-in-england"&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government remains committed to seeking to implement an appropriate form of decentralisation in those parts of England where it is sensible to do so. Following the responses to the consultation, &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue informal discussions with those bodies who have submitted proposals or firm expressions of interest. It will consider further a number of issues that need to be resolved in order to proceed with any decentralisation agreement, subject to any changes to franchising policy which may emerge from the Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most train services are specified, procured and funded centrally by the Department for Transport in London. A public consultation has shown broad support for devolving greater responsibility for local rail services to local authorities, Passenger Transport Executives (PTEs) and Transport for London, where conditions are right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposals for decentralisation have been received from the Rail in the North consortium comprising Transport for Greater Manchester, West Yorkshire PTE with York City Council and South Yorkshire PTE; Centro and Transport for London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressions of interest have been received from West of England Partnership (the Greater Bristol area), Devon and Cornwall Councils, Merseytravel, the Association of North East Councils and Cumbria County Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is envisaged that interested bodies will be ready to submit formal proposals in the first half of next year. In the meantime, the Department for Transport will continue informal discussions with these bodies as they prepare and consult on their formal proposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 70% of respondents to the consultation said they supported devolution of powers to manage the railways to regional bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
