<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/expanding-and-improving-the-rail-network/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Expanding and improving the rail network"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16063</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T10:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T10:25:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/boxing-day-boost-for-bargain-hungry-passengers"/>
    <title>Boxing day boost for bargain-hungry passengers</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bargain hunters will find it easier to get to the sales this year under plans to boost Boxing Day rail services, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra rail services – which will make it easier for shoppers to access retail hubs in central London, Stratford and Kent – are being provided thanks to an agreement between the Department for Transport, Southeastern, and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have devised a unique agreement to enable Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; to make it easier for their passengers to get to the sales following Christmas, which will provide more services at no cost to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Southeastern ran some very successful services on High Speed 1 during the Olympics and the train operator has shown there is sufficient demand for these services so we were happy to consider allowing them to adjust their timetables. This is an excellent example of the government, infrastructure owners and train operators working innovatively together to improve services for passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern’s managing director, Charles Horton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to offer this trial Boxing Day service for our passengers thanks to the collaboration with &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; and the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. Our high speed Javelin service will transport people from Ashford to St Pancras International in just 37 minutes, and 19 minutes from Ebbsfleet. We’re also pleased to offer free parking at these 2 stations for Boxing Day so everyone has a little bit extra to spend in the sales!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Ruse, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd, the company that owns High Speed 1 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Demand for high speed rail travel is rising all the time and this welcome example of teamwork on the railways means we can offer high speed rail customers a service that will prove hugely popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The half hourly service will run between Ashford International, Ebbsfleet International, Stratford International and St Pancras International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southeastern and &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt; Ltd ran a special timetable through the Olympics and Paralympics with extra high speed services to carry spectators to and from Stratford International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timetables and ticket information can be viewed online at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/"&gt;nationalrail.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14868</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T14:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:50:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-headquarters-for-rail-accident-investigators"/>
    <title>New headquarters for rail accident investigators</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today officially opened the new premises of the Rail Accident Investigation Branch (&lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt;), the independent investigators working to make the railways safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southern team of the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is now based at Cullen House, near Aldershot, Hampshire, on the same site as the Air Accident Investigation Branch (AAIB). Previously the team were based in Woking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail is significantly safer now than in previous years because the industry has ensured safety issues have been identified and safeguards introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; is helping to ensure that our safety record continues to improve by carrying out thorough investigations when something goes wrong and identifying what needs to change to prevent it happening again. The new premises at Cullen House give the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; an excellent base from which to carry out their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief Inspector Carolyn Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cullen House provides a continuing presence for the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; in the south east which together with its northern team in Derby provides a balanced coverage for the geographical territory we investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To date since becoming operational in 2005 we have completed 196 investigations The industry has implemented 95% of recommendations from those investigations, bringing about real changes that improve safety for passengers and those who work on the railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cullen House, Patrick McLoughlin met &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; staff and unveiled a plaque marking the official opening of the new premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new premises are named after Lord Cullen who in 2000 led a public enquiry into the Ladbroke Grove rail crash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sole purpose of &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; investigations is to prevent future accidents and incidents and improve railway safety - the &lt;abbr title="Rail Accident Investigation Branch"&gt;RAIB&lt;/abbr&gt; does not establish blame, liability or carry out prosecutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For media enquiries, please call 020 7944 3248&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3248  &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/12799</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T15:58:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/additional-car-parking-at-bedwyn-station"/>
    <title>Additional car parking at Bedwyn station</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Freedom of Information response letter and supporting material concern additional car parking at Bedwyn station.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15227</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T15:43:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/rail-interoperability-derogations"/>
    <title>Rail interoperability derogations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interoperability regime provides for the possibility of an exemption to be granted to allow a specific project not to comply with particular standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 provide for derogations to be granted, at the discretion of the Secretary of State, for projects to introduce new, upgraded or renewed subsystems but these are only available in limited circumstances which can be summarised as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;projects at an advanced stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gauge or energy incompatibility issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network separation or isolation by sea or geography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;economic viability issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accident or natural disaster recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some circumstances, other factors can allow exemptions for upgrade and renewal work, and in all cases, the Secretary of State must notify the European Commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="list-of-derogations"&gt;List of Derogations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/a-list-of-rail-interoperability-derogations-applied-for-by-the-united-kingdom"&gt;A list of derogations applied for by the United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15321</id>
    <published>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-05T12:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/help-notes-for-the-railways-interoperability-regulations-2011"/>
    <title>Help notes for the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These help notes are for the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 (RIR 2011) which apply to all of the United Kingdom including the British half of the Channel Tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These help notes are published by the Department for Transport (DfT) to assist industry and others who are affected by the Railways (Interoperability) Regulations 2011 to fulfil their statutory obligations. They do not cover every circumstance and users should consider seeking further advice from the appropriate safety authority (Office of Rail Regulation, Intergovernmental Commission and Department for Regional Development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These help notes are produced in line with the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills guide to code of practice on guidance which is available at:  &lt;a href="http://www.betterregulation.gov.uk"&gt;www.betterregulation.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reader will find that the process-based parts of help notes variously use the two terms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“must” and “shall”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“should” or “may”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Must” or “shall” indicates that a statutory duty needs to be fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Should” or “may” indicates a recommendation to achieve the best outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments, queries or suggestions on existing or further help notes, please e-mail &lt;a href="mailto:mailto:interoperability@dft.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;interoperability@dft.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/15799</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T22:57:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/all-party-parliamentary-rail-in-the-north-group-reception"/>
    <title>All party parliamentary rail in the north group reception</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introductory-remarks"&gt;Introductory remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Julie (Julie Hilling - Chair of &lt;abbr title="All Party Parliamentary Group"&gt;APPG&lt;/abbr&gt;). And many thanks for asking me along today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reputation of this group and its members as rail champions for the north really does go before you, so I’m genuinely delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to kick things off with a promise - always a hostage to fortune for a politician I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, here it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you all have packed diaries and busy schedules - so I promise to try and keep my speech short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was going to say keep it “brief”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, since becoming a minister, I’ve discovered that Whitehall is the only place on earth where, without a trace of irony, the term “brief” is used to describe a ten thousand word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern enough, connected enough, fast enough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I have a pretty straightforward view about Britain’s rail network, and it’s this - out-dated and over-burdened railways just won’t cut it in today’s global economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cost hard working families and hard pressed businesses time and money. And, in these testing economic times, you can be sure they are anything but an engine for powering up the recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t do our environment too many favours either. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest, relying on creaking and crumbling rail infrastructure is no way to shrink transport’s carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it doesn’t matter if it’s a regional link or a national network - Britain needs railways that are modern enough, connected enough and fast enough:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern enough to support economic growth and spur job creation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected enough to spread prosperity and open up life-changing chances for people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And fast enough to attract passengers and freight away from less eco-friendly alternatives like long-distance road travel and short-haul flying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="rolling-up-our-sleeves"&gt;Rolling up our sleeves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely convinced that a good rail system can do great things - socially, economically and environmentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we all know, the good and the great don’t come about simply because politicians are very keen on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, you only get concrete results by rolling up your sleeves and getting on with it. And that’s precisely what this government’s been doing on rail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£18 billion invested in our railways during this Spending Review period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A massively ambitious programme of rail modernisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And a range of groundbreaking reforms…. …from driving down costs and driving up efficiencies to devolving decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, on the second of those reforms, devolution, I know that there was a big response from people and organisations in the north to our rail decentralisation consultation…so I want to thank everyone who took the trouble to have their say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No community left out, no region left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a government that believes in top quality railways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that belief is underpinned by a rock-solid principle. Namely that no community should be left out, no region should be left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned, if we want all of Britain to be open for business then we can’t afford for any part of Britain to be isolated or disconnected from the country’s wider transport system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local, and actually national success, demands that north, south, east and west are plugged in and joined up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-the-performance-and-prospects-of-rail-in-the-north"&gt;Transforming the performance and prospects of rail in the north&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the very reason that transforming the performance and the prospects of rail in the north is a first order priority for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when it comes to one particular component of rail services in the north, I’ll admit that the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; hasn’t enjoyed its best media coverage lately. I’m of course talking about the west coast mainline bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t for one minute seek to carp or complain about that coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serious matters tend to generate serious headlines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also demand a serious response…which is why we are facing up to what went wrong and putting things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None-the less, I genuinely hope that none of the recent coverage obscures the bigger, and more positive, picture about what’s happening to rail in the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take our recent approval of a £4.5 billion contract to build a new generation of intercity trains at a purpose-built factory in County Durham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that passengers will be speeding along the tracks onboard new high-tech, high-spec trains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s also a welcome employment bonus, with the creation of 730 skilled jobs, as well as another 200 jobs during construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget our &lt;abbr title="High level output specification"&gt;HLOS&lt;/abbr&gt; announcement - a £9.4 billion investment programme that will uplift rail capacity and improve rail connections right across the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also pleased to say that work is well underway on the north-west electrification scheme….improving travel between Manchester and Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re not stopping there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we also intend building a brand new electric passenger and freight corridor - a rail spine linking the towns, cities and economies of the North, with the towns, cities and economies of the Midlands and south of England such as Sheffield, Nottingham, Reading and Southampton. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electric trains that run on these lines will be cleaner and cheaper to run than diesels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll have better acceleration and shift greater loads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’ll carry more passengers with fewer delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain English our investment is good for passengers, good for business and good for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also tell you that funding worth some £240 million will mean that rail users in the North enjoy more seats, quicker journeys and better services on the East Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, the communities and companies of the region are set to be big winners from the backing the government is giving to the northern hub.&lt;br&gt;
And let me say this - the Northern Hub is about the transforming the rail experience across the whole North, from Newcastle in the north-east to Liverpool in the north-west. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in terms of travel benefits this is a genuine landmark enterprise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s even better news&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because Network Rail estimate the northern hub will also bring over £4 billion worth of wider economic benefits to the region and potentially as many twenty to thirty thousand new jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ll forgive the unintended pun, looking down the track there is another game-changing rail modernisation heading towards the North - &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This national high speed rail network will slash journey times and deliver a step change in capacity on routes between Leeds, Sheffield, Birmingham, London and Manchester - and possibly to Edinburgh and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firms in the north will be able to use &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to exploit new markets and attract new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the region’s communities will have better access to jobs and essential services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a core component of the government’s long-term transport strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, for the sake of every region, it’s a project we’re determined to push across the finishing line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I think it’s time I kept the promise I made right at the start of this speech by winding up my remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s be frank, nobody ever complained that a politician’s’ speech was too short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if I may, I’d like to finish with a quote by one of America’s founding fathers, Benjamin Franklin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I grant you that’s a less than orthodox way to end a rail speech. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, for me, this quote sums up our approach to rail modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the 18th century Ben Franklin argued that, when it came to governing, “well done is better than well said.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me, that’s a yardstick which still stands the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m equally sure that, judged against it, the way this government is renewing, rebuilding and reforming our railways proves that, just like the great man said - actions really do speak louder than words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13024</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T18:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/meetings-between-the-secretary-of-state-and-bombardier"/>
    <title>Meetings between the Secretary of State and Bombardier</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Response concerning meetings between the Secretary of State and Bombardier and material relating to High Speed 2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/14889</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T12:47:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-transposition-of-directive-2008-57ec-on-the-interoperability-of-the-rail-system"/>
    <title>The transposition of Directive 2008/57EC on the interoperability of the rail system</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents set out the government’s final proposals for implementing Directive 2008/57RC on the interoperability of the rail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents seek stakeholder’s views on how we implement the requirements of the Directive including proposed draft Regulations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:191:0001:0045:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G1 - EC Directive 2008-57-EC (Interoperability Recast)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:108:0004:0019:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G2 - EC Regulation 352-2009 (CSM Risk Assessment)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:273:0012:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G3 - EC Directive 2009-131 (Interoperability Annex VII)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2009:341:0001:0013:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G4 - EC Decision 965-20095 (Amenments to Annex V11)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:326:0011:0024:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G5- EC Decision 1158-2010 (CSM Safety Certificate)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2010:327:0013:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G6 - EU Decision 1169-2010 (CSM Safety Authorisation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:043:0033:0054:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G7 - EU Decision 107-2011 (Common Specification for NVR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0008:0009:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G8 - EC Regulation 201-2011 (Declaration of Conformity)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:057:0021:0028:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G9 - EU Directive 18-2011 (Amending Annexes 11,V &amp;amp; V1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:063:0022:0025:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G10 - EC Decision 155-2011(Reference Document)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:256:FULL:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex G11 - EC Decision 633-2011 (Specification for infrastructure register)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:095:0001:0029:EN:PDF"&gt;Annex H - EC recommendation 217-2011 Authorisation for placing into srervice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/13588</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T15:49:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-coast-main-line-laidlaw-inquiry-interim-findings"/>
    <title>West Coast Main Line: Laidlaw Inquiry interim findings</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the Department for Transport’s handling of the franchise competition to run the West Coast Main Line has submitted an initial findings report to Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interests of transparency, Mr McLoughlin has today published that report, alongside a covering letter, and this afternoon delivered an update to Parliament about this report and wider progress on ensuring continuity of service on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw, the senior business figure and DfT non-executive director leading this independent review, has asked the DfT to release the following statement on behalf of his inquiry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the limited time available this is necessarily only a preliminary report. What is clear however is that in seeking to run a complex and novel franchising competition process, an accumulation of significant errors, described in the report, resulted in a flawed process.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These errors appear to have been caused by factors including inadequate planning and preparation, a complex organisational structure and a weak governance and quality assurance framework. The full causes and the lessons to be learnt will be addressed in the final report of my independent Inquiry to be published at the end of November.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Firm judgments should not be made based upon what are provisional findings or wider conclusions drawn at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Laidlaw Inquiry interim findings and Mr Laidlaw’s covering letter to the Transport Secretary are available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/laidlaw-inquiry-interim-report"&gt;DfT website.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Transport Secretary’s oral statement to the House of Commons of this afternoon is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/mcloughlin-20121029a/"&gt;DfT website.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Laidlaw Inquiry team: 020 7922 2402.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/13180</id>
    <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-08T18:49:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/guild-of-travel-management-companies-conference"/>
    <title>Guild of Travel Management Companies conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="opening-remarks"&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that introduction Ian (Ian Taylor - travel writer/journalist and conference host).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you also to everyone at the Guild for asking me along, it’s a genuine pleasure to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cant-and-wont-ignore-the-facts"&gt;Can’t and won’t ignore the facts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not sure if there are any fans of the “Yes Minister” TV series in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you too young to remember, “Yes Minister” was the 1980s version of “The Thick of it” but without the four letter words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there’s one scene where the civil servant, Sir Humphrey Appleby, says of the Minister Jim Hacker - “if he can’t ignore the facts he’s no business being a politician.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, based on that definition of politics I’m definitely in the wrong profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because, when it comes to the relationship between Britain’s transport system and Britain’s business travellers I can’t, and I won’t, ignore the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the facts are these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;today we have to earn our living and pay our way in a fast moving global economy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a global economy in which this Association’s members face cut-throat competition. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a global economy where the state of your transport system can be the difference between missing a meeting or making a deal…between winning a contract or losing a customer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And I have to tell you that those facts have not been lost on the countries we compete against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They know that creaking and crumbling transport links are a business burden that cost time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look around the world - the evidence is there in plain sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From North America to Latin America, and from our continental neighbours to the emerging economic powers of China and India, nation after nation is upgrading and expanding their transport infrastructure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every bridge they construct, every road they repair and every track they lay is a boost for their businesses and their economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we really don’t have the luxury of sitting back and looking on while our rivals invest in world class transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are our competition in the international marketplace, the economies we’re up against in a race to win the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if we’re going to out-produce, out-innovate and out-sell them, we cannot afford to be left behind in the starting blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="status-quo---latin-for-the-mess-were-in"&gt;Status quo - Latin for the mess we’re in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s something this guild and its members understand only too well&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know better than anyone that ours is a trading nation, as well as an island nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nation where what we sell in Boston or Shanghai is just as important as what we make in Bristol or Sheffield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the reason you have consistently called for a transport system that is high quality and high performance - one that helps, not hinders, our business travellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I want you to know that we hear what you say&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And trust me…those aren’t just warm words from a minister. The record proves that this is an issue where we are on your side and in your corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the minute we took office, this government made it clear that maintaining the transport status quo was not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, as someone once said, “status quo is simply Latin for the mess we’re in”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe me, that translation has more than a ring of transport truth about it because frankly, we didn’t just inherit a financial deficit back in May 2010, we inherited an infrastructure deficit too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely why we took the deliberate decision to focus time, effort and resources on making Britain’s transport networks fit for the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ll admit that the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; hasn’t enjoyed its best media coverage lately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t for one minute seek to carp or complain about that coverage&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serious matters like the west coast mainline bid tend to generate serious headlines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also demand a serious response - which is why we are facing up to what went wrong and putting things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None-the less, I genuinely hope that none of the recent coverage obscures the bigger transport picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, I can say with absolute conviction that there has been real success and welcome progress on many of the transport issues that matter most to the people you represent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="renewing-and-rebuilding-the-railways"&gt;Renewing and rebuilding the railways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the way we’re renewing and rebuilding the railways that so many of your members use and rely on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re engaged in a massive modernisation effort. And just this summer we announced a new rail investment programme worth more than £9 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re driving through landmark projects like Crossrail, Thameslink and the Northern Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to electrify more than 850 miles of track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, right across the country, we’re making rail travel a whole lot better with new services and extra carriages, more seats and faster journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our focus doesn’t begin and end with the conventional railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like this guild, the government recognise the huge benefits of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, just like you, we also know that our country and our economy need more than a high speed line - they need a high speed network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s exactly what we’re committed to building with HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only links London and Birmingham. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also speeds further north to Manchester and Leeds, and possibly to Edinburgh and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A network that not only opens up business opportunities at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one that also opens up business opportunities abroad by ensuring passengers have an opportunity to connect up with the Channel Tunnel rail link (HS1) and Heathrow airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HS2 will transform the way we live and work every bit as much as it transforms the way we travel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So make no mistake, the government is determined to push this project across the finishing line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="first-class-highways"&gt;First class highways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, business travellers don’t just need top-notch railways - they also need first rate highways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve been investing in this country’s roads and motorways too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cutting congestion by removing bottlenecks and tackling pinch points on vital corridors like the M5 and the M27&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using innovations like hard shoulder running and managed motorways to unlock capacity on crucial arteries like the M1 and the M25&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;even supporting the uptake of electric cars with a nationwide network of re-charging points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All this, and more, is designed to help motorists here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’ve also been thinking carefully about the key long-term challenges by undertaking a major Feasibility Study: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;looking at how we can best secure new investment capital &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reviewing new models of ownership and financing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and weighing up the most effective and efficient ways to maintain and modernise our strategic road network &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today and tomorrow - modern highways for a modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s our vision, and that’s what we’re working hard to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aviation"&gt;Aviation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having spoken about rail and road, let me now turn a subject that rarely fails to generate debate and discussion - aviation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the Wright Brothers defied gravity, air travel has shrunk our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in doing so, it has also broadened our horizons - personal and business &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s little wonder that issues like airport capacity and connectivity are high on the agenda for this guild and its members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, as the minister responsible for aviation, my response is the same. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m with you - aviation is a big deal. It matters, it counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me quickly walk you through some of the things being done to make sure the aviation sector is successful and sustainable &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re steering the Civil Aviation Bill through Parliament - legislation that will improve the passenger experience by reforming the 25 year old set of regulations that currently govern our main airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re just about to finish consulting on our draft Aviation Policy Framework- a framework that forms the basis for future sustainable aviation growth in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To increase reliability and reduce delays we’ve been trialling operational freedoms at Heathrow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, from electrifying rail tracks to building new rail links, we’re improving the connections between the train and the plane at airports like Stansted and Cardiff, Luton and Manchester, Birmingham and Heathrow, Gatwick and Coventry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all global gateways to new markets and new customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’re all set to become much easier places to get to, and fly from, when you’re travelling on business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re thinking ahead too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that the future of aviation in Britain is one where our airports are globally competitive and where you can connect to places all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m not talking about the future as just the next 4, 5, 6 years - but in terms of the next 4, 5 and 6 decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capacity, connectivity, hub status - aviation faces long-term challenges that require long-term solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lots of people and lots of organisations have ideas about how to meet those challenges, including this Guild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’ve asked Sir Howard Davies to chair an independent Airports Commission to consider the connectivity needs of the UK, and to make recommendations to government on how those needs can be met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I expect that Sir Howard will soon be setting out further details on the membership of the Commission and its work, including how he intends engaging with interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is determined to build the consensus needed to deliver a lasting solution to the issue of the UK’s aviation capacity and we believe that Sir Howard Davies’ Commission is the way to do that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, the Commission is in its early stages, but we are convinced that it will deliver and help us to maintain the UK’s hub status. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="wi-fi"&gt;Wi-fi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one last area I want to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not the usual “planes, trains and automobiles” stuff of business travel. But, in today’s internet driven world, it’s perhaps just as important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about Wi-fi connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern business traveller doesn’t just ply their trade in face to face meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a smart phone, a lap-top or the latest touch-screen tablet they work on the move, they work at home and they work outside of normal office hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that makes fast and reliable Wi-fi connections a business must, a business essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know it. Your members know it. And I’m pleased to be able to tell you that this government knows it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve made broadband one of our top infrastructure priorities and published a National Broadband Strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve set up a “Broadband Delivery UK” team in Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve given that team £530 million to help bring superfast broadband to homes and businesses across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve announced a special £100 million fund to help ten major cities become “super-connected cities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This country’s Britain’s business travellers deserve world class Wi-fi connections, as well world class transport connections - and we’re working hard to delver both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Britain’s transport networks are its arteries of trade, then this guild’s members are surely the heartbeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our business travellers - clocking up the miles, putting in the hard graft, making sure that Britain is always open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before I conclude, I just wanted to pay tribute to the work you do and the difference you make - this minister and this government recognise, value and appreciate everything you’re doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, having started off with a quote from a British comedy, I’d liked to finish off with one by an American President - Harry Truman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Truman once offered the following advice on public speaking - “If you can’t convince ‘em, confuse ‘em.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I hope that in speaking to you today I’ve been more convincing than confusing. I’ve certainly enjoyed having this chance to come along and talk about some of the things we’re doing to support the crucial work you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I thank you for you time. I thank you for listening. And I look forward to working with you all in the months and years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This speech represented existing departmental policy but the words may not have been the same as those used by the minister.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
