<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing housing support for older and vulnerable people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16958</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-better-deal-for-mobile-home-owners"/>
    <title>A better deal for mobile home owners</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes a number of reforms to the park homes sector, aimed at tackling a number of complaints made by residents of some mobile home site operators. These can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking an owner’s sale of their home - without justifiable reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees, breaching site rules and stopping owners from improving their homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures are designed to ensure site operators who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already whilst the rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring compliance with site licence conditions by enabling the courts to impose unlimited fines on operators who do not manage their sites properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing local authorities to make a reasonable charge on site operators for their licensing services, which they are currently unable to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving local authorities the power to carry out works on sites in an emergency or where the site operator has been found guilty of a breach of the licence, and charge the cost back to them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the rules around the sale of mobile homes so that unscrupulous operators cannot interfere with owners selling to a qualifying buyer who they have chosen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing legislation to improve other residents’ rights to reflect their status as home owners by, for example, allowing them to carry out home improvements without seeking permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15152</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:52:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-allocation-of-housing-and-homelessness-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2588/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 8 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations amend &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1294/contents/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) Regulations 2006&lt;/a&gt; in order to maintain the Government’s policy on eligibility for social hog and homelessness assistance in relation to non European Economic Area nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is making these amendments following a ruling in the Court of Justice of the European Union in the case of Zambrano (C-34/09).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wrote to chief housing officers about the new regulations on 17 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:36:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13294</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:53:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-changes-in-the-localism-act-2011-supplementary-guidance"/>
    <title>Homelessness changes in the Localism Act 2011: supplementary guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This supplementary guidance explains the changes sections 148 and 149 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/part/7/chapter/1/crossheading/homelessness/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; make to the homelessness legislation. It explains in practice how the new power, that allows private rented sector offers to be made to end the main homelessness duty, should work and what local authorities should do as a consequence of the new power’s introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance also explains the requirements of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2601/contents/made"&gt;Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012&lt;/a&gt;. The Order requires local authorities to put in place arrangements to ensure that the private rented sector offer accommodation that is suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance supplements parts of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-code-of-guidance-for-councils-july-2006"&gt;‘Homelessness code of guidance for local authorities’&lt;/a&gt; published in July 2006.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15620</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:27:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/gypsy-and-traveller-caravan-count-july-2012"/>
    <title>Gypsy and traveller caravan count: July 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release presents data from the count of gypsy and traveller caravans in England which took place on or around 19 July 2012. The twice-yearly count takes place in January and July, recording the number of caravans on both authorised and unauthorised sites across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The July 2012 count also included a count of new affordable residential pitches for the second time. This was done to allow such pitches to be included in the calculation of the New Homes Bonus for individual local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14732</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-statement-on-dale-farm"/>
    <title>Department statement on Dale Farm</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A spokesman said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The public want to see fair play - with planning rules being upheld and action being taken against those who try to cheat the system.
&amp;gt; “The Government has already changed the law to tackle abuses of the planning system, and we propose to strengthen the law further to allow councils to stop unauthorised sites as soon as they happen, to prevent future drawn-out cases like Dale Farm.
&amp;gt; “We are also providing £60 million of funding to help support authorised pitches for travellers, supporting law-abiding citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14727</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/welcome-support-for-park-home-residents"/>
    <title>Welcome support for park home residents</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today welcomed a Parliamentary Bill that will seek to offer additional protections for residents of park homes against unscrupulous or dishonest operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Aldous’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/mobilehomes.html"&gt;Private Members’ Bill&lt;/a&gt; (external link) is fully supported by the Government, led by the Housing Minister Mark Prisk, and has its second reading debate in the House of Commons on Friday 19 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many park home residents live in poor conditions and are unable to exercise their existing legal rights. The worst practices of dishonest site owners include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking the open market sales of park homes on their sites - without justifiable reason;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees and breaching site rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These abuses have manifested in real-life examples where operators have lied to prospective purchasers about the conditions of homes and even dug holes around homes to make them unsaleable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms are designed to ensure site owners who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already while rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms to the licensing system that applies to park home sites;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures to prevent operators from blocking residents’ sales in the open market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the existing law to protect occupiers from harassment and make it an offence to lie to prevent a home being sold;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a possible future ‘fit and proper’ registration to restrict the ability of unscrupulous operators from management of sites; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme to make pitch fee reviews more transparent and new rules on reviews so they are fairer and reflect the condition of the site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many people choose a park home expecting a peaceful retirement and a good quality of life. This bill will help to make that a reality by ensuring that sites are safe and properly managed and that residents are better able to exercise their rights.
&amp;gt; “This industry has been blighted by rogue operators - these reforms aim to drive them out of the industry securing a fairer deal both for home owners and for the good operators, running decent businesses.
&amp;gt; “This is why the Government is fully backing Peter Aldous’ Mobile Homes Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14706</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-responds-to-an-article-in-the-daily-mirror-that-claims-8000-elderly-people-have-been-denied-the-disabled-facilities-grant-due-to-council-funding-cuts"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk responds to an article in The Daily Mirror that claims 8000 elderly people have been denied the Disabled Facilities Grant due to council funding cuts</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk responds to an article in The Daily Mirror that claims 8000 elderly people have been denied the Disabled Facilities Grant due to local authority funding cuts, forcing many into care homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government has increased funding for the Disabled Facilities Grant. In 2011-12 the national allocation to local authorities was £200 million compared to £156.9 million under the last administration. This central support will total £745 million over the Spending Review period.
&amp;gt; “Despite the need to tackle the deficit we have inherited from the last Administration, we are also investing £6.5 billion in Supporting People services, providing £51 million for handyperson services and supporting Home Improvement Agencies to provide a range of services to a quarter of a million elderly and disabled households every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14697</id>
    <published>2012-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-sees-gurkhas-settling-into-rushmoor"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles sees Gurkhas settling into Rushmoor</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles saw first-hand the positive effect of Government funding in helping Nepalese Gurkhas and their families settle in the country on a visit to Aldershot today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles met council officials, Citizens Advice Bureau staff and local Nepali community leaders and discovered how Rushmoor Borough Council are spending £500,000 that he had given to help with integration of former soldiers and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2216606.jpg" alt="Eric Pickles meets Gurkhas at Rushmoor"&gt;Eric Pickles meeting Gurkhas and their families&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding has helped ease the exceptional pressures on Rushmoor, which has seen a large number of Gurkha ex-servicemen and their dependents arrive in the towns of Aldershot and Farnborough over a relatively short period of time. The recent arrivals include a high proportion of children and elderly Nepalese nationals which has placed a recognised strain on local social, health and education services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These brave British army veterans have given our country loyal service over many years. It is their bravery that has helped protect our way of life and our traditions and it is right that their dedication is honoured.
&amp;gt; “Many of these ex-servicemen and their families have been proud to call this country their home and we too are proud of the strong ties that have been established between the ex-Gurkhas, their families and their wider communities. We are determined that if they chose to settle in the UK to see that they and their families are treated with dignity and respect and are made to feel welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also used the visit to announce the final instalment of the funding, a £150,000 payment towards English language training which is seen as a vital element in helping the Nepali people settle and contribute to their local community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government and the Deputy Prime Minister announced a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2030149"&gt;£1.5million fund for the Gurkha community&lt;/a&gt; in November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1598005.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1598005.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
