<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing housing support for older and vulnerable people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16044</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:40:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/increasing-protection-for-homeowners"/>
    <title>Increasing protection for homeowners</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles today announced that homeowners will be protected from having their homes taken against their wishes by councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect civil liberties, Mr Pickles has introduced powerful safeguards to restrict the use of Empty Dwelling Management Orders. Legislation came into force today that means people who leave their house empty for more than 6 months no longer risk having it seized by their local authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the previous government introduced Empty Dwelling Management Orders. They allowed councils to take over properties that had been empty for as few as 6 months even if they weren’t boarded up or where the occupant had died. Furniture and possessions were often taken and councils could even seize the property when it was for sale if they thought the asking price was unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers will now be limited to empty properties that have become magnets for vandalism, squatters and other forms of anti-social behaviour - blighting the local neighbourhood. A property will have to stand empty for at least 2 years before an Empty Dwelling Management Order can be obtained, and property owners will have to be given at least 3 months’ notice before the order can be issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils have previously used the orders to instigate action against homeowners that is inappropriate, including against people in vulnerable situations. Councils have, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempted to use the powers against a homeowner while she was caring for her injured daughter in France &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taken action against the house of a 96-year old howeowner as soon as he passed away in a nursing home&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taken action against a divorcee, who faced action because he only lived in the property at weekends to visit his estranged children&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These new safeguards will ensure that responsible homeowners do not face having their properties seized. Mr Pickles said it is wrong that a bereaved family could face having their loved one’s home seized for a period if there is a delay in them deciding what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“An Englishman’s home is his castle and I’m proud to be able to help homeowners protect theirs from councils who are too draconian and heavy-handed in using their powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government is standing up for the civil liberties and property rights of hard-working people. Those suffering the loss of a loved one should not have to endure the added indignity of having their home seized because of a delay in them deciding what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why I’ve introduced these safeguards that mean the rights of responsible homeowners will be protected, while allowing action to be taken against genuine derelict buildings which blight neighbourhoods.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move comes on top of government plans to bring back into use many of the 300,000 properties in England that have been empty for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils now have a new incentive to bring empty properties back into use through the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, under which the government will match the Council Tax raised from any Council Tax collected from a property that previously stood empty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12712</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T18:04:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/offering-suitable-housing-to-homeless-people"/>
    <title>Offering suitable housing to homeless people</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Localism Act 2011 enables local authorities to end the main homelessness duty by arranging an offer of suitable accommodation in the private rented sector, without requiring the applicant’s agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed draft Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012 sets out those circumstances in which accommodation used for the private rented sector offer to end the main homelessness duty is not to be regarded as suitable.  It also looks at how best to strengthen requirements in relation to location and suitability, when local authorities secure accommodation for the use of households owed duties under the homelessness legislation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12789</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/english-indices-of-deprivation"/>
    <title>English indices of deprivation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks user views on plans for the English indices of deprivation. Responses to this consultation will help inform the content, guidance and outputs of the indices, alongside other sources of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/12788</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:38:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/evaluating-the-extent-of-rough-sleeping"/>
    <title>Evaluating the extent of rough sleeping</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document describes a set of proposed changes to the existing rough sleeping guidance. It also gives users of the rough sleeping figures and those involved in evaluating the scale of rough sleeping in their local area an opportunity to comment on the proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a public consultation and the Department for Communities and Local Government particularly welcomes responses from local authorities and the voluntary sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15152</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:52:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-allocation-of-housing-and-homelessness-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2588/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 8 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations amend &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1294/contents/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) Regulations 2006&lt;/a&gt; in order to maintain the Government’s policy on eligibility for social hog and homelessness assistance in relation to non European Economic Area nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is making these amendments following a ruling in the Court of Justice of the European Union in the case of Zambrano (C-34/09).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wrote to chief housing officers about the new regulations on 17 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:36:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13294</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:53:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-changes-in-the-localism-act-2011-supplementary-guidance"/>
    <title>Homelessness changes in the Localism Act 2011: supplementary guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This supplementary guidance explains the changes sections 148 and 149 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/part/7/chapter/1/crossheading/homelessness/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; make to the homelessness legislation. It explains in practice how the new power, that allows private rented sector offers to be made to end the main homelessness duty, should work and what local authorities should do as a consequence of the new power’s introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance also explains the requirements of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2601/contents/made"&gt;Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012&lt;/a&gt;. The Order requires local authorities to put in place arrangements to ensure that the private rented sector offer accommodation that is suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance supplements parts of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-code-of-guidance-for-councils-july-2006"&gt;‘Homelessness code of guidance for local authorities’&lt;/a&gt; published in July 2006.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15620</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:27:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/gypsy-and-traveller-caravan-count-july-2012"/>
    <title>Gypsy and traveller caravan count: July 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release presents data from the count of gypsy and traveller caravans in England which took place on or around 19 July 2012. The twice-yearly count takes place in January and July, recording the number of caravans on both authorised and unauthorised sites across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The July 2012 count also included a count of new affordable residential pitches for the second time. This was done to allow such pitches to be included in the calculation of the New Homes Bonus for individual local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14732</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-statement-on-dale-farm"/>
    <title>Department statement on Dale Farm</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A spokesman said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The public want to see fair play - with planning rules being upheld and action being taken against those who try to cheat the system.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The Government has already changed the law to tackle abuses of the planning system, and we propose to strengthen the law further to allow councils to stop unauthorised sites as soon as they happen, to prevent future drawn-out cases like Dale Farm.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We are also providing £60 million of funding to help support authorised pitches for travellers, supporting law-abiding citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14727</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/welcome-support-for-park-home-residents"/>
    <title>Welcome support for park home residents</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today welcomed a Parliamentary Bill that will seek to offer additional protections for residents of park homes against unscrupulous or dishonest operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Aldous’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/mobilehomes.html"&gt;Private Members’ Bill&lt;/a&gt; (external link) is fully supported by the Government, led by the Housing Minister Mark Prisk, and has its second reading debate in the House of Commons on Friday 19 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many park home residents live in poor conditions and are unable to exercise their existing legal rights. The worst practices of dishonest site owners include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking the open market sales of park homes on their sites - without justifiable reason;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees and breaching site rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These abuses have manifested in real-life examples where operators have lied to prospective purchasers about the conditions of homes and even dug holes around homes to make them unsaleable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms are designed to ensure site owners who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already while rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms to the licensing system that applies to park home sites;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures to prevent operators from blocking residents’ sales in the open market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the existing law to protect occupiers from harassment and make it an offence to lie to prevent a home being sold;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a possible future ‘fit and proper’ registration to restrict the ability of unscrupulous operators from management of sites; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme to make pitch fee reviews more transparent and new rules on reviews so they are fairer and reflect the condition of the site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Many people choose a park home expecting a peaceful retirement and a good quality of life. This bill will help to make that a reality by ensuring that sites are safe and properly managed and that residents are better able to exercise their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This industry has been blighted by rogue operators - these reforms aim to drive them out of the industry securing a fairer deal both for home owners and for the good operators, running decent businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is why the Government is fully backing Peter Aldous’ Mobile Homes Bill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
