<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing housing support for older and vulnerable people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15152</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:52:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-allocation-of-housing-and-homelessness-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2588/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 8 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations amend &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1294/contents/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) Regulations 2006&lt;/a&gt; in order to maintain the Government’s policy on eligibility for social hog and homelessness assistance in relation to non European Economic Area nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is making these amendments following a ruling in the Court of Justice of the European Union in the case of Zambrano (C-34/09).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wrote to chief housing officers about the new regulations on 17 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:36:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13294</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:53:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-changes-in-the-localism-act-2011-supplementary-guidance"/>
    <title>Homelessness changes in the Localism Act 2011: supplementary guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This supplementary guidance explains the changes sections 148 and 149 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/part/7/chapter/1/crossheading/homelessness/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; make to the homelessness legislation. It explains in practice how the new power, that allows private rented sector offers to be made to end the main homelessness duty, should work and what local authorities should do as a consequence of the new power’s introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance also explains the requirements of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2601/contents/made"&gt;Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012&lt;/a&gt;. The Order requires local authorities to put in place arrangements to ensure that the private rented sector offer accommodation that is suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance supplements parts of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-code-of-guidance-for-councils-july-2006"&gt;‘Homelessness code of guidance for local authorities’&lt;/a&gt; published in July 2006.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15620</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:27:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/gypsy-and-traveller-caravan-count-july-2012"/>
    <title>Gypsy and traveller caravan count: July 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release presents data from the count of gypsy and traveller caravans in England which took place on or around 19 July 2012. The twice-yearly count takes place in January and July, recording the number of caravans on both authorised and unauthorised sites across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The July 2012 count also included a count of new affordable residential pitches for the second time. This was done to allow such pitches to be included in the calculation of the New Homes Bonus for individual local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14732</id>
    <published>2012-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-statement-on-dale-farm"/>
    <title>Department statement on Dale Farm</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A spokesman said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The public want to see fair play - with planning rules being upheld and action being taken against those who try to cheat the system.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The Government has already changed the law to tackle abuses of the planning system, and we propose to strengthen the law further to allow councils to stop unauthorised sites as soon as they happen, to prevent future drawn-out cases like Dale Farm.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We are also providing £60 million of funding to help support authorised pitches for travellers, supporting law-abiding citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14727</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/welcome-support-for-park-home-residents"/>
    <title>Welcome support for park home residents</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today welcomed a Parliamentary Bill that will seek to offer additional protections for residents of park homes against unscrupulous or dishonest operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Aldous’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/mobilehomes.html"&gt;Private Members’ Bill&lt;/a&gt; (external link) is fully supported by the Government, led by the Housing Minister Mark Prisk, and has its second reading debate in the House of Commons on Friday 19 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many park home residents live in poor conditions and are unable to exercise their existing legal rights. The worst practices of dishonest site owners include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking the open market sales of park homes on their sites - without justifiable reason;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees and breaching site rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These abuses have manifested in real-life examples where operators have lied to prospective purchasers about the conditions of homes and even dug holes around homes to make them unsaleable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms are designed to ensure site owners who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already while rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms to the licensing system that applies to park home sites;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures to prevent operators from blocking residents’ sales in the open market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the existing law to protect occupiers from harassment and make it an offence to lie to prevent a home being sold;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a possible future ‘fit and proper’ registration to restrict the ability of unscrupulous operators from management of sites; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme to make pitch fee reviews more transparent and new rules on reviews so they are fairer and reflect the condition of the site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Many people choose a park home expecting a peaceful retirement and a good quality of life. This bill will help to make that a reality by ensuring that sites are safe and properly managed and that residents are better able to exercise their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This industry has been blighted by rogue operators - these reforms aim to drive them out of the industry securing a fairer deal both for home owners and for the good operators, running decent businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“This is why the Government is fully backing Peter Aldous’ Mobile Homes Bill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14706</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-responds-to-an-article-in-the-daily-mirror-that-claims-8000-elderly-people-have-been-denied-the-disabled-facilities-grant-due-to-council-funding-cuts"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk responds to an article in The Daily Mirror that claims 8000 elderly people have been denied the Disabled Facilities Grant due to council funding cuts</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk responds to an article in The Daily Mirror that claims 8000 elderly people have been denied the Disabled Facilities Grant due to local authority funding cuts, forcing many into care homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This Government has increased funding for the Disabled Facilities Grant. In 2011-12 the national allocation to local authorities was £200 million compared to £156.9 million under the last administration. This central support will total £745 million over the Spending Review period.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Despite the need to tackle the deficit we have inherited from the last Administration, we are also investing £6.5 billion in Supporting People services, providing £51 million for handyperson services and supporting Home Improvement Agencies to provide a range of services to a quarter of a million elderly and disabled households every year.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14697</id>
    <published>2012-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-sees-gurkhas-settling-into-rushmoor"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles sees Gurkhas settling into Rushmoor</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles saw first-hand the positive effect of Government funding in helping Nepalese Gurkhas and their families settle in the country on a visit to Aldershot today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles met council officials, Citizens Advice Bureau staff and local Nepali community leaders and discovered how Rushmoor Borough Council are spending £500,000 that he had given to help with integration of former soldiers and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2216606.jpg" alt="Eric Pickles meets Gurkhas at Rushmoor"&gt;Eric Pickles meeting Gurkhas and their families&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding has helped ease the exceptional pressures on Rushmoor, which has seen a large number of Gurkha ex-servicemen and their dependents arrive in the towns of Aldershot and Farnborough over a relatively short period of time. The recent arrivals include a high proportion of children and elderly Nepalese nationals which has placed a recognised strain on local social, health and education services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These brave British army veterans have given our country loyal service over many years. It is their bravery that has helped protect our way of life and our traditions and it is right that their dedication is honoured.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Many of these ex-servicemen and their families have been proud to call this country their home and we too are proud of the strong ties that have been established between the ex-Gurkhas, their families and their wider communities. We are determined that if they chose to settle in the UK to see that they and their families are treated with dignity and respect and are made to feel welcome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles also used the visit to announce the final instalment of the funding, a £150,000 payment towards English language training which is seen as a vital element in helping the Nepali people settle and contribute to their local community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government and the Deputy Prime Minister announced a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2030149"&gt;£1.5million fund for the Gurkha community&lt;/a&gt; in November 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1598005.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1598005.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/11797</id>
    <published>2012-09-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:35:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/statutory-homelessness-in-england-april-to-june-2012"/>
    <title>Statutory homelessness in England: April to June 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest national statistics on statutory homelessness, for April to June 2012, were released on 6 September 2012, under arrangements approved by the UK Statistics Authority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/14694</id>
    <published>2012-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/safety-net-against-homelessness-continues-to-2015"/>
    <title>Safety net against homelessness continues to 2015</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support secured for those facing homelessness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding to help those facing the real and frightening prospect of homelessness will continue to the end of this Parliament, Housing Minister Grant Shapps said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2208882.jpg" alt="StreetLink poster"&gt;A preview of the new StreetLink poster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils across the country are set to receive a share of £160million over the next two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister also confirmed that a new website and telephone line, where anyone anywhere looking to get help for someone sleeping on the streets can go to, is on track to be available by Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also offered a first-look at a new campaign aimed at encouraging people to seek help for rough sleepers in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-support"&gt;Funding support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps announced that councils across the country would receive £160million over the next two years in Homelessness Prevention Grants - offering certainty that homelessness services will be funded to the end of this Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is on top of the £160million that has been allocated to councils over this and last year, which has been used to offer support to those facing the threat of homelessness, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing rent deposit schemes to enable homeless people to get accommodation in the private rented sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mediation services to help prevent relationship breakdown leading to homelessness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;outreach services to help get rough sleepers off the streets and into accommodation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Latest figures show that 199,000 households were last year given help to stay in their homes or find new places to live - stopping them from facing losing their home and, potentially, a life on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="streetlink-support"&gt;StreetLink support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Mr Shapps also confirmed that plans for a new website and national phone line are on track to be available by Christmas, so that anyone will be able to ring if they are looking for help for someone sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;StreetLink, to be run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway, will include a national telephone line, and website accessible via smart phone, so anyone anywhere can provide details of someone sleeping rough in their neighbourhood so they can be found and connected to local services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A series of posters will be released in December alongside these new tools, so residents, charities and councils can all work together to ensure as few people as possible face spending this Christmas on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister released the first images from a campaign due to start in the run-up to Christmas to encourage members of the public to come forward and seek help for local rough sleepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“All too often, we see people sleeping rough on our streets and don’t know what to do for the best, where to turn to get them help and whether offering a handout really does offer them help out of homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“That’s why I’m delighted that this December, StreetLink will offer a solution, with members of the public able to ring a national helpline or use a website accessible by smart phone to help ensure someone sleeping rough can be found and connected to local services.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“And to ensure that we shore up the strongest safety net in the world, I can today confirm £160m funding right up to the end of this Parliament, giving councils the means to continue their strong work in preventing homelessness in the first place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A preview of what StreetLink, the new national rough sleeping campaign, will look like, can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208862.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf.2208862.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 435kb).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the £160m Homelessness Prevention Funding, which will be awarded to councils in 2013/14 and 2014/15, are published today and can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208843.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208843.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 89kb).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
