<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/providing-housing-support-for-older-and-vulnerable-people/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Providing housing support for older and vulnerable people"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-31T10:01:07+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/61041</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T10:01:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/make-it-your-new-year-s-resolution-to-help-get-rough-sleepers-off-the-streets"/>
    <title>Make it your New Year’s resolution to help get rough sleepers off the streets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>People setting their New Year’s resolutions can now pledge to offer practical help to rough sleepers in 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk urged anyone wanting to get help for someone sleeping rough to use the new StreetLink hotline and website to ensure they are put in touch with the local agencies offering it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that while people want to offer help to those facing homelessness, they often don’t know where to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But StreetLink, run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway with support from the government, offers a “valuable alternative” to a cash handout for people sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those looking to offer help can call 0300 500 0914 or go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk" title="StreetLink"&gt;www.streetlink.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; to put those facing sleeping rough in touch with local charities and councils who can them get them long-term support and safe accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued this new and innovative service helps support the No Second Night Out initiative as it is extended across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London, where No Second Night Out has been adopted, 70% of rough sleepers have not spent more than one night on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The New Year offers many of us an opportunity to make a new start - StreetLink offers that opportunity to those facing the prospect of living on our streets and a valuable alternative to simply a cash handout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge anyone looking to set themselves a New Year’s resolution to use this service to ensure people sleeping rough in their area get the support they need to get off the streets and into a stable home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;Mark Prisk on rough sleeping and Streetlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56673</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:29:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-backs-new-rough-sleeping-helpline"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk backs new rough sleeping helpline</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new national hotline and website will connect rough sleepers with local help.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone looking to help rough sleepers this winter should contact a new service to get them long-term support, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke at the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt;, a new national hotline and website service that connects rough sleepers with the local help and advice they need to get off the streets and get their lives back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="StreetLink poster" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2025/streetlink_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said that while many want to help the people they see sleeping rough, they don’t know what to do. So the government has supported homelessness charities Homeless Link and Broadway to develop this new service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that StreetLink offers concerned members of the public a better option than handing out money or food, by directing rough sleepers to the help they need, and providing them with a “hand up, not a hand out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this service, the public can now turn their concern into practical action and take a direct step to help rough sleepers change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister urged people across the country to get behind StreetLink and call if they see someone in need this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the nights getting colder, many people will be wondering how they can help when they see someone facing a night on the streets. StreetLink will give them the chance to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new service will help rough sleepers across the country to connect with their local services, offering the help and advice they need to get back on track. So save the StreetLink number, 0300 500 0914, onto your phone, download the app or bookmark the webpage today. Your action could help a rough sleeper get out of the cold and into long-term support.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;StreetLink video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/54937</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:00:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-summit-to-end-rough-sleeping"/>
    <title>National summit to end rough sleeping</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister Mark Prisk on the launch of StreetLink and successful local steps to end rough sleeping.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of year, when the cold weather bites, it’s natural that people are concerned when they see people sleeping on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as you know better than most, this is not just an issue at Christmas; it’s a year-round problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it is not enough to offer a helping hand just during the season of good will. To really make a difference, we need to tackle the causes of rough sleeping, all the year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-action"&gt;Government action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the problems we face today, is a lack of affordable homes in the housing market. A market in which, for 15, maybe 20 years, we have seen just half the homes we actually need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, when this government came to power, we committed to building more homes, and more affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means unlocking substantial investment of £19.5 billion so we’re able to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes over this Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means a significant expansion of the private rented sector, to give tenants much greater choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it’s a sector that has often been overlooked, which is why we asked Sir Adrian Montague to carry out an independent review of the sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve now adopted his excellent report with a clear commitment, to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, so that we can deliver more new homes for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s often a debate about whether to focus on owner occupied homes, or the private rented sector, or affordable housing. But we need to deliver in all 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want there to be a bigger, better housing market, capable of providing people with more quality and more choice at affordable prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are building more homes, but we’re also determined to address all the issues that drive people towards homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we protected £400 million of funding, for tackling and preventing homelessness, over 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because homelessness is caused by the convergence of different problems, my predecessor Grant Shapps established the Ministerial Working Group that, for the first time, regularly brings ministers together from across Whitehall - from Health and Welfare, to Justice and even Defence - because we need to look at all the links between homelessness and for example, mental health, as well as some of the unique challenges which people face if veterans or former prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="homelessness-prevention"&gt;Homelessness prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve put the right building blocks in place, and today I want to discuss how else we’re moving forward, not least by focussing on prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular the new approach, through StreetLink to stop people slipping through the net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means tackling the underlying problems. And, (if people do turn to sleeping rough), early intervention to ensure they are swiftly helped off the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why, (on top of the £400 million funding for tackling homelessness), we announced an additional £70 million last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extra cash is ensuring vulnerable single people, (a high risk group), get early access to good housing advice, to prevent them becoming homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also looking to boost hostel provision, and supporting the national roll out of ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now after a really encouraging pilot in London (which we were able to support), this initiative is proving essential in ensuring people do not become caught up in a pattern of sleeping rough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s proved effective at providing a rapid response to new rough sleepers, by ensuring that no one has to sleep out for a second night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, tackling problems early is fundamental to the scheme’s success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m pleased that the momentum for ‘No Second Night Out’ is growing, with several more authorities adopting the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merseyside was quick off the mark, being the first area outside London to introduce their own initiative last February. 6 local authorities are now working in partnership, to really put an end to persistent rough sleeping they’ve had to endure right across the Liverpool city region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a commendable achievement and an example to other authorities - and you will hear more about how they delivered this when Councillor Anne O’Byrne speaks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="streetlink"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are many people beyond government (and the professionals) who also want to help. Often they see people sleeping rough, but they are not quite sure what they can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re concerned that giving money isn’t the best solution, but don’t know where else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, as a government, we decided to support your sector to develop a new approach, with the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk/"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt; today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how will it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for the general public StreetLink provides a central point of contact, that people who want to help rough sleepers can call. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minute anyone sees someone on their local street or town centre sleeping rough in their neighbourhood, they will be able to contact StreetLink and provide details on a confidential and secure basis, so vulnerable people can be found and connected to local services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the new approach is that it’s easy to use. StreetLink will be contactable by phone on 0300 500 0914, by using the website, the mobile website accessible by smartphone, or by using the StreetLink ‘app’, available for iphones and android devices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You maybe concerned that it’s difficult to do, but if I can get it on my mobile (and my wife will confirm), anyone can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it won’t just be about reporting problems: members of the public will also be able to see what action has been taken. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll be able to ask for email feedback from local services about the outcome of the information they’ve provided, and see the outcomes of their referrals on the StreetLink website, on a Google map that they can search by location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the first time, the public will be able to judge for themselves whether rough sleeping is being taken seriously and tackled effectively in their locality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does it mean for service providers - local authorities and your sector? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By involving the public, it will mean your outreach teams can help more people, because you will have better intelligence about what’s happening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homeless Link tell me that every local authority has agreed to accept referrals, with some already receiving and acting on the details provided by the public through the website, which has been live for over two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also supports your approach to helping rough sleepers. You, more than anyone, know that they need a hand-up, not just a handout. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the public will now be able to turn their concern into practical, effective action, and take a direct step to help vulnerable adults change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - it will help link up the different services helping rough sleepers. Callers in an area with a ‘No Second Night Out’ initiative or other rough sleeping helpline will be transferred directly to that scheme. In other areas StreetLink will refer the details to the local authority or local outreach team for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a smart, joined-up way of tackling the problem, and will have truly national coverage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to pay tribute to Homeless Link and Broadway for its development, using the support from government. It’s real partnership in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, most of us will struggle to understand what it is like to sleep on the streets. That’s why, when people see rough sleepers, they want to reach out and help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to engage with this issue, and ensure the right intervention is made, as early as possible. We need to break the habit to help people to turn their lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this must be a collaborative effort - including local authorities and the voluntary and charity sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me say a big thank you to all of you for the vital work you do. It’s tempting for the media to think it’s just a Christmas issue, but it’s 365 days a year. You are part of the reason we have one of the best safety nets in the world, to prevent and tackle homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted that, from today, StreetLink will strengthen this safety net. Everyone will now have an easy and effective way of helping change the lives of those who have been on the fringe, for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more to do, but I’m confident that, together, we can make a real difference to thousands of people, who are real in need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18653</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T14:58:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rough-sleeping-help-offers-winter-lifeline"/>
    <title>Rough sleeping help offers winter lifeline</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today that the "lifeline" support that rough sleeping services provide are vital at this time of year.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night the minister visited Westminster’s Cathedral Piazza, a rough sleeping hotspot, where he saw the outreach work of homelessness charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.passage.org.uk/"&gt;The Passage&lt;/a&gt; and the help provided by local hostels to get those at their lowest ebb back on the road to a stable, healthy lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister said that the services, from an offer of immediate help to long-term support, were a last line of defence in helping vulnerable people, especially as the temperature continues to drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was part of joint work between government, local authorities, homelessness charities and other agencies who work with the homeless to prevent rough sleeping and support those who fall through the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is investing £400 million over 4 years to help local authorities prevent and tackle homelessness, including rough sleeping, with an additional £70 million investment last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, on top of a pledge to roll out London’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt; service across the country, means that anyone facing losing their home and sleeping rough this winter will get the support they need and deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nobody should have to face the frightening prospect of a night on the streets, and we have some of the strongest homelessness protections in the world to help prevent it. But sometimes people fall through the cracks, which is why we have the emergency support in place to protect them, especially as the winter weather continues to bite. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The work I saw last night showed me the real issues faced by rough sleepers, and the important role local services play in helping them get their lives back on track. For many, they are a vital lifeline at the most difficult time, and the last line of defence, not only against the cold, but against a long-term life on the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/16958</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:47:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/a-better-deal-for-mobile-home-owners"/>
    <title>A better deal for mobile home owners</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation proposes a number of reforms to the park homes sector, aimed at tackling a number of complaints made by residents of some mobile home site operators. These can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking an owner’s sale of their home - without justifiable reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees, breaching site rules and stopping owners from improving their homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures are designed to ensure site operators who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already whilst the rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring compliance with site licence conditions by enabling the courts to impose unlimited fines on operators who do not manage their sites properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing local authorities to make a reasonable charge on site operators for their licensing services, which they are currently unable to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving local authorities the power to carry out works on sites in an emergency or where the site operator has been found guilty of a breach of the licence, and charge the cost back to them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the rules around the sale of mobile homes so that unscrupulous operators cannot interfere with owners selling to a qualifying buyer who they have chosen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing legislation to improve other residents’ rights to reflect their status as home owners by, for example, allowing them to carry out home improvements without seeking permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15152</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T13:52:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/changes-to-the-allocation-of-housing-and-homelessness-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>Letter to local housing authorities about the Allocation of Housing and Homelessness Regulations which came into force on 8 November 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2588/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) (Amendment) Regulations 2012&lt;/a&gt; came into force on 8 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations amend &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1294/contents/made"&gt;The Allocation of Housing and Homelessness (Eligibility) (England) Regulations 2006&lt;/a&gt; in order to maintain the Government’s policy on eligibility for social hog and homelessness assistance in relation to non European Economic Area nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is making these amendments following a ruling in the Court of Justice of the European Union in the case of Zambrano (C-34/09).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wrote to chief housing officers about the new regulations on 17 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:36:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk announces new rules to house homeless people and help cut waiting lists.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/13294</id>
    <published>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T15:53:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-changes-in-the-localism-act-2011-supplementary-guidance"/>
    <title>Homelessness changes in the Localism Act 2011: supplementary guidance</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This guidance explains the changes that the Localism Act 2011 makes to the homelessness legislation.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This supplementary guidance explains the changes sections 148 and 149 of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2011/20/part/7/chapter/1/crossheading/homelessness/enacted"&gt;Localism Act&lt;/a&gt; make to the homelessness legislation. It explains in practice how the new power, that allows private rented sector offers to be made to end the main homelessness duty, should work and what local authorities should do as a consequence of the new power’s introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance also explains the requirements of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2012/2601/contents/made"&gt;Homelessness (Suitability of Accommodation) (England) Order 2012&lt;/a&gt;. The Order requires local authorities to put in place arrangements to ensure that the private rented sector offer accommodation that is suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance supplements parts of the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-code-of-guidance-for-councils-july-2006"&gt;‘Homelessness code of guidance for local authorities’&lt;/a&gt; published in July 2006.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-20T12:09:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister, Mark Prisk, to the Council of Mortgage Lenders' annual conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/15620</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:27:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/gypsy-and-traveller-caravan-count-july-2012"/>
    <title>Gypsy and traveller caravan count: July 2012</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <summary>This release shows data from the twice-yearly count of gypsy and traveller caravans in England which took place in July 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release presents data from the count of gypsy and traveller caravans in England which took place on or around 19 July 2012. The twice-yearly count takes place in January and July, recording the number of caravans on both authorised and unauthorised sites across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The July 2012 count also included a count of new affordable residential pitches for the second time. This was done to allow such pitches to be included in the calculation of the New Homes Bonus for individual local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
