<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-companies-more-accountable-to-shareholders-and-the-public/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Making companies more accountable to shareholders and the public"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48221</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/jo-swinsons-response-to-non-governmental-organisation-campaigns-on-transparency-in-the-extractives-industry-ministerial-statement"/>
    <title>Jo Swinson's response to non-governmental organisation campaigns on transparency in the extractives industry: ministerial statement</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Statement by Minister Jo Swinson given in response to letters and emails received regarding the new corporate transparency measures included in the European Union Accounting Directive relating to the oil, gas and mining industries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48140</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ensuring-equity-markets-support-long-term-growth-government-response-to-the-kay-review"/>
    <title>Ensuring equity markets support long-term growth: government response to the Kay review</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government’s response to Professor John Kay’s report into the effect of UK equity markets on the competitiveness of UK business (URN 12/917). Explains why the Government accepts Professor Kay_s analysis and his suggested principles for UK equity markets,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/47152</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-responds-to-the-kay-review"/>
    <title>Government responds to the Kay Review</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;22 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The need for a fundamental change in the culture of investment was endorsed by Business Secretary Vince Cable today, in his response to the Kay Review of UK Equity Markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/12-1188-equity-markets-support-growth-response-to-kay-review"&gt;Download the response.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable sets out his support for Professor John Kay’s 10 Principles for Equity Markets, which focus on reversing the culture of short-termism and restoring relationships of trust and confidence in the investment chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also committed to exploring whether changes in law or regulation are needed to deliver Kay’s principles in practice. The response sets out the work which is being taken forward to deliver Kay’s recommendations, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with EU counterparts to end mandatory quarterly reporting and help reduce the excessive focus on short-term earnings. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endorsing clear minimum standards of behaviour for all investment intermediaries to ensure they act in the long-term best interests of their clients. The Law Commission has been asked to review the legal obligations on intermediaries to take appropriate long-term factors into account. The FSA has also been asked to ensure that the regulatory framework promotes high standards of behaviour throughout the investment chain. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging industry to establish an Investors’ Forum to champion constructive engagement with companies. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endorsing Good Practice Statements for company directors, asset managers and asset holders, which emphasise the need for trust-based relationships and advocate more collective action by institutional shareholders; better disclosure of costs in the investment chain; increased transparency and fairness in stock lending; and better alignment between pay and long-term performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many of us feel that in the past, our public companies and investors have focused on short-term profit at the expense of long-term value. The behaviour of many banks in the run up to the financial crisis is an extreme example of this quick buck mentality, but there is clearly a wider problem. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why I asked John Kay to look at what could be done to ensure equity markets support good, long-term decision making. His insightful review calls for a shift in the culture of investment and sets a clear challenge to companies and those who invest in them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“His agenda is an ambitious one but I am very encouraged by the level of engagement we have seen already from investors. Not only on Kay’s ideas, but through our directors’ pay and shareholder voting reforms; in addressing diversity on corporate boards and through changes to the way companies report their business strategy and results. These actions will help restore trust in markets and in the system of capitalism on which our future prosperity depends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable will be launching the Government’s response in a speech at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.napf.co.uk/Conferences_and_Seminars/Corporate_Governance_Conference.aspx"&gt;National Association of Pension Funds’ (NAPF) Annual Conference&lt;/a&gt; later today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-kay-review"&gt;The Kay Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/kayreview"&gt;The Kay Review, published in July&lt;/a&gt;, presented a compelling argument for market participants to change their behaviour and make investment decisions based enhancing the performance of UK companies and supporting long-term growth, rather than maximising short-term gains.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government response looks in detail at each of the Kay Review’s 17 recommendations and highlights the steps being taken to deliver them, either through specific policy measures or by business and industry working together to develop good practice.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering on this agenda will require a sustained commitment from Government, regulators and others. The Government will publish an update in Summer 2014 setting out the progress achieved in delivering Professor Kay’s recommendations and reporting how well companies and investors have stepped up to the plate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Government-sets-out-steps-to-change-culture-683c1.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Government sets out steps to change culture in Equity Markets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/November_2012/22-11-12/1-BIS-KayReview.pdf"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement: The Government Response to the Kay Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/corporate-governance/kay-review"&gt;The Kay Review of UK Equity Markets and Long-Term Decision Making&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/corporate-governance"&gt;Corporate governance at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48189</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-directors-pay"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: directors' pay</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in  the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to directors’ pay and shareholder voting on this issue. Explains the main purpose and benefits, and provides context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48190</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/enterprise-regulatory-reform-bill-equalities-equality-act-2010"/>
    <title>Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform Bill: equalities (Equality Act 2010)</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overview of measures in the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill relating to removing obstacles preventing the government from achieving a fair society, and introducing stronger steps towards addressing the gender pay gap. Explains the main purpose and b&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47195</id>
    <published>2012-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/employee-ownership-and-share-buy-backs-consultation-on-implementation-of-nuttall-review-recommendations"/>
    <title>Employee Ownership and Share Buy Backs - Consultation on implementation of Nuttall Review recommendations</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on deregulatory changes to the conditions under which companies can authorise and finance the repurchase of its own shares, and hold these shares once repurchased. The regulation of share buy backs is governed by the Companies Act 2006. Changes to these regulations, such as those proposed in this consultation would require changes via secondary legislation. The draft regulations attached below indicate how the government would implement these changes. Through this consultation we would also like to understand the implications for companies, employees, and other shareholders. In particular we wish to ensure there are no unintended consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/12-1162-employee-ownership-share-buy-backs-consultation.pdf"&gt;Employee ownership and share buy backs: consultation on implementation of Nuttall review recommendations (PDF, 157 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/12-1162rf-employee-ownership-share-buy-backs-consultation-form.doc"&gt;12-1162rf-employee-ownership-share-buy-backs-consultation-form (DOC, 146 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/12-1165-employee-ownership-and-share-buy-backs-impact.pdf"&gt;Employee ownership and share buy backs: impact assessment (PDF, 131 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/c/12-1248-companies-act-2006-amendment-part-18-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;Draft statutory instrument: The Companies Act 2006 (Amendment of Part 18) Regulations 2013 (PDF, 50 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48166</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/initial-assessment-by-the-uk-national-contact-point-for-the-oecd-guidelines-for-multinational-enterprises-complaint-from-an-individual-in-india-against-a-uk-registered-company"/>
    <title>Initial assessment by the UK national contact point for the OECD guidelines for multinational enterprises: complaint from an individual in India against a UK registered company</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Records the decision of the UK national contact point on whether to accept for further consideration a complaint from an individual against a UK company, for a breach of the OECD guidelines for multinational enterprises. See URN 12/1230 for a request for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48167</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/specific-instance-under-the-oecd-guidelines-for-multi-national-enterprises-application-for-review-of-the-initial-assessment"/>
    <title>Specific instance under the OECD guidelines for multi-national enterprises: application for review of the initial assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Records the recommendation of the Steering Board on a request for review of the decision of the UK national contact point on a complaint from an individual against a UK company, for a breach of the OECD guidelines for multinational enterprises. See URN 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/47193</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/consultation-on-implementing-employee-owner-status--2"/>
    <title>Consultation on implementing employee owner status</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under this new status, employee owners will receive shares between £2,000 and £50,000 which will be exempt from capital gains tax. Employee owners will have the same rights as current employees excluding unfair dismissal (except where this is automatically unfair or relates to anti-discrimination law), certain rights to request flexible working and training, and statutory redundancy pay. Individuals will also need to give longer notice to return from maternity leave or adoption leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation seeks views on how the government will implement the employee owner status in practical terms. Through this consultation we would also like to understand the implications for employers, individuals, and the labour market in general. In particular we wish to ensure there are no unintended consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/c/12-1215-consultation-on-implementing-employee-owner-status.pdf"&gt;Consultation on implementing employee owner status (PDF, 185 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/c/12-1215rf-consultation-on-implementing-employee-owner-status-form.doc"&gt;Consultation on implementing employee owner status: response form (DOC, 105 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/e/12-1228-equality-impact-implementing-employee-owner-status.pdf"&gt;Equality impact assessment of implementing employee owner status (PDF, 226 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/48251</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:31:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reforming-uk-narrative-reporting-impact-assessment"/>
    <title>Reforming UK narrative reporting: impact assessment</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A final stage assessment of the impact of proposed measures to reform narrative reporting in the UK. Accompanies a Regulatory Policy Committee opinion (URN 12/1227) and a paper setting out a package of measures expected to achieve this (12/979). See also&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
