<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/modernising-company-law--2/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Modernising company law"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Publication/39669</id>
    <published>2012-09-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:53:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/women-on-boards--2"/>
    <title>Women on boards</title>
    <category>Publication</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Freedom of information release relating to the relationship between the proportion of women on corporate boards and enhanced corporate financial performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44954</id>
    <published>2011-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/financial-reporting-council-reform"/>
    <title>Financial Reporting Council Reform</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FRC is already well-regarded in the UK, the EU and internationally, but we believe by tightening the focus of its activities and reforming its structural framework that it could be even more effective, increasing still further the contribution it makes to supporting the UK’s business interests. This consultation document seeks views on a set of reforms designed to build on the FRC’s strengths as well as tackle the underlying issues that currently inhibit its effectiveness. Reform is needed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reinforce the FRC’s independence from those it regulates;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve its efficiency and effectiveness; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rationalise and minimise the regulatory burdens on market participants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not intended that reform should introduce further regulatory processes which impact significantly on business. However, to achieve our aims some proposed reforms will require changes to the legislative framework. We are committed to reducing the cost to business associated with FRC regulation and will consider carefully any opportunities for cost reduction identified through responses to this consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-1250-frc-reform-proposals-consultation.pdf"&gt;Proposals to reform the Financial Reporting Council: a joint BIS and FRC consultation (PDF, 241 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/p/11-1251-proposal-to-reform-frc-impact-assessment.pdf"&gt;Proposals to reform the Financial Reporting Council: impact assessment (PDF, 474 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-government-response"&gt;Download the government response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/p/12-700-proposals-reform-financial-reporting-council-response.pdf"&gt;Proposal to reform the Financial Council: a joint Government and FRC response (PDF, 357 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/p/12-701-proposals-financial-reporting-council-final-impact.pdf"&gt;Proposals to reform the Financial Reporting Council: final impact assessment (PDF, 515 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18307</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cutting-accountancy-and-reporting-fees-for-smes--2"/>
    <title>Cutting accountancy and reporting fees for SMEs</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 100 thousand UK businesses could save in excess of £600 million in accountancy and administration costs every year under proposals to reduce financial reporting requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/audit-exemptions-and-accounting-framework"&gt;The consultation on Audit Exemptions and Change of Accounting Framework&lt;/a&gt; sets out plans to allow more small companies and subsidiaries to decide whether or not to have an audit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It covers the whole of the UK and will close on 29 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current EU rules mean a company must comply with two out of three criteria in order to be classified as ‘small’ for accounting purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No more than 50 employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A balance sheet total no more than £3.26 million. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No more than £6.5 million in turnover. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, to obtain an audit exemption in the UK, small companies must fulfil both the balance sheet and turnover criteria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new proposals, UK SMEs would be eligible for audit exemption by meeting any two of the three criteria, saving them an estimated £206m per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister responsible for Corporate Governance, Edward Davey, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Audit is very valuable for many companies. But the proposals we’ve published today are aimed at removing EU gold plating and freeing up enterprise, which ultimately benefits the whole UK economy and will help put us on the path to long-term, sustainable growth. So I encourage businesses to read the consultation document and share their views with us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cutting-gold-plating"&gt;Cutting gold plating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is also proposing to introduce legislation in 2012 to exempt most subsidiary companies from mandatory audit, provided their parent is prepared to guarantee their debts. Savings are estimated at £406m per year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, removing this EU gold plating could save UK businesses £612m per year. These moves are part of the Government’s wider focus on cutting red tape and reducing unnecessary burdens on business, in particular addressing the impact of European legislation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, following the consultation by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/asb/"&gt;UK Accounting Standards Board &lt;/a&gt;on changes to UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles (UK GAAP), the Government is also seeking views on whether to allow companies which currently prepare accounts under International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) more flexibility to change their accounting framework to UK GAAP. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011 the Chancellor and Business Secretary published The Plan for Growth. One of the Plan’s ambitions is to ensure the UK ranks among the best places in Europe to start and grow a business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve this, the Government is committed to removing regulatory burdens and improving corporate governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421482&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-law/accounting-auditing-reporting"&gt;Audit, accounting and reporting at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/"&gt;Financial Reporting Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/"&gt;Companies House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44994</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/audit-exemptions-and-change-of-accounting-framework-consultation-and-summary-of-responses"/>
    <title>Audit Exemptions and Change of Accounting Framework: Consultation and Summary of Responses</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation paper concerned two separate proposals: a change in the audit exemptions and a change in the law to allow companies to change their accounting framework. Each proposal has its own draft Impact Assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="update---march-2012"&gt;Update - March 2012&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;?Û¢ The consultation closed on 29 December 2011. A summary of responses to the consultation was published on 2 March 2012 and is available to view below, as are the individual responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-summary-of-responses"&gt;Download the summary of responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/12-609-audit-exemptions-accounting-framework-summary-responses.pdf"&gt;Audit Exemptions and Change of Accounting Framework: Summary of Responses to Consultation (PDF, 162 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="responses-to-the-consultation"&gt;Responses to the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/audit-exemption-accounting-framework-responses-part-1.zip"&gt;Audit exemptions and framework responses part 1 (ZIP, 3.4 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/audit-exemption-accounting-framework-responses-part-2.zip"&gt;Audit exemptions and framework responses part 2 (ZIP, 6.1 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/audit-exemption-accounting-framework-responses-part-3.zip"&gt;Audit exemptions and framework responses part 3 (ZIP, 2.5 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/audit-exemption-accounting-framework-responses-part-4.zip"&gt;Audit exemptions and framework responsespart4 (ZIP, 3.9 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/c/11-1193-consultation-audit-exemptions-and-accounting-framework.pdf"&gt;Consultation on audit exemptions and change of accounting framework (PDF, 220 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/11-1194-audit-exemptions-impact-assessment.pdf"&gt;Audit exemptions: impact assessment (PDF, 445 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/a/11-1195-amendment-restrictions-for-companies-impact-assessment.pdf"&gt;Amendment of restrictions for companies moving between IFRS and UK GAAP: impact assessment (PDF, 370 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44953</id>
    <published>2011-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-future-of-narrative-reporting-a-further-consultation"/>
    <title>The future of narrative reporting: a further consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation seeks views on Government plans to make narrative reporting simpler, clearer and more focussed. It includes proposals to change company narrative reports to make the framework clearer for companies and easier for investors to locate the information they need. We are also reviewing the disclosure requirements that we place on companies to streamline and remove inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation also includes a number of proposals to make the reporting of executive remuneration clearer and more relevant to investors. In addition to this, the Government has published a separate &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/executive-remuneration-discussion-paper"&gt;discussion paper seeking views on a range of issues relating to executive remuneration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="update-february-2012"&gt;Update February 2012&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial analysis shows support for the proposed new structure, although several organisations said that bringing the changes into force in October 2012 will not give companies enough time to adjust. We therefore propose to bring the changes into force in April 2013. We hope to publish a response to the consultation in March 2012.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-response"&gt;Government Response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 27 March 2012 the Government published a summary of responses and indication of the next steps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-945-future-of-narrative-reporting-consulting-new-framework.pdf"&gt;Future of narrative reporting: consulting on a new reporting framework (PDF, 378 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-945rf-future-of-narrative-reporting-consulting-new-framework-form.doc"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: consulting on a new reporting framework. Response form (DOC, 177 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/n/11-1293-narrative-reporting-impact-assessment.pdf"&gt;Narrative reporting: impact assessment (PDF, 234 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-1294-future-of-narrative-reporting-regulatory-policy-committee-opinion.pdf"&gt;Regulatory Policy Committee opinion: impact assessment on narrative reporting (PDF, 69 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-government-response"&gt;Download the government response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/12-588-future-of-narrative-reporting-government-response.pdf"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: the Government response (PDF, 203 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44995</id>
    <published>2011-09-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-kay-review-of-uk-equity-markets-and-long-term-decision-making"/>
    <title>The Kay Review of UK Equity Markets and Long-Term Decision Making</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review’s principal focus is to ask how well equity markets are achieving their core purposes: &lt;br&gt;
to enhance the performance of UK companies by facilitating investment and enabling effective governance and decision making in support of long-term profitability and growth; and to enable investors to benefit from this corporate activity in the form of returns from equity investment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is considering to what extent equity market participants are excessively focused on short-term outcomes to the detriment of these core purposes, and if so, what actions might be taken to address this. It is examining the incentives, motivations and timescales of all participants in the equity markets - from end investors, through pension funds, advisers, fund managers, and the markets, to company boards - and the relationships between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full details of the review are available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-law/corporate-governance/kay-review"&gt;the Kay Review page &lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation closed on &lt;strong&gt;Friday 18 November 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copies of the responses to the call for evidence are available &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-law/corporate-governance/kay-review/kay-review-responses"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/12-631-kay-review-of-equity-markets-interim-report.pdf"&gt;The Kay review of UK equity markets and long-term decision making: interim report (PDF, 555 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/11-1286-kay-review-call-for-evidence.pdf"&gt;The Kay Review: call for evidence (PDF, 48 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/k/kay-review-napf-speech-sept-2011.pdf"&gt;Professor Kay’s speech: call for evidence launch (PDF, 40 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/18221</id>
    <published>2011-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cable-outlines-agenda-for-growth"/>
    <title>Cable outlines agenda for growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/speeches/vince-cable-mansion-house-speech-2011"&gt;Speaking to the City of London at Mansion House&lt;/a&gt; on Thursday 3 March, Secretary of State Vince Cable outlined the Government’s work in growing the economy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He expressed frustration about assumptions that the Government can guarantee an immediate return to rapid growth, and said there is no cookery book recipe for growth.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our central task- and mine in particular - is to strengthen a framework in which the private sector can grow the economy out of its current problems,” he said.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He encapsulated the Government’s approach as: “Vigorous, targeted action where the government can make a difference; combined with robust and unsentimental withdrawal from unnecessary interference.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He set out key areas that underlie his vision for the economy, including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade and international competitiveness - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/trade-policy-unit"&gt;the trade white paper&lt;/a&gt; sets out how targeted support would be offered to SMEs wishing to export and strengthen the single market to remove barriers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deregulation - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Jan/workplace-dispute-reforms-and-employers-charter"&gt;steps have been taken on tribunals and unfair dismissal&lt;/a&gt; but more needed to be done, particularly on planning. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills - there are clear market failures and the Government has responded by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Feb/national-apprenticeship-week-2011"&gt;investing in apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“But a growing economy isn’t just about government getting out of the way,” he said. “Government has a major role even when slimmer and less intrusive.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This role includes include ensuring longer term clarity to aid infrastructure provision, and investing in skills and cutting edge innovation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to the ongoing &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2010/Nov/government-launches-growth-review"&gt;Growth Review&lt;/a&gt; he said the Government had turned down the easy option of putting out yet another paper about growth in favour of a “rigorous and challenging” exercise.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It has challenged every department to get behind the growth agenda, critically examining every policy that might get in the way or hold back our vision for private sector recovery,” he said.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth Review will continue for the duration of the parliament, he promised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-action-to-save-small-firms-40m"&gt;Government action to save small firms £40m&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vince Cable announced on Friday 4 March that small firms will no longer need independently audited accounts, saving 42,000 businesses £40 million per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary outlined changes to regulation in one area which is a massive burden to business - producing accounts. Small businesses in particular often suffer the most under the burden of bureaucracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government recognises the need for high standards in audit and accounting. But some areas could do with reform so the following action is being taken: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small company audit and account rules are stricter in the UK than is required by EU law. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For smaller businesses (with less than 10 employees) Government will push for exemptions to remove the requirement to produce two sets of accounts. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For medium sized businesses Government will push for EU restrictions to be lifted so that they no longer need their account independently audited. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Government will look at relaxing the audit and accounts rules for subsidiaries.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The changes would mean small companies would produce just one simplified set of accounts and save £400m for some of the smallest businesses in the country - roughly 2 million of them will be able to concentrate on growing, expanding and creating jobs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/speeches/vince-cable-mansion-house-speech-2011"&gt;Read the Mansion House speech in full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Government action to save small firms £40m - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/Detail.aspx?ReleaseID=418437&amp;amp;NewsAreaID=2"&gt;Bis press notice&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth"&gt;Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/home"&gt;Business Link&lt;/a&gt; - practical advice for business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/55534</id>
    <published>2010-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/building-long-term-growth"/>
    <title>Building long-term growth</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister and the Business Secretary today outlined the steps the Government is taking to ensure a long-term commitment to the country in building confidence and leading to economic growth and jobs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to an audience of business leaders at the CBI conference, The Prime Minister spoke first, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/topstorynews/2010/10/creating-a-new-economic-dynamism-3-56114"&gt;setting out the Government’s plans&lt;/a&gt; to back British business and create “a new economic dynamism”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He announced the creation of a £200 million network of technology centres, linking university researchers with business, and the UK’s first ever National Infrastructure Plan. Speaking later in the afternoon Dr. Cable launched a review to investigate whether there are failures in corporate governance and the markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="investing-in-growth"&gt;Investing in growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describing the difficulties that the country faced following the near collapse of the banking system, Dr. Cable spoke of the importance of investing in lasting economic growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He highlighted the need for reform which is not characterized by the lessons of the past; superficial economic prosperity based on booming property markets, low investment of industry and a dependence on banking. He addressed the question of how it could be done in a better way;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is partly about removing government imposed obstacles to growth: onerous business taxes, red tape which suffocates small firms, and a slow oppressive planning regime. But it is also about government doing its job properly. Doing the jobs the market does not do by itself: education and training, infrastructure provision and basic science leading to innovation.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to describe that the tough decisions in the CSR would look to the long term, such as the defence of science, the new technology centres and boosting the numbers of apprentices, but that the government had limited scope to promote growth through fiscal stimulus;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With private consumers being so debt-laden, growth will have to come from the business sector and overseas trade. Trade and openness are crucial to recovery.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="section"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-banking-sector-for-the-future"&gt;A banking sector for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Cable went on to state that maintaining the flow of credit to good, credit worthy companies would remain central to his agenda, and asked what type of banking system did the country need in the future. He explained that the current situation, where most businesses only have a choice of 4 or 5 partners, needed to change;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In five years time we would like a much broader choice for businesses. More banks who understand SME finance. More non-bank sources of finance. More use of equity. More specialist knowledge of sectors.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also emphasised the importance of investing for the long-term. “I believe that empowered, informed shareholders, investing for the long term, are good news for the companies they own. Alongside directors and managers aware of their wider duties, such shareholders provide the space vital for longer term decision-making.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-long-term-focus-for-corporate-britain"&gt;A Long term Focus for Corporate Britain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the CBI Conference the Business Secretary launched a call for evidence on the subject of pay, corporate governance and takeovers called “A Long term Focus for Corporate Britain”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation aims to investigate issues including; the problems of short-termism, investor engagement, directors’ remuneration and - following on from last week’s announcement by the Takeover Panel - the economic case for takeovers. It also asks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do boards understand the long-term implications of takeovers, and communicate the long-term implications of bids effectively? &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are the implications of the changing nature of UK share ownership for corporate governance and capital markets? Whether disclosure of directors’ pay should be more transparent? &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do shareholders and investors focus too much on the short-term?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/topstorynews/2010/10/creating-a-new-economic-dynamism-3-56114"&gt;Prime Minister’s Speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=416169&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Business Secretary’s Speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/press_56_10.htm"&gt;The National Infrastructure Plan &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=416174&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Technology and Innovation Centres &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=416167&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Review on Corporate Governance &amp;amp; Short-Termism opens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=416178&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Government launches new programme to make UK global partner of choice for R&amp;amp;D collaboration &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44962</id>
    <published>2010-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/the-future-of-narrative-reporting-a-consultation"/>
    <title>The Future of Narrative Reporting: a Consultation</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation is part of implementing the Coalition Agreement commitment to “reinstate an Operating and Financial Review to ensure that directors’ social and environmental duties have to be covered in company reporting and investigate further ways of improving corporate accountability and transparency”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of the consultation is to look at ways to drive quality of company reporting to the level of the best and thereby enable stronger and more effective shareholder engagement. The consultation paper is open in exploring all options - regulatory and non-regulatory - to achieve the objectives. The consultation focuses in particular on the business review provisions, but as part of its exploration of wider narrative reporting, it also looks at issues relating to the Directors’ Remuneration Report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="update---december-2010"&gt;Update - December 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation closed on 19 October. A summary of responses document was published in December 2010 and is available to view below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="update---september-2011"&gt;Update - September 2011&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government hascompleted itsanalysis ofthe responses to the consultation, andhas chosen to respond to the issues raised bypublishing a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/future-of-narrative-reporting-further-consultation"&gt;further consultation on the future of narrative reporting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No other form of response will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/n/10-1057-future-narrative-reporting-consultation.pdf"&gt;Corporate law and governance. The future of narrative reporting: a consultation (PDF, 113 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/10-1318-summary-of-responses-future-narrative-reporting-consultation.pdf"&gt;10-1318-summary-of-responses-future-narrative-reporting-consultation (PDF, 371 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/future-of-narrative-reporting-responses-1-25.pdf"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: responses 1-25 (PDF, 6.4 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/future-of-narrative-reporting-responses-26-50.pdf"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: responses 26-50 (PDF, 15.3 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/future-of-narrative-reporting-responses-51-70.pdf"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: responses 51-70 (PDF, 3.0 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/future-of-narrative-reporting-responses-71-89.pdf"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: responses 71-89 (PDF, 6.2 Mb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-government-response"&gt;Download the government response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-945-future-of-narrative-reporting-consulting-new-framework.pdf"&gt;Future of narrative reporting: consulting on a new reporting framework (PDF, 378 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/f/11-945rf-future-of-narrative-reporting-consulting-new-framework-form.doc"&gt;The future of narrative reporting: consulting on a new reporting framework. Response form (DOC, 177 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Consultation/44976</id>
    <published>2010-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:26:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/registration-of-charges-created-by-companies-and-limited-liability-partnerships"/>
    <title>Registration of charges created by companies and limited liability partnerships</title>
    <category>Consultation</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current system of registration for company charges dates back to the start of the 20th century. Over one hundred years later and following extensive consultation a fully-modernised system has been developed, which aims to: &lt;br&gt;
?Û¢ streamline procedures and reduce costs for those putting &lt;br&gt;
information on the public record, in particular by enabling electronic filing &lt;br&gt;
?Û¢ reduce uncertainty as to what charges must be registered &lt;br&gt;
?Û¢ replace two current schemes with a single scheme for all UK companies &lt;br&gt;
?Û¢ improve the quality of information about security given by companies &lt;br&gt;
?Û¢ improve access to instruments creating companies’ charges.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department wishes to give stakeholders a final opportunity to consider the text of the draft regulations before they are laid before both Houses of Parliament in the Autumn and also to make any preparations they deem necessary ready for when the proposed changes come into force. If you have any concerns about any significant effects, intended or unintended, that these changes may have which you wish to raise with the Department, please email &lt;a href="mailto:part25companiesact2006@bis.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;part25companiesact2006@bis.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; before **5pm on the 7th September 2012. &lt;br&gt;
**&lt;br&gt;
Please find below draft regulations for companies and Limited Liability Partnerships (LLPs) as well as an explanatory note which sets out the rationale for our proposed amendments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/l/12-1027-limited-liability-partnership-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;Draft regulations for Limited Liability Partnerships (LLPs) (PDF, 207 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/e/12-1028-explanatory-notes-draft-regulations-part-25-companies.pdf"&gt;Explanatory notes of draft regulations Part 25 of the Companies Act (PDF, 149 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/c/12-1025-companies-act-amendment-part-25-regulations-draft.pdf"&gt;Draft regulations for Companies amendments to Companies Act 2006 Part 25 (PDF, 222 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2011, we published the Government’s proposals for the revised scheme together with a mock-up of Part 25 of the Companies Act 2006 a amended in accordance with the proposals and revisions to the cost assumptions for the Impact Assessment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Views are sought on the proposed revisions to Part 25 and the cost assumptions &lt;strong&gt;by 30 September 2011&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="purpose-of-consultation"&gt;Purpose of consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that any changes to the current scheme takes account of the views of UK companies, overseas companies, limited liability partnerships (LLPs), their creditors, legal advisors to companies and LLPs and their creditors, and to those who assess the financial status of companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background-to-consultation"&gt;Background to consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under English law, companies are able to use any or all of their assets as security for loans. This involves the creation of a charge over the company’s assets. The scope for companies to use assets as security for loans is more restricted under Scots law as that law does not recognise fixed non-possessory charges over goods. The scheme for registration of company charges is set out in the &lt;a href="mailto:http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2006/ukpga_20060046_en_1"&gt;Companies Act 2006&lt;/a&gt;. This scheme, which is intended to prevent the concealment by companies of secured credit, has been criticised particularly because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the list of registrable charges has not been revised in line with changes in law and commercial practice; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the particulars on the public record for a charge may not be an accurate reflection of the charge created; and &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the procedures for registration are cumbersome. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This consultation relates only to modifications to the scheme provided by the Companies Act 2006. Fundamental changes for the longer term are being considered by the Secured Transactions Law Reform Project; the project director is Professor Sir Roy Goode, CBE, QC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Spring 2011, all those who responded to the 2010 consultation were asked for their views on certain issues that need to be resolved before the Regulations are drafted. These relate to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Period allowed for delivery &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On whom obligation to register falls &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trustees &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registrable and non-registrable charges &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charges over acquired property &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Constructive notice &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rectification of register &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Floating charge issues &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The charge instrument &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Satisfaction and release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please see the link at the bottom of this page for the document &lt;em&gt;‘Registration of Company Charges - Issues to be resolved before preparation of draft regulations’&lt;/em&gt;. The deadline for responses to this document was 13 May 2011.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-the-consultation"&gt;Download the consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/10-697-registration-of-charges-created-by-companies-proposals.pdf"&gt;Registration of charges created by companies and limited liability partnerships: proposals to amend the current scheme and relating to specialist registers (PDF, 440 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/s/10-1230-summary-responses-consultation-registration-of-charges.pdf"&gt;Summary of responses: consultation on registration of charges created by companies and limited liability partnerships (PDF, 98 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="download-the-government-response"&gt;Download the government response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/r/11-1108-revised-scheme-registration-of-charges-part-25.pdf"&gt;Revised scheme for registration of charges created by companies and limited liability partnerships: proposed revision of part 25, Companies Act 2006 (PDF, 175 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/g/10-1319-government-response-consultation-registration-of-charges.pdf"&gt;Government response: consultation on registration of charges created by companies and limited liability partnerships (PDF, 82 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/r/11-862-registration-of-company-charges-issues.pdf"&gt;Registration of company charges: issues to be resolved before preparation of draft regulations (PDF, 96 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/business-law/docs/i/10-1336-impact-assessment-registration-of-charges.pdf"&gt;Impact assessment: registration of charges (PDF, 82 Kb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
