<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/activity</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/activity"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/promoting-human-rights-internationally/activity.atom"/>
  <title>Latest activity on "Promoting human rights internationally"</title>
  <subtitle>Recently associated</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56983</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:47:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust"/>
    <title>Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Seventy years ago the British Government, shocked by mounting evidence from Poland of Nazi extermination of the Jews, joined eleven other war-time allies in a sharp united condemnation of what was happening on the continent of Europe. Sir Anthony Eden’s Statement to Parliament on 17 December 1942 was followed by much public and Parliamentary discussion in the UK and among the United Nations about what could be done to stop the genocide and had a strong impact on subsequent allied planning for the post-war trials of Nazi leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The disastrous events of the Holocaust continue to reverberate through Western society, as the Stockholm Declaration in 2000 so eloquently reaffirmed. The British Government supports the work of the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research (&lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt;) and looks forward to assuming the chairmanship of the &lt;abbr title="Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education, Remembrance and Research"&gt;ITF&lt;/abbr&gt; in 2014/15.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.holocausttaskforce.org/about-the-itf.html" title="Holocaust Task Force"&gt;Information on the Task Force for International Cooperation on Holocaust Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56976</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet"/>
    <title>UK has serious concerns about human rights in Tibet</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a European Union statement on self-immolations in Tibet, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We strongly support the recent statement from Baroness Ashton about the situation in Tibet. We continue to have serious concerns about the human rights situation there, including the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We urge the Chinese authorities to exercise restraint. At the same time, I join Baroness Ashton in calling on Tibetans not to resort to extreme forms of protest such as self-immolation, and urge their community and religious leaders to use their influence to stop this tragic loss of life. We strongly support the resumption of meaningful dialogue to resolve the underlying grievances of Tibetan communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I also urge the Chinese government to ensure unrestricted access to the Tibetan Autonomous Region and other Tibetan areas of China for diplomats, international media and other concerned parties. We believe a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/en/cfsp/134378.pdf" title="EU statement on Tibetan self-immolations"&gt;European Union statement on Tibetan self-immolations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56877</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T14:57:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-condemns-palestinian-refugee-camp-bombing-in-damascus"/>
    <title>UK condemns Palestinian refugee camp bombing in Damascus</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of Syrian government air strikes on the Yarmouk refugee camp in Damascus, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I condemn the Syrian regime’s aerial bombardment of the Yarmouk Palestinian refugee camp in Damascus, which killed at least 20 people yesterday. They are among four hundred Syrians killed across the country this weekend in yet another tragic reminder that the Assad regime continues to attack its own people with brutality and without remorse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Syrian government actions have already driven hundreds of thousands of Syrian civilians from their homes into neighboring countries. The senseless targeting of Palestinian refugees, who had hitherto looked to Syria for shelter and protection, will only exacerbate the risk of contagion across the region. Our objective remains an end to the violence and a transition to a more democratic and stable Syria.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/56249</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice"/>
    <title>Iranian investigation into death of detained blogger is missed opportunity for justice</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marking the 40th day anniversary of the death of Sattar Beheshti, Foreign Officer Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is now forty days since the blogger Sattar Beheshti died in custody in Iran. I would like to use this occasion to extend my condolences to his family. That the Iranian authorities instigated an investigation into Sattar’s tragic death should have been a positive step. However, once again the authorities have failed to deliver justice. Neither Sattar’s family who have reportedly faced harassment and threats from the security services, nor Sattar’s countrymen and women have been given credible answers about the events that led to his death. Instead, the state-controlled media and the parliament have dismissed his death as a heart attack brought on by a fear of arrest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sattar was right to be afraid of the security forces and what could happen to him in jail. The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention. We are deeply disappointed that having taken the initiative to investigate,  Iran has been unwilling to hold those responsible to account. The sacking of the head of Cyber Police will not stop the security and detention forces from operating with impunity. Systemic change is needed to bring about a more transparent and accountable system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous statement on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/reports-that-an-iranian-blogger-has-died-in-detention" title="Reports that an Iranian blogger has died in detention"&gt;Sattar Beheshti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt on twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO" title="@AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:Speech/55967</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uk-to-contribute-funds-to-courts-in-sierra-leone-and-cambodia--2"/>
    <title>UK to contribute funds to Courts in Sierra Leone and Cambodia</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague has updated parliament on UK contributions to the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in a written ministerial statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce that in order to strengthen international justice and help secure accountability for some of the most horrific crimes against humanity in the last 50 years, the UK will make a voluntary contribution of £1,000,000 to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and a voluntary contribution of £600,000 to the international component of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s contribution will help ensure the Special Court for Sierra Leone is able to complete its work, and leave a lasting legacy for the people of Sierra Leone. On 30 May, the Court sentenced Charles Taylor, a former President of Liberia, to 50 years in jail for aiding and abetting war crimes. Taylor is the first former Head of State to be convicted by an international tribunal and the Court is currently hearing his appeal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia is delivering long awaited justice for millions of Cambodians through the trials of the most senior and responsible surviving members of the Pol Pot regime. The scale of the crimes committed and the number of victims makes it one of the most significant tribunals of its kind since Nuremberg. The Government’s contribution will help to prevent the collapse of the Court which has faced a significant shortfall in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International justice is central to foreign policy. It is essential for securing the rights of individuals and states, and for securing peace and reconciliation. Through the International Criminal Court, and the separate international tribunals, we are working to make clear that those responsible for the worst crimes will be held to account and that political leaders will not enjoy impunity. Our support to these institutions is an important element in our strategy to reduce conflict, promote stability and strengthen the rules based international system. In order to give Parliament a full accounting of this work we will, from this point forward, also provide an annual statement at the start of the financial year detailing our progress on this important issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/50138</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T15:07:39+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T15:07:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region"/>
    <title>FCO Minister shows continued UK support to Libyan people on trip to region</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whilst in Libya the Minister will offer continued support to the Libyan people as they build a new future after Qadhafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from Tripoli, Mr Burt said:          &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be back in Libya for the third time in twelve months. Since my last visit in April, Libya has held incredibly successful elections, convened a new General National Congress and formed a new Government. I congratulate President Magarief, Prime Minister Zeidan and the Libyan people on these significant achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Government faces many challenges: improving security across Libya, particularly taking steps to ensure that armed groups are reintegrated into society, respect government decisions and act within the law; strengthening the justice system to ensure the transfer of all detainees to the custody of the state, where they must be held in accordance with international standards; delivering improved public services to its people; and reforming and revitalising the economy to provide better jobs and opportunities for ordinary Libyans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These challenges are significant but the British Government will continue to support Libya throughout its transition. I am meeting the Deputy Prime Ministers and Ministers for Justice and Finance to discuss how the UK can build on its current work to offer even greater assistance to the Libyan Government. I am also meeting a delegation of politicians, business leaders and civil society activists from Benghazi to reiterate our ongoing commitment to the East of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During these meetings I will emphasise the importance of securing justice for the victims of the Qadhafi regime in the UK, and I look forward to the continued cooperation of the Libyan authorities in resolving these outstanding legacy cases.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the Minister &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/alistairburtfco" title="@AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinlibya.fco.gov.uk/en/" title="UK in Libya"&gt;British Embassy in Libya website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/48346</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:51:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/podcast-marks-international-human-rights-day--2"/>
    <title>Podcast marks International Human Rights Day</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fight against torture has been a priority for the British Government for many years. We make clear time and time again that torture is an abhorrent, unjustifiable violation of human rights and human dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This audio download is introduced by the Louise de Sousa, head of the Foreign Office Human Rights and Democracy Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the podcast, we hear from Kolbassia Haoussou, a survivor of torture and Coordinator of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.freedomfromtorture.org/feature/survivors_speak_out/5993" title="Survivor Speak OUT.com"&gt;Survivor Speak OUT.com&lt;/a&gt;, Alex Wilks Senior Programme Lawyer at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ibanet.org/IBAHRI.aspx" title="International Bar Association Human Rights Institute"&gt;International Bar Association Human Rights Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and Nick Hardwick CBE, who has been Her Majesty’s Chief Inspector of Prisons since 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The podcast is available to download via &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/social-media/podcasts" title="FCO website"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a rel="external" href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/podcast/human-rights/id462779772" title="iTunes"&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/social-media/podcasts/" title="human rights podcasts"&gt;Listen or subscribe to human rights podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/ameliabate/2012/12/10/16-days-with-a-difference/" title="human rights and communications blog"&gt;Read our human rights and communications blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/FCOHumanRights" title="@FCOHumanRights"&gt;@FCOHumanRights&lt;/a&gt; on twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/foreign-commonwealth-office/id392006693" title="FCO on iTunes"&gt;FCO on iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://fcohrdreport.readandcomment.com/" title="FCO Human Rights and Democracy Report"&gt;FCO Human Rights and Democracy Report: read and comment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice on Twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office on Facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/+foreignoffice/posts" title="Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office on Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:NewsArticle/48336</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T06:50:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day</title>
    <category>News Article</category>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi, will mark International Human Rights Day by hosting the London launch of the United Kingdom’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is standing for election to the UN’s Human Rights Council next year to ensure that the UK is at the forefront of efforts to drive forward the human rights agenda. Calling to account countries that commit the most serious and widespread violations against their own citizens, ensuring the Human Rights Council is at the forefront of the international response to international crises and fighting hard against those who seek to weaken or undermine international human rights mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s campaign will focus on four key human rights priorities: protecting those most vulnerable in societies, working towards human dignity for all, responding proactively to evolving challenges, and keeping human rights at the heart of multilateral priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“International Human Rights Day is a stark reminder that there are still too many around the world who are not able to enjoy fundamental freedoms. It is important to focus on those who are fighting for their rights and the rights of their loved ones, those who are prepared to put themselves in danger for a better future for others and to remember those who have left a legacy to inspire us all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must keep those voices at the heart of our efforts to promote and protect human rights around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am proud of the UK’s commitment to protecting those most vulnerable in our societies. Across the world, too many people are discriminated against on the basis of their race, religion, sexual orientation, disability, or gender-identity. The reasons for discrimination are many, and we must tackle the causes and the acts themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking later today at the reception for the London launch of the UK’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council, Baroness Warsi will say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear. A Council that is not bogged down by politics, but where the rights of the individual are paramount. A body where states are held accountable for their actions against their citizens, where peers review peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe strongly that we have an important role to play, which is why the UK is standing for election. We bring experience, commitment and ambition. We want to play a part in strengthening the Council, as we have since its inception in 2006. In that time the Human Rights Council has grown in status and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through the Council, we have called to account countries who commit the most heinous and systematic violations against their citizens. We have actively supported the Human Rights Council’s international response to the crisis in Syria. We have also run thematic initiatives including through a resolution which used the Olympics to promote awareness on human rights through sport and established a commitment with the future hosts of the Games to do the same.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=842675682" title="Follow @FCOHumanRights "&gt;Follow @FCOHumanRights &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter "&gt;Twitter &lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook "&gt;Facebook &lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+ "&gt;Google+ &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
