<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/alistair-burt</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/alistair-burt.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Alistair Burt MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65670</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T16:25:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--107"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-updates-parliament-on-syria"&gt;updated parliament on the crisis in Syria&lt;/a&gt; and outlined further UK action for the coming weeks. He said: “Our country has a moral obligation to help save lives in Syria, and a national interest in ensuring that the country provides no haven for terrorist activity. We know that to achieve lasting stability we must work with the Syrian opposition and countries of the region, not try to impose a political settlement from outside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-hosts-conference-on-syrian-led-political-transition"&gt;meeting organised by the UK this week,&lt;/a&gt; the Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt will &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"&gt;answer questions about the UK’s policy on Syria&lt;/a&gt; via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="middle-east-peace-process"&gt;Middle East Peace Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-will-be-year-of-peace-for-people-in-the-middle-east"&gt;Foreign Secretary met the Secretary General of the League of Arab States&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the Middle East Peace Process and Syria. Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Secretary said: “We expressed the shared hope that this year will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bahrain"&gt;Bahrain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt expressed dismay at the decision&lt;/a&gt;, saying: “I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pakistan"&gt;Pakistan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-terrorist-attacks-in-pakistan"&gt;condemned the brutal terrorist attacks in Quetta and Swat this week.&lt;/a&gt; He said: “The United Kingdom strongly condemns these senseless attacks and the persecution of the Shia population. It was a tragic day for Pakistan. We will continue to stand with the people of Pakistan in their fight against terror and violent extremism.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="saudi-arabia"&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemned the beheading&lt;/a&gt; of a Sri Lankan national Rizana Nafeek and reiterated the UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-urge-s-laotian-authorities-to-investigate-disappearance-of-community-leader"&gt;urged the Laotian authorities to investigate disappearance of respected community leader Sombath Somphone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Baugh the British Ambassador to Somalia &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/mattbaugh/2013/01/09/somalia-a-new-years-resolution-together-into-2013/"&gt;blogged about how the changes of 2012 offer better prospects for improved stability in Somalia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We advised British nationals travelling in Australia to &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/travel-advice-bushfires-in-australia"&gt;check with local state authorities for the latest bushfire information.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65592</id>
    <published>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T11:48:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-to-answer-questions-on-syria-via-twitter"/>
    <title>FCO Minister to answer questions on Syria via Twitter</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions on Syria live via Twitter on 14 January 11:15am-12:00pm GMT.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his statement to Parliament on 10 January, the Foreign Secretary set out further UK action on Syria in the coming weeks. On 9-10 January, the UK organised a successful meeting at Wilton Park as part of our efforts in stepping up support for Syrian-led political transition and planning for the day after Assad. The meeting was an important step in taking forward this support. The Syrian National Coalition leadership shared its thinking for a future Syria and helped to identify practical options for how the UK and wider international community can support a successful Syrian-led transition to a stable and democratic country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives from 14 countries and international organisations agreed, alongside the Syrian National Coalition, that transition should build towards a Syria which offers equal opportunities for all, through which all Syrians can help determine the shape of a future Syria. This was an important milestone in Syria’s journey towards a lasting and peaceful democracy and we hope that our contributions play an important role in shaping it. The UK stands ready to support transition in Syria. But it will be a collective international effort to assist the Syrian National Coalition to bring about the changes the Syrian people so truly deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East Alistair Burt will answer your questions about the UK’s policy towards Syria live via Twitter on Monday 14th January from 11.15am-12.00pm GMT. Questions can be submitted to Mr Burt &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/AlistairBurtFCO"&gt;@AlistairBurtFCO&lt;/a&gt; using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt;. He will answer questions in English and as many as time allows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can follow the Q&amp;amp;A using the hashtag &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23askfco&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#askFCO&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65329</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T14:48:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-killing-of-rizana-nafeek-in-saudi-arabia"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister condemns killing of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alistair Burt reiterates UK’s opposition to the death penalty as a matter of principle</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Sri Lankan national, Ms Rizana Nafeek, was executed yesterday in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn the execution of Rizana Nafeek in Saudi Arabia yesterday, despite the many appeals for her sentence to be commuted. The UK opposes all use of the death penalty as a matter of principle, whatever the crime committed. The beheading of Ms Nafeek is particularly concerning as reports suggest she may have been a child of 17 at the time the crime was committed. We also find the practice of beheading to be particularly cruel and inhuman. We continue to raise our concerns about human rights with the Saudi authorities, including its frequent use of the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64188</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T18:17:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-dismayed-at-verdict-in-bahraini-activists-appeal"/>
    <title>Minister “dismayed” at verdict in Bahraini activists’ appeal </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt, has called on Bahrain to guarantee its citizens’ fundamental liberties.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bahraini Cassation Court today upheld the sentences of 13 activists for their part in anti-government protests in 2011. Commenting earlier, Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am deeply dismayed at the decision of the Bahraini Cassation Court to uphold the sentences of 13 political activists in today’s appeal hearing. At the time these individuals were sentenced, reports which were acknowledged by the Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry suggested that some had been abused in detention, denied access to legal counsel and were coerced into confessing. I call on the Government of Bahrain to meet all its human rights obligations and guarantee its citizens the fundamental liberties to which they are entitled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bahrain-independent-commission-of-inquiry-bici"&gt;Minister comments on Bahrain Independent Commission of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64014</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T16:23:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--106"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="uk-presidency-of-the-g8"&gt;UK Presidency of the G8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 1st January the UK took over the one year &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;Presidency of the G8.&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"&gt;UK’s priorities for the G8&lt;/a&gt; are to advance trade, to strengthening international tax standards and to improve the transparency and accountability of governments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague will host the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"&gt;G8 foreign minister’s&lt;/a&gt; meeting, in addition to the priorities above the Foreign Secretary will focus on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-initiative"&gt;Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative&lt;/a&gt; and ensuring that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukintunisia.fco.gov.uk/en/news/?view=PressR&amp;amp;id=604439682"&gt;G8’s Deauville Partnership&lt;/a&gt; provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the British Embassies in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/zoesmith/2013/01/02/transparency-a-top-priority-for-2013/"&gt;San Salvador&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.fco.gov.uk/gregdorey/2013/01/03/uk-2013-g8-presidency/"&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; blogged about how the work they are doing fits in with the UK priorities for the G8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="somalia"&gt;Somalia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-discusses-progress-in-somalia-with-foreign-minister"&gt;Foreign Secretary met Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam&lt;/a&gt; the Somali Foreign Minister to discuss recent progress in Somalia. Fawzia Yusuf H. Adam outlined the challenges ahead including improving security, increasing access to justice, transparent financial management, political reconciliation and economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-falklands"&gt;The Falklands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to Argentina’s invitation to negotiations about the sovereignty of the Falkland Islands the Foreign Office reiterated the UK government’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/supporting-the-falkland-islanders-right-to-self-determination"&gt;policy on the Falklands.&lt;/a&gt; A spokesperson said: “The people of the Falklands are British and have chosen to be so. They have the right to self-determination as set out in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.un.org/en/documents/charter/chapter1.shtml"&gt;UN Charter.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;Sudan and South Sudan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-urge-progress-between-sudan-and-south-sudan"&gt;The Foreign Secretary, the Norwegian Foreign Minister and the U.S. Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; called on the Presidents of Sudan and South Sudan to implement agreements on border security and oil, and to resolve all other outstanding issues. They said: “We remind the leaders of Sudan and South Sudan that the international community is fully committed to a vision of two viable countries at peace with one another, and that we stand ready to support them in realising that vision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="burma"&gt;Burma&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing violence and reports of airstrikes in Burma’s Kachin State, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"&gt;“An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma.&lt;/a&gt; It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-democratic-republic-of-congo"&gt;The Democratic Republic of Congo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Mark Simmonds welcomed the inclusion of  the milita groups the M23 and Forces Democratiques de Libération du Rwanda (FDLR) on the UN Security Council Sanctions committee list of sanctioned organisations. The Minister said: &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministerial-statement-on-un-sanctions-against-the-m23-fdlr-eric-badege-and-jean-marie-runiga-legerero"&gt;“The dialogue needed to resolve the crisis must ensure that all violence stops,&lt;/a&gt; that external support to M23 ends and that there is no impunity for M23 commanders and others who have committed serious human rights abuses, including the FDLR.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"&gt;condemned Iran’s descision to re-arrest a Christian Pastor&lt;/a&gt; on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK Government sent &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"&gt;condolences to the Ivory Coast&lt;/a&gt; following the tragic loss of life during a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/honours-awarded-to-brits-for-exceptional-international-achievement"&gt;Diplomatic Service and Overseas New Year 2013 Honours list&lt;/a&gt; recognised British people doing outstanding work for the UK internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61172</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T17:51:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-condemns-persecution-of-religious-minorities-in-iran"/>
    <title>Foreign Office condemns persecution of religious minorities in Iran</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has condemned the re-arrest of Christian pastor in Iran.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports that Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani had been re-arrested in Iran, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa Alistair Burt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I condemn Iran’s decision to re-arrest the Christian Pastor Yousef Nadarkhani, and to do so on Christmas Day. In September I welcomed his release from prison, where he was detained on baseless charges of apostasy. That he has now been re-arrested, on the grounds of serving the remainder of his sentence for “evangelising Muslims”, is a cynical move by the Iranian Government and yet further proof of Iran’s widespread and systematic persecution of religious minorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Religious freedom in Iran is a matter of ongoing and deep concern. Reports that more than 50 people were arrested for celebrating Christmas in a private home show the depths of intolerance with which the Iranian Government treats its own citizens. Amongst those arrested, Reverend Vruir Avanessian, who suffers serious ill health, remains imprisoned. I call on the Iranian Government to release immediately any citizens who remain in prison on the basis of their faith or belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statement welcoming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-welcomes-release-of-christian-pastor-in-iran"&gt;release of the pastor in September 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-concerned-by-iran-s-appalling-treatment-of-christian-pastor"&gt;sentencing of pastor Yousef Nadarkhani&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60865</id>
    <published>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-26T17:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-condemns-new-settlement"/>
    <title>Foreign Office minister condemns new settlement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>FCO Minister Alistair Burt statement: the approval of new units is a 'provocative action' contrary to Fourth Geneva Convention.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the announcements on 24 December that the Jerusalem District Planning Board issued approval for 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South, and that Ariel College is to be upgraded to university status thereby creating the first university in a settlement illegal under international law, Alistair Burt, Minister for the Middle East said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last week Foreign Secretary William Hague made clear our condemnation and deep disappointment at the approval of the East Jerusalem Ramat Shlomo plan. We also condemn the Jerusalem District Planning Board’s approvals for over 3150 units in Givaat Hamatos and 1242 units in Mordot Gilo South. These are further profoundly provocative actions that run contrary to the Fourth Geneva Convention. By taking these steps, despite the international community repeatedly raising our profound concerns, the Israeli Government is damaging Israel’s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are also deeply disappointed in the decision to upgrade Ariel’s university centre. Ariel is beyond the Green Line in a settlement that is illegal according to international law. This decision will deepen the presence of the settlements in the Palestinian territories and will create another obstacle to peace. We reiterate our call on Israel urgently to reverse these decisions and take no further steps aimed at expanding or entrenching settlement activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I spoke with President Abbas last week I expressed our appreciation for the measured response the Palestinian Leadership had been taking in response to Israel’s recent settlement announcements.  We utterly and unreservedly condemn the recent call for a third intifada and a suicide campaign by a Hamas official. Incitements to violence and terror are unacceptable. We welcome that President Abbas has publicly rejected the recent inflammatory statements by Hamas leaders, and that he has stated clearly the position of the legitimate Palestinian Leadership which has accepted the State of Israel in 1967 borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taken together, these further settlement announcements and comments deepen our worry for the region at such a crucial time, and demonstrate why we are convinced of the urgency for more positive indicators of change. Accordingly we continue to call on President Abbas and Prime Minister Netanyahu to show the strong leadership needed to achieve a return to negotiations for a two-state solution, which will bring a just and permanent solution to this conflict.  We repeat our hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60862</id>
    <published>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-24T15:42:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-appalled-by-killing-of-civilians-at-bakery-in-syria"/>
    <title>FCO Minister appalled by killing of civilians at bakery in Syria</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt condemns shelling that killed over 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, Syria .</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on reports of shelling which reportedly killed more than 60 people queuing for bread at a bakery in Halfaya, the Foreign Office Minister for the Middle East, Alistair Burt, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am appalled by emerging reports of the brutal shelling and killing of civilians in Halfaya in Hama province yesterday. Opposition groups report that over 60 people were killed while queuing for bread with more believed to be buried in the rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If verified, this would be the most recent in a long line of human rights violations and abuses committed by the Syrian regime, which continues to wage a remorseless war against its own people. The attack highlights the urgent need for a political transition and end to the violence, and for those responsible for these appalling acts to be held to account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60831</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T17:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eu-puts-iran-sanctions-into-law"/>
    <title>EU puts Iran sanctions into law</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt comments following the EU's formal implementation of additional sanctions against Iran.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the EU adopted the regulation that translates Iran sanctions agreed by the Foreign Affairs Council in October into law.  These include a prohibition on financial transactions with Iranian financial institutions and further trade restrictions in key sectors like energy and metals, from which Iran derives funds and materials for its proliferation activities.  The UK played a leading role in the negotiation of the regulation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting today, Minister for the Middle East and North Africa, Alistair Burt, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The adoption of a tough EU regulation on Iran sanctions should send a clear message to the Iranian Government that the pressure will only increase until it takes concrete actions to address the international community’s serious concerns about its nuclear programme. Iran continues to enrich uranium on a scale that has no plausible civilian justification, in contravention of international law. The EU’s move follows the decision taken yesterday by the United Nations Security Council to designate two Iranian companies caught red-handed trying to supply arms to the brutal Syrian regime. This continued support for Assad’s efforts to suppress the people of Syria undermines peace and security in the Middle East, and shows the contempt with which the Iranian authorities treat international law and the concerns of the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The E3+3 wants to reach a diplomatic solution with Iran on the nuclear issue, but Iran needs to co-operate. We hope that political talks with Iran can begin again in the New Year, based on mutual respect, but clear in the need for an urgent solution to this issue. Time for a diplomatic solution is not open-ended. Iran’s leaders have a clear choice: work with the international community on a diplomatic agreement which addresses our concerns and which would bring significant benefits to Iran. Or continue on the path of mistrust, damaging the Iranian economy and putting the peace and security of the region at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s leaders know that sanctions are having a significant impact. They should be in no doubt that the international community will keep up the pressure until they are ready to negotiate in good faith and take the concrete steps needed to convince the international community that they are not building a nuclear weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanitarian payments and goods, including food and medicines, will remain exempt from EU and UK sanctions. The UK will continue to prioritise the licensing of transactions for food and medicines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60765</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T15:46:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/renewed-effort-needed-on-two-state-solution-for-israeli-palestinian-conflict"/>
    <title>Renewed effort needed on two-state solution for Israeli-Palestinian conflict</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt has spoken with the President of the Palestinian Authority about the need for peace in the region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the telephone conversation with Mr Mahmoud Abbas today, Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;President Abbas and I had a productive conversation today. I reaffirmed our strong support for President Abbas, Prime Minister Salam Fayyad, and for the Palestinian Authority. We are in no doubt that President Abbas is a courageous man of peace. President Abbas and I discussed our shared profound concern at Israel’s recent settlement announcements, which the Foreign Secretary has condemned in the strongest terms. I expressed appreciation for the measured response of the Palestinian Leadership, and asked the President to engage in a renewed effort - led by the United States with full European support - to achieve a just and permanent solution to this conflict. I welcomed President Abbas’s determined commitment to maintain security co-operation in the West Bank, despite the serious financial pressures on the Palestinian Authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK continues to urge both sides to show the political will and leadership needed to bring about peace and to refrain from any steps that would make the two state solution, or a return to negotiations, more difficult. We agreed that the New Year offered new opportunities to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict by negotiation, and reiterated our determination to do all that we can to make next year decisive. We expressed the shared hope that 2013 will be the ‘year of peace’ for Palestinians, Israelis and all people of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;statement condemning Israels decision to build new settlements.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
