<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/andrew-robathan</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/andrew-robathan.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Andrew Robathan MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-09-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34809</id>
    <published>2012-09-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-mod-ministerial-team-announced"/>
    <title>New MOD ministerial team announced</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new ministerial team is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Secretary of State for Defence - The Rt Hon Philip Hammond MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Minister of State for the Armed Forces - The Rt Hon Andrew Robathan MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans - The Rt Hon Mark Francois MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology (including Defence Exports) - Philip Dunne MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and Minister for International Security Strategy - Dr Andrew Murrison MP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Parliamentary Under Secretary of State and the Lords spokesman on Defence - Lord Astor of Hever&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34774</id>
    <published>2012-08-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-31T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/118-2012-70th-anniversary-of-the-battle-of-el-alamein-to-be-commemorated"/>
    <title>118/2012 - 70th Anniversary of the battle of El Alamein to be commemorated</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill famously described the battle, which began on 23 October 1942 and ended on 4 November 1942, as the end of the beginning of the war. Led by General Montgomery, the Battle of El Alamein was the climax of months of struggle in the Western Desert as the Allies fought to keep open vital supply lines from the Mediterranean to the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence, Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Andrew Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Battle of El Alamein was hugely significant as it was the first time the British gained the upper hand over the German Army. “The end of the beginning”. We should honour the survivors of the Battle and commemorate all those who took part. El Alamein turned the tide in the Western Desert – and arguably of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those wishing to attend are asked to apply by email to tracey.broome576@mod.uk or by telephone 0207 807 0970. Tickets will be posted by 19 October.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A reception will follow in Church House.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commemorations to mark the 60th Anniversary of The Battle of El Alamein included a service at the Commonwealth War Cemetery, El Alamein, Egypt and at a Service of Thanksgiving at Westminster Abbey on 23 October 2002, followed by a reception.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information please contact:
* Tom Callagher on 020 7218 0341/ 07500 121264 or by email at &lt;a href="mailto:tom.callagher880@mod.uk"&gt;tom.callagher880@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;
* Naomi Moore on 020 7218 6162/ 07836 721768 or by email at &lt;a href="mailto:naomi.moore952@mod.uk"&gt;naomi.moore952@mod.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34783</id>
    <published>2012-07-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-31T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/106-2012-new-armed-forces-pension-proposed"/>
    <title>106/2012 - New Armed Forces pension proposed</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme will also deliver on the approach set out in Lord Hutton’s Independent Public Service Pensions Commission to reform pensions and ensure that they are more affordable and sustainable for the long-term. Changes will not affect accrued rights of those currently serving or the age at which their accrued benefits can be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other public service pension schemes, Service personnel will still not have to make personal contributions, and will still receive a lump sum if they leave the Armed Forces at 40 if they have served the required number of years, again unlike any other public service pension. The Normal Pension Age will be 60, whereas for other public service pensions the Normal Pension Age will be linked to the State Pension Age, which is considerably higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Andrew Robathan said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government has had to make some tough decisions to ensure sustainable public service pensions which provide a fair deal for both service personnel and for the taxpayer. We recognise the unique commitment made by the Armed Forces and we have done all we can to protect them and make these changes in the fairest way possible. The proposed new scheme will remain among the very best available in the public or private sector, with no individual contributions required by Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits of the proposed new scheme include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It creates one scheme for all – including Reservists. There are currently several different Armed Forces pension schemes; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Service personnel won’t have to make any personal contributions to their pension;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Service personnel will receive a tax-free lump sum and monthly income if they leave the Armed Forces at 40 and have served for over 20 years. No other public service makes any pension payment that early;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As recommended by Lord Hutton, the Normal Pension Age will be 60 – considerably lower than other public service pensions;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accrued pension rights have been protected so there is no change to the age at which those currently serving can draw their accrued benefits, which are based on final rank and salary; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is in line with Lord Hutton’s recommendations and other public service schemes, moving to a pension based on career average earnings, rather than final salary; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All members of the Armed Forces Pension Scheme who were within ten years of their Normal Pension Age on 1 April 2012 will receive transitional protection and see no change in their pension age or the amount they receive at retirement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme was designed after extensive consultation with over 17,500 personnel both in the UK and overseas including Afghanistan, Germany, Gibraltar and the Falkland Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will now be a further period of consultation for personnel to make comments before the new scheme design is finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 the Government announced it would be reforming all public service pensions and later accepted the Independent Public Service Pensions Commission’s recommendations to make them fair and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence began an Armed Forces Pension Scheme consultation exercise at the end of March 2012 to set out the reasons for change and invite views from Service personnel and external stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, the Ministry of Defence has published the Outline Scheme Design, which sets out the key features of the new scheme. The document is primarily aimed at Service personnel and external stakeholders, including the Forces’ Families Federations, the Forces Pension Society and the Royal British Legion. There will now be a further period of consultation for personnel to make comments before the new scheme design is finalised.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following this further period of consultation, a new Armed Forces Pension Scheme will be introduced from April 2015. All those serving when the new scheme is introduced will be automatically enrolled unless they qualify for transitional protection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The total cost of the new Armed Forces Pension Scheme is 31.5 per cent of pensionable pay, which is all borne by the Exchequer, as there are no employee contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the consultation document can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/TheNewArmedForcesPensionSchemeFinalConsultation.htm"&gt;http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ConsultationsandCommunications/PublicConsultations/TheNewArmedForcesPensionSchemeFinalConsultation.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For further media enquiries please call Robert Mead at the Ministry of Defence press office on 020 7218 7924.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/40907</id>
    <published>2012-05-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-15T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/extra-funding-for-armed-forces-online-mental-health-network"/>
    <title>Extra funding for Armed Forces online mental health network</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The award-winning Big White Wall (BWW) is an online forum specifically for serving personnel, veterans and their families which provides information on mental health issues and is staffed by professional counsellors who can be contacted 24-hours-a-day, seven-days-a-week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was launched in 2009 as a pilot scheme and yesterday’s extra funding announcement represents a long-term commitment by the government to address the mental wellbeing of the Armed Forces community and ensure a smooth transition into civilian life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help for Heroes also supports the service, providing a grant to co-fund the pilot scheme with the Department of Health, and now committing a further £300,000 to the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service allows users to chat anonymously to others who may have gone through similar experiences, and in the last nine months has been used by over 2,500 registered users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the extra funding announcement during a visit to the BWW and its joint venture partner the Tavistock and Portman NHS Foundation Trust, in North London yesterday, Health Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We understand that many veterans feel a stigma attached to seeking help for mental distress. That is why initiatives like the Big White Wall are so invaluable, allowing veterans and their families to talk to others in an anonymous yet interactive space.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Department of Health is proud to announce that the Big White Wall will receive £400,000 over the next three years, allowing more veterans to benefit from the support provided by this wellbeing network and its professional counsellors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is by funding services such as the Big White Wall that are easily accessible and trustworthy that we can create an environment in which members of the Armed Forces community feel understood and can take important steps towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Andrew Robathan, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted this important resource has been given additional funding by the Government and Help for Heroes. Looking after the mental health of our people is a key priority.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am particularly pleased that they will be able to continue to benefit from the Big White Wall by discussing the issues they face through this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this newly-funded programme, the Armed Forces community will have free unlimited access to BWW’s online services, which include the ability to discuss issues - from post-traumatic stress disorder to addictions, disability and injury to anxiety and depression - anonymously in forums with their peers as well as with specially-trained counsellors who can offer immediate support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so much stigma incorrectly associated with seeking treatment for mental health disorders, particularly in the military, BWW offers a discreet and confidential platform where help can be sought anonymously, allowing for early intervention in potentially serious psychological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Hyatt, Chief Executive Officer and founder of the BWW, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The success of the pilot scheme has demonstrated that there is a huge appetite amongst the Armed Forces community for issues around their mental wellbeing to be addressed in a secure and confidential environment.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The invaluable funding from the Department of Health and Help for Heroes will enable us to extend the programme and ensure continued help and support is there 24/7 for those who are most in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BWW is the only online wellbeing service that combines social networking principles with a choice of clinically-informed interventions to improve mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Available 24/7, recent developments include the introduction of ‘live therapy’ which, developed through funding from the NHS National Innovation Centre, offers safe, remote online access to a course of real-time therapy and extends the choice of, and accessibility to, a broad range of psychological therapies. This service will officially launch in June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since BWW began in 2009, the service has supported 7,000 people across the country and has been commissioned to support thousands more by a range of healthcare and other organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BWW operates within a governance framework jointly developed with clinicians at the Tavistock and Portman NHS Foundation Trust. All ‘wall guides’ are supervised and trained by clinicians from the Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BWW is a community of people who are experiencing common mental health problems and who are supported to self-manage their own mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service is already available free to the general public in several areas within the UK, where it is funded by the local NHS. Should anyone wish to join outside those areas they can do so for as little as £2 per week or less, or register their interest in the service and BWW will lobby their local NHS to create free places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See Related Links to gain access to services provided by the Big White Wall.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/41207</id>
    <published>2012-04-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-04-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-and-sepa-agree-dalgety-bay-plan"/>
    <title>MOD and SEPA agree Dalgety Bay plan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOD has been working with SEPA to develop the plan with a view to undertaking the work necessary to support the newly established Expert Group advising on the risks and inform the work to determine the scope of any remediation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Robathan, Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Working with SEPA, this represents a key milestone in understanding the situation at Dalgety Bay and presents the timetable for the investigation. I reaffirm our commitment to keeping the community informed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He reiterated that MOD remained committed to assisting SEPA and challenged claims that MOD has sought to shirk its responsibilities stating that his department’s policy on matters of land contamination was very clear: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where MOD is found to be a party responsible, namely, the Appropriate Person, in whole or part for contaminated land under the statutory regime, then we will work with the regulator and other responsible and interested parties such as landowners, to meet our portion of the liability and carry out voluntary remediation where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreement comes after some three months of collaboration and consultation involving both SEPA and the Expert Group established to assist them with examining the level of risk to human health and the need for and scope of any further work including remediation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan, prepared by MOD contaminated land specialists, will assist SEPA with their statutory inspection and sets out a staged investigation consistent with current best practice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**To read the plan, see Related Links. **&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54969</id>
    <published>2012-04-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-04-04T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/services-for-personnel-and-veterans-with-mental-health-problems--2"/>
    <title>Services for personnel and veterans with mental health problems</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These measures, announced in the past month, are part of the concerted effort to destigmatise issues around mental health and promote awareness of the professional medical care and support available for troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of Service personnel make the transition to civilian life successfully, but a small number suffer problems as a result of their service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Health Service (NHS) is responsible for delivering veterans’ healthcare needs, and services are available which cater specifically to veterans’ mental health needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24-hour Combat Stress helpline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD is working with Service charities, including Combat Stress, to promote awareness of veterans’ issues and, last year, the Department of Health, along with Combat Stress, launched a free 24-hour helpline, run by charity Rethink, to offer support for veterans and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health Minister Simon Burns said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military personnel make daily sacrifices to serve their country and help protect innocent people all over the world; it is only right that they receive the best possible care and support from the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Last year we launched a free 24-hour helpline which offers vital support for our veterans and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Through working closely with Combat Stress and Rethink, this fantastic service has now taken over 5,000 calls, and I am pleased to announce that we are providing funding for a further year to continue to provide ex-Service personnel and their families with help and support whenever and wherever they need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helpline is based on the principle of lifelong care and offers support to veterans of any age and at any stage in their lives. Families may also contact the helpline, both for themselves and to talk about a loved one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows both groups to receive targeted support from people trained and experienced in dealing with often complex mental health needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big White Wall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Combat Stress helpline, The Department of Health and the MOD are funding a one-year wellbeing network pilot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Big White Wall’, is an online social network for serving personnel, their families, veterans and the general public that allows people with mental health problems from every walk of life to engage with others who have similar problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymity of the network allows for a free and frank exchange of experiences, with a view to generating a wider sense of support, and it is staffed by professional counselors. Mr Burns said, in the House of Commons in March:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased to say that it has had excellent take-up. Up to 1 March, 2,019 places of the original 2,400 provided in the pilot have been filled. Of those, veterans represent 40 per cent, with 38 Per cent being serving personnel and 22 per cent family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get more details on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.combatstress.org.uk/"&gt;24-hour Combat Stress helpline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bigwhitewall.com/"&gt;the Big White Wall&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ministry of Defence Medical Assessment Programme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in March, the Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Andrew Robathan, announced that the Ministry of Defence Medical Assessment Programme (MAP) would come under the control of APHCS (Army Primary Healthcare Service) on 1 April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently located at St Thomas’ Hospital, London, the MAP will, prior to October 2012, collocate with other Mental Health programmes based at the Reinforcements Training and Mobilisation Centre (RTMC) at Chetwynd Barracks in Chilwell, and offer a comprehensive service to reservists and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAP currently offers mental health assessments to ex-Service personnel who have deployed on operations since 1982 and have mental health problems related to their military service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Robathan said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are significant advantages in collocating the MAP with the RTMC at Chilwell.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This will provide a more structured professional environment for the MAP physician; benefits for clinical governance and flexibility from working alongside the Reserves mental healthcare service; and improved cost effectiveness from sharing the facilities already in place at Chilwell.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This move isalso expected to benefit the majority of veterans as demographic data indicates that a high percentage are being referred from the North and the Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announcing the changes to the MAP to the House of Commons last month, Mr Robatham referred to the report ‘Fighting Fit - A mental health plan for servicemen and veterans’, published in October 2010 by Dr Andrew Murrison MP:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We fully support [Dr Andrew Murrison’s] report’s recommendation that the MAP service continues while NHS mental health services are further developed across the UK, and remain committed to doing all we can to help veterans with mental health problems related to their military service and to making improvements to the services we provide,” he told the Commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fighting-fit-a-mental-health-plan-for-servicemen-and-veterans--2"&gt;Read Dr Murrison’s report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18746</id>
    <published>2011-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-12-01-mod-civilian-apprentice-awards"/>
    <title>2011/12/01 - MoD Civilian Apprentice Awards</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon, Ladies and Gentlemen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Bernard [Gray - Chief of Defence Materiel] for that introduction, and for inviting me to say a few words before presenting this year’s MoD civilian apprentice awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also thank all of today’s sponsors for their continued support of this important event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted that Lady Cardwell could be with us once again - after last year’s snow prevented her attendance for the first time since 1982 - to present the Sir David Cardwell Memorial Prize.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir David was one of Bernard’s predecessors - in charge of buying the equipment our Armed Forces need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the organisation has changed greatly since Sir David’s time in charge, some things endure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships continue play an important role in helping us to produce the engineers and craftsmen of the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly 500 apprenticeships and 300 advanced apprenticeships were completed last year; we’re here today to recognise the best of them - 29 in all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the value of apprenticeships to our Armed Forces and our broader economic well-being is as high as ever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, in the modern age, the work of the engineer and the craftsman is not as revered as it should be in the eyes of the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many students are lured away from inventing the future and making things people can actually use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet heavy industry generates more cash, more exports, more technology, and more jobs than many of the more fashionable sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want engineers and craftsmen to be the wonder of our age as they were in the Britain of Telford and Brunel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An architect may have designed London’s latest landmark - the Shard - but it takes engineers and craftsmen to build it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also takes excellence, and in a range of fields. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the practical engineering skills which Brunel would admire, today’s engineers need other skills like project management in their toolbox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our prize-winners today have shown they have the tools to meet the demands of modern engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why they have a great deal to offer to our Armed Forces and to our economy; and I want to reflect briefly on that this morning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because this isn’t some abstract debate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men and women in our Armed Forces - particularly those on operations - rely on the quality of the equipment and support we can provide them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, soldiers in Afghanistan rely on their vehicles to carry out their mission as well as keep them safe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anything breaks down it can be a life-threatening situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes the job of today’s engineers and craftsmen a vital one, though they don’t always get the credit they deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the engineers of the future are not born; they’re made, and they’re nurtured. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships play such an important role in that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the MoD continues to value and support apprenticeships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our scheme remains an enviable one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a unique opportunity to work on some of the country’s most advanced engineering and equipment projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from our perspective, it’s a shrewd investment in our future workforce. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the work on the new aircraft carriers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an apprentice supporting the MoD project team, while others are embedded with industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this colossal project has reinvigorated industry apprenticeship schemes across the six shipyards engaged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 800 apprentices are currently involved, and this number is set to increase as production continues to ramp up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever they’re working, these apprentices are proud to learn their trade on such a prestigious project which will be at the heart of Britain’s defence for decades to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we want everyone who undertakes an apprenticeship provided by us to stay with us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that some will go on to use their skills elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in good times, we should welcome the contribution they will make to the broader economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s particularly welcome in tough economic times like these. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t defer investing in our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a false economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing now in the skills we will need in the future is a key part of our plan for recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as true for us in the public sector as it is for those in the private sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want a skills system where responsibility is shared between government, employers, and employees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we want to address the problem of youth unemployment so that young people are earning or learning again before long-term damage is done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we launched a £1 billion Youth Contract last week which will provide over 400,000 new work places for 18 to 24 year olds over the next three years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apprenticeships are at the heart of this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, we want to double the incentive payments to encourage employers to take on young apprentices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good news for young people up and down the country, and good news for the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pay-off for business is a skilled, motivated, and loyal workforce. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m proud to be the MoD’s apprentice champion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need more engineers and craftsmen like you - you are becoming a rare breed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are vital to the Defence of this country, and central to its future prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted that we can recognise your achievements with your friends and family today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18739</id>
    <published>2011-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-11-01-local-government-association-conference"/>
    <title>2011/11/01 - Local Government Association Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Sir Merrick for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My congratulations on organising a fascinating day with some excellent speakers - they’re still to come..! -and workshops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a Councillor myself, and my wife is currently - within Westminster - so I have some understanding of the issues you face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic to see so many representatives from across local government, and the voluntary and charitable sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are in the vanguard of our plans to cement the bond between our communities and the Armed Forces through the Armed Forces Covenant and Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone down the years would have embraced such localism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General de Gaulle once observed of France, “How can you govern a country which has 246 varieties of cheese?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He would have really struggled in Britain which - according to the gloriously named British Cheese Board - boasts over 700 distinct local cheeses! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he would have despaired at your job, Merrick, representing as you do hundreds of councils and thousands of councillors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, in part, De Gaulle’s complaint seems to have been that localism interferes with the smooth pursuit of the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps so in France, but in Britain I’ve always believed that’s the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government believes in ‘small government’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Westminster and Whitehall should lead on those issues which are truly national in scope. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, at most, they should complement - not substitute - local efforts on everything else. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why decentralising power is at the heart of this government’s agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet Britain’s Armed Forces straddle the national and local divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one level, they are rooted in lock communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the British infantry system of county regiments helped to forge deep ties between those who serve - often alongside neighbours and friends - and the communities they left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At another level, our Armed Forces are woven into the fabric of our nation’s history and psyche. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson on the quarterdeck; the Pals on the Somme; the SAS on TV as they stormed the Iranian Embassy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage, sacrifice, excellence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why the British public have a deep respect for, and pride in, our Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But respect and pride are not the same as understanding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces Community may be an integral part of our society, but in recent decades the link has declined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When World War II ended in 1945, there were around five million men and women in uniform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone in the country knew someone close who had served. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents and her generation gave up their youth in the service of this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Service generation only added to the ledger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for many years, our Armed Forces have been a professional, volunteer force - declining in number - while the older generations have dwindled. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public understanding of our Armed Forces has declined as a result.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matters hugely. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of our Armed Forces depends on them knowing that they have their country’s support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliament has taken to welcoming home units of the Armed Forces, and yesterday we welcomed 3 Commando. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked them to go to war, and it is right that we welcome them home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such support requires the public to understand the role of our Armed Forces, and the sacrifice our men and women in uniform make with their families. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never take public support for granted, even in times of plenty.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor should we under-estimate their principled conviction that our Armed Forces Community should get the support they need and the dignity they deserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That they should suffer no disadvantage as a result of serving; indeed should receive special consideration in some instances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that they have a right to expect a whole of society approach - not just a top-down, or bottom-up one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m pleased to say that in the 18 months since the General Election we’ve taken action over a very broad canvas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time ever, the principles I have mentioned (no disadvantage) will be recognised in the law of the land through the Armed Forces Bill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the front line, we’ve doubled the operational allowance and extended it to Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve improved the Rest and Recuperation leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve doubled Council Tax relief from 25% to 50% for all personnel on operations, including Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, we set out - in the ‘Today and Tomorrow’ paper - what we’re doing to give the Covenant practical effect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, we have endorsed all of Andrew Murrison’s recommendations for improving mental health care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have allocated resources for 36,000 Service children as part of the pupil premium, and introduced a separate fund for schools with high proportions of Service children.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are giving our personnel a high priority in Affordable Housing Schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, as I’ve said, the Armed Forces Covenant is not just about action from the centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are fewer than 200,000 serving members of our Armed Forces, whereas there are still more than four and a half million people who have served. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With their families, our Armed Forces Community is roughly one in six of the total population. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing support to this vast number of people involves all areas of local government working with communities up and down the land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10 NHS Armed Forces Networks have proved particularly useful in ironing out local healthcare and adult social care issues through their extensive local networks.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, an RAF couple were devastated to hear that their application to adopt a child had been scuppered by orders posting them overseas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Authority had withdrawn from the process as ‘suitable’ counselling services would not be available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contacting their regional Armed Forces Network lead, they were able to get SSAFA Forces Help to liaise with the Local Authority until the issue was resolved and the adoption went ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ‘no disadvantage from service’ principle in action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also shows the importance of local authorities forging links with Service charities and the wider voluntary and charitable sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in June, four counties became the first in Britain to demonstrate community-led support for the Armed Forces through the Community Covenant scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll hear more about best practice later this morning from three of the counties involved so far - Oxfordshire, Hampshire, and North Yorkshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further seven councils have signed, with over 30 in the pipeline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant has been well-received, and my hope is that every community will sign one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important as a symbol of our beliefs, and it’s important as a commitment to action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon you will hear more about the Community Covenant Grant Scheme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have allocated up to £30 million until 2015 to fund projects which support the aims of the Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel considered the first bids last month. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to announce that we have approved 11 superb bids in full, and another two in part, totalling over £400,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly pleased to see that those bids will draw in matched funding of over a quarter of a million pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the successful bids themselves, they include help towards a new Scout and Guides Headquarters in Bedale; supporting the Dover Diamond Jubilee Tattoo; and helping elderly residents in their village during adverse weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions on another 14 applications will be made once we have received some additional information.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are all approved, it would take total project funding past £1 million in just this first round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panels are due to sit again in December and March, and quarterly thereafter - so it’s not too late! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, Defence is a very human endeavour -  and the consequences of Service life are very human too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that today inspires you to deepen the relationship between our Armed Forces and the communities they’re drawn from. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because that relationship is as important now as it’s ever been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How we, as a nation, treat our Armed Forces Community is a litmus test of who we are as a nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m confident that the nation will respond to the challenge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that it will be driven in part by localism in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18738</id>
    <published>2011-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-10-27-the-confederation-of-service-charities-cobseo-agm"/>
    <title>2011/10/27 - The Confederation of Service Charities (COBSEO) AGM</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Tony [Air Vice-Marshal Tony Stables, Royal Air Force (ret’d), Chairman, COBSEO] for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, good morning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[As Tony said], it is indeed a privilege to meet here in St. James’s Palace, and we are honoured that the Prince of Wales will be joining us shortly in his new capacity as COBSEO Patron. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that Simon Burns from the Department of Health spoke at last year’s event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’ll speak on behalf of the MoD.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, perhaps a Minister from another government department - maybe even a Lib Dem?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a shrewd move. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sends a clear message that the contract between the nation and the Armed Forces Community goes beyond one Department or one sector of society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO is at the heart of that contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You represent the best of what the French philosopher, Tocqueville, called “the art of association”, which gives society a “habit and taste for serving others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be difficult for Government to engage in a meaningful way with each of the 180 or so organisations - including some 66 regimental associations - which come under the COBSEO umbrella. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of COBSEO, we are able to develop a far greater degree of coherence across government in our approach to all these organisations and the important work they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And COBSEO makes their voice in Government far more powerful as a result. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are also a helpful voice of conciliation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our overriding objective is the same: to dignify, honour, and support our Armed Forces Community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet sometimes the priorities of one organisation do not always mesh with those of another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they overlap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoD has no role in telling your members what to do; individual organisations, not government, know what’s best for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the Chairman of SSAFA Forces Help, Sir Kevin O’Donoghue has said, “As time goes by, it is natural and right that some organisations merge with others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Poppyscotland and the Royal British Legion have recently merged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn’t changed the brand of Poppyscotland; the Scottish poppy and Scottish Poppy Appeal remain firmly in place; and the manufacture of poppies continues - as it has for almost 90 years - at Lady Haig’s Poppy Factory in Edinburgh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it has provided is major additional investment, which will mean better services for ex-Service personnel and their families north of the border. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, SSAFA Forces Help have taken on the charitable objectives and assets of The Royal Patriotic Fund Corporation which supported Britain’s forces and their families for 156 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples like these underscore Sir Kevin’s view, and I know that COBSEO has lent a deft touch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that (where appropriate) the voluntary and charitable sector should consolidate, not diverge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t have to mean mergers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the way forward will lie in better co-operation and collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what matters most is the service and the best way of providing it, not the structures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen that with the Defence Recovery Capability which has taken the way we support our wounded, injured, and sick personnel to a new level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In large part, this is thanks to Help for Heroes and the Royal British Legion pooling their resources with the MoD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this partnership represents the single largest charitable contribution to the Armed Forces in British history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Government has a major role to play too, and I’ll come to that in a minute. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as I’ve said before, action from the top, or just from the bottom, is rarely the panacea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glass will only be half-full unless Government, local authorities, the Devolved Administrations, charities, businesses, communities, and individuals come together and maximise the benefit their services can offer the Armed Forces Community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a whole of society approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate that with some specific issues which I know are close to COBSEO’s heart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take transition issues.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early Service leavers are said to be a particularly vulnerable group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as finding a new job, they may often have welfare, housing, education, healthcare, and psychological needs which have to be addressed simultaneously. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many organisations out there willing and able to help. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently visited one of the smaller COBSEO members - the recently renamed Stoll. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The housing and support they provide for vulnerable and disabled ex-Service personnel - particularly the homeless - is quite simply the Big Society in action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support and advice is provided by the voluntary and charitable sector across the UK so that those who choose to serve their country can look to their country with confidence when they most need help. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it can nonetheless be daunting for those who need help to know where to turn, and we’re addressing this issue through the Service Personnel and Veterans Agency hotline and website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But COBSEO has also helped enormously as people can now look at their website and their inaugural ‘handbook’ to find out who does what. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO is also running a transition system for early Service leavers to trial. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’ve set up a number of cluster groups within COBSEO to look at specific issues such as residential and care homes; criminal justice support; and welfare delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, through the “Forces in Mind” trust, COBSEO is leading a partnership of Service charities and mental health organisations seeking Big Lottery funding to support the psychological well-being and successful transition of Service leavers and their families into civilian life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll know if they’ve been successful shortly, and I wish them every success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said I would come back to the Government’s role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some areas where the MoD is firmly in the lead within government - the operational allowance to the Veterans’ helpline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my colleagues across Whitehall recognise the role they have too.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoD has developed a Transition Protocol with the Department of Health, Devolved Administrations, and the Association of Directors of Adult Social Services to ensure a seamless transition for the most seriously ill and injured Service personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Prime Minister announced investment in the NHS of up to £15 million to improve the prosthetics services for ex-Service personnel who have lost a limb due to activities while serving their country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also much more going on as part of our wider work on the Armed Forces Covenant and Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week, for example, we shall be announcing the first tranche of grant funding for projects which support the aims of the Community Covenant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other areas, we work together, taking the lead or complementing the efforts of your members. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must work together, but we must also talk to each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value the input of the independent members of the Covenant Reference Group, of which COBSEO is a member along with TRBL, SSAFA Forces Help, the War Widows Association, the three Family Federations, and Professor Hew Strachan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be a particularly important contribution as we prepare the new Annual Report on the Covenant, as required by the Armed Forces Bill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, we all know that times are tough.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet such is the respect in which our Armed Forces are held that the public continues to support so many service charities to re-pay the debt of honour we all owe those who serve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that COBSEO will be in the vanguard of that effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18731</id>
    <published>2011-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-09-19-sir-oswald-stoll-foundation-agm"/>
    <title>2011/09/19 - Sir Oswald Stoll Foundation AGM</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Sir John [Field Marshal Sir John Chapple, President, Sir Oswald Stoll Foundation] for that introduction, and for inviting me to join your AGM. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning Ladies and Gentlemen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The housing and support which the Sir Oswald Stoll Foundation provides for vulnerable and disabled veterans - particularly the homeless - is quite simply the Big Society in action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s replicated across the charitable and voluntary sector so that those who choose to serve their country can look to their country with confidence when they most need help.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sheer breadth and depth of this effort never ceases to amaze me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An excellent example is Pryors Bank Cafe, here in Fulham, which, as you know, is a not-for-profit business run in partnership with the Foundation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was founded by a former soldier, which to my mind gave it a fighting chance from the outset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It trains former Service personnel to NVQ standard with the chance of working in West End Restaurants. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it pays people a wage, gives them a chance to study at college, and assists them in finding accommodation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when your Chief Executive invited me to see for myself the terrific work the Foundation does, I was only too happy to oblige. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also a good opportunity for me to set your work in the broader context of Government policy towards serving and former Service personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are testing times for the country - and Defence is no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Government seeks to put the public finances back on a sustainable path, we in Defence are doing the same for a Defence budget which has been in disarray for some time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also seeking to transform our Armed Forces so that they are fit for the 21st century and the demands which living in this century will place on our Servicemen and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no denying that there are serious issues to address, and the context in which we will operate will be tough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has had to make some difficult, painful, but necessary decisions to get the Defence budget broadly back towards balance, and further tough decisions lie ahead of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have had to prioritise ruthlessly in order to ensure that any extra money we can spend, we do so wisely, and on those things that are most urgent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s at times like these that having some guiding principles stands us in good stead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those serving today, we are clear that our priorities are caring for those who are physically and mentally injured in the course of their service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those who have ever put country before self we are determined that the country as a whole should unite in its determination to provide the very best support possible in return. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we have published the first ever Tri-Service Armed Forces Covenant in which these key principles will be recognised, among others, for the first time, in the law of land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the ‘Today and Tomorrow’ paper, we have set out what we’re doing to give the Covenant practical effect, for example in the areas of Healthcare, Education, and Housing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Government has a major role. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intervention by the charitable and voluntary sector has a long tradition of making an impact - this Foundation alone has been operating since 1917. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But action just from the top, or just from the bottom, is rarely the panacea.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glass will only be half-full unless Government, local authorities, Devolved Administrations, charities, businesses, communities, and individuals come together and maximise the benefit their services can offer the Defence Community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a whole of society approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, with the Army Recovery Capability, we’ve seen the way we support our wounded, injured, and sick personnel taken to a new level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In large part, that’s thanks to the MoD, Help for Heroes, and the Royal British Legion pooling their resources in a common aim. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the MoD has developed a Transition Protocol with the Department of Health, Devolved Administrations, and the Association of Directors of Adult Social Services to ensure a seamless transition for the most seriously ill and injured Service personnel.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the new Big White Wall on-line support network to support the mental health needs of the Armed Forces community is another example excellent example of a whole of society approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is clearly still more to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing the homeless is the subject most dear to your hearts, so let me say a few words about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister has said, “It is an affront to this country that last winter, one of the coldest on record, there were people still sleeping rough on our streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, some of those on the streets in that bitter winter cold were former Service personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some may have been affected by their experiences of active service; others by what happened to them before or since. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While other Departments have the lead role, we in the MoD have an ongoing duty of care to those who serve our nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are leaving no stone unturned to see if there are preventative measures we can take in-Service to minimise the impact on our people when they leave.  I mentioned the Transition Protocol just now, but there are other initiatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we intend to consult on how the Armed Forces are managed on social housing lists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And current and former members of the Armed Forces will be put at the front of the queue for the new FirstBuy scheme, and other Government initiatives to support first time buyers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Service in our Armed Forces is not a pre-requisite for homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at the Ministerial level, we’re taking a broad approach to homelessness through the inter-Ministerial Working Group on homeless issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July, we published a cross-Government report called, ‘Vision To End Rough Sleeping: No Second Night Out Nationwide’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to tackle the complex causes of homelessness - not only housing, but family breakdown and mental health; drug addiction and alcoholism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s about partnership at all levels with the ultimate aim of helping the homeless along the path to full independent living. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Government can only do so much; the whole of society must play its part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s here that the excellent work of the Sir Oswald Stoll Foundation really comes into its own, and you should be proud of the high-regard in which you are held by the ex-Service community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures show a reduction in rough sleeping by ex-Service personnel in London, and your hard work has undoubtedly played a major part. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wish you the best with your Veterans Nomination Scheme which dovetails neatly with the Covenant and the Big Society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also pay tribute to other initiatives such as ‘The Beacon’ near Catterick Garrison which offers 31 flats to homeless veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, these projects would not have been possible without effective partnership at all levels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So despite the tough times we are going through, there are reasons to be cheerful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Brigadier Ricketts of Veterans Aid said recently, “I’m still firmly of the opinion that if you are in crisis in Britain today, you are lucky if you are a veteran. There is a huge military family that will reach out to you in your hour of need.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s more than that: there is a grateful society at large to turn to as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the forefront of that effort - as it has been for almost a century - is the Sir Oswald Stoll Foundation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are further proof that compassion for those who serve on our behalf remains at the heart of who we are as a nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
