<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/andrew-mitchell</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/andrew-mitchell.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon  Andrew Mitchell MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-07-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27794</id>
    <published>2012-07-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-celebrates-ramadan-with-british-muslims-and-islamic-relief"/>
    <title>Minister celebrates Ramadan with British Muslims and Islamic Relief</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the event, the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to celebrate Ramadan by sharing this Iftar with so many members of the Muslim community from across Britain and Islamic Relief who have done so much to support people in need across the world. At this time of reflection and solidarity, we should remember those less fortunate that us who today are face an uncertain and difficult future. Nowhere it this more poignant than in Syria where people continue to seek greater freedom in the face of brutal repression. I hope that the UK’s development assistance will stand as a sign of our commitment to charity and compassion at a time when Muslim families and friends celebrate these values. Ramadan Mubarak”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Development Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted that the Government will be matching pound for pound public donations to the Islamic Relief Ramadan appeal, up to a total of £5 million. We share with them their spirit of compassion and giving during Ramadan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will help hundreds of thousands of the world’s poorest, most vulnerable people - parents in the Sahel struggling to feed their children, and farmers in areas of Bangladesh and Pakistan whose crops are threatened by flooding or drought caused by climate change. It will help both to meet people’s immediate needs and to give them the resources they need to lift themselves out of poverty.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27606</id>
    <published>2012-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/britain-allies-with-africa-for-greater-food-security"/>
    <title>Britain allies with Africa for greater food security</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK joined G8 nations, African countries, aid agencies and 45 leading multinational and African companies in a new alliance to help millions of African farmers boost their productivity and help poor farmers produce more reliable crops and healthier livestock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is shameful that one in three people in Africa go to bed desperately hungry every night,” said Mr. Mitchell. “Hunger is directly linked to poverty, so farmers need investment and support if they are to grow more nutritious food and escape the threat of harvest failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Governments cannot tackle this challenge alone. The skills, resources and financial expertise of leading private businesses will help transform African agriculture, giving poor farmers the chance to pull themselves out of poverty, hunger and malnutrition.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s first contribution to the New Alliance for Food and Nutrition Security will include its first ever support to the World Bank’s Global Agriculture and Food Security Programme (GAFSP) fund, helping it to expand agricultural investment in low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is already instrumental in tackling global hunger. By 2015, the UK’s African Free Trade Initiative will cut border crossing times in Eastern and Southern Africa by a third. This will increase cross-border food trade in staples such as maize by 15 per cent, making food more readily available and helping farmers increase their profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alliance, announced by President Barack Obama ahead of the G8 leaders’ meeting, is expected to increase average agriculture sector growth rates by 1.5 per cent per year over 10 years across sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Food security is a moral imperative, but it’s also an economic imperative,” President Obama said, addressing an audience at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thechicagocouncil.org/globalagdevelopment/gad/Events/Symposium_2012.aspx"&gt;3rd Annual Symposium on Global Agriculture and Food Security&lt;/a&gt; in Washington, DC. “History teaches us that one of the most effective ways to pull people and entire nations out of poverty is to invest in their agriculture.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Alliance for Food and Nutrition Security builds on the previous international agreement made at L’Aquila in 2009 by stimulating growth in African agriculture by providing technical and financial support to help develop farming and agriculture. This will drive private investment and make it easier to invest responsibly in the food and agriculture sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventy per cent of African people are engaged in agriculture, yet across Sub-Saharan Africa farmers are struggling to meet local and regional demands for food and only four per cent of arable land is irrigated. Improving farming methods, increasing irrigation and boosting trade links could have an immediate effect on food shortages, levels of chronic hunger and the incomes of farming families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African leaders from Ghana, Ethiopia, Tanzania and Benin were invited to the food security conference, where they discussed ways to boost agricultural production across the continent. Other speakers included U.S. Secretary of State Hilary Clinton and musician and development advocate Bono.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/46969</id>
    <published>2011-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-secretary-of-state-for-international-development-visits-kabul"/>
    <title>UK Secretary of State for International Development visits Kabul</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a busy programme, Mr Mitchell met President Karzai and visited British development projects in Kabul and Herat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the International Committee of the Red Cross’ orthopaedic centre in downtown Kabul Mr Mitchell met children, like Qabila (aged 10), whose right leg was blown off after she stood on a mine, and accompanied her on her walking practice. He also met adults who had been fitted with prosthetic limbs and who are working their way back to full mobility. He announced that the UK is to help provide 3,800 new artificial limbs and 10,000 crutches for Afghan children and adults disabled during 30 years of conflict and extreme poverty. UK aid will also support the International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) to run a network of seven orthopaedic centres across Afghanistan to assist those affected by the resulting mobility disabilities, including hundreds of mine victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effort is part of a 40% increase in the UK’s aid programme in Afghanistan, which includes extra help for children and families who have been blighted by decades of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Mr Mitchell also launched a new fund that will help ordinary Afghans to challenge abuse of powers and expose corruption. The new ‘Tawanmandi’ fund - which means ‘strengthening’ in Dari - will help Afghan civil society to hold their government to account, promote transparency and human rights and challenge abuses of power. The new scheme will provide grants to Afghan civil society organisations to work throughout the country, focussing on more vulnerable groups, such as women, youth, disabled and regional organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also announced extra funding for a scheme to employ people in traditional Afghan trades. The innovative Turquoise Mountain Institute in Kabul provides job opportunities for local people through revitalising traditional Afghan design and craftsmanship. The Institute - backed by HRH Prince Charles and President Karzai - has won widespread praise for rediscovering and preserving ancient Afghan heritage and jobs. The new UK funding will enable 180 Afghans to learn vital skills which will equip them with a livelihood for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Development Secretary emphasised that the new measures were part of the UK’s long-term development commitment to the country, which was focussed on improving the lives of people affected by poverty and war. Mr Mitchell emphasised that British aid support would continue long after transition.&lt;br&gt;
Andrew Mitchell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is heartbreaking to meet young children who have lost arms and legs as a result of landmines and explosions. The UK is providing practical help that will improve their day to day life immeasurably, while our wider aid efforts mean they can hope for a brighter future too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“British aid is making a difference on the ground but we must never forget the scale of the challenges Afghanistan faces. We need a sustained push to ensure we continue to make progress, which is why we have increased our aid programme by 40% and why we will continue to support the country through transition and beyond.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26115</id>
    <published>2011-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/development-secretary-visits-libyan-tunisian-border"/>
    <title>Development Secretary visits Libyan Tunisian border</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spending time in the transit camp just beyond the border area near Ras Ajdir, the Development Secretary met some of the 179,925 displaced migrant workers who have been leaving Libya since 20 February.?&lt;br&gt;
?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from the Libyan Tunisian border, Andrew Mitchell announced that the UK will send two air logistics officers to support the increasingly pressurised Djerba airport, now the hub for incoming humanitarian supplies and outgoing repatriation flights as individuals are evacuated from the border.&lt;br&gt;
?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air logistics experts will work directly for the UNHCR and the Tunisian authorities to ensure the smooth running of the airlift operation.?&lt;br&gt;
?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, a second UK flight carrying tents and blankets will leave Dubai today for the camps. They will deliver 2,000 blankets and 1,100 tents to provide shelter for 5,500 people. This follows the first contingent of 36,000 blankets and tents to shelter 1,500 people on Tuesday. ?&lt;br&gt;
??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three UK charter planes continue to work on rotation to fly people away from the camps and back to Cairo, relieving the pressure on the border and the transit camp.?&lt;br&gt;
?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, 12 flights have left Djerba carrying 3,135 people to Cairo where they are being met by the Egyptian authorities.?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
