<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/andrew-stunell</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/andrew-stunell.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Andrew Stunell OBE MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14683</id>
    <published>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/race-equalities-minister-andrew-stunell-commemorates-the-international-day-for-the-remembrance-of-the-slave-trade"/>
    <title>Race Equalities Minister Andrew Stunell commemorates the International Day for the Remembrance of the Slave Trade</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Equalities Minister Andrew Stunell attended the National Maritime Museum in Greenwich on 23 August, for a day of song and historical talks, to commemorate the International Day for the Remembrance of the Slave Trade and its Abolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2206183.jpg" alt="Gospel singers"&gt;Gospel singers Ethnovox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a tour of The Atlantic Worlds Gallery that recounts the personal histories of Toussaint l’Ouverture, Olaudah Equiano, Samuel Sharp and other leaders of resistance and rebellion, he joined in on a performance from Gospel singers Ethnovox, which explored the significance of song in the history of resistance against slavery. The Minister then joined a lecture given by historian Dr Hakim Adi on the transatlantic slave trade and African Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Race Equalities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The human suffering, caused by slavery and the slave trade are amongst the most dishonourable and abhorrent chapters in human history and it remains vital that we recognise the achievements of the abolition movement and ensure that the impact of the slave trade is not forgotten.
&amp;gt; “It is a sad fact that, although slavery is outlawed internationally, millions of people are still living in conditions of slavery worldwide. Wherever, whenever and in whatever form slavery occurs, the Government unreservedly condemns it and is committed to eliminating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO’s General Conference in 1997 decided that 23 August should be designated “International Day for the Remembrance of the Slave Trade and its Abolition”. The night of 22 to 23 August 1791, in Santo Domingo (now Haiti and the Dominican Republic) saw the beginning of the uprising that would play a crucial role in the abolition of the transatlantic slave trade. UNESCO chose this date as a reminder that enslaved Africans were the main agents of their own liberation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1618431.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1618431.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14676</id>
    <published>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/paralympic-flag-flies-at-eland-house"/>
    <title>Paralympic flag flies at Eland House</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Agitos - the flag of the Paralympics - was proudly raised today by Communities Minister Andrew Stunell and two members of the disAbility staff network, to mark the final week in the run-up to the Paralympic Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2202664.jpg" alt="Paralympic flag"&gt;The Paralympic flag flying outside Eland House&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flag, also flying at 10 Downing Street and other government departments, will fly outside Eland House - alongside the Union Flag - until the end of the Games on the 9 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flag bears the symbol of the Paralympics which is composed of three separate agitos coloured red, blue, and green, encircling a single point, on a white field. The agito, translated as “I move” in Latin, is a symbol of movement in the shape of an asymmetrical crescent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2012 Paralympics marks the return of the event to its ancestral home with the 1948 Stoke-Mandeville Games being the first organised sporting event for disabled athletes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a great honour for me to raise the Paralympic flag outside Eland House, and to use this opportunity to highlight the work of DCLG’s disAbility Network in supporting staff with disabilities.
&amp;gt; “I look forward to seeing a repeat of the medal success enjoyed by Team GB earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turnball and John Dawson were the lucky winners of a disAbility network staff ballot and had the opportunity to raise the flag alongside the minister. They were joined by Barbara Curley from European Regional Development Fund, who was a London 2012 Ambassador, will also attend the event wearing her London Ambassadors uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turnball said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Paralympics is an excellent opportunity to raise the profile of people with disabilities on an international scale and that was what inspired me to participate in the flag raising ceremony at DCLG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Dawson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I feel privileged in being chosen as a representative of the disAbility Network in the department and helping DCLG mark these Paralympics, which highlight what the disabled can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631160865054/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14675</id>
    <published>2012-08-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/response-to-daily-mail-claims-about-the-green-belt"/>
    <title>Response to Daily Mail claims about the green belt</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Green Belt provides an important protection against urban sprawl, providing a ‘green lung’ around towns and cities. The Coalition Agreement commits the Government to safeguarding Green Belt and other environmental designations, which they have been in the new National Planning Policy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14656</id>
    <published>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/andrew-stunell-urges-councils-to-give-voluntary-sector-a-leading-role"/>
    <title>Andrew Stunell urges councils to give voluntary sector a leading role</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell has told local authorities that there is no excuse for leaving the voluntary and community sector behind when it comes to funding allocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the lead-up to the next spending round, Mr Stunell has written to every local authority Leader in the country, reminding them of the expertise and excellence that the voluntary sector can bring in delivering services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing gratitude for the positive way the majority of councils have worked with the sector over the last year, Mr Stunell urged councils not to let this hard work go to waste and continue to utilise the voluntary and community sector’s abilities to provide high quality, good value services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the best councils can and will continue to support their voluntary and community sector, as we get the country’s economy on the road to recovery.
&amp;gt; “Many local authorities are already setting a good example showing what can be achieved under demanding circumstances, and the government has now published further guidance to help councils working with voluntary groups.
&amp;gt; “Whilst councils have more tough decisions to make in the coming months, that is no excuse for abandoning the voluntary and community sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year the Government published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/bestvaluestatguidance"&gt;Best Value Guidance&lt;/a&gt; which set out the manner in which councils should work with the voluntary sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils have now been freed from excessive and prescriptive guidance and duties in return for a ‘social responsibility’ deal which asks that they continue to give support to local voluntary and community groups and small businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compact Voice and the Department for Communities and Local Government have now also jointly produced a briefing note which provides practical views on how the guidance can be best used to ensure effective partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best examples of local authorities working hand-in-hand with the voluntary sector over the past year include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colchester council increased their budget for the voluntary and community sector by £42,000 in 2011/12 and have protected it for 2012/13;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Merton council has protected voluntary and community sector budgets and grants because they are seen as a good investment; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community Action Derby used the Best Value Guidance as a way to influence proposed funding decisions made by Derby City Council. As a result, sixteen charities had their funding reinstated while further consultation was undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The briefing note produced by the Department for Communities with Compact Voice can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.compactvoice.org.uk/resources/briefings-and-responses/best-value-guidance-and-compact-briefing-note"&gt;www.compactvoice.org.uk/resources/briefings-and-responses/best-value-guidance-and-compact-briefing-note&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14651</id>
    <published>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-calls-on-racist-footballers-to-face-sack"/>
    <title>Minister calls on racist footballers to face sack</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Race Equalities Minister Andrew Stunell has called on football clubs to sack players found guilty of racist behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in Liverpool, Mr Stunell echoed calls from the Professional Footballers Association that clubs should look to tear up the contracts of players who have engaged in racist behaviour on or off the pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also recommended that teams look to invest in diversity training for players, especially those coming to the UK for the first time from overseas, to help educate them on race issues and on the behaviour expected from professional sportsmen in 21st century Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appearing on a panel alongside other MPs from the North West, Mr Stunell answered questions from a live audience on a wide range of race-related issues including a number related to the current spate of controversies surrounding high profile Premier League players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We saw last season that the ugly face of racism reappeared in the beautiful game. I want to see it kicked out once and for all and to show there are severe consequences for those players who continue to behave in such an unacceptable manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our clubs have a clear duty-of-care to their players, particularly when bringing them over to a new and unfamiliar country. They need to produce well-rounded human beings as well as well-rounded footballers.
&amp;gt; &amp;gt; “Whether they like it or not, these global superstars are role models to millions of young people. Teams need to invest in prevention to root out this problem before it takes hold and have tough sanctions in place if it all goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, the Prime Minister hosted a meeting at Number 10 that looked at how the Government could support the football authorities and campaign groups to send a clear message that any form of discrimination will not be tolerated in the national game. £3million of funding was also announced to help coaches from BME backgrounds progress further in the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13381</id>
    <published>2012-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/unpublished-research-reports-building-planning-and-the-environment"/>
    <title>Unpublished research reports: building, planning and the environment</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today the Government is publishing a group of reports presenting the findings from research projects commissioned by the previous administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are publishing these documents in the interests of transparency and as part of our Freedom of Information commitment to publish the results of all commissioned research. For transparency, all completed work is being published regardless of format or robustness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/archived/general-content/corporate/researcharchive/volume12building/"&gt;seven reports&lt;/a&gt; published today represent the findings from seven research projects at a total cost of 190,320. These findings cover the topics of building, planning and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research provides an improved evidence base to understand the costs, benefits and practical implications of applying the Lifetime Home Standard to new build housing development. In particular it develops cost analysis which more accurately reflects the likely contribution of access standards to the cumulative impact of regulation on housing supply, and sets out clearly the likely impact on different housing typologies, and on site density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these reports are from the last Administration, they do touch upon current government policy. The Coalition Government has set out in the National Planning Policy Framework that Local Plans must take into account the housing needs of a range of users including older and disabled people. In November’s Housing Strategy, this Government also set out its expectation that new development should have a diverse mix of property types, including more accessible designs such as the Lifetime Home Standard. However, we do not intend to introduce national regulation. We believe that decisions should be made at a local level, in proportion to local need and aligned with other local housing support and information services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lifetime-homes-standards"&gt;Lifetime Homes Standards&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(i) ** &lt;em&gt;Modelling the current and potential accessibility of the housing stock&lt;/em&gt; ** - This report by Building Research Establishment considers the accessibility of the existing housing stock in England with particular reference to its utility for older and disabled people. The report uses data from the English Home Condition Survey to identify the frequency and suitability of a range of built features within homes to arrive at an overall assessment of their accessibility and future adaptability. The report was commissioned in 2006 at a cost of 56,305.
&amp;gt; (ii) _ &lt;strong&gt;Assessing the cost of Lifetime Homes Standards&lt;/strong&gt; _ - This report by the Building Cost Information Service (BCIS) looks at establishing the cost impact of introducing the Lifetime Homes Standards in private sector housing, identifying best practice and the potential cost savings that can be delivered through efficiency of design. The report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 34,818.
&amp;gt; (iii) ** &lt;em&gt;Health benefits of Lifetime Home Standards&lt;/em&gt; ** - This report by the Building Research Establishment sets out findings from work to determine the relative benefits of building to the Lifetime Home Standard. Utilising existing data from the Housing Health and Safety Rating System, the research evaluated the health costs associated with the different levels of harm relating either to direct NHS costs or to societal costs. The report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 21,302.
&amp;gt; (iv) ** &lt;em&gt;Lifetime Homes: Technical forum&lt;/em&gt; ** - This report by Habinteg Housing Association captures discussions and recommendations which emerged from a Technical Working Group established to test proposals for improving guidance in the Lifetime Home Standard. This report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 17,448.
&amp;gt; (v) ** &lt;em&gt;Analysis of distribution of housing typologies in Public and Private Sector and typical compatibility with the Lifetime Home Standard&lt;/em&gt; ** - This research conducted by Levitt Bernstein considers the impact of and current compliance with the 16 point standard of &lt;em&gt;Lifetime Homes Lifetime Neighbourhoods - a National strategy for Housing in an Ageing Society&lt;/em&gt;. Mindful that the standards were originally developed with very suburban 2, 3 and 4 bed detached housing in mind, there was a need to review the 16 point standard and consider the implications of applying it to current and emerging new build housing typologies in England and Wales. The research develops and agrees a model of the variety and distribution of future housing typologies in England and Wales and analyses what impact the application of Lifetime Homes Standards will have on varying house typologies. The study focussed primarily on private sector housing. This report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 34,360.
&amp;gt; (vi) ** &lt;em&gt;Impact on site density of Lifetime Homes&lt;/em&gt; ** - This research work conducted by Levitt Bernstein is an extension to an earlier piece of work and represents an initial exploration of the impact that the application of Lifetime Homes Standards is likely to have on the site density of private sector housing. It concentrates on low to medium density suburban developments, typically 30-60 dwellings per hectare (dph). The research consisted of a theoretical analysis to calculate the effect on plot size of various increases to plan footprints; an assessment of impact on density on a small sample of typical site layouts in addition to feed back from industry about site density and marketability. This report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 16,087.
&amp;gt; (vii) _ &lt;strong&gt;Design of Lifetime homes&lt;/strong&gt; _ - This research conducted by Hunt Thomson Architects seeks to evaluate the impact on designing private sectors homes to meet the Lifetime Home Standard, and in particular to understand the likely impact of seeking to minimise both increase in cost and any necessary increase in the overall size of properties by adopting the standard. The project utilised analysis of a range of typical speculative housing development plans and compares these designs with entirely new housing layouts which incorporate the 16 elements of the Lifetime Home Standard. This report was commissioned in 2009 at a cost of 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when public budgets must be reduced, the new Government wants to ensure its research delivers best possible value for money for the taxpayer and that sums expended are reasonable in relation to the public policy benefits obtained. My department has put in place new scrutiny and challenge processes for future research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any new projects will be scrutinised to ensure the methodology is sound and that all options for funding are explored at an early stage. This includes using existing work from other organisations, joint funding projects with other departments or organisations and taking work forward in-house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copies of these reports are available on the Department for Communities and Local Government &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/archived/general-content/corporate/researcharchive/volume12building/"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14642</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/love-your-local-market-to-return-next-year"/>
    <title>Love Your Local Market to return next year</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Markets Minister Andrew Stunell confirmed the Government would support another year of the highly successful Love Your Local Market event at a summit of markets representatives today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful of Love Your Local Market has seen markets take centre stage over two weeks with special events including ministerial visits, discount stalls for new traders and celebrity tips for a successful trading day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the highlights of the fortnight have included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;over 400 markets across England;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2158076" alt="Love Your Local Market logo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;over 3,000 bargain pitches offered;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1,400 potential new businesses;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;special events and attractions including celebrity chefs and cookery demonstrations;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;increased footfall in many markets; and&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;extra support for traders including free insurance, a how-to guide and TV’s Adam Corbally’s Top 10 Tips.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending a summit of key markets representatives Mr Stunell was delighted to be able to announce confirmation that the event will run again with the help of the markets industry next year further building on this year’s success where numbers exceeded expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve been extremely pleased to see how well the Love Your Local Market events have gone this year. It has shown that people still want the authentic market experience on their local high street.
&amp;gt; “I’d like to thank all those traders and market operators who helped the event to be such a success and the trade bodies that gave their wholehearted support. I look forward to working with them again next year to give a further boost for local markets and to encourage new traders onto markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Wilson, National Association of British Markets Authorities said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The impact of Love Your Local Market and National Market Day exceeded all expectations. Market operators all over the country made special efforts to promote the value of their local markets and it is important that we build on the success of the event and nurture the new traders who have come to markets over the last fortnight in large numbers. We are already planning to make 2013 even bigger and more successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Harrison, National Markets Traders’ Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The NMTF are extremely pleased that as many markets took part as they did encouraging new start ups in the industry. We are happy to support and partner NABMA in the pursuit of running the event again next year. We believe that the experience we gained this year will lead to us developing a bigger and better event next time around with an improved focus on taking the would-be traders and moving them onto sustainable businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/"&gt;Love Your Local Market&lt;/a&gt; (external link) was an exciting new campaign to showcase markets of all types from around the UK. Many markets featured special activities between 23 June and 08 July 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Campaign was co-ordinated by the National Market Trader Federation and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marketsalliance.org.uk/"&gt;Markets Alliance&lt;/a&gt; (external link) which comprises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/"&gt;National Association of British Market Authorities&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.atcm.org/"&gt;Association of Town Centre Management&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.aolm.co.uk/"&gt;Association of London Markets&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.country-markets.co.uk/"&gt;Country Markets&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.farma.org.uk/"&gt;National Farmers’ Retail and Markets Association&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmtf.co.uk/"&gt;National Market Traders Federation&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More details of the Love Your Local Market campaign including a list of markets that participated can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/"&gt;www.nabma.com/your-local-market&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14638</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-groups-to-bring-2-000-empty-homes-back-to-life-with-government-help"/>
    <title>Community groups to bring 2,000 empty homes back to life with government help</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community groups across the UK will be supported by government cash to bring almost 2,000 empty homes back into use, Communities Minister Andrew Stunell announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Stunell announced the winners sharing £25.1million of government funding on a visit to one of the successful projects in Newark, Nottinghamshire alongside Independent Empty Homes Adviser and TV presenter George Clarke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newark and Sherwood Homes Ltd successfully applied for a £50,000 grant to purchase and bring four empty properties back into use from the Empty Homes Community Fund. These will be a mix of 2-3 bedroom houses and bungalows that will provide affordable housing for 20 people. Mr Stunell also visited Newark and Sherwood Federation of Tenants and Residents Associations to find out first hand how they have been involved in these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the scheme in Newark, other successful projects include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A homesteading scheme in Stoke to refurbish terraced housing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A scheme in Leeds to work with homeless people and volunteers to bring homes back into use;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A scheme led by Southwark Habitat for Humanity to bring homes back into use across London;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seven schemes from YMCAs to return properties to use; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renovated properties to provide accommodation for women at risk of domestic violence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In many areas the expertise for returning empty homes to use lies with community groups or voluntary organisations, and that is why the Government is supporting innovative schemes around the country that will allow groups to make a real difference where in the past they have often struggled to be involved or raise finance. £25.1million has been allocated so far out of a total of £30million, with a further 20 organisations bidding for the remainder of the cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s great to see for myself the work being carried out to transform empty properties into safe family homes.
&amp;gt; “Empty properties are a national disgrace - they attract crime and are a shocking waste of housing when millions of families need a home.
&amp;gt; “I’m determined to tackle this problem, and that’s why the Coalition is helping local groups breathe new life into their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent Empty Homes Advisor George Clarke said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is so refreshing to meet people like those in Newark who are dedicated to bringing empty homes back into use. We need to find more creative and innovative ways to refurbish and remodel the many thousands of perfectly sound properties currently standing empty all over the UK. Newark is making positive strides in the right direction. However, the problem of empty homes and the demolition of perfectly good homes is a national problem and it is my job to ensure that more and more people recognise the value of refurbishment and that money is spent in the right way to stop these homes going to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A table of the initial successful schemes can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/21768569.xls"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2176856.xls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A full list will be published on the Tribal website once all due diligence checks are completed. See &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tribalgroup.com/Pages/default.aspx"&gt;www.tribalgroup.com&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;George Clarke was appointed in April 2012 to advise the Government on how to bring empty homes back into use and to help raise public awareness of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14633</id>
    <published>2012-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/more-than-30-million-for-communities-taking-over-valued-services-and-assets"/>
    <title>More than £30 million for communities taking over valued services and assets</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community groups wanting to bid to run local services or buy their local shop, library or pub will benefit from more than £30 million of new specialist support, Communities Minister Andrew Stunell announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the £19 million Community Ownership of Assets programme communities wanting to take control of a much loved local asset will have access to support they need through each stage of the process from forming a group through to preparing and submitting a bid. The programme will also help communities use the Right to Bid when it comes into force this Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the £11.5 million Community Right to Challenge programme - which became law last week - communities with good ideas for how they can run local public services and want to use the Community Right to Challenge, can access advice and support to develop their skills to be able to bid for and run excellent local services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 90 per cent of the funding will go directly to communities in the form of grants allowing them to buy the support they need. In addition to this, funding will support a website and advice service &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link) and telephone helpline run by Locality, with the grants programme provided by the Social Investment Business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Stunell was speaking at Hebden Bridge Town Hall, which has been brought back to the centre of community life following its transfer into community ownership from Calderdale Council. A major new extension to the building - hosting brand new community and enterprise facilities - has just opened through the fundraising efforts of the Hebden Bridge Community Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have all heard about much-loved community assets being sold off with out anyone locally having a say, let alone given the time to get a decent plan together. And many groups who felt they could run council services better, by doing things differently, have simply been overlooked.
&amp;gt; “Taking over assets and running services isn’t easy. As well as dedication, groups need skills, support and funding to get projects off the ground. But with the right backing, it’s not as daunting as it first seems and communities up and down the country are showing that taking ownership of assets and services can work for the benefit of everyone.
&amp;gt; “Hebden Bridge Town Hall is testament to that and we want more communities to get a fair hearing and the chance to bid to take control of the buildings or run services that are important to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralisation Minister Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Local people often have great ideas about how to run their communities, but can struggle to have their voices heard.
&amp;gt; “These powerful new rights will give communities the ability to challenge the status quo, and do things differently to improve the places where they live.
&amp;gt; “This support will help people to take advantage of the rights available and use them to shape a vision for their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wyler, Locality Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Locality has believed in and pushed for the new Rights in the Localism Act for many years and is very proud to be running the Community Rights support service. These Rights give greater powers to communities to influence what happens in their local area, avoiding complicated legislation and lengthy negotiations.
&amp;gt; “These Rights are for everyone who cares about their community, who value their local community centre, shop or pub; want to build new housing or facilities, and run a local service differently and better. Locality is here to give people information, inspiration, ideas and advice from our team of Community Rights experts and to see communities across the UK transformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Jenkins, Chief Executive of the Social Investment Business said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Community Rights grants programme presents a fantastic new opportunity for social ventures to grow through increased revenue, and therefore build their capacity to secure further investment - all with the goal of being able to reach more beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new Community Rights give communities opportunities to take ownership and management of important local assets and to shape and run local public services. The Community Right to Challenge - which became law last week - gives communities the right to bid to run local council services where they think they can do it differently and better. The Community Right to Bid - which will become law in the autumn and complements existing asset transfer activity - will give communities the right to bid to buy and take over the running of local assets that are important to them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These two 3 year funding programmes will run until March 2015. Groups will also be able to apply for grants under the Right to Challenge from 16 July. More details on the grants programme to support community ownership of assets will be available soon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Community Rights website has been launched to give groups more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The telephone advice support can be contacted on: 0845 345 4564.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some other examples of community groups who have already taken ownership include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Old Norden Library building, Rochdale&lt;/strong&gt; - The Norden Community Trust was founded in 2007 by local people determined to preserve the old library building and develop it as a community facility. The Trust has renovated the lower floor as a modern building to be used by the whole community, while a new doctors surgery occupies the refurbished upper floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diss Corn Hall Trust, Diss Norfolk&lt;/strong&gt; - A group of volunteers set up a charity, the Diss Corn Hall Trust, Diss Norfolk and took over management of the Corn Hall from the Town Council, turning it into a vibrant centre for arts, culture, music and drama in the South Norfolk/North Suffolk area and increasing attendance from 3,500 to 15,000 in just two years. The Diss Corn Hall Trust is bidding for Heritage Lottery funding to regenerate the whole area in which the Corn Hall is located and promote the heritage of the town.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14634</id>
    <published>2012-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/andrew-stunell-sets-out-the-stall-for-new-sheffield-market"/>
    <title>Andrew Stunell sets out the stall for new Sheffield market</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister closes Love Your Local Market Fortnight with visit to site of new indoor market&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets Minister Andrew Stunell saw the exciting developments for market traders and buyers when he attended the turf-cutting ceremony for the new Moor Market in Sheffield today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2175287.jpg" alt="Andrew Stunell speaking at Moor Market in Sheffield"&gt;Andrew Stunell speaking at the turf-cutting ceremony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a celebratory, closing event for the Love Your Local Markets fortnight, Mr Stunell saw work getting under way on the city’s new multi-million pound market that is the only purpose-built market under construction in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new £18 million market is due to open next year and will house over 200 stalls and eight permanent shopping units. Alongside the market, investment in the surrounding area will also see improved paving, seating and a green face-lift with new plants and flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This new development shows there is a real appetite amongst consumers for the authentic market experience - seeing the produce, bartering for a good price and chatting to your friendly stall owner.
&amp;gt; “Love Your Local Market fortnight has been a great success in highlighting how markets can breathe life back into town and city centres and visiting this new grand development is the perfect way to finish. It will be a credit to the city of Sheffield for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leader of Sheffield Council, Councillor Julie Dore said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This marks a very exciting new chapter in the 800 year history of markets in Sheffield. Our market has one of the highest concentrations of small businesses in the city and the new hall underlines our commitment to helping them succeed.
&amp;gt; “The new development will reinforce The Moor’s position as one of Sheffield’s main shopping areas. While work is going on it’s business as usual for The Moor and we will try to keep disruption to a minimum. The second phase of The Moor’s transformation has begun and we trust shoppers will bear with us during this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love Your Local Market has been a two-week campaign that has seen over 400 local markets will involved in celebrations all over the country, attracting visitors into towns, helping new start-ups and boosting enterprise. Star of TV’s Apprentice, Adam Corbally, has given traders his &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2146931"&gt;Top 10 tips&lt;/a&gt; for success and Government ministers have been visiting their local markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two weeks of trading have also seen thousands of budding entrepreneurs and shopkeepers try their hand at operating a low-cost retail business at markets as thousands of extra low-cost pitches were made available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="video"&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/v/w5MWFuTtmAQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_GB&amp;amp;rel=0" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/word/2166522.doc"&gt;Love Your Local Market - Transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;MS Word, 25 kb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="photos"&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love Your Local Market is an exciting new campaign to showcase markets of all types from around the UK. Many markets will feature special activities between 23 June and 8 July 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign is co-ordinated by the National Market Trader Federation and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.marketsalliance.org.uk/"&gt;Markets Alliance&lt;/a&gt; (external link) which comprises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/"&gt;National Association of British Market Authorities&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.atcm.org/"&gt;Association of Town Centre Management&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.aolm.co.uk/"&gt;Association of London Markets&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.country-markets.co.uk/"&gt;Country Markets&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.farma.org.uk/"&gt;National Farmers’ Retail and Markets Association&lt;/a&gt; (external link)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;More details of the Love Your Local Market campaign including a list of participating markets can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/"&gt;www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2158071?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2158071?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
