<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/baroness-hanham</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/baroness-hanham.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Baroness Hanham CBE</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-29T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60888</id>
    <published>2012-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-years-honours-2013"/>
    <title>New Year's Honours 2013</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham congratulates all those recognised in the New Year Honours.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to all those working in the local government, housing, fire and voluntary and community sector who have been recognised in the New Year Honours list which acknowledges their extraordinary contribution to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to see colleagues in local government being honoured. It’s testament to their services to the local community that their hard work, dedication and achievements have been recognised in this way. Many congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-government"&gt;Local government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the local government sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Jones, Leader of East Sussex County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in the South East&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Tapster, lately Chief Executive of Hertfordshire County Council receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ian Greenwood, lately Leader of Bradford City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Kelly, lately Chief Executive of Gateshead Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government and the community in Gateshead and the North East &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharon Taylor, Leader of Stevenage Borough Council and Deputy Chair of the Local Government Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jane Todd, Chief Executive of Nottingham City Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Nottingham &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clare Whelan, Member, London Borough of Lambeth receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brian Beale, Councillor in Southminster receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to local government in Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linda Green, Member, Gateshead Metropolitan Borough Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tyne &amp;amp; Wear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raymond Puddifoot, Leader of Hillingdon Council receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Hillingdon, Middlesex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katherine Gilcreest, Anti-Social Behaviour Manager, Brentwood Borough Council receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Brentwood, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="housing"&gt;Housing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the housing sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthony Pidgeley, Chairman of the Berkeley Group receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the housing sector and the community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Ruback, Deputy Director, Housing Revenue Account and Decent Homes Programe, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Commander of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;CBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sue Chalkley, Chief Executive of the Hastoe Housing Association receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to housing and tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Downie, Deputy Director, Affordable Housing Management and Standards, Department for Communities and Local Government receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="fire-and-rescue"&gt;Fire and rescue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the fire and rescue sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Beardsall, Retained Watch Manager in Charge, Nottinghamshire and City of Nottingham Fire and Rescue Authority receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Mottram, Equipment Officer, South Yorkshire Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Richard Stanton, firefighter in West Midlands Fire and Rescue Service receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Cole, Retained Firefighter, Isle of Wight receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the communities of Shanklin and the Isle of Wight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Boulton, Senior Adviser to the Chief Fire and Rescue Adviser, Department for Communities and Local Government receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glynis Lomax, Head of the Operational Intelligence Unit receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gary Reason, Director of Operational Resilience and Training for services to the Olympics receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colin Rockey, Group Manager, Devon and Somerset Fire and Rescue Service receives a &lt;abbr title="Queen's Fire Service Medal"&gt;QFSM&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="voluntary-and-community-sector"&gt;Voluntary and community sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have received honours for services to the voluntary and community sector:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herschel Gluck, founder of the Muslim Jewish Forum receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to interfaith understanding &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Denys Shortt, founder of DCS Europe PLC and Chair, Coventry and Warwickshire Local Enterprise Partnership receives an &lt;abbr title="Officer of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;OBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the economy in the West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruth Abrahams receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the voluntary and community sector in Newcastle upon Tyne&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margaret Barker, founder of the Dorset Poverty Action Group receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to homeless and underprivileged people in Dorchester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Barker receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community of the Mixenden Social Housing Estate, Halifax &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Blower receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement in Fleetwood &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anita Halliday, Chief Executive of St Pauls Community Development Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Balsall Heath, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caroline Highton, founder of the Brian Shields Trust receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to personal finance and community support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mary Jones receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenants and the community in Saffron and Neston, Leicester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter McNestry, Chair of the Coalfields Regeneration Trust, Waith upon Dearne, Rotherham, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to coalfield communities &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggarwal-Singh Neelam receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to community cohesion, health and welfare through the Indian Hindu Welfare Organisation &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gerry Proctor receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Liverpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emdadur Rahman, journalist and community volunteer, receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Tower Hamlets and to the Bangladeshi Media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Sheehy receives an &lt;abbr title="Member of the Order of the British Empire"&gt;MBE&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valerie Ahern, Chair of the Templar’s Estate Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment in Witham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eileen Alldritt receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant empowerment and the community in Liverpool &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christine Allen, Chief Executive of the Forum Housing Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Merseyside &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rose Cooke-Coton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Masefield, Birmingham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heather Didwell, volunteer at Catton Grove Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Norwich &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John Filby receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Abridge, Essex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Muriel Healey, board member, Havebury Housing Partnership receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to Tenants in Suffolk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Highton receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in West Ealing, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asim Iftikhar receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Poplar &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Betty Koppa receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community and residents of North Curry, Taunton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shaun Lansfield receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to tenant engagement and to the community in Edmonton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jacqueline McGrew, Chair of the Whitebirk Tenants and Residents Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Blackburn, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew Milnes, founder of the Scholemoor Community Association receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Bradford&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Riaz Ravat, Development Manager, St Philip’s Centre, Leicester receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to inter-faith understanding in Leicester &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freda Smith receives a &lt;abbr title="British Empire Medal"&gt;BEM&lt;/abbr&gt; for services to the community in Leyland, Lancashire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/33686</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-07T15:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-local-government-efforts-to-tackle-fraud"/>
    <title>Minister praises local government efforts to tackle fraud </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham welcomes the ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ end of year review.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential for local government to take action to tackle fraud in every possible way and therefore help prevent the current loss of £2 billion of taxpayers’ money, Baroness Hanham said in a keynote address on 6 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarks came as the review on the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud locally’ report was launched at the annual Fighting Fraud Locally conference, which highlighted the progress made by councils in 2012 in reducing the risks they face. Fraud costs every adult in the country about £1,140 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the event, attended by over 200 local authority members, the minister said councils needed to assess whether they had sufficient controls in place to prevent fraud happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister praised the action already taken by most councils to tackle fraud and encouraged them all to follow the lead set by the &lt;abbr title="Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea, and Hammersmith and Fulham"&gt;west London tri-borough authorities&lt;/abbr&gt;, in particular in the investigation of tenancy fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fraud costs this country more than £73 billion a year, over £2 billion of which is lost to local government. This is a complete waste of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is essential councils do everything they can to not only prevent fraud, but recover lost money and pursue fraudsters in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The approaches recommended in the local government’s ‘Fighting Fraud Locally’ report sets out how to tackle local fraud through better detection and fraud recovery. Councils cannot afford to have resources meant for vulnerable people and front line services being stolen by fraudsters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is helping create an environment where councils can tackle tenancy fraud, in particular through a series of measures including: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;through the provisions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/preventionofsocialhousingfraud.html"&gt;Prevention of Social Housing Fraud Bill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leading on the request in &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/agencies-public-bodies/nfa/fighting-fraud-locally-strategy/"&gt;Fighting Fraud Locally&lt;/a&gt; for central government to enable there to be greater information sharing to identify fraud and fraudsters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-local-authorities-more-control-over-how-they-spend-public-money-in-their-area--2/supporting-pages/localising-council-tax-support"&gt;localising council tax support&lt;/a&gt;, which will give councils a strong incentive to reduce fraud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest survey of fraud against local bodies can be found in the Audit Commission’s report, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/fraud/protecting-the-public-purse/Pages/protecting-the-public-purse-2012.aspx"&gt;Protecting the Public Purse 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14748</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/successful-graduate-support-scheme-secures-future-with-additional-4-million-funding"/>
    <title>Successful graduate support scheme secures future with additional £4 million funding</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business entrepreneurs emerging from West Midlands universities will continue to be able to access vital support to get a new business venture off the ground, with the announcement of an additional £4million investment to support the programme over the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following on from the success of the SPEED WM programme, phase 2 called SPEED Plus will provide 600 graduates and students with the opportunity to access tailored advice and support focussed on how to get a business idea off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is supported by just over £2million from the European Regional Development Fund, which is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and matched by five West Midlands universities - the University of Wolverhampton, Birmingham City University, Coventry University, Keele University and Staffordshire University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Baroness Hanham CBE said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Retaining graduates and the valuable skills they hold, by helping them to take forward creative entrepreneurial business ideas is really important for the future of the local economy. It is vital that we are able to recognise the success of support programmes such as this and offer additional funding to ensure they continue for the benefit of future graduates and students.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We are looking for future entrepreneurs with great business ideas to come forward and size the opportunities that this project provides, helping to bring their ideas to life and turn them into profitable new businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that we have been able to play our part in securing the future for this important programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Moore, Deputy Director Graduate Enterprise from The University of Wolverhampton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that we will be able to support more and more young people from our partner universities in launching their future business careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPEED WM which was originally launched in 2009, has proved to be a valuable support service, helping 562 graduates and students explore and take forward enterprise ideas over the last 3 years. Mike Chinn and Matt Weston set up Stone’s Throw Media with the assistance of the programme. The video production company based in Wolverhampton, believe that;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without the assistance of SPEED WM we would never have started up this business or have progressed as quickly as we have with all of the support that we have received. SPEED WM is a really important asset to students and graduates who want to start up a business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about phase 2 of the programme, contact Sarah Taylor at the University of Wolverhampton on &lt;a href="mailto:speed@wlv.ac.uk"&gt;speed@wlv.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt; or visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.speed-plus.org"&gt;www.speed-plus.org&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2250067.pdf"&gt;News Release - Successful graduate support scheme secures future with additional £4million funding
&lt;/a&gt;(PDF, 40 kb, 2 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is the managing authority for the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Programme which runs from 2007 to 2013. This is one of the funds established by the European Commission to help local areas stimulate their economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme has been allocated 400million euros to invest in projects which will support local businesses and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West Midlands the priority areas and themes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Innovation and Research and Development
**Increasing investment in research and development through helping businesses take forward new innovation, sharing of knowledge and developing and demonstrating new technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Enterprise Development
**Increasing business performance through supporting high growth businesses, improving resource efficiency, providing access to finance and developing a strong entrepreneurial culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Sustainable Urban Development
**Improving the performance of key urban areas through regenerating local areas, encouraging investment and new businesses, creating job opportunities and helping communities most in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Inter-Regional Activity
**Working with European partners to learn and improve, share and apply best practice and solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow us on Twitter at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/erdfwmnews"&gt;www.twitter.com/erdfwmnews&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Lynsey Cooke, Communications Manager on 0303 444 6587 or email &lt;a href="mailto:lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12144</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:47:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-hanham-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Baroness Hanham praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Baroness Hanham praised the efforts made by Wiltshire Council to manage their assets and save Council Tax payers' money.

</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and the state of the art library, which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medallist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medallists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torchbearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. This will save Wiltshire’s Council Tax payers at least £85 million. As two-thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14747</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-praises-wiltshire-council-for-saving-85-million-on-council-facilities"/>
    <title>Minister praises Wiltshire Council for saving £85 million on council facilities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Baroness Hanham hails council's trailblazing asset management strategies that are protecting frontline services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a visit to Wiltshire Council Baroness Hanham saw first-hand the significant achievements made by the council whose trailblazing assets management strategies are protecting frontline services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The County Hall refurbishment is part of a major transformation programme that will save £85 million over the next 20 years by rationalising the number of buildings used by the council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the official opening, the minister was taken on a tour of the new office building redesigned to make the best use of office space and state of the art library which has already seen over 1,000 visitors in 7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also at the opening ceremony were Olympic kayak gold medalist, Ed McKeever and Paralympic swimming silver medalists Aaron Morres and Stephanie Milward. Local torch bearers and games makers also attended the community event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the past 2 years I have worked closely with local authorities to encourage them, together with other local public bodies, to have a programme of asset management. Wiltshire Council has made significant progress with this and I am delighted to be able to see their innovative approach today at first hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will save Wilstshire’s council tax payers at least £85 million. As two thirds of all public sector assets are owned by councils, if they all followed this example it could potentially save billions of pounds, as well as making better use of public assets and improving services for local residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images from Baroness Hanham’s visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631902676938/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14729</id>
    <published>2012-10-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-midlands-businesses-boost-profits-with-a-little-help-from-the-virtual-world"/>
    <title>West Midlands businesses boost profits with a little help from the virtual world</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing businesses in the West Midlands now have the chance to try out and test new product prototypes and ideas through virtual simulation technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of the innovative technology on offer at the University of Birmingham and the Manufacturing Technology Centre in Coventry, will help businesses save time and money with costly repeat experiments which normally go hand in hand with testing new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new project called CASiM2 is supported by £2.6million from the European Regional Development Fund, which is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and matched through funding and staff skills by the University of Birmingham, the Manufacturing Technology Centre, Airbus and Rolls-Royce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Baroness Hanham CBE said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In order for businesses to survive and thrive new ways of working that save time and money but still gain the results is key. This project offers businesses an exciting opportunity to try out and explore the innovative technology by putting their new products and ideas to the test in a cost effective, reliable and safe environment. I am pleased that we are able to provide support to a project that will be really beneficial to the future development of businesses in the West Midlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will firstly help to raise awareness of the new technology on offer and the benefits it can bring to a business, followed by a demonstration of its capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Richard Williams, Pro-Vice Chancellor and Head of the College of Engineering and Physical Sciences, from the University of Birmingham, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted to be driving the translation of our fundamental modelling and manufacturing technology developed at the University of Birmingham into industrial practice through this initiative in collaboration with the Manufacturing Technology Centre and partners. The partnership model encourages the application of frontier science in materials and metallurgical engineering and maximises the speed of adoption. It also enables effective feedback to the academic partners for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery of CASiM2 brings together public and private sector organisations providing businesses who participate in the project access not only to the technology, but also valuable credibility from leading companies, Airbus and Rolls-Royce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Burgess, Rolls-Royce Manufacturing Process and Technology Executive said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Advanced computational techniques delivering ‘Virtual Manufacturing’ capabilities continue to be increasingly important to Rolls-Royce as they enable evaluation, optimisation and verification of key manufacturing processes in a fraction of the time and cost of traditional experimental methods. CASIM2 is a collaborative programme that will deliver essential modelling and simulation capability to UK ‘High Value’ manufacturers and their supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Young, technology director at the Manufacturing Technology Centre added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Manufacturing Technology Centre is proud to be working with the University of Birmingham, along with Rolls-Royce and Airbus to deliver the CASiM2 programme which recognises the fundamental role that SMEs will play in reinvigorating the UK manufacturing sector. CASiM2 will accelerate the delivery of high value manufacturing products and processes through the use of advanced simulation methods to underpin this future growth. Through the programme we have a fantastic opportunity to encourage, promote and transfer knowledge on the application of simulation technologies at an industrial level.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We will engage SMEs in the West Midlands through demonstrating the commercial benefits of using innovative technologies to deliver step changes in their business offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about the innovative support on offer, contact Jonathon Shaw, Business Engagement Manager tel: 02476 701649, email: &lt;a href="mailto:jonathon.shaw@the-mtc.org"&gt;jonathon.shaw@the-mtc.org&lt;/a&gt; or John Woodward, Senior Research Facilitator, tel: 0121 414 5158, email: &lt;a href="mailto:j.woodward@bham.ac.uk"&gt;j.woodward@bham.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2238385.pdf"&gt;News Release - West Midlands businesses boost profits with a little help from the virtual world
&lt;/a&gt;(PDF, 52 kb, 2 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is the managing authority for the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Programme which runs from 2007 to 2013. This is one of the funds established by the European Commission to help local areas stimulate their economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme has been allocated 400million euros to invest in projects which will support local businesses and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West Midlands the priority areas and themes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Innovation and Research and Development
**Increasing investment in research and development through helping businesses take forward new innovation, sharing of knowledge and developing and demonstrating new technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Enterprise Development
**Increasing business performance through supporting high growth businesses, improving resource efficiency, providing access to finance and developing a strong entrepreneurial culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Sustainable Urban Development
**Improving the performance of key urban areas through regenerating local areas, encouraging investment and new businesses, creating job opportunities and helping communities most in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Inter-Regional Activity
**Working with European partners to learn and improve, share and apply best practice and solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow us on Twitter at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/erdfwmnews"&gt;www.twitter.com/erdfwmnews&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Lynsey Cooke, Communications Manager on 0303 444 6587 or email &lt;a href="mailto:lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13397</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T16:52:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/localising-council-tax-support"/>
    <title>Localising Council Tax support</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Statement by Barnoness Hanham on localising Council Tax support</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 2010 Spending Review, the Government announced plans to localise council tax benefit and this is being taken forward through the Local Government Finance Bill currently before Parliament. From April 2013, these reforms will localise council tax support and give councils stronger incentives to support local firms, cut fraud, promote local enterprise and get people back into work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms contribute to the Government’s deficit reduction programme, delivering savings of 470million a year of taxpayers’ money in Great Britain from 2013-14. Welfare reform is vital to tackle the budget deficit, as council tax benefit expenditure in England increased from 2.0billion to 4.3billion from 1997-98 by 2010-11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Localisation will give local authorities the flexibility to design council tax support schemes for working age claimants in their area. We have been clear that councils have the scope to help manage the impact of the reduction in council tax support funding through securing sensible savings. To help the transition to these changes, my Department has already provided 30million of funding to help councils draw up local support schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a real incentive for councils to make savings in the new localised system from cutting fraud and error, where an estimated 200 million was paid out unnecessarily in 2011-12. However, we appreciate that these savings may not be delivered immediately in the first year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, to further assist the transition process, my Department is today announcing an additional 100million of funding for councils to help support them in developing well-designed council tax support schemes and maintain positive incentives to work. This is new and additional funding for local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As councils draw up their local schemes, it is clear that many are delivering savings using their local flexibilities and discretion, without unfairly increasing the burden on those who are currently on benefits. Equally, there are some councils which are asking for very large additional contributions from those on benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new 100million transition grant will seek to encourage best practice. The voluntary grant will be available to councils (billing and major precepting authorities) who choose to design their local schemes so that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;those who would be on 100 per cent support under current council tax benefit arrangements pay between zero and no more than 8.5 per cent of their council tax liability;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the taper rate does not increase above 25 per cent;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no sharp reduction in support for those entering work - for claimants currently entitled to less than 100 per cent support, the taper will be applied to an amount at least equal to their maximum eligible award.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In allowing flexibility over aspects of the scheme, we would not expect local authorities to impose large additional increases in non-dependant deductions. Councils will rightly want to avoid collecting small payments, and it may consequently be better value for money for councils to avoid designing schemes which seek to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of funding for which councils will be eligible to apply and the timescales and process for making an application will be published shortly. We anticipate that councils will make applications after 31 January 2013, and that funding will be paid in March 2013. The grant will be a simple one, easy to apply for and swiftly paid out, to help those councils who choose to do the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has a clear goal in tackling the deficit, and reducing spending on benefits. This measured, transitional approach will help deliver an important programme of welfare reform, whilst still protecting taxpayers’ broader interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14724</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/heart-of-stoke-on-trent-set-for-dramatic-transformation"/>
    <title>Heart of Stoke-on-Trent set for dramatic transformation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plans to transform the city of Stoke-on-Trent into a thriving and successful centre are well underway thanks to a fresh injection of funding and an ambitious vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements will help enhance the image and appeal of the city to businesses, attracting fresh inward investment and job opportunities, and also help join up other developments taking place around the city from the Central Business District through to the Mitchell Memorial Theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public realm improvements, supported by £2.1million from the European Regional Development Fund, which is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and matched by Stoke-on-Trent City Council, are part of a package of improvements to develop and upgrade the city centre - creating a legacy for local people and making it more attractive to potential new investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Baroness Hanham CBE said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To improve the overall perception and performance of an area you have to get the foundations right. Stoke-on-Trent city centre is in great need of regeneration to ensure its future is prosperous. This has already started with key developments taking place in city and I am delighted that we are able to offer funding support to activities which complement these developments. From new street furniture to landscaped areas the changes planned will help create an attractive, vibrant and welcoming environment.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As well as creating something special for local people, I also hope this investment will send a clear signal to private sector investors, helping to continue the much needed and on-going regeneration of the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents, workers and visitors alike will be able to enjoy newly landscaped public spaces and street furniture, creating an attractive environment. The improvements will focus on the areas of Tontine Street, Percy Street and Stafford Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Ruth Rosenau, Stoke-on-Trent City Council cabinet member for regeneration, planning and transport, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re delighted to mark the start of these long-awaited works. It’s a very exciting project. It will give the area a contemporary city style and feel, but retain its very special character and heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The area will become much more attractive and provide a more welcoming shopping environment, with natural stone paving and granite benches with ceramic detailing, plus new lighting, signs and trees.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It’s around 25 years since work on this scale and quality was last done in the area so it’s literally getting its biggest makeover in a generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about activities set for Stoke-on-Trent, contact Ciara Hill in Stoke-on-Trent City Council Press Office on 01782 232130 or e-mail &lt;a href="mailto:ciara.hill@stoke.gov.uk"&gt;ciara.hill@stoke.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2236525.pdf"&gt;News Release - Heart of Stoke-on-Trent set for dramatic transformation&lt;/a&gt;
(PDF, 45 kb, 2 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is the managing authority for the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Programme which runs from 2007 to 2013. This is one of the funds established by the European Commission to help local areas stimulate their economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme has been allocated 400million euros to invest in projects which will support local businesses and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West Midlands the priority areas and themes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Innovation and Research and Development
**Increasing investment in research and development through helping businesses take forward new innovation, sharing of knowledge and developing and demonstrating new technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Enterprise Development
**Increasing business performance through supporting high growth businesses, improving resource efficiency, providing access to finance and developing a strong entrepreneurial culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Sustainable Urban Development
**Improving the performance of key urban areas through regenerating local areas, encouraging investment and new businesses, creating job opportunities and helping communities most in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Inter-Regional Activity
**Working with European partners to learn and improve, share and apply best practice and solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow us on Twitter at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/erdfwmnews"&gt;www.twitter.com/erdfwmnews&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Lynsey Cooke, Communications Manager on 0303 444 6587 or email &lt;a href="mailto:lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14722</id>
    <published>2012-10-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/future-of-vital-innovation-scheme-secured-with-new-funding-boost"/>
    <title>Future of vital innovation scheme secured with new funding boost</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful and established scheme helping West Midlands businesses boost their innovation and research and development activities is set to continue for another three years after receiving a huge funding boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation Networks Phase 2 seeks to raise the levels of innovation amongst West Midlands small and medium sized businesses by providing grants to groups of companies that can work together and collaborate on the development of innovative new products, processes or services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second phase of this important project is supported by just under £1.9million from the European Regional Development Fund, which is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and matched by investment from the supported businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Baroness Hanham CBE said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is vital that we continue to help support projects that have shown real benefits to local businesses and with innovation and research and development activities remaining key to future business development, this truly is an important investment. I am delighted that we are able to provide the support needed that will help keep this scheme alive and assist local businesses and local people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success from Phase 1 really demonstrates how successful and effective this type of support is to local businesses. With 90 small and medium sized businesses supported through grants, nearly £1million of new sales has been generated for the participating companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One business to have experienced first hand the benefits is B&amp;amp;G Products Ltd - a company manufacturing handles for reusable cool bags used for protecting chilled and frozen foods. Based in Stafford and with large supermarket chains as their main customers, B&amp;amp;G had to find ways of retaining these customers whilst reducing production costs and battling with continued pressure to reduce prices. After redesigning their handles B&amp;amp;G used their Innovation Networks grant to purchase new tools to start production reducing the cost of raw materials used by 15 per cent and without sacrificing product quality. By cutting costs they were able to agree to new contracts with major supermarket chains and within six months of launching the new handle B&amp;amp;G had £126,000 of new sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Shorthouse, Assistant Director at Coventry University Enterprises Ltd that manages the scheme said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Innovation Networks project has a great track record of providing practical and accessible support to regional businesses that want to innovate. The flexibility of the scheme makes it attractive to a wide range of businesses, whether they are new start ups or medium sized businesses that are experienced in developing new products. The grant can be used towards any type of project related costs such as the purchase of machinery or tooling, bringing in technical consultancy or buying parts and materials. Any small or medium sized business that is currently planning to develop something new should look at applying for a grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about the project, contact Judy Lambourne at Coventry University Enterprises Ltd on 024 7623 6391 or email &lt;a href="mailto:jlambourne@cad.coventry.ac.uk"&gt;jlambourne@cad.coventry.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/regeneration/pdf/2235720.pdf"&gt;News Release - Innovation Networks Phase 2&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 70 kb)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is the managing authority for the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Programme which runs from 2007 to 2013. This is one of the funds established by the European Commission to help local areas stimulate their economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Midlands European Regional Development Fund Programme has been allocated 400million euros to invest in projects which will support local businesses and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West Midlands the priority areas and themes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Innovation and Research and Development
**Increasing investment in research and development through helping businesses take forward new innovation, sharing of knowledge and developing and demonstrating new technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Enterprise Development
**Increasing business performance through supporting high growth businesses, improving resource efficiency, providing access to finance and developing a strong entrepreneurial culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Sustainable Urban Development
**Improving the performance of key urban areas through regenerating local areas, encouraging investment and new businesses, creating job opportunities and helping communities most in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Inter-Regional Activity
**Working with European partners to learn and improve, share and apply best practice and solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="more-information"&gt;More information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information follow us on Twitter at &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/erdfwmnews"&gt;www.twitter.com/erdfwmnews&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Lynsey Cooke, Communications Manager on 0303 444 6587 or email &lt;a href="mailto:lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;lynsey.cooke@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14696</id>
    <published>2012-09-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-welcomes-select-committee-acknowledgement-of-improvements-to-management-of-the-european-regional-development-fund"/>
    <title>Government welcomes Select Committee acknowledgement of improvements to management of the European Regional Development Fund</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government has issued its response to the Communities and Local Government Select Committee’s report into the European Regional Development Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It welcomed the Committee’s acknowledgement that this Government has done a good job of managing the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) in England, including, in particular, the transfer of programme administration from the Regional Development Agencies to the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although welcoming most of the findings in the report, the Government does not agree with the Committee’s view that the transfer led to delays in approving projects and that there was a lack of match funding which affected their development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister responsible for the European Regional Development Fund in England, Baroness Hanham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the Committee’s acknowledgement of the improvements this Government has made to the management and delivery of English European Regional Development Fund programmes, by transferring responsibilities for their management to the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, I do not believe that this led to delays in the approval of projects. All English programmes met their 2011 spend targets, which is an indication that projects were being approved and processed on time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;With regard to the issue of the availability of match funding - at present, some 98 per cent of the 2007-13 English European Regional Development Funding allocation is either contracted or waiting to be contracted, which means that there is match funding in place. Therefore the need for part of the Regional Growth Fund to be ring fenced for ERDF purposes is not at present necessary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Communities and Local Government Select Committee held an inquiry into the European Regional Development Fund earlier this year. The Government submitted written evidence to the Committee in April and Baroness Hanham subsequently gave oral evidence to the Committee on 9 May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Committee published its final report on 13 July. The main areas the Committee investigated were the impact and value for money of ERDF; the role of DCLG in programme management and the provision of match funding; and improvements for the future, 2014-20 programme period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key conclusions in the report are that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ERDF is a highly valuable source of funding for local authorities and other recipients;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the transfer of ERDF management from the Regional Development Agencies to DCLG went well, but there were delays in project approvals and the emphasis on compliance with the EU Regulations has led to more innovative bids being rejected;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a lack of match funding for ERDF projects, so part of the Regional Growth Fund budget should be set aside to provide match funding;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many of the EC’s proposals for the 2014-20 programmes are welcome, notably the possibility that Local Enterprise Partnerships could take a greater role in managing ERDF; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;beyond 2020 the Committee would like to see repatriation of the Funds backed with a HM Treasury guarantee that there will be no loss of funding for the poorest regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of ERDF is to reduce the economic disparities between and within Member States, by supporting economic regeneration and creating jobs. DCLG is the Managing Authority for ERDF programmes in England. It oversees 10 Operational Programmes with a total value of €3.2 billion (around £2.8 billion) in the 2007-13 programming period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until July 2011, the Regional Development Agencies carried out the day to day management of ERDF programmes in England. Following the decision to abolish the Regional Development Agencies, DCLG took over responsibility, whilst retaining a locally based ERDF Programme Delivery Team in each Operational Programme area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERDF generally pays up to 50 per cent of the eligible costs of a project. The remaining match funding must be found by the applicant and can come from a range of public and private sources, including Government funds such as the Growing Places Fund, Broadband UK and the Regional Growth Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2011, the European Commission published the draft Structural Funds Regulations to cover the next, 2014-20, programming period. The Regulations are currently the subject of negotiations between the European Commission and Nation-States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
