<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/baroness-warsi</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/baroness-warsi.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Baroness Warsi</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60117</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-everyone-a-happy-christmas"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish everyone a happy Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for Christmas.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As the year draws to a close and families up and down the country get ready to celebrate Christmas, we should all be immensely proud of the vital role that churches play in our neighbourhoods and the special place the Christian faith holds in our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our Christian communities have a strong tradition of giving back and improving the lives of those around them, as I saw for myself at a harvest festival service at London’s Borough Market where food and clothing was donated to the homeless, regardless of faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to those who will be selflessly helping others this year, whether through volunteering in a soup-kitchen or collecting and donating gifts - these generous acts make a real difference within our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The upcoming holiday is a strong reminder of the Christian ethos within our country and I wish a very merry Christmas to one and all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith and Communities Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Minister for Faith and Communities I would like to send my warmest wishes to everyone this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Christmas is an extremely special time for Britain, a country where the majority of people identify themselves as Christian. None of us should forget that, amid the turkeys, the tinsel and all the traditions that accompany this festival, lies the true meaning of Christmas: the birth of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a time for goodwill and generosity, reflection and redemption. These are themes we can all celebrate - people of all faiths and of none, who break their busy routines to come together with families and friends in the spirit of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Christmas let’s also remember the positive impact of faith on society and think about those who face persecution for holding a belief. Let’s also be confident in Britain’s Christianity, as I said when I led the largest ever ministerial delegation to the Holy See earlier this year. We cannot erase this faith from our history any more than we can erase the spires from our landscapes - or, indeed, the stars from the tops of our trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wishing everyone a very merry Christmas and a happy, peaceful New Year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56661</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T16:28:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--104"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary outlined the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-secretary-remarks-at-the-friends-of-syria-meeting" title="Foreign Secretary remarks at Friends of the Syrian People meeting"&gt;immediate priorities for the Friends of the Syrian People&lt;/a&gt; at the meeting in Marrakesh this week. He said “Syria needs a political transition leading to an inclusive new government, with full executive authority. This is the course most likely to achieve stability in the country.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-human-rights-day"&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On International Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi launched the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day" title="Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day"&gt;UK’s campaign for election to the Human Rights Council&lt;/a&gt;. She said: “We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear.” The Foreign Office marked &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/" title="16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence"&gt;16 Days of Activism Against Gender Violence&lt;/a&gt; ending on Monday with a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://preventsexualviolenceinconflict.tumblr.com/post/37632415718/helen-pankhurst" title="guest post"&gt;guest post from Dr. Helen Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt; from CARE international. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="foreign-office-website-moves-to-govuk"&gt;Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-website-moves-to-gov-uk" title="Foreign Office website moves to GOV.UK"&gt;Foreign Office began publishing its news&lt;/a&gt;, speeches, policy, publications and corporate information on GOV.UK – the single home for all government services and information. Our travel advice and consular information, and our Embassy and High Commission websites will follow by March 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="democratic-peoples-republic-of-korea-dprk"&gt;Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-condemns-dprk-s-satellite-launch" title="Foreign Secretary condemns DPRK’s satellite launch"&gt;condemned the DPRK’s satellite launch&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday saying that the launch was a clear violation of UN Security Council Resolutions 1718 and 1874 because it involved the testing of ballistic missile technology. The Permanent Under Secretary, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/north-korean-ambassador-summoned-to-foreign-and-commonwealth-office" title="DPRK Ambassador summoned"&gt;summoned the DPRK’s Ambassador&lt;/a&gt; in London to the Foreign Office to make clear to the UK’s condemnation of the DPRK’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="parental-child-abduction"&gt;Parental Child Abduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New figures revealed that the number of parental child abduction cases dealt with by the Foreign Office has risen by 88% in under a decade. The child abduction section at the Foreign office launched a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/parental-child-abduction-is-a-worldwide-problem" title="Parental Child Abduction"&gt;campaign to increase understanding of the issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="jordan"&gt;Jordan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-met-the-king-of-jordan" title="The Foreign Secretary met the King of Jordan"&gt;the Foreign Secretary met His Majesty King Abdullah of Jordan&lt;/a&gt; they discussed the situation in Syria, the Middle East Peace Process and institute reforms in Jordan that would bring about greater political participation, transparency and economic opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that the Iranian investigation into the death of the blogger Sattar Beheshti whilst in custody had &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iranian-investigation-into-detained-blogger-is-missed-opportunity-for-justice" title="Iranian investigation is missed opportunity for justice"&gt;failed to deliver justice&lt;/a&gt;. The Minister said: “The bruises on his body – which the authorities have abjectly failed to explain – are almost certainly a result of mistreatment and brutality that he – like so many others – suffered in detention.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister David Lidington set out the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-europe-renews-uk-commitment-to-eu-enlargement" title="UK’s commitment to EU enlargement"&gt;UK’s commitment to EU enlargement to all countries of the Western Balkans, Iceland and Turkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister for Africa Mark Simmonds called for &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-calls-for-an-immediate-return-to-civilian-rule-in-mali" title="UK calls for an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali"&gt;an immediate return to civilian rule in Mali&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visited Libya to strengthen &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fco-minister-shows-continued-uk-support-to-libyan-people-on-trip-to-region" title="Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt visit to Libya"&gt;UK relations with the new Libyan government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minister for Africa Marks Simmonds &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-hails-ghana-as-a-beacon-of-democracy-following-successful-elections" title="Ghana election"&gt;hailed Ghana as a ‘beacon of democracy’&lt;/a&gt; following successful elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48336</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T06:50:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-baroness-warsi-marks-human-rights-day"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi marks Human Rights Day</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi will launch the UK’s campaign for election to the UN Human Rights Council, she will say: "We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Foreign Office Minister Baroness Warsi, will mark International Human Rights Day by hosting the London launch of the United Kingdom’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is standing for election to the UN’s Human Rights Council next year to ensure that the UK is at the forefront of efforts to drive forward the human rights agenda. Calling to account countries that commit the most serious and widespread violations against their own citizens, ensuring the Human Rights Council is at the forefront of the international response to international crises and fighting hard against those who seek to weaken or undermine international human rights mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s campaign will focus on four key human rights priorities: protecting those most vulnerable in societies, working towards human dignity for all, responding proactively to evolving challenges, and keeping human rights at the heart of multilateral priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking Human Rights Day Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“International Human Rights Day is a stark reminder that there are still too many around the world who are not able to enjoy fundamental freedoms. It is important to focus on those who are fighting for their rights and the rights of their loved ones, those who are prepared to put themselves in danger for a better future for others and to remember those who have left a legacy to inspire us all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We must keep those voices at the heart of our efforts to promote and protect human rights around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am proud of the UK’s commitment to protecting those most vulnerable in our societies. Across the world, too many people are discriminated against on the basis of their race, religion, sexual orientation, disability, or gender-identity. The reasons for discrimination are many, and we must tackle the causes and the acts themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking later today at the reception for the London launch of the UK’s campaign for election to the United Nations Human Rights Council, Baroness Warsi will say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe in a Human Rights Council that can make its voice heard, even when the issues are unpopular or difficult to hear. A Council that is not bogged down by politics, but where the rights of the individual are paramount. A body where states are held accountable for their actions against their citizens, where peers review peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe strongly that we have an important role to play, which is why the UK is standing for election. We bring experience, commitment and ambition. We want to play a part in strengthening the Council, as we have since its inception in 2006. In that time the Human Rights Council has grown in status and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Through the Council, we have called to account countries who commit the most heinous and systematic violations against their citizens. We have actively supported the Human Rights Council’s international response to the crisis in Syria. We have also run thematic initiatives including through a resolution which used the Olympics to promote awareness on human rights through sport and established a commitment with the future hosts of the Games to do the same.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;amp;id=842675682" title="Follow @FCOHumanRights "&gt;Follow @FCOHumanRights &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="Twitter "&gt;Twitter &lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="Facebook "&gt;Facebook &lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/105922144104190309938/posts" title="Google+ "&gt;Google+ &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50196</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State and Minister for Faith and Communities send a message of good wishes for the Jewish holiday.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish community has made, and continues to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17574</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:27:34+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As part of inter-faith week, the winners have been announced for the Faith Through a Lens photography competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;'There but for the Grace of God'. Picture: Rob Boler&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and the other winners and finalists in the competition can be found on the awards and highlights section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ftal.staged.ws/awards-highlights-from-2012/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Together in Service event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632131148440/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17189</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T18:39:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/inter-faith-week-and-a-year-of-service-speech"/>
    <title>Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service speech</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Faith Minister Baroness Warsi on interfaith action and identity.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to thank you all for coming to this a wonderful event, marking both Inter Faith Week and A Year of Service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks also to the Faith-based Regeneration Network, Mitzvah Day, the Co-exist Foundation and others for their help in making the event a reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for the people here, it’s Inter Faith Week every week and it’s A Year of Service every year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because day in, day out, you are giving your time, your energy, your hearts and your souls to making your communities better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;United by faith and driven by faith - whichever faith that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Sikh-run Nishkam Centre in Birmingham, which provides a whole range of training and educational opportunities for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Sewa Day, which inspires Hindus across the country to acts of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like the St Vincent de Paul Society, which provides gifts and hospitality to the needy in the run-up to Christmas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These projects and many more prove that faith motivates good works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today you have a government that doesn’t deny that fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a government that supports, celebrates and - in my case - shares that motivation. A government that does God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know that people who ‘do God’ do good things up and down the country every single day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys show people of religious observance are more likely to become volunteers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see that fact in the 30,000 faith-based charities making a difference throughout Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="interfaith-action"&gt;Interfaith action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the interfaith movement officially started in 1893 with the ‘World’s Parliament of Religions’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s major religions came together in Chicago for serious discussions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I don’t think they would have a parliament; they’d have a day of social action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because today interfaith dialogue has become much more about interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always argued that interfaith shouldn’t just be tea in a draughty church hall or a samosa in the local mosque between the imam and the vicar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t just be clergy to clergy: it should be congregation to congregation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I helped get a programme called Active Faith off the ground - which, of course, became Near Neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the wonderful projects we see here today are just a small selection of the 300 local projects that have been supported so far.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Producing projects like the Departure Café, a drop-in centre and community hub for Tower Hamlets, which I hope to visit soon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of local congregations coming together to ‘do their bit’ underpin our support for the A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’ll agree - there can be no better way of marking Her Majesty the Queen’s many years of service to our country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Year of Service has produced some fantastic projects, like the wonderful Mitzvah Mummies, who I went to see yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers and their toddlers, meeting, talking to and sharing moments with residents of a retirement home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integenerational interaction - such a simple idea and so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Faith and Communities, every day I see the power and the potential of interfaith action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take last Thursday as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a catch-up with the Chief Rabbi… A meeting with Christian groups… An introduction with the Buddhist Network… A speech at my department’s Eid event… And a House of Lords debate on the importance of religion in society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the common thread running through these events wasn’t the fact these people observed a faith. It was that they were inspired to do good things as a result of their belief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I’m so proud that we have so many local and national 300 inter faith organisations in the UK - more than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why I’m so proud that 3 Faiths Forum, the Joseph Interfaith Foundation, the Christian-Muslim Forum are leading the way in the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I am so heartened to see the launch this week of advice to couples and families on interfaith marriages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stronger-identities"&gt;Stronger identities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had my own theory on inter faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that if you are stronger in your identity then you are more tolerant of others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who don’t associate with people of other beliefs because they think it somehow weakens theirs - they have got it the wrong way round. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because if you’re a person who unites with people of other faiths for a common goal - it doesn’t make you less of a Muslim, less of a Hindu, less of a Jew - it makes you more of one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is no more powerful demonstration of one’s security in one’s identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I went to the Vatican earlier this year and argued that Europe should be stronger in its Christian identity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Christian heritage of Britain is what has made me feel comfortable here in practising my faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending my daughter to an Anglican convent school made her feel stronger in her identity. When she would swap ‘Amen’ for ‘Ameen’ during the Lord’s Prayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain leads the world in its interfaith ethos. But I think we can build on the progress we’ve made since that conference in American back in 1893. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that if we - people of all faiths and none - pull together, we can defeat the intolerance and bigotry faced by people of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, an attack on a mosque is an attack on a church; an attack on a gudwara is an attack on a synagogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, an attack on one faith is an attack on all faiths. So let’s be inspired by the story of Siavosh Derakhi, who has recently been recognised for founding Young Muslims Against Anti-Semitism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by the words of President Obama, following the release of the abhorrent, gratuitously offensive ‘Innocence of Muslims’ film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he said: “to be credible, those who condemn that slander must also condemn the hate we see when the image of Jesus Christ is desecrated, churches are destroyed, or the Holocaust is denied. Let us condemn incitement against Sufi Muslims, and Shia pilgrims.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be inspired by all the good things that are done and can be done in the name of faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the subject of inspiration I want to present this beautiful piece of artwork.
Doctor Fox, I know you’re accepting this on behalf of the Evelina Hospital, so thank you, and also to the extremely talented artist Sam Cowan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m off to see some more fantastic artwork now as I go and award the winner of the Faith Through a Lens competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me once again thank you for coming today and thank you for all you do. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16140</id>
    <published>2012-11-15T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-15T15:54:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/faith-minister-visits-temple-to-start-diwali-celebrations"/>
    <title>Faith Minister visits temple to start Diwali celebrations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Baroness Warsi joined spectators at a fireworks display to mark the start of Diwali celebrations at London’s famous Neasden Temple.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neasden Temple is the first traditional Hindu Mandir in Europe and the largest temple outside India. During her visit, the Faith and Communities Minister received a traditional welcome by the trustees of the temple and heard about their work before embarking on a tour of the building. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She met volunteers and heard about the central role the temple plays within the local community and beyond - having attracted devotees and visitors from across the world since it opened in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was then invited to set off the spectacular fireworks display enjoyed by the thousands of people who had travelled to the temple to mark the beginning of Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every year I look forward to celebrating Diwali, the festival of lights, so it was a particular honour to mark it this year at the magnificent Neasden Temple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fascinating to hear about the central role the temple plays within the local community, from hosting school visits and organising charitable events - and how the Mandir has attracted devotees from all corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to pay tribute to the trustees and volunteers many hours of devotion and commitment and thank them for the warm hospitality I received during my visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632012718099/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35584</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wilton-park-conference-on-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations"/>
    <title>Wilton Park conference on preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Speaking before the conference Foreign Secretary William Hague said: "Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the Foreign Secretary will attend and deliver the keynote speech on the final afternoon of a Wilton Park Conference on “Preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his announcement in May that Britain would set up a specialist team of experts that could be deployed to conflict areas to support UN missions and local civil society to investigate allegations of sexual violence, gather evidence and help build the capabilities of other nations, the Foreign Secretary will today announce that the specialist team now consists of 70 people and is ready to deploy overseas in the near future.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those recruited for the team include police, lawyers, psychologists, doctors, forensic experts, gender-based violence experts and experts in the care and protection of survivors and witnesses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will also announce additional funding of more than £¼ million over a three year period to the UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations and the Department of Field Support to develop policies, guidance and training for use by UN peacekeepers as first responders to incidents of sexual violence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the conference, the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that a critical mass of public opinion has now begun to build up against the use of rape as a weapon of war in many countries. My experience as a politician leads me to believe that this is the moment to mobilise global public opinion and to rally the efforts of nations, in the same way that we have mustered the will to ban the use of landmines and cluster munitions, and are on the verge of securing an international Arms Trade Treaty. Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation. It is a cause whose time has come.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants at today’s conference are drawn from over 25 countries and include ministers and senior practitioners and experts.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference which includes sessions on the international normative framework; addressing impunity; early warning indicators; strengthening justice mechanisms; and communications, was also attended by the following:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mrs Zainab Bangura, UN Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margot Wallstrom, the former Special Representative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Madeleine Rees, Secretary-General of the Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serge Brammertz, a prosecutor from the ICTY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be working with Foreign Secretary Hague again on the United Kingdom’s initiative on Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict. In many conflicts, sexual violence is used as a tactic of war, intended to hurt not only a single individual, but their family, their community, their ethnic group. Today this  has almost become a rule rather than an exception, and we all must work together to combat the impunity and ensure justice for the victims.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35584</id>
    <published>2012-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/wilton-park-conference-on-preventing-sexual-violence-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations"/>
    <title>Wilton Park conference on preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Speaking before the conference Foreign Secretary William Hague said: "Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation."</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the Foreign Secretary will attend and deliver the keynote speech on the final afternoon of a Wilton Park Conference on “Preventing sexual violence in conflict and post-conflict situations”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his announcement in May that Britain would set up a specialist team of experts that could be deployed to conflict areas to support UN missions and local civil society to investigate allegations of sexual violence, gather evidence and help build the capabilities of other nations, the Foreign Secretary will today announce that the specialist team now consists of 70 people and is ready to deploy overseas in the near future.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those recruited for the team include police, lawyers, psychologists, doctors, forensic experts, gender-based violence experts and experts in the care and protection of survivors and witnesses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary will also announce additional funding of more than £¼ million over a three year period to the UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations and the Department of Field Support to develop policies, guidance and training for use by UN peacekeepers as first responders to incidents of sexual violence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the conference, the Foreign Secretary said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that a critical mass of public opinion has now begun to build up against the use of rape as a weapon of war in many countries. My experience as a politician leads me to believe that this is the moment to mobilise global public opinion and to rally the efforts of nations, in the same way that we have mustered the will to ban the use of landmines and cluster munitions, and are on the verge of securing an international Arms Trade Treaty. Shattering the culture of impunity for those who use rape as a weapon of war is the next great global challenge of our generation. It is a cause whose time has come.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants at today’s conference are drawn from over 25 countries and include ministers and senior practitioners and experts.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference which includes sessions on the international normative framework; addressing impunity; early warning indicators; strengthening justice mechanisms; and communications, was also attended by the following:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mrs Zainab Bangura, UN Special Representative on Sexual Violence in Conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Margot Wallstrom, the former Special Representative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Madeleine Rees, Secretary-General of the Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serge Brammertz, a prosecutor from the ICTY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelina Jolie, Special Envoy of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to be working with Foreign Secretary Hague again on the United Kingdom’s initiative on Preventing Sexual Violence in Conflict. In many conflicts, sexual violence is used as a tactic of war, intended to hurt not only a single individual, but their family, their community, their ethnic group. Today this  has almost become a rule rather than an exception, and we all must work together to combat the impunity and ensure justice for the victims.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14760</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:01:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/baroness-warsi-sends-her-best-wishes-on-diwali"/>
    <title>Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes on Diwali</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>On 13 November, Hindu, Jain and Sikh communities will gather to celebrate the Festival of Lights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister, Baroness Warsi sends her best wishes to all of those celebrating Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As people celebrate this special time in communities across the country, I send my warmest wishes to you all for a peaceful and happy Diwali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Diwali provides an important opportunity for prayer and reflection as the festival which celebrates the victory of good over evil and light over darkness. It is a time for family and friends, the reaffirmation of hope and renewed commitment to friendship and goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In celebrating Diwali we can appreciate the diversity that characterises this country and also recognise the common values of compassion, honesty and goodwill in which we can all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As communities across the country begin their celebrations, I am delighted to wish everyone a very happy Diwali and a prosperous new year.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
