<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/bob-neill</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/bob-neill.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Bob Neill MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-08-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14667</id>
    <published>2012-08-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympics-legacy-minister-returns-to-weymouth-and-portland-and-supports-local-business"/>
    <title>Olympics Legacy Minister returns to Weymouth and Portland and supports local business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill, Olympics Legacy and Growth Minister, visits Weymouth and Portland on Tuesday, 7 August to watch sailing events on the Nothe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include the Men’s and Women’s RS:X (windsurfing) medal races, and the Women’s Elliot 6m quarter finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is absolutely fantastic that team GB are doing so well at the Games, and I’m thrilled to be here again in Weymouth and Portland to experience the sailing events first hand. The local area has had a real buzz over the last few days with Ben Ainslie striking gold and the superb race that Iain Percy and Andrew Simpson gave to win their silver medal on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My visit has also provided a wonderful opportunity to visit the town and see, first hand, some of the key local projects including the sports arena on the beach, where children are getting the chance to try a wide range of sports.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The fact that so many people are enjoying both the sailing and the free events here shows these really are Great Britain-wide games. If anyone is looking for something fun to do in their holidays this week and beyond, I can whole heartedly say that Weymouth and Portland is a splendid place to visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2195769.jpg" alt="Bob Neill visits the Dorset Ice Cream Company"&gt;Bob Neill visits the Dorset Ice Cream Company&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the Minister will also visit local businesses including the innovative pop-up store ‘Quba’ in Brewers quay. And he will watch some of the Olympic events on the large screens on the Live site on the beach with the thousands of local supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a huge effort from people across the UK to ensure that everything is ready for the Games, and Weymouth and Portland has played a key role. The whole Olympics package on offer in the local area is a great chance to show off Weymouth and Portland, and celebrate the role that people, places and businesses from the region are playing in London 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. South West and Sport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South West region has hosted more than 40 pre-Games training camps for many of the world’s sailing teams who have trained at the new Weymouth and Portland Sailing Academy, the Castle Cove Sailing Club and Weymouth College. The University of Bath has hosted the Chinese swim team and the Malaysian Olympic team and will host the British and Danish Paralympic teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympic and Paralympic athletes from the region include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ben Ainslie CBE (Sailing)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tom Daley (Diving)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liam Tancock (Swiming)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anne Dunham (Paralympian - Equestrian)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. South West and the Olympic Park&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 60 local businesses have played a role in the construction of the Olympic Park, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Structural Metal Decks in Poole - supplied metal decking and studs for the Olympic Stadium&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Riise in Plymouth - which provided underfloor heating for the Athlete’s Village&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;B&amp;amp;B Moulds near Ilminster in Somerset - supported the concrete casting on the Olympic Stadium&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blom UK - an aerial photography firm which has captured images of the Olympic Park developing over time&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than £12 million worth of Olympic Park contracts were won by businesses based in the South West, with further benefits cascading down the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. South West and Torch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Torch was in the region for eleven days, taking in key landmarks such as St Michael’s Mount Cornwall and Royal Crescent in Bath, Stonehenge and Durdle Door on the Jurassic Coast. It also travelled by Rainforest Balloon at the Eden Project and was carried by Vintage Boats in Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. South West and Inspire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 270 community projects have been awarded the Inspire Mark, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Community Action Through Sport (CATS) in Bude, Cornwall, which encourages troubled teenagers to do voluntary work by offering surfing courses which help them gain accredited surfing and beach safety awards&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dance in Devon, a group encouraging the county to don their dancing shoes in a series of events and activities - among them a ‘Dancing on Dartmoor’ extravaganza featuring live music and traditional dancing at Haytor in Dartmoor National Park&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RELAYS (Regional Educational Legacy in Arts and Youth Sport) - a project delivered through universities in the south west of England. It aims to inspire young people and their communities to participate in, create and promote cultural and sporting activities. Successful festivals, events, collaborations and mentoring have been delivered through the three strands of the RELAYS programme: sport, cultural and business support.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. South West and Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been more than 100 locally funded and managed cultural projects officially inspired by London 2012 in the South West, including Teenage Rampage which supports young musicians across the region and played a starring role at the unveiling of the Olympic Rings at St Pancras in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the major cultural highlights include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give me tomorrow - (19 May - 23 Sep), a new exhibition at Tate St Ives by one of the most important and respected living American artists, Alex Katz, covering all six decades of his career&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Piercing Brightness (Penzance 24 Jun - 29 Sep), an exhibition of new work by internationally acclaimed Shezad Dawood presented in two venues in Penzance&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Music Nation (March), which saw the BBC Concert Orchestra working with children and families across Devon and Cornwall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14665</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-guidance-to-help-councillors-with-new-transparency-agenda"/>
    <title>New guidance to help councillors with new transparency agenda</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the introduction of a new local standards regime last month guidance clarifying the requirements of councillors to declare their pecuniary interests has been published, Local Government Minister Bob Neill announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new local standards regime, outlined in the Localism Act, has replaced the bureaucratic and controversial Standards Board, which ministers believed had become a vehicle for petty, partisan and sometimes malicious, allegations of councillor misconduct that sapped public confidence in local democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the drive for greater transparency across all Government all councillors have been required to register certain pecuniary interests, including trade union dealings on a publicly available local register since July. Deliberate failure to declare interests could result in a criminal conviction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help make sure the new approach is properly understood, the Government is publishing a practical guide, which shows the new local standards strike a common sense balance between electoral accountability and personal privacy. It clarifies specific issues like urgency of declarations; personal information safety; handling spouse or partner interests and gold plating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Government Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Standards Board regime led to an explosion in petty, partisan and malicious complaints that dragged down the reputation of local government, as well as suppressing freedom of speech. We have published a practical guide that shows how the new local standards strike a common sense balance between electoral accountability and personal privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As a former councillor myself, I know councillors are motivated about doing a good job for the local residents they serve. Instead of having hundreds of expensive and frivolous investigations hanging over their heads, local councillors should now be free to get on with their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editor"&gt;Notes to editor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Openness and transparency on personal interests: A guide for councillors&lt;/em&gt; is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/personalinterestsguide"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/personalinterestsguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister has written to all councillors and chief executive highlighting the guidance &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/personalinterestsletter"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/personalinterestsletter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Standards Board for England ceased its regulatory functions on 31 January 2012, and was formally abolished on 31 March 2012. The abolition of the Standards Board was included in the Localism Act. The Localism Act received Royal Assent on 15 November 2011. &lt;em&gt;A plain English guide to the Localism Act&lt;/em&gt; is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since 1 July 2012, all standards matters became the responsibility of local authorities, to be handled under the new arrangements, which include a code of conduct based on ‘Nolan principles’, the involvement of an independent person in allegations of misconduct, a register of members’ pecuniary interests, and a new criminal offence for failing to declare or register pecuniary interests. The new arrangements reflect the Government’s policy that elected representatives should continue to declare financial interests in an open and transparent way, to avoid conflicts of interest especially on issues such as planning applications or financially benefiting from the issuing of council contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An illustrative example of what a local code of conduct could look like can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localcodeconduct"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localcodeconduct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14664</id>
    <published>2012-08-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-visits-national-football-museum"/>
    <title>Minister visits National Football Museum</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill, Olympics Legacy and Growth Minister, visited Manchester last week as the Olympic action kicked off in the city at Old Trafford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while a key reason for his visit was to attend the Olympic Football matches at Old Trafford, he also found time to visit some key projects within the Manchester area, including the landmark and internationally acclaimed National Football Museum in the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Museum Director and founder Kevin Moore was on hand to show the Minister, a keen football fan, around the four floors of football artefacts, memorabilia and interactive games and displays. The Museum which has received financial backing from Manchester City Council and the Heritage Lottery Fund, has also received £3.8 million from the North West European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) programme, managed by Bob Neill’s department, the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2193048.jpg" alt="Olympics Legacy and Growth Minister Bob Neill with Olympic Torch Bearer Claire Dixon at the National Football Museum in Manchester"&gt;Bob Neill with inspirational Olympic Torch Bearer Claire Dixon at the National Football Museum in Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a truly world class attraction which seizes on the local love of football and brings it to life in a fantastic way. The museum will bring many thousands of visitors into the city and the surrounding area and will have a major impact on the local economy, local supply chains and local people.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am hugely impressed with what this museum has to offer - an intriguing and inspiring collection complimented wonderfully by the exciting interactive games and displays. I’m definitely coming back so I can spend a whole day here - if you like football you’ll love this place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Museum, which has an annual visitor target of 350,000, has been extremely busy since it opened at the beginning of July. Entry to the venue is free with charges only made for some of the interactive games, which include a life-size penalty shoot-out simulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Museum Director Kevin Moore said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Designers asked me if they could just reduce the length of the penalty simulator by 10 centimetres to make it easier to build - I said absolutely not, it’s got to be the full 12 yards. We’ve worked hard to make sure everything is authentic across the whole museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his day in Manchester, the Minister also visited the Enterprise Zone facilities at Manchester Airport and University Hospital South Manchester and another ERDF project, the soon to be opened Media Enterprise Centre at MediaCity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; **European Regional Development Fund in the Northwest
**The European Regional Development Fund is making a real difference to people and businesses in the North West. With €755 million to invest between 2007 and 2013, the Fund is enhancing the competitiveness of the region’s economy by supporting growth in enterprise and employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Regional Development Fund in the North West is managed by the Department for Communities and Local Government. For further information visit: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/regenerationfunding/europeanregionaldevelopment/"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/erdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; **The National Football Museum
**The National Football Museum was established and its collection acquired thanks to £9.3 million investment by the Heritage Lottery Fund. The Museum has also received £3.8 million in funding from the European Regional Development Fund and significant financial support from Manchester City Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Football Museum is a registered charity overseen by a board of trustees, and also counts notable names amongst its honorary positions, including Museum President Sir Bobby Charlton, Museum Vice Presidents Sir Alex Ferguson, Sir Tom Finney, Sir Trevor Brooking and Sir Geoff Hurst, plus Museum Special Ambassador Mark Lawrenson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The museum will also provide a permanent home for its nationally-recognised Hall of Fame, with new legends being inducted in a prestigious awards ceremony every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The museum is expected to attract over 350,000 visitors per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrance will be free, and to enhance the Museum experience, it will include some additional exclusive paid-for interactive exhibitions to help to ensure that visitors enjoy one of the best days out in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further information visit: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nationalfootballmuseum.com"&gt;www.nationalfootballmuseum.com&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.&lt;/strong&gt; **Claire Dixon
**Claire Dixon was a torch bearer on 23 June in Reedsholme, Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A former professional cyclist, Claire’s career was ended abruptly by a life threatening accident in which she suffered a brain haemorrhage and broke her back in two places. She fought back to write and present TV sports programmes, showcase the legacy of world events in Manchester and champion grass routes sports schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14659</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-minister-to-attend-olympic-football-matches-and-see-some-of-the-key-local-growth-projects-in-and-around-manchester"/>
    <title>Communities Minister to attend Olympic football matches and see some of the key local growth projects in and around Manchester</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill, Olympics Legacy and Growth Minister, will visit Manchester on Thursday, 26 July to attend the two Olympic football preliminary matches at Old Trafford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include the Team GB men’s first match against Senegal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is fantastic that the Olympics are finally upon us and high profile events such as this Team GB football match are a fabulous way to kick things off - that this event is taking place in Manchester shows these really are a Great Britain-wide games.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is projected that hosting the Olympic Football will generate an economic benefit of around £30 million for Greater Manchester. This will give the area a significant economic boost, and will leave a great Olympic legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My visit has also provided a wonderful opportunity to see, first hand, some of the key local growth projects in and around Manchester. The Media Enterprise Centre and the Enterprise Zone at Manchester Airport are truly world class projects. And The National Football Museum has given me the chance to catch up on my football history before seeing team GB make football history tonight (whatever the result!). They will all have a significant positive impact on the local economy providing local jobs, supporting local enterprise and attracting businesses to the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a huge effort from people across the UK to ensure that everything is ready for the Games, and Manchester has played a key role.  These preliminary matches are a great chance to show off the North West and celebrate the role that people, places and businesses from the region are playing in London 2012. This marks the beginning of a very exciting Games period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit the Minister will also attend the Enterprise Zone at Manchester Airport and two local European Regional Development Fund projects, both of which are playing a significant role in supporting the local economy and encouraging growth. The recently opened National Football Museum, located in the city centre, is already attracting international acclaim and will draw visitors into the area from far and wide. And within a stone’s throw of Old Trafford at MediaCity in Salford the Minister will be shown some of the cutting edge facilities and technologies at the Media Enterprise Centre, another ERDF funded project, which is aiming to stimulate and support the growth of the media technology sector within the North West of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For more information please view the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://goc2012.culture.gov.uk/2012/07/communities-minister-to-attend-olympic-football-matches-in-manchester/"&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt; (external link) on The Government Olympic Communication (GOC) online newsroom. GOC provides an integrated press office service on behalf of all UK Government Departments and Agencies from the arrival of the Olympic Torch on 18 May to the end of the Paralympic Games on 9 September. Visit their news website at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://goc2012.culture.gov.uk/"&gt;www.goc2012.culture.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link) or follow GOC on Twitter &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/2012GovPress"&gt;@2012govpress&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14655</id>
    <published>2012-07-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/shining-a-light-on-bexley-and-bromley-bob-neill-greets-the-torch"/>
    <title>Shining a light on Bexley and Bromley - Bob Neill greets the Torch</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Olympic Legacy and Fire Minister Bob Neill was out and about with the Torch over the weekend - firstly welcoming it at Erith Yacht Club as it sailed across the Thames on a Fire Boat. And then in his constituency in Bromley as part of St  Mark’s community breakfast celebration of the Torch and the local Torch bearers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2187610.jpg" alt="Bob Neill greets the Torch at Erith Yacht Club"&gt;Bob Neill greets the Torch at Erith Yacht Club&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Erith Yacht club he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was fantastic to be invited to Bexley’s magnificent Torch celebration and to greet the Torch as it crossed our great river. I’m pleased to see it was in the capable hands of London fire-fighters and experienced the welcome from this vibrant Yacht Club in Erith. This is a wonderful club that offers affordable sailing for local people and the many children we saw enjoying the river and accompanying the Torch. I’m proud that regeneration money has helped to provide a much needed new clubhouse and workshops - all for the benefit of local people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Neil greeted the torch at Erith with Teresa O’Neill, Leader of the Council and Will Tuckley, Chief Executive, Bexley Council, as well as hundreds of young sailors and members of the Yacht Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erith Yacht club works to provide affordable and accessible sailing opportunities for local people, particularly young people and people with disabilities. DCLG has helped fund and support the Yacht Club, which was awarded £2.35 million from DCLG’s Homes and Community Agency’s Sustainable Communities Fund, designed to create a lasting sporting legacy from the Olympic Games. They now have a brand new, multi functional clubhouse designed by local people for local people, and new accessible boats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning Bob Neill was on the Torch route in Bromley where he breakfasted at St Mark’s Bromley with members of the church and the wider community. He shared food with Doug Patterson, Chief Executive of Bromley Council, community leaders and Torch bearers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s been lovely to be here in Bromley supporting the Torch and the Torch bearers as they run past St Mark’s. The community is here at the church celebrating the splendid occasion of the Torch Relay whilst enjoying breakfast with our friends and colleagues. The Reverend  Steve Varney, Vicar of St Mark’s has welcomed us all into his church to join with the community including Doug Patterson, Chief Executive of the Council to support the Torch as it shines a light on Bromley and this wonderful Borough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reverend Varney said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was wonderful that the community joined in a breakfast feast in celebration of the Torch in Bromley. Families and friends coming together is at the heart of the Olympic spirit and we really demonstrated this today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on Erith Yacht Club please see: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.erithyachtclub.org.uk"&gt;www.erithyachtclub.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2187616.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2187616.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14652</id>
    <published>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/olympic-flag-flies-high-at-eland-house"/>
    <title>Olympic flag flies high at Eland House</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Olympic Legacy Minister Bob Neill proudly hoisted the Olympic flag today, outside Eland House, the headquarters of the Department of Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2185931.jpg" alt="Olympic flag"&gt;The Olympic flag flying outside Eland House&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today will also see the hallowed rings raised across Whitehall as all Government departments mark the start of the build-up to the Games. The flag will be flown alongside the Union Flag until 20 August when it will then be replaced by the Agitos - the flag of the Paralympics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympic flag was created by Pierre De Coubertin in 1914. Its five rings symbolise the five inhabited continents of the world, united by the Olympics, and the six colours were those used on all national flags when it was designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Neill was joined by competition winner and member of DCLG staff, Robert Segall, who also leads on planning policy issues surrounding flag flying. The Department is currently assessing responses to a discussion paper on relaxing the planning regime on flag flying and allowing people to fly more flags without having to seek and pay for planning consent from their local authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an honour to raise the Olympic flag over DCLG today. All Government Departments are doing this today and I am very pleased to show our support and demonstrate DCLG’s commitment to making these Games a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Segall said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I feel privileged to play this small part in the Olympic programme. It is a special feeling to have a hands-on role in your own policy area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157630664457756/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14646</id>
    <published>2012-07-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-give-councils-more-control-over-local-finances"/>
    <title>New powers give councils more control over local finances</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New details of measures that help councils boost local growth and that give them more control over their finances have been published by Local Government Minister Bob Neill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s new business rate retention scheme enables councils to retain a proportion of locally collected business rates which they can use to help fund services to their communities. A consultation was launched today setting out proposals of how the retention scheme could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plain English guide explaining business rate retention was also published so people can easily see how the scheme will work and what benefits it can bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local growth scheme is part of the Local Government Finance Bill currently before Parliament and has huge potential to boost local growth and councils’ coffers and could add an additional £10 billion to the national Gross Domestic Product over the next seven years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill seeks to create a new incentive for local government across England to support growth by directly linking a council’s financial revenue to the decisions they take to back local firms and local jobs. Councils will be able to keep 50 per cent of their business rates, providing a strong incentive to go for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill also puts councils in charge of providing council tax support so it can be administered in a way that best meets local needs and supports local people. These changes go hand in hand with the wider economic reforms and will ensure the new system is a fairer one, where taxpayers can be more confident that work pays and the benefits bill is controlled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draft regulations were also published to help Local Authorities set up localised council tax support schemes, which must be in place by the end of January 2013. This gives councils the time and opportunity to design and implement those new local schemes in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re determined to give councils more financial control and the Local Government Finance Bill gives them a new incentive system that ensures they have the best opportunity to boost local growth, which could potentially add £10 billion to the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Spending on council tax benefit has more than doubled since 1997. The Bill will also put council tax support in local hands so it can better meet local needs. Councils now have all the information they need to start putting in place their own local schemes well ahead of the new year deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business rate retention scheme consultation can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/businessratestechnical"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/businessratestechnical&lt;/a&gt;  and will close on 24 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has already published key details of the rate retention framework: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2146764"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/news/corporate/2146467&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new system will be fair and equitable for all areas with protections for vulnerable or less prosperous areas. Business rate growth would be shared evenly between central and local government. The ‘local share’ would be retained in full by councils and would be set at 50 per cent for the seven year period. The full ‘central share’ will always be returned in grants to local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition councils would get to keep 100 per cent business rates from new renewable energy projects. These would not count against the local-central shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A centrally run safety net fund would provide support should a council’s income drop below a set baseline, protecting areas which suffer a downturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1784905.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1784905.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14644</id>
    <published>2012-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/bob-neill-visits-weymouth-and-portland-as-olympic-flame-visits-dorset"/>
    <title>Bob Neill visits Weymouth and Portland as Olympic flame visits Dorset</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and Olympic Legacy Minister Bob Neill, was in Weymouth and Portland on 12 July to meet local partners and community leaders to thank them for all the valuable work they have been doing to support the Olympic and Paralympic Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2180978.jpg" alt="Bob Neill holding an umbrella"&gt;Bob Neill and the Mayor of Chickerell watch the Torch Relay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit he toured the athletes’ village at the Olympic and Paralympic sailing venue which after the Games will made available to the public as affordable housing. He then went to visit the town of Chickerell to see the Olympic Flame as it entered the Weymouth and Portland area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Weymouth and Portland has worked incredibly hard to make sure that everyone who comes to the borough to experience the sailing events has a fantastic time and to ensure that they maximise the legacy opportunities created by the Games. It’s great to see local authorities working so well together to support the Games.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Despite today’s torrential rain, the enthusiasm about the arrival of the Olympic Flame has been unwavering and I am sure that this passion will continue right until the middle of September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Weymouth Mr Neill also took the opportunity to visit Dorset Fire and Rescue service personnel at Weymouth Community Fire Station and thanked them for their work in helping local communities cope with immediate effects of the floods in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’d like to thank the Dorset Fire Service for their work during the recent floods which have hit Dorset severely in recent days. The professionalism and support of that the fire service in dealing with these incidents is of great comfort and reassurance to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1621296.jpg?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13379</id>
    <published>2012-07-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/fire-and-rescue-national-framework-for-england"/>
    <title>Fire and Rescue National Framework for England</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have today published the Fire and Rescue National Framework for England. The Framework resets the relationship between fire and rescue authorities and Government. One of the key principles of which is to acknowledge the proficiency and experience of fire and rescue authorities; and to allow them the freedom and flexibility to deliver the services for which they are respected and renowned without Whitehall prescription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The priorities in the Framework are for fire and rescue authorities to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify and assess the full range of foreseeable fire and rescue related risks their area faces, make provision for prevention and protection activities and to respond to incidents appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work in partnership with their communities and a wide range of partners locally and nationally to deliver their service; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be accountable to communities for the service they provide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and rescue authorities face new challenges: the need to deal with the continuing threat of terrorism, the impact of climate change, and the impacts of an ageing population, against a backdrop of change and the need to cut the national deficit. The Framework enables fire and rescue authorities to efficiently deliver their services; including working collaboratively with other fire and rescue authorities, or with other organisations, to improve public safety and cost effectiveness. Principally, it is to local communities, not central government, that fire and rescue authorities are accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework delivers on the Government commitment in its response to the Fire Future Reports, to clearly define national resilience and to set out clear roles and responsibilities in relation to national resilience. The Framework also sets out arrangements for fire and rescue authorities to collectively engage with Government on national resilience issues through a new Fire and Rescue Strategic Resilience Board. Through this Board, we will take a collaborative approach to national resilience that is based on and drawn from local capability, expertise, knowledge and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework has an open-ended duration which gives fire and rescue authorities greater certainty. The high level, strategic nature of the Framework should mean that it will remain unchanged for the medium to long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copies of the Fire and Rescue National Framework for England have been deposited in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14641</id>
    <published>2012-07-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/fire-and-rescue-national-framework-for-england-published"/>
    <title>Fire and Rescue National Framework for England published</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire and Rescue Minister Bob Neill has today published the new Fire and Rescue National Framework for England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Framework recognises the proficiency and experience of fire and rescue authorities and gives them the freedom and flexibility to deliver services to their communities without prescription from Whitehall. It will move accountability away from central government and place power in the hands of local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Minister Bob Neill said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Framework delivers on the Government commitment to clearly define national resilience and to set out clear roles and responsibilities. I welcome the opportunity to take a collaborative approach to national resilience that is based on, and drawn from, local capability, expertise, knowledge and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key priorities for fire and rescue authorities in the new framework include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identifying and assessing the full range of foreseeable fire and rescue related risks their area faces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making provision for prevention and protection activities and responding to incidents appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working in partnership with their communities and a wide range of partners locally and nationally to deliver their service; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being accountable to communities for the service they provide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Framework enables fire and rescue authorities to efficiently deliver their services against a backdrop of change and the need to cut the national deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition the Framework clearly defines national resilience setting out clear roles and responsibilities as well as setting out arrangements for fire and rescue authorities to collectively engage with government on national resilience issues through a new Fire and Rescue Strategic Resilience Board. The Board will enable a collaborative approach to national resilience that is based on and drawn from local capability, expertise, knowledge and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fire and Rescue National Framework for England was published on Wednesday 11 July 2012 and is available on the Department’s website at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/fire/nationalframework"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/fire/nationalframework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From December 2011 to March 2012 the Draft Fire and Rescue National Framework for England was out for public consultation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Framework has an open-ended duration which gives fire and rescue authorities greater certainty with the high level, strategic nature of the Framework meaning that it should remain unchanged for the medium to long term.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
