<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/daniel-poulter</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/daniel-poulter.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Dr Daniel Poulter MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65345</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:48:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/2013-health-partnership-awards-launched"/>
    <title>2013 Health Partnership Awards launched</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Nominations are now open for this year's Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards which were launched today in Cardiff and Edinburgh.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ceremony honours the people, projects and initiatives that provide serving military personnel, including reservists, and their families and veterans with the very best in healthcare and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awards are open to civilian health staff and military medics working within the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/defence-medical-services" title="Defence Medical Services website"&gt;Defence Medical Services&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nhs.uk/" title="NHS website"&gt;&lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and private or voluntary sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 awards ceremony, to be held on 21 May, is being hosted by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://wales.gov.uk/" title="Welsh Government website"&gt;Welsh Government&lt;/a&gt; and, from today, people can nominate individuals or teams who provide care and support to Service personnel. Nominations close on 21 February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two launch ceremonies took place today - one at the Army’s Dreghorn Barracks in Edinburgh and one at the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://www.army.mod.uk/army-medical-services/11018.aspx" title="203 Field Hospital web page"&gt;203 (Welsh) Field Hospital&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards provide a great opportunity to pay tribute to the dedication and fantastic results that our military and civilian colleagues achieve by working together to improve military health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to encourage people to visit the website to nominate all those who have provided the very best health and social care to our Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the awards in Cardiff, Welsh Health Minister Lesley Griffiths said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am proud Wales is hosting the 2013 awards. The awards celebrate the hard work, commitment and dedication shown by health professionals from across the public, private and voluntary sectors in caring for the men and women of the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important we recognise the immense contribution the Armed Forces and veterans have made to our country. We owe them a huge debt of gratitude and a duty of care, particularly those who have developed health problems as a result of their military service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Tri-Service healthcare specialists" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6006/hqscot-2013-001-4476.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The awards honour the people who provide military personnel with the best health and social care [Picture: Mark Owens, Crown Copyright/MOD 2013]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also vital we acknowledge the role of those who care for and support Service personnel and veterans, especially in recent years when the Armed Forces have been heavily engaged overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would encourage people to consider nominating either themselves or others for these awards as it is important we recognise their contribution to improving the lives of Service personnel and veterans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Health Minister Dr Dan Poulter said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These awards will shine a light on the efforts of the military, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and Service charities to make sure members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans have the best care possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such important work should not go unnoticed. I urge people to put themselves or their colleagues forward to have their efforts and achievements in caring for our Armed Forces, their families and veterans recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;203 Field Hospital was founded in 1914 and consists of reservist volunteers made up of civilian, &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; and military medics. The unit has already begun preparations for its upcoming deployment to Afghanistan in support of the Regular Army on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch event included a demonstration of the treatment of a casualty from ambulance to resuscitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the visit, Lesley Griffiths was accompanied by Surgeon Rear Admiral Calum McArthur, Brigadier Philip Napier, Commander of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/structure/28224.aspx" title="160 (Wales) Brigade web page"&gt;160 (Wales) Brigade&lt;/a&gt;, and Colonel Tina Donnelly, Commanding Officer of 203 Field Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the awards, including how to apply or nominate, are available at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org/" title="Military and Civilian Health Partnership Awards website"&gt;www.militarycivilianhealthawards.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
