<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/david-mundell</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/david-mundell.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - David Mundell MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T16:31:50+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56845</id>
    <published>2011-10-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T16:31:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-big-society-in-scotland"/>
    <title>The Big Society in Scotland</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>David Mundell, Scotland's Parliamentary Under Secretary of State, talks about The Big Society in Scotland and if it can work.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much for inviting me to speak this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference is dedicated to examining the Big Society and assessing whether it can work in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it can and it will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an opportunity, not a threat, to charities, voluntary organisations and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I want to share my thoughts with you on the Big Society in greater detail; before updating the conference on welfare reform and the Scotland Bill - 2 issues I know you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-big-society-the-big-picture"&gt;The Big Society: the big picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representing Scotland on the UK Ministerial Group advancing the Big Society agenda, I am determined that our voice and interests are heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am not wedded to titles such as the Big Society. Indeed, some have suggested that in Scotland it would be the ‘Wee Society’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the purposes of this discussion, I’ll use Big Society as this has partially led so many people to show a significant interest here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 pillars to this agenda:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;community empowerment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reforming and opening up our public services and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging greater social action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These 3 pillars are vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most important is what is happening on the ground and acknowledging those who are doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Society is not another government programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the Big Society is quite the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about giving power back to individuals, families, communities and groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about turning government upside down - so that society, not the state, is in the driving seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-empowerment"&gt;Community empowerment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of our critics have said that government cannot create a Big Society on our own. They’re right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is no need for such a magic wand solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we are not starting from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland already does the Big Society or whatever we call it. I want us to do more of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are building on the long-standing tradition of community engagement and social action in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grass roots are there. Many of you are the manifestation of movements already out there - helping Scots nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s role is to play an enabling role in the Big Society and it will focus on ensuring that all parts of society are able to play their part and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish government will also have a part to play and I hope they will engage, whether they formally acknowledge the Big Society concept or not or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it will mean that the state, in all its forms, pulling back when it has overreached and acknowledging that it doesn’t have all the answers to local issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want our vision to interact with the work that so many Scots are already doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this is an opportunity to shine a spotlight on the excellent work done by local groups across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government has opened up a dialogue on taking forward the Big Society in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is already proving a rewarding conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders across the country have given me a flavour of what they are doing and the good practice they are encouraging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an ongoing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more Scotland Office events in the pipeline, culminating with a Scotland-wide forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowerment stands at the forefront of our vision of a Big Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about freeing people and communities to make the decisions which affect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It marks a radical and welcome break from the tired old view that civil servants in London and Edinburgh, or dare I say local authorities, always know what is best for you and your community.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reforming-and-opening-up-public-services"&gt;Reforming and opening up public services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of our critics claim that the Big Society is geared to providing public services on the cheap.  I don’t agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I view the Big Society as more about working with, and improving, existing services rather than replacing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all answers and services need to be provided by officials, councils or government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tough times also demand innovative thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no escaping the need to tackle the deficit - the challenge we face in terms of public finances cannot be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our detractors also characterise the Big Society as a shorthand for cuts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s both wrong and unfair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Society is a positive, proactive agenda developed before the recession to achieve a better quality of outcomes with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our priority must be to seek the best value provider of public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the right answer for service users and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="greater-social-action"&gt;Greater social action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I want to see people and communities across Scotland feeling both free and powerful enough to help themselves and transform their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in many ways the Big Society is a challenge to achieve even greater social action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to think and act differently&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to consider the personal and social consequences of your actions &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to take ownership of an area and find ways of to transform it for the better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And it poses the question to the state, ‘why can this not be done by individuals themselves, by voluntary, community or social enterprises?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen the success of the National Citizens Service pilot south of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s designed to build a more cohesive, responsible and engaged society by bringing together 16 year olds from different backgrounds for a programme of activity and service during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives these young people an introduction to community action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows them the positive differences they can make in their localities and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are planning to expand the service to offer 90,000 places by 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that over time, the Scottish government will look at what we’re doing and want to take part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This renewed commitment to a stronger sense of society, where taking a more active role will be both expected and recognised, can only benefit us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I recognise that we need to make it simpler for individuals and organisations who offer their time and knowledge to benefit their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good intentions must not be deterred by the burdens of bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are examining ways of reducing regulation and red tape faced by charities, voluntary organisations and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not for government to tell Scots how they can best support their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But government can provide support when society is restricted - such as by removing the red tape which can hinder community groups from forming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local people and local bodies know their communities better than anyone. Charities, churches and co-operatives have the unique grassroots knowledge to drive social action at local level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make it easier for you to do what you do best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s self-evident that most of the specific policy areas within the Big Society are devolved to the Scottish government and not all the major Westminster Big Society projects have exact equivalents in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it’s imperative that Scotland’s 2 governments work together and co-operation is central to our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m keen to engage on the issue and have had useful discussions with both John Swinney and Alex Neil; and my Cabinet Office colleague Nick Hurd will be in Scotland soon to share experiences from elsewhere in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="big-society-bank"&gt;Big Society Bank&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know you will also be interested to hear about the Big Society Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have delivered on our commitment to set it up, although it is no longer being called a bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been renamed the Big Society Capital Group, in case people are confused into thinking there is a new high street bank on the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it’s open for business in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big Society Capital will invest in social investment intermediary organisations across the UK, such as Charity Bank and the Key Project. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these intermediaries will bring together bodies that need capital and bodies that have capital and want to invest it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big Society Capital will not make grants to individual organisations or charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your organisations should be able to gain access to capital at a more competitive rate than you would be able to secure from a high street lender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big Society Capital will act independently of government to support social enterprise through intermediaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want organisations in Scotland to benefit from the very favourable terms it will offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="encouraging-charitable-giving"&gt;Encouraging charitable giving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK government is also committed to helping charities in these challenging economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand that charity law and charity reform straddles reserved and devolved policy areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key focus in the UK government’s Giving White Paper is on encouraging charitable giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovative schemes can make it easier to give - at the cash point, at the till, by text or by phone app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government is committed to incentivising giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to grow and raise the profile of payroll giving and are sponsoring the National Payroll Giving Awards to encourage this activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, inheritance tax will be cut for those who leave 10% or more of their estate to charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the 2011 Budget we announced a number of significant tax incentives and the removal of red tape for gift aid donations up to £5,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are sensible, practical measures geared to making it easier for charities to raise more money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Society also has responsibility at its heart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It offers the opportunity for individuals, businesses and organisations to step forward to help address the social issues in their communities and help shape the future direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like you are already giving significant amounts of your time for the benefit of your communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses are seeing the benefits of supporting volunteering and encouraging their staff to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals and groups are improving communities across Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On recent visits I have seen how volunteers at Peterhead Projects are raising funds in their town by recycling furniture, running a gift shop and holding car boot sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or how Cambuslang and Rutherglen Community Health Initiative is promoting better health locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim is that volunteering becomes a social norm and is considered by all the responsible thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 more issues I want to touch on - 2 significant issues for this sector - welfare reform and the Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="welfare-reform"&gt;Welfare reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairness is a pivotal part of the Coalition’s approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to helping the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will take over 90,000 Scots out of tax altogether by April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have helped one million older Scots by re-establishing the link between pensions and earnings after a gap of 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have maintained Winter Fuel Allowance payments for Scottish pensioners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While last year’s Spending Review turned the temporary increase in Cold Weather Payments into a permanent increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are geared to reforming the benefit system to make it fairer, more affordable and better able to tackle poverty, worklessness and welfare dependency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of Universal Credit in 2013 will radically simplify the system - and make work pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are determined to remove the barriers to work and to ensure that work pays more than benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our back-to-work initiatives will pay a crucial part in supporting employment in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of our reforms, the Work Programme went live in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that one size cannot fit all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the Work Programme is built around the needs of individuals - providing the personalised support people need, when they need it - so they have the right support to move into employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government’s ‘Get Britain Working’ measures like work experience are geared to this end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Youth Unemployment Seminars, hosted by the Scotland Office across the country, we are hearing about the benefits of work experience with local employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Scottish employers see young people, particularly inexperienced young people, as high risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So giving young Scots greater work experience enhances their readiness for work by developing the skills which are essential for the workplace.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to work side by side on this - to collaborate more effectively to support our young people into work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the Big Society, Scotland’s 2 governments must work together, alongside our key partners to address the labour market challenges we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scotland-bill"&gt;Scotland Bill&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the Coalition’s key commitments is to improve the devolution settlement and strengthen the accountability of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill delivers this pledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Bill has real economic teeth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It signifies the largest transfer of financial powers out of London since the creation of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will give the Scottish Parliament new levers over the Scottish economy and strengthens its accountability and responsibility to the people of Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The First Minister has told us about other areas he thinks should be devolved to Scotland in the Scotland Bill.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made clear that we will consider all proposals for amendments to the Bill on their merits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any amendments must meet the three tests set out by the Secretary of State for Scotland. They must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be based on detailed and well evidenced proposals &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maintain the cross-party consensus on which the Bill is based &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;demonstrate that they would benefit Scotland, without prejudice to the UK as a whole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Scottish government has made their set of demands as a package and we will respond as a package at the appropriate time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government will also fight to maintain the United Kingdom in any independence referendum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not place obstacles in the way of a referendum but we believe strongly that more powers for the Scottish Parliament - through the Scotland Bill - is the right constitutional route for Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we will oppose separatism in any guise whenever the referendum takes place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside our commitments to more tailored welfare and improved devolution we are also determined to build a bigger and stronger society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months and years we aim to build on the deep-rooted foundations we have in Scotland to achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government can be an enabler but it cannot be expected to deliver the Big Society alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have an important role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to support a thriving market in charities, voluntary organisations and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I support and admire what so many public-spirited Scots are doing in their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to working with you to realise the benefits of the Big Society in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64220</id>
    <published>2010-09-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T10:37:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/scdi-highlands-and-islands-annual-dinner-and-business-excellence-awards"/>
    <title>SCDI Highlands and Islands Annual Dinner and Business Excellence Awards</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>David Mundell, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Scotland, talks about opportunities for Scottish businesses and Scotland's constitutional future.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many thanks Joe [Moore, Chair, &lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt; Highland Committee] for your kind introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be in Inverness and to address this prestigious Scottish Council for Development and Industry (&lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;) event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight we salute business success and recognise the benefits prosperous enterprises bring to the local economy and communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic base of the Highlands and Islands is more robust and diverse than ever before. This diversity marks a real strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From premium food and drink to pioneering renewable energy projects and from tourism excellence to cutting edge life sciences. And at the centre, the thriving hub of Inverness. A city for the past decade [since 2000], with the prospect of a new university campus on the horizon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also want to balance this with requisite realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that your local MP and my former Scotland Office ministerial colleague Danny Alexander addressed the Chamber of Commerce here three weeks ago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny wasn’t a colleague for very long - indeed he was Scottish Secretary for a mere 16 days - even Premier League managers still get longer than that these days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his new job as Chief Secretary to the Treasury - surely a case of jumping from the fat into the fire - Danny has outlined some of the tough decisions the coalition government must take to achieve our twin goals of controlling public spending and rebuilding economic confidence. I would like to go a bit further by outlining some of measures we will take to create a business-friendly environment in which to establish, run and grow private enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dealing-with-the-deficit"&gt;Dealing with the deficit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition inherited the largest-ever peacetime deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures are eye watering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An annual deficit of £155 billion means we are losing £3 billion every week. That’s the equivalent of everyone in Britain taking on an extra £50 of debt weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is not right to retreat into deficit denial mode or claim it is fine to wait a few more years before we start to live within our means again. The world won’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inaction is a recipe for even higher debt charges, higher domestic interest rates and an end to recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business in Scotland cannot prosper while the risk of a debt crisis hangs over the economy. I know you also believe deficit reduction is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a sense, the first and most important policy for economic growth announced by the coalition is our tough fiscal position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been well warned. The crisis in some Eurozone states underlined the urgency to act now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the tough decisions we have taken since May, and the many more we will make before this year is out, are geared to getting a grip of the debt, rebalancing the economy and creating the right conditions for sustainable economic growth. We are in this for the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-coalition-response"&gt;The coalition response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergency budget in June set us on firmer fiscal foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a five year plan to restore the economy by eliminating the structural deficit and getting overall debt falling by 2015/2016. Some decisions will be difficult but even more painful would have been the cuts forced upon us if we did not get spending under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burden of deficit reduction is shared and we will continue to support the most vulnerable Scots. All sectors in society will contribute but the richest will pay more than the poorest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The budget illustrated our commitment to fairness. Around 90,000 low paid Scots were lifted out of income tax. We hope to continue raising thresholds so more will benefit in subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At opposite ends of the age spectrum the child element of child tax credits was increased and the earnings link to the basic state pension was re-established after 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spending Review is the next key step. The Treasury is fully consulting the Scottish government during this process and will announce its conclusions on 20 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not solely about cutting public spending. It marks a complete re-evaluation in our approach to public services provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about empowerment - giving more power to people, local communities and front-line public servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about the divergence in policy we have experienced since devolution. With the potential this creates for earmarking best practice and for bringing about yardstick competition to incentive efficiencies in the delivery of public services. Here in Scotland, the Scottish government will respond to this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about the Spending Challenge online public consultation. And tapping into the expertise of public service providers and users to produce proposals for fair savings across spending areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some suggestions will apply to matters devolved to the Scottish Parliament but we are committed to the best ideas being taken forward as part of the Spending Review process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I fully understand that defence is a significant area for Scotland, and particularly for this region. The Strategic Defence and Security Review is underway. I assure you that the Secretary of State and I will continue to make Scotland’s case strongly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-recovery"&gt;Building recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the coalition is about a lot more than sorting out the deficit and imposing cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand the importance of private enterprise in generating the growth necessary to secure sustainable economic recovery in Scotland. This government backs business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The budget outlined our blueprint for sustained growth - private-sector led, balanced across the country and across sectors. And it is private sector enterprise and profits which powers our public services too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The budget acted as a springboard for private sector recovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incorporating a range of measures tailored to support business and restore competitiveness. Such as simplifying the tax system and reducing red tape. One-third of a million Scottish &lt;abbr title="Small and Medium-sized Enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; will benefit from budget measures to tackle red tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make it as easy as possible to start, run and expand a business. Returning Scotland to an enterprise culture and restoring the spirit of entrepreneurialism to the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Outer Hebrides that spirit has transformed the social and economic landscape. Over three-fifths of the population now live in collectively owned communities. Local people have taken responsibility for land and the future sustainability of their communities. They understand they cannot be dependent on public grants and have established businesses to try to secure their futures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More widely, we want to build a recovery with increased investment and net exports at its heart. We’re committed to creating the right conditions for investors and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the investment attracted to Scotland from Hewlett Packard, Barclays and Virgin Money in recent weeks.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phased reduction in Corporation Tax will see it fall to 24p in the pound by 2015 - in line with the government’s aim to create the most competitive corporate tax regime in the G20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threshold for employer National Insurance contributions will be increased. And a special National Insurance contributions holiday for the first 10 staff will help 59,000 new Scottish enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And rather than highlighting China, India and other emerging mass economies as potent competitors, it is their role as potential customers which offers the greatest potential benefits for Scotland. Growing exports are the means of benefiting in the growing global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And looking forward we must model an economy which is greener, more enterprising and more technologically advanced than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland already has numerous cutting edge firms. And the Highlands and Islands is a major contributor to key, expanding areas of the Scottish economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life Sciences are growing worldwide and already support 1,800 jobs in this region alone, the majority at Lifescan Scotland, which I visited this afternoon. I welcome the efforts of Highlands and Islands Enterprise to build on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, renewable energy offers Scotland, and especially this region and off its coasts, great opportunities in wind and wave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green electricity is the future. We are seeing this confirmed in new generation capacity in Europe and the United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are determined to make very best use of the government’s huge influence on the business environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll do this by keeping markets free and fair, empowering consumers, keeping a lid on damaging regulation, managing risk and ensuring a stable tax regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are committed to working alongside business people like you to pinpoint the drivers of growth. It might be improved broadband access, an upgraded transport infrastructure or the development of the low carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that companies across Scotland are still finding it difficult to access finance from the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks have a vital role to play in providing affordable credit to boost the business-led recovery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The supply of finance must support not constrain the recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government is looking at a range of options to ensure that firms can access the finance they need to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="agenda-of-mutual-respect"&gt;Agenda of mutual respect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the economy has been the coalition’s overriding concern, we are committed to an agenda of mutual respect with the devolved administrations. Scotland benefits when its two governments work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron visited the Scottish Parliament three days after assuming office. And Danny Alexander and Michael Moore have both formally appeared before &lt;abbr title="Members of Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSPs&lt;/abbr&gt; at Holyrood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agenda is being realised in other ways too. The Chancellor agreed the Scottish government can delay efficiency savings to 2011-12 and commitments have been made to bring forward a rural fuel tax pilot and to review the Fossil Fuel Levy as part of the Spending Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scotland-bill"&gt;Scotland Bill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is also fulfilling its commitment contained in the coalition Agreement and Queen’s Speech to introduce a Scotland Bill to strengthen the devolution settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The management of this Bill through Parliament is the Scotland Office’s big task for the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a process which is driving forward. A Scotland Bill team has been established and the High Level Implementation Team has met. Scotland’s three Unionist parties are participating in the cross-party, cross-Parliament Steering Group, which met again last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business often demands that politicians are made more financially accountable. The Scotland Bill will make this happen for the Scottish Parliament.  Increasing spending decisions at Holyrood will go hand in hand with corresponding changes to taxation levels in Scotland. Choices will be made between different levels of taxation and spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, there will be scare stories about the operation of the new tax system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill is predicated on retaining the wider, unified UK tax system. This means no separate tax system for Scotland, so avoiding the compliance issues this would create for firms operating on either side of the border and the incentives this would generate for avoidance. We understand that the rest of the UK is the destination for over two-thirds of Scotland’s exports. The Scotland Bill is an elegant solution not a ‘messy fudge’ as some Scottish Ministers have claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are ensuring the continuation of the UK’s unimpeded single market - this would not be guaranteed with the wider devolution of taxes to the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greater fiscal autonomy would only lead to much greater Scottish budget volatility. Indeed, there is no example in the world of a sub-national government with full fiscal autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill gives us the best of both worlds - the benefits of financially accountable governance at Scottish Level and the benefits of being a fundamental part of the world’s 6th largest economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Scotland still faces real economic challenges. We are not out of the woods yet and the recovery will be choppy. That’s why it is essential for Scotland’s two governments work together, and with business, to restore economic confidence and help generate new private sector employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition government will take the fair and responsible decisions necessary to allow Scotland to grow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57634</id>
    <published>2010-06-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T17:29:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-scotsman-retail-business-summit"/>
    <title>The Scotsman Retail Business Summit</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>David Mundell, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State, talks about retail, reducing the deficit and the coalition's programme for government.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am very pleased to be in Edinburgh this morning. It is a real privilege to be a Scotland Office minister and to have the chance to address conferences like today’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Office has a cross-party team for the first time in 65 years. Michael Moore and I are determined to take this historic opportunity to improve our nation’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I want to speak about three things today. First, I want to take this opportunity to discuss the changing face of retail. Second, I would like to highlight the new government’s overriding commitment to reduce the deficit and restore economic growth. And third and finally, I will set out our vision of the new politics which are at the heart of the Coalition’s programme for government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="retail"&gt;Retail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might come as a surprise but it was that famous son of Kirkcaldy, Adam Smith, who first coined the phrase ‘nation of shopkeepers’. He used it over two centuries ago in The Wealth of Nations. Smith believed that the building of the British Empire was extremely fit for a nation whose government was influenced by shopkeepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, this term would be used by Napoleon Bonaparte to describe Britain in a disparaging tone. When in fact retail was one of our greatest economic strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution ushered in a retail revolution. The centre of Victorian Glasgow was transformed by a ‘proliferation of new building types, such as… hotels, shopping arcades and retail warehouses’. Enterprising Scots like Sir Thomas Lipton, the grocery store magnet and tea merchant, changed the way Britons shopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Scotland has a rich retail heritage, the retail sector remains a vital component of the modern Scottish economy. Indeed, I think it is fair to say that the state of the retail sector is a key barometer of Scotland’s economic health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail now has such a varied presence. The changing face of retail reflects the changing face of Scotland. The traditional image of the corner shop and the high street, of small specialist shops in town centres has made way for a vast and varied retail experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of retail has been transformed. Over the last half century we have witnessed the advent of the supermarket, the building of out of town retail parks and the construction of massive distribution depots adjacent to our motorways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Bill [Jamieson] said at the start, in the last decade we have experienced the phenomenal growth of online shopping. Offering the possibility for the smallest online operation set up on a Scottish kitchen table to go global overnight. So the business environment is constantly evolving and innovative Scots face the challenge of staying ahead of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all aware that retail has endured tough times in recent years. The recession has led canny customers to make more careful choices in an intensely competitive marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly some famous names and established brands have vanished from the scene entirely. Others have been swallowed up in fresh rounds of consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I remain convinced that retail will be a significant contributor to the economic recovery. For it will be business, with retail at the forefront, which will power Scotland out of recession. To borrow the title of this conference for a moment, we hope to see ‘shopping for growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past 11 years the Scottish Retail Consortium has surveyed the Scottish retail scene. I know that your membership is varied and wide both in size and in scale but I salute your admirable determination to showcase the manifest achievements of the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You rightly stress the message that a strong and vibrant retail sector is crucial for the Scottish economy and for employment in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics are impressive. Even in recession, Scottish retail sales totalled £24 billion in 2009, that’s 11% of our total turnover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so many Scots go to the shops to work - an often overlooked fact. Some 245,000 Scots work in retailing. That’s a figure which exceeds the population of Aberdeen, our third largest city. It means that the sector employs over 10% of Scotland’s total workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that conditions remain tough right across the sector. We saw this when the SRC reported falling like-for-like sales last month. It is the reason that we have to restore confidence in the marketplace and among consumers. And our first step, as a government, as I will highlight later, will be actioning a credible plan to cut the unsustainable budget deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dealing-with-the-deficit-and-building-recovery"&gt;Dealing with the deficit and building recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to seeing Scottish businesses succeeding and generating the growth and jobs our economy needs. We are pledged to listen to Scottish business and their industry bodies. I want the business community to know that we want to work with you to realise the common objective of building Scotland’s recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that we support sustainable growth and enterprise and that we want to see all regions of Scotland and all our industries sharing the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our first priority must be to act on the deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structural budget deficit that the new Coalition government inherited three weeks ago is the largest since records began. Recent events in the Eurozone underlines the importance of taking action this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reducing the deficit is our most important common mandate as a coalition government. We will take action to significantly accelerate the reduction of the structural deficit over the course of this Parliament. And our plans have already been welcomed by Bill, the Governor of the Bank of England and the Director General of the CBI (Confederation of British Industry) have both welcomed our plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deficit is an issue which affects every one of us across Scotland and the UK. We will set out our comprehensive plans for deficit reduction in the emergency growth budget on 22 June. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a first step, over £6 billion of UK spending cuts were set out last week. And we have already made it clear that the main burden of budget reduction will be met by decreased government spending rather than by increased taxation. We have demonstrated our political will to cut lower priority programmes and government waste in the first fortnight of the new coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are cuts with care - for as far as possible we will protect key frontline services and protect people on the lowest incomes. We have taken the first steps on the road to restore good management to our public finances. Fully aware that unless the government tackles the huge public deficit, it could derail the recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor underlined that urgent action was necessary. To keep interest rates lower for longer, to boost confidence in our economy and to protect jobs. We are starting to show the world that we can live within our means and will not allow our debt repayments to spiral out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honesty and transparency will underpin our approach. That’s why we have created an independent Office of Budget Responsibility to maintain confidence in the management of the public finances. Fiscal confidence and credibility are crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while it is essential that we tackle our record debts, we cannot have a programme of deficit reduction that only applies to England. Scotland, and the other nations and regions of the UK, must pay its share too. Because without sound finances we will be unable to deliver the ambitions that we have for all of Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One ambition which we will seek to realise from the outset is our determination to make it easier for people to start new businesses. These are the fresh and vibrant lifeblood of our economy. Our objective is to cut the time it takes to get a new business up and running. The UK must become one of the fastest countries in the world to get new enterprises started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, we are determined to break down the barriers which stifle businesses and employment in this country. The government will get Britain working by boosting enterprise.  We will implement measures to make the tax and benefits system simpler and fairer and National Insurance must not be a hindrance to employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to getting Scots back to work. A reformed benefits system will improve work incentives and start lifting hundreds of thousands of Scots currently on benefits into work and out of poverty. And we are prepared to impose sanctions on those who turn down available jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, a fairer tax system will be created that will help Scots on lower and medium incomes. Central to this is our longer term aim of increasing the personal allowance to £10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be business which will power economic growth and innovation. We want to unlock all the undoubted talent in Scotland. Our Programme for government specified our commitment to boost enterprise, support green growth and construct a new and more responsible economic model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulations and red tape have to go on a long overdue diet. No regulation will be brought in without another regulation being cut by a greater amount. And regulations will be regularly reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of fairer and simpler regulations are wide and varied. I would like to highlight just 3. They remove undue administrative burdens, they reduce uncertainty among the self-employed and they offer a route to labour market flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are determined to reform the corporate tax system to reduce headline rates. We will do this in two ways. First, by simplifying reliefs and allowances, and second by tackling avoidance. This way we can progress towards our set aim of creating the most competitive corporate tax regime in the G20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the new government can bring great benefits to Scotland’s business environment. We are committed to investing in our infrastructure too. That’s why in the Queen’s Speech we set out our proposals to back investment in new high-speed broadband and to enable the construction of a high speed rail network throughout Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a core priority for this government is to ensure the flow of credit to viable SMEs (small and medium enterprises). We will reform the banking sector to promote responsible banking in a more competitive industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tough times it is imperative that Scotland’s businesses have the best platform on which to survive and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-new-politics"&gt;A new politics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we aim to secure economic recovery and look to the future, I believe that this will take place in tandem with a change in the nature of Scottish and UK politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will forge a new politics which has people and policies at its heart and leaves the old differences behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parties in the Coalition government have found common ground. We are united in our determination to build a strong, stable and durable government and maintain a united front at a critical but hopeful time for Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has made his feelings clear when he visited Scotland immediately after last month’s General Election. There should be no going back to the bad old ways. They offer Scotland no solutions to the challenges and opportunities of the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to see a new politics between Scotland and Westminster of respect not rancour. Realising a respect agenda where cooperation not confrontation is key. That means extending the hand of cooperation towards the Scottish government down the road from here too. We understand that a good relationship between Westminster and Holyrood serves Scotland best. That’s why we have given the Scottish government the option of deferring cuts until next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am optimistic that we are entering an era of partnership politics and grown up government. There is a real chemistry among the coalition leadership and a sense of common purpose.  That was borne out by the quick settlement of the coalition agreement and in the drafting of our programme for government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as we have seen in recent days, it will not be plain sailing. Needless to say, there will be bumps and scrapes along the way. But I have witnessed the determination to make the new arrangement work for the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of our programme for government is a strong, progressive coalition inspired by the enduring principles of freedom, fairness and responsibility. And it is a programme for five years of partnership government driven by these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During which time we are determined to deliver for the people of Scotland. Not hanging around but implementing the Calman recommendations on tax and other powers - and seeking to maintain a dialogue with the Scottish government and Scottish Parliament throughout this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope it will deliver for the retail sector as it will for Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57715</id>
    <published>2010-05-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T08:35:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/facing-up-to-climate-change"/>
    <title>Facing up to climate change</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>David Mundell, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State, talks to the Royal Society of Edinburgh Inquiry about tackling climate change.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me to participate in this event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a chance tonight to discuss the steps that individuals can take in the shift to a low carbon Scotland. I also want to hear your thoughts on government’s role in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government believes that climate change is one of the gravest threats we face. Urgent action at home and abroad is required to meet the challenge head on. We will use a wide range of levers to cut carbon emissions, decarbonise the economy and support the creation of new green jobs and technologies. That’s why, we will implement a full programme of measures to build a low carbon, eco-friendly economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a positive willingness to engage with the Scottish government to address these significant challenges. A good relationship between Westminster and Holyrood serves Scotland well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both administrations have signed up to very challenging carbon reduction and renewable energy targets. The targets set by Scottish Ministers will be crucial in meeting UK and &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition’s programme features radical measures to support our climate change objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include encouraging the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; to demonstrate leadership in tackling global climate change and supporting an increase in the &lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;EU&lt;/abbr&gt; emission reduction target to 30% by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to increase the renewable energy target, subject to the advice of the Climate Change Committee. Meanwhile, in our commitment to a diverse energy mix, we will continue public sector investment in carbon capture and storage (&lt;abbr title="Carbon Capture and Storage"&gt;CCS&lt;/abbr&gt;) technology for four coal-fired power stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also establish a full system of feed-in tariffs in electricity - as well as maintaining banded Renewables Obligation Certificates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when we think of renewables we think only of wind.  It is an important source of electricity for meeting our 2020 targets. But we want to encourage marine energy and biomass and achieve a huge increase in energy from waste through anaerobic digestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive localism can help too. We will encourage more community-owned renewable energy schemes where local people benefit from the power produced. We want communities that host renewable energy projects to keep the additional business rates they generate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to be the greenest government ever. Through our ‘Green Deal’, we will encourage home energy efficiency improvements paid for by savings from energy bills. Energy efficiency in businesses and public sector buildings will improve too. Central government must reduce its carbon emissions by 10% within 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy Efficiency is vital - there are many low cost or no cost measures which can reduce carbon and save us all money. The cheapest and cleanest unit of energy is the one we don’t use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an early measure we will review the Fossil Fuel Levy with a view to unlocking these funds and will meet the industry to discuss transmission charging. We intend to reform energy markets to deliver security of supply and investment in low carbon energy, and ensure fair competition, including a review of Ofgem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unacceptable that we have some of the world’s best renewable resources but have underperformed in harnessing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are huge opportunities in clean energy. We have the expertise and potential to lead the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government and industry organisations believe that we have the resources to be a net energy exporter by 2050. Creating hundreds of thousands of new jobs and pumping billions into the economy in the process. Meeting our priority to safeguard the UK’s energy security in a volatile world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential is enormous - Scotland must make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to hearing your views on realising this vision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/58221</id>
    <published>2010-05-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T09:32:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laggan-tormore-launch-ceremony"/>
    <title>Laggan-Tormore launch ceremony</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>David Mundell, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State, marks the start of work on the Laggan Tormore Gas Plant.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be on Shetland today. And it is great to be here at the impressive and striking Shetland Museum, the home of Shetland’s rich heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this unique building Shetland’s past - its culture and its customs - comes alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also positive about Shetland’s economic future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I carried out the peat cutting ceremony which marks the start of work on the Laggan Tormore Gas Plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="continued-growth"&gt;Continued growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will play a leading part in Shetland and Scotland’s energy future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of the new gas fields west of Shetland shows the continued significance of oil and gas in Scotland’s energy mix over the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total’s project marks a milestone in the development of the West of Shetland area, which contains about one-fifth of the UK’s remaining oil and gas reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Sea oil and gas has been a hugely important aspect of Scottish economic life for most of my lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, in the process, oil and gas has transformed the Shetland economy too. Shetland has been home to Sullom Voe, the largest oil and liquefied gas terminal in Europe, since construction began 35 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the years to come the new gas fields west of Shetland will be the deepest yet developed on the UK Continental Shelf. They will also be operated remotely from the new processing plant and control room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased that Total has been able to take advantage of the field allowance for remote gas fields located in deep water. And it is good to see that the necessary gas infrastructure is being put in place to meet further development and expansion. I believe that this represents a successful outcome to the work of the West of Shetland TaskForce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jobs dividend is significant for the local economy and beyond. The new gas plant will create up to 500 new jobs during construction. And support more than 2,000 jobs across the UK during the project’s lifetime. Four years from now, in mid-2014, we look forward to seeing the first production of gas from the new field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy is a key factor in Scotland’s future economic prosperity. And it is grounded on the expertise which we have built up in the challenging environment of the North Sea. That’s why I am optimistic that we will fully harness the possibilities presented by the new oil and gas fields as well as our exploiting our abundant natural wind and wave resources. I believe that Scotland has the skills and experience to realise our energy potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-governments-position"&gt;The government’s position&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to take this opportunity to say a few words about the new coalition government. We know that Scotland and the UK faces serious and urgent challenges but we will meet them with a united front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can assure you that the new government is determined to act in the national interest as we tackle the tasks that we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister underlined in Scotland last week that we are committed to providing strong and stable leadership built on the key pillars of freedom, fairness and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rancour and conflict of the past does not address the challenges of today. And it fails to provide us with the best platform to exploit the undoubted opportunities of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are pledged to forging a new politics. The Scotland Office will be at the frontline of the new politics, with the spirit of co-operation at its heart - and a real commitment to extend this co-operation to the Scottish government too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to see a stronger and more prosperous Scotland. I look forward to working with you all to achieve this common goal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
