<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/david-willetts</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/david-willetts.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon David Willetts MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60131</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T17:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T17:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/small-businesses-to-benefit-from-1-1-million-innovation-boost"/>
    <title>Small businesses to benefit from £1.1 million innovation boost</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innovation is vital for business growth. The aim is simple – to accelerate economic growth by stimulating and supporting business-led innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £2 million fund has been created for the Innovation Vouchers scheme, running over the next 3 years. The vouchers provide £5000 for a UK start-up, micro, small or medium-sized businesses to work with external experts and gain new knowledge to help their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra £1.1 million announced today is for companies who want to use public open data to commercialise their ideas and develop products and prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open data business innovator or inventors could use an Innovation Voucher by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;growing services and solutions using open data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing an idea into a working prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integrating open data with other data sources to develop products and prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;seeking intellectual property advice in respect of ideas incorporating open data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme is already open to businesses who want to develop ideas relating to the agri-food, built environment, space industries, energy, water and waste sectors, with a hundred vouchers allocated every 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figures from round one show that over 200 projects were successful in the draw for Innovation Vouchers for agri-food, built environment and space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the announcement, Universities and Science Minister David Willetts said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new wave of Innovation Vouchers will give SMEs a great opportunity to bid for funding that can make a real difference to the growth of their business ideas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will be able to develop exciting proposals that can make use of open data, which have the potential to unlock great value and boost economic growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="innovation-vouchers"&gt;Innovation Vouchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will be able to apply for the Innovation Vouchers directly through the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://vouchers.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt; and the Open Data Institute (ODI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business can use their Innovation Vouchers to work with knowledge suppliers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;universities and further education colleges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;research and technology organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technical consultancies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;catapult centres&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design advisers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;intellectual property advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional funding for open data vouchers comes after BIS announced this week new measures &lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-funding-to-accelerate-benefits-of-open-data-684c1.aspx"&gt;to open up access to public data&lt;/a&gt;, including a new £7.5 million Data Strategy Board Breakthrough Fund and a new £850,000 open data Immersion Programme which will assist public organisations and companies in opening up new opportunities for data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Minister-unveils-1-1-million-Innovation-boost-for-SMEs-684e3.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Minister unveils £1.1 million Innovation boost for SMEs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.innovateuk.org/"&gt;Technology Strategy Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56056</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"/>
    <title>Strategy for UK Life Sciences – One Year On</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="check-against-delivery"&gt;Check against delivery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This really is an exciting time to be discussing the prospects for life sciences in the UK. We have a positive story to tell – right up to the announcements of the past week, with more than £100 million of dedicated funding for life sciences capital in the Autumn Statement and the pioneering genomics programme confirmed by the Prime Minister in Cambridge on Monday, which comes with up to £100 million more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost two years ago, however, and the situation was rather different. Indeed, while today’s event is all about reflecting on the progress we’ve made in the past 12 months since the launch of the Government’s Strategy for UK Life Sciences, I’m like to start further back – with Pfizer’s decision to close its R&amp;amp;D operations at Sandwich. Learning of that decision in early 2011 – not so long after AstraZeneca had elected to shut its facility at Charnwood – provided the starkest of warnings. It brought home the major changes underway globally in the life sciences industry: the shift away from in-house R&amp;amp;D to external collaborations and partnerships; the increasing mobility of capital as other countries raise their game and, therefore, the need for an integrated approach to attract investment and maintain competitive advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of the Sandwich taskforce certainly taught us a great deal about the direction in which the industry is heading. And then, in June last year, the Prime Minister hosted a valuable and interesting seminar focused on life sciences which clearly demonstrated that we need to do better to make the necessary connections between our outstanding research base, our increasingly diverse life sciences sector – one featuring a growing number of SMEs – and our clinical strengths across the National Health Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was these fundamental insights that informed the preparation of the life sciences strategy published this time last year. In it, we determined to achieve three main things. The first was to dramatically improve collaboration between academia, industry and the NHS. The second was to boost the skills and pipeline of researchers, clinicians and technicians – without whom collaboration could not be properly realised. And the third was to foster the right business environment in the UK to encourage investment, so that we could translate discovery into real benefits for patients, support innovation through the translational funding gap, and remove bureaucratic barriers to the early adoption and diffusion of medical breakthroughs in the NHS. This week we published the Strategy for UK Life Sciences - One Year On report, showing lots of progress is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first of these ambitions – boosting collaboration in a stronger life sciences ecosystem – the Medical Research Council has promised £130 million for work on stratified and experimental medicine, with the first round of grant recipients in stratified medicine, announced on Monday, tackling rheumatoid arthritis, hepatitis C and Gaucher’s disease. These three awards will establish research consortia in each of these disease areas and taken in total will combine 34 academic groups and 20 industry partners with charities and patients across the UK. We are investing £1 billion per annum through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500 million in our translational research infrastructure in the NHS.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the new Biomedical Catalyst, established to bridge the gap between innovative research and actual commercialisation, is already funding some great projects: to develop a new vaccine for the hospital-acquired infection C. difficile, which currently kills around 3,000 people a year in the UK; to advance a treatment for late-stage Parkinson’s that significantly reduces patients’ time in surgery; to utilise a mobile phone app that helps people with conditions like schizophrenia and bipolar disorder to manage them more effectively on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also made good progress on our second objective to support skills and talent. We’ve seen the launch of the dedicated Technical Apprenticeship Service, confirmation of the first eight Research Professorships under the aegis of the National Institute for Health Research and the successful piloting of the Society of Biology’s degree accreditation programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are committed to our third objective of having a competitive business environment. From April 2013, the Patent Box will come into force – offering a 10 per cent corporation tax rate on profits attributable to patents. To optimise the commercial environment, we are also improving the visibility and certainty of R&amp;amp;D tax relief. We hope that the introduction of an above the line R&amp;amp;D tax credit will attract large scale investment in innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all exciting, tangible stuff – promising for patients, promising for business and job creation. What’s vital now is that the work of integration continues, refining a system that makes full and optimum use of every one of its constituent elements. Ours is a 10 year strategy – and it hinges on achieving success in all areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take public investment. The ring-fenced science settlement, agreed early on by the Coalition, was a serious commitment in these straitened times – and we have built on it since. The latest money in the Autumn Statement will build the necessary research capability for the UK to compete globally in a potential $100 billion synthetic biology market. It will fund the development of a large manufacturing facility for biologic medicines such as antibodies and vaccines – improving our marketability as the location of choice for internationally mobile life sciences companies. And it will help fund imaging and cell manufacture technologies and a clean room for the UK Regenerative Medicine Platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we pumped £42 million into the life sciences sector in 2012 through the Regional Growth Fund, matched by private investment of almost £185 million. We have committed £300 million for the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund. To secure investment, universities are required to match by at least double the amount they receive from the fund from non-public sources. There are several projects relevant to life sciences around the UK that have secured funding of almost £147 million. However, we understand in the UK that financial resource alone is not enough to make us the go-to destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On increasing the take up of medical innovation on the ground, the Office for Clinical Research Infrastructure at the NIHR - or NOCRI as it is known - is starting to connect industry to the best investigators, research facilities and technologies. We know that we also need to continue improvement in study performance and there is a new 70-day benchmark for providers of NHS services to proceed from receiving a valid research application to recruiting the first patient. It has been a condition of new NIHR contracts since December 2011, and performance against this will affect further funding as of April 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this and several other measures in the strategy, we know that we will only be able to truly assess impact once they have been fully implemented. For example, earlier this week Sir David Nicholson said we know good progress is being made at a time of great change in the NHS but more always remains to be done. There are deep-seated barriers to innovation that must be changed right at the heart of the NHS. David Nicholson and the new Commissioning Board will continue to push ahead to achieve a true culture of innovation throughout the NHS which is important to patients and business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message we’re seeking to transmit globally is that life sciences companies can do everything they need to in this country. They can, like Astellas Pharma, establish their headquarters here. They can, like Eli Lilly, conduct early-stage research here – exploiting UK-based expertise in an unusually broad range of disciplines, from clinical pharmacology to statistics and data sciences. Or, like GSK and Eisai, they can establish cutting-edge manufacturing plants on these shores. In the past year, the UK has received more than £1 billion of industry and private sector investment – from Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson, Novartis and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate our capacity for pioneering research, we will of course be taking forward the large-scale genomics project – the first attempt to exploit this technology within a mainstream health system. As the Prime Minister explained on Monday, we’ll be sequencing the entire genome of up to 100,000 patients. As patterns emerge, doctors will gain more advanced understanding of cancers and inherited diseases, enabling more targeted care. A critical feature of the project, which relates to one of my earlier comments, is how it will provide the training ground for a new generation of British geneticists and will educate the wider community in harnessing genomics technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, it is essential that international companies appreciate what’s available in the UK – the knowhow, the facilities, the opportunities to conduct clinical trials. That’s where UK Trade and Investment come in. Earlier this year, UKTI established the Life Science Investment Organisation to help connect international investors and companies with all parts of our life sciences sector. Later on at today’s event, the UKTI will launch a new global campaign highlighting the many opportunities to invest in and partner with our knowledge base, our SMEs, our manufacturers and our commercial supply chain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2012, I’m proud to report that there are over 380 pharmaceutical companies based in the UK, employing nearly 70,000 people, with an annual turnover of £30 billion. The medical technology and medical biotechnology sectors represent over 4,000 companies employing nearly 100,000 people with an annual turnover of around £20 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task ahead is to build on this solid base by encouraging more spinouts, attracting more companies from overseas and further investment. We’ll be sticking with the strategy formulated a year ago with such wise counsel from experts such as Sir John Bell, Chris Brinsmead and George Freeman – and we’ll be continually exploring ways to make the UK the best place in the world to pursue life sciences. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56230</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/life-sciences-strategy-one-year-on"/>
    <title>  Life Sciences Strategy: one year on</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the UK has generated more than £1 billion on industry and private sector investment within 12 months.  This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£500 million from GSK to build its first new manufacturing plant in almost 40 years at Ulverston in Cumbria and invest more in its two sites at Montrose and Irvine in Scotland as a direct response to the introduction of the Patent Box&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£25 million leveraged in from the private sector to bridge the ‘Valley of Death’ adding to a government commitment of £49 million to 64 projects through the Biomedical Catalyst&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£294 million through the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (&lt;abbr title="UK Research Partnership Investment Fund"&gt;UK RPIF&lt;/abbr&gt;) from businesses and charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Real progress has been made working closely with companies across the sector to ensure the measures in the strategy are making a real difference to their work and their decisions to invest in and remain in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes investing £1 billion per annum through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500 million in our translational research infrastructure in the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; to boost networks between academia, industry and the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="revolutionising-the-fight-against-cancer"&gt;Revolutionising the fight against cancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron also announced that the UK will be the first country in the world to introduce to introduce high-tech &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; mapping for cancer patients and those with rare diseases, within the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.  Up to  100,000 patients over three to five years will have their whole genome – their personal &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; code –sequenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genome profile will give doctors a new, advanced understanding of a patient’s genetic make-up, condition and treatment needs, ensuring they have access to the right drugs and personalised care far quicker than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also help to develop life-saving new drugs, treatments and scientific breakthroughs, which experts predict could significantly reduce the number of premature deaths from cancer within a generation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has earmarked £100 million: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to train a new generation of British genetic scientists to lead on the development of new drugs, treatments and cures, building the UK as the world leader in the field. And train the wider healthcare community in harnessing this technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to pump-prime &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; sequencing for cancer and rare inherited diseases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to build the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; data infrastructure to ensure that this new technology leads to better care for patients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="reaction"&gt;Reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Science and Universities David Willetts said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life sciences is one of the most truly international sectors – so if we are to continue to be a world player and compete in the global race we must do everything we can to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past year, our initiatives have attracted more than £1 billion of private sector investment to the UK. We can see clear evidence the UK is succeeding in creating the right environment to attract global investment to our shores and continue to be world leader in life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am announcing today that we are committing a further £100 million to support this sector out of the extra money for science announced by the chancellor in his Autumn Statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;David Willetts speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;Life Sciences at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;a Strategy for UK Life Sciences: One Year On’ report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/dna-tests-to-fight-cancer/"&gt;Notice: &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; tests to revolutionise fight against cancer and help 100,000 &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; patients&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47153</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-billion-investment-for-uk-science-and-research"/>
    <title>£1 billion investment for UK Science and Research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash boost comes from the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (UK RPIF), which will deliver over £1 billion to support the development of new facilities and projects in areas including life sciences, energy and advanced manufacturing. The projects announced today are:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A £48 million partnership between Manchester University, Christie Hospital and Cancer Research UK to develop the Institute for Cancer Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An £85 million partnership between UCL (University College London) and the Great Ormond Street Hospital for The Centre for Children’s Rare Disease Research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £32 million partnership between Queen’s University Belfast, The Atlantic Philanthropies and a Wellcome-Wolfson Capital Award to deliver the next phase of the Institute of Health Sciences. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £34 million partnership between the University of Nottingham and GlaxoSmithKline to support the Centre of Excellence in Sustainable Chemistry. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £38 million partnership between Swansea University, British Petroleum (BP), and TATA Steel Europe for the development of the Energy Safety Research Institute. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £60 million partnership between Brunel University, TWI and other companies to develop a National Research Centre for Structural Integrity. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £150 million partnership between Imperial College London and Voreda to contribute to the development of a major new campus adjacent to the White City regeneration area.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This takes the  total number of projects supported by the fund to 14.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities will shortly be able to bid for the remaining £80 million of public investment from the fund. This must be matched by at least double from private sources.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Willetts, Minister for Universities and Science, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is fantastic that our top businesses and top charities are queuing up to collaborate with our world-class universities. They want to work together to deliver innovation, commercialisation and growth, which will help make sure the UK competes and thrives in the global race.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The winning projects will tackle the key issues we face - like fighting disease, ensuring energy efficiency and improving infrastructure - for the benefit of all.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK RPIF was first launched with £100 million of public finance in May 2012 and, in response to the large number of high-quality bids, the Government recently tripled the public support to £300 million. All projects have to include private funding from industry or the charitable sector worth a minimum of double the public contribution - making more than £1 billion of investment in total.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UKRPIF is managed and allocated by Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE), working in collaboration with devolved counterparts.  All proposals are assessed by an independent assessment panel.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/whatwedo/rsrch/howfundr/ukresearchpartnershipinvestmentfund20122015/#d.en.72999."&gt;HEFCE’s fund details&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/More-than-1-billion-to-be-invested-in-UK-science-and-research-68276.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: More than £1 billion to be invested in UK science and research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/science"&gt;BIS Science &lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55454</id>
    <published>2012-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/uuk-conference-a-world-without-boundaries"/>
    <title>UUK conference: "A world without boundaries"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s great to join you all at Keele as our hosts celebrate their 50th anniversary. Recalling the creation of universities back in the 1960s reminds us of an optimistic sector in one of its most ambitious periods. Today, even during this era of inevitable austerity, I believe that we can still be ambitious and optimistic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-place-of-he-in-the-nation"&gt;The place of HE in the nation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 has certainly been a big year for Higher Education, with our reforms coming into effect. I recognise that inevitably some stress and uncertainty accompanies changes on this scale. The Government appreciates the maturity of the sector and the leadership of vice chancellors in what are, for some, challenging times. In particular, I appreciate the Government’s close working relationship with UUK. We cannot always agree, but our discussions are always open and founded on mutual trust. More than that, they are based on a shared belief that our universities are a tremendous national asset which we need to sustain and to grow.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In popular consciousness, of course, 2012 will be remembered for the Olympics and Paralympics - which gave our universities some excellent opportunities to demonstrate their place in national life. I congratulate UUK for illustrating the many connections between universities and the Games. We all think especially of Usain Bolt and his fellow Jamaican sprinters thanking their Birmingham University hosts after capturing all the medals in the men’s 200 metres final. But there have also been plenty of examples of volunteering and community engagement. We can all be proud of the university research which improved the performance of our athletes and the university-designed equipment which gave them a competitive edge. Now, the University of Worcester has launched a new degree programme for those wanting to study and ultimately work in disability sport.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debt of Olympians and Paralympians to HE is just one example of a wider debt of many of us to our universities. Last week, I was at the annual British science festival, sharing the excitement around the discovery of the Higgs Boson and most recently the discovery that redundant DNA is not so redundant after all. Again, British academics and universities are at the heart of these breakthroughs. With your contributions to the intellectual life of our nation, to educating the next generation, and to innovation and research, universities are more central to our society than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="protecting-our-national-assets-cyber-security"&gt;Protecting our national assets: cyber security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HE’s growing economic importance was made plain at the recent launch of the Government’s cyber security guidance because quite simply, much of the UK’s intellectual property resides in our universities. Only this month, Oxford University confirmed that its online security had been compromised by a cyber attack - just a day after the Cambridge University network experienced disruption. The Government will work closely with universities to ensure that the UK’s higher education system has a visible and credible international reputation for protecting commercially sensitive research from the growing risks posed via cyber space. But we can go further than just protection. Although UK universities are potential victims of cyber attacks, they can also be a large part of the long term solution. GCHQ, the EPSRC and BIS recently recognised eight UK universities as centres of academic excellence in cyber security. There is real scope to translate this knowledge into commercial opportunities and export earnings, while - for graduates - there are good prospects in cyber jobs as demand increases, providing of course they develop the right skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I can announce the first academic research institute - receiving total investment worth £3.8 million - to improve understanding of the science behind cyber threats. This new facility, based at UCL, will draw on university expertise in both technological and behavioural disciplines. Academic teams from UCL, Imperial, Newcastle and Royal Holloway will be the first beneficiaries of research money. The institute opens for business next month. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-kinds-of-impact"&gt;Other kinds of “impact”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, part of the case for well-funded universities - as suggested by the example of cyber security - is their economic benefit. But I readily acknowledge that this is not what drives many academics, for whom intellectual curiosity is the main motive. It is a noble motive, which must be respected. However, it does help when academics and universities demonstrate how their research contributes to a strong economy and a good society. We are supporting this crucial work.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can announce today that we are providing an extra £6 million for the Higher Education Innovation Funding to be shared amongst a number of universities to assist them in further driving growth, creating and supporting innovative enterprises and building strategic relationships.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Research Excellence Framework will, for the first time, recognise the highest levels of research excellence with reward for the past impact that it has achieved. I know that you are currently busy preparing impact case studies for the REF - and that you will all be aware of the breadth of “impact” that this encompasses. It is not about “commercialisation” but more widely anything which has an effect on, changes or benefits the economy, society, culture, public policy or services, health, the environment or quality of life.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The REF is an assessment of research excellence. It is not about “journal rankings” or “journal impact factors”. Whether the research output has been published in an open access journal, a traditional publication, or even if it hasn’t been published in any journal at all, this does not affect the assessment of its quality in the REF. REF panels will not make use of “journal impact factors”, rankings or lists, nor the perceived standing of the publisher, in assessing the quality of research outputs. An underpinning principle of the REF is that all types of research and all forms of research output shall be assessed on a fair and equal basis by experts in the relevant disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-access"&gt;Open access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, we have also announced that we are shifting to open access for publicly funded research published in these peer reviewed journals - following the excellent report from Janet Finch, the former vice chancellor of this university. Removing pay walls will have real economic and social benefits. Still, we understand that making the transition to “gold” open access has a cost - roughly one per cent of the national science and research budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I announced an extra £10 million to be allocated to our 30 most research intensive universities to assist with the costs. This is in addition to the contribution RCUK will be making to institutions to support payment of article processing charges associated with open access, through block funding grants from next April onwards. We’ll be providing more detail on this soon, and the UK Funding Councils will launch a consultation on setting a requirement that research outputs submitted to any REF should be as widely accessible as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="he-and-philanthropy"&gt;HE and philanthropy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another report, published only yesterday by HEFCE, I particularly commend to you. I took Professor Shirley Pearce’s excellent Review of Philanthropy in UK Higher Education on holiday with me, and very much enjoyed reading it - sad but true.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been substantial momentum since Eric Thomas’s excellent 2004 report. The matched funding pot has meant that many more universities and colleges have been able to attract philanthropic gifts over recent years, and voluntary giving has improved across the piece.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these financially strapped times a challenge for every institution is to diversify its income streams and develop strategies to stimulate donations- to position their institution as an attractive proposition. Both BIS and HEFCE will be giving the report’s recommendations serious attention. Shirley and her team have made many telling observations, including on donor behaviour. We will be guided on your views. We do need to remind people of the charitable status of many university activities. If the option of a charity number for a university would help, we can take it up with the Charity Commission. And it is right philanthropy is properly recognised in honours system, so do put people forward to us and the Cabinet Office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-new-fees-regime"&gt;The new fees regime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is the month when the first students will arrive at university under the new fees regime. I believe the financing changes, despite the controversy, are in the best interests of universities, students, and the nation. As the Institute of Fiscal Studies concluded over the summer, the new regime is “substantially more progressive” than the previous system - with the poorest 30 per cent of graduates set to pay back less over their lifetimes. The IFS noted that universities will receive more money to invest in education, while taxpayers will save around £2,500 per graduate. And we are proud of the extra financial support for part-time students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in constrained circumstances the reforms achieve three crucial objectives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we have saved money for the Exchequer without reducing the cash flowing to our universities. In 2011-12, the sum of teaching grant and student loan money reaching institutions was £7.2 billion. In 2012-13, it is £7.4 billion. The indicative figure for 2013-14 is £7.9 billion. That is not bad in these austere times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is more competition and choice for the benefit of students. Under the new funding system, students still receive public funding. We have to predict and control this cost, so - like every previous government - we have to maintain student number controls. But we favour relaxing these controls for individual universities within an overall total, so that more students can go to whichever university wants to accept them. We favour maximum possible choice for students, to accommodate for example those who may want to study locally, and those who may want to choose an institution offering lower tuition charges. We are moving from a world in which each institution is allocated a fixed number of students to what is indeed a more open and competitive system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, the AAB and core/margin policies seek to move towards those objectives, within the fiscal constraints we face. We asked HEFCE to implement them, including making the best assumptions they could about numbers. In order to set the necessary rules in a competitive system, the assumptions had to be fixed in advance.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is still too early to know fully what the outcome has been, and how students are responding. It looks as if there may have been fewer pupils achieving predicted AAB grades at “A” level, but rather more getting top grades in equivalent high-class vocational qualifications, such as BTECs. The net result may be total numbers getting AAB or equivalent which are closer to 80,000 than to 85,000, which was HEFCE’s best estimate. Different institutions will have been affected differently; that is inevitable when making significant changes, which are intended to take greater account of student choice. I recognise this comes at a time when there have been other pressures too. The number of 18 year olds is falling. Demand is unusually depressed this year because more students went straight to university last year, missing out a gap year. And more may be delaying until next year when ABB kicks in. The evidence from the Labour government’s changes in 2006 is that individual institutions can face a temporary jolt when changes like this are introduced. All this creates real pressures for some institutions. But HEFCE will take this year’s outcomes into account as it implements the changes we announced for 13/14, in the shape of a move to ABB or equivalent, plus a more flexible margin policy.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third objective to which the reforms contribute is the greater information becoming available to prospective students - what I consider to be the final piece in the jigsaw. The Which guide has only just gone live, and I was pleased to attend the launch. Later this month we will be launching new Key Information Set data - which will also be available on university websites and on the updated Unistats site, enabling comparisons among institutions. The key indicators and summary information for students are unquestionably a force for good, but they are certainly not perfect and we should strive to improve them. HEFCE will carry out a comprehensive review of the student information landscape starting next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-revolution-in-teaching"&gt;A revolution in teaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add all this together and we’re looking at what amounts to a revolution in teaching - the largest cultural change in our universities for a generation. Research has been the primary focus of attention for a long time; it’s time for teaching to be in the spotlight as well. In 2010 two important reports were published - not just Lord Browne’s but also Graham Gibbs’s conclusions on how to measure teaching quality. It’s also worth remembering, as we approach the 50th anniversary of the Robbins report, that Robbins himself was preoccupied with teaching quality. I met Claus Moser earlier this year, one of Robbins’s key researchers alongside Richard Layard, and he confirmed that teaching was uppermost in their minds.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keele, of course, put heavy store by teaching from the very beginning. Indeed, the 1964 Hale report on “University Teaching Methods” found that it was, at one time, the only institution with a Research Fellow on university teaching. I am also glad to acknowledge that the NUS, whose 90th anniversary we marked last night, has long campaigned about the quality of teaching.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now universities really do need to focus on the excellence of their teaching. At the end of this new term there will be many students returning home whose parents will be asking what they got for £3000. How crowded were the seminars? What were the labs like? How many essays did you write? How much academic feedback did you get? Every university in this room needs to be confident your students will have good answers to those questions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An environment that focuses on engaging students in their academic study means that those students are continually encouraged to apply themselves. I hope that applicants will make full use of the KIS data in figuring out which institutions can offer the most appropriate teaching environment for their individual needs - and that universities will adjust to student- and parent-power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="student-numbers"&gt;Student numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbins, of course, is most associated with expansion of the sector, even though that was partly set in train before he reported, as Keele perfectly illustrates. Perhaps we can best view the history of our HE sector as successive waves of expansion - a progressive interpretation that I welcome. There are periods between the waves where consolidation is the order of the day - like the current one where the number of 18-year-olds is in decline - making the raw UCAS application figures somewhat misleading. However, I believe that more growth will come and universities can rise to the challenge of proving Kingsley Amis wrong in his sour prognostication that “More will mean worse”.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed various surveys show that the number of young people aspiring to go to university has increased steadily over the past 10 years. The most recent Sutton Trust survey, published in April this year, encouragingly showed that around three quarters of year 10 to 12 pupils were likely to apply to university with a similar proportion of those in year 13 actually applying. According to the Millennium cohort study, 97 per cent of mothers want their children to go to university. I’m also very encouraged by the evidence that increased fees are not putting off young people from poor backgrounds - with a recorded fall of just 0.2 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="improving-access"&gt;Improving access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the more reason to welcome Les Ebdon, who has now started work as the Director of Fair Access. OFFA has additional resources to support as well as challenge institutions. Vince Cable and I wrote to HEFCE and OFFA in May, asking them to develop a shared strategy for promoting access which maximises the impact of all spending by Government, HEFCE and institutions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much going on now that it is right to assess what works best to widen participation and broaden access, taking into account the latest available evidence here and abroad.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes it is right for institutions to seek to broaden access because real meritocracy means making sure talent is spotted, not wasted. Individuals must be considered on their merits, and institutions’ procedures must be, as we say in the White Paper, “fair, transparent and evidence-based”. And we all understand the Director’s duty to protect academic freedom, including an institution’s right to decide who to admit and on what basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-providers--vat"&gt;New providers &amp;amp; VAT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the HE sector grows it needs to continue to be open to new types of provider. It always has been. Represented here today are universities that can trace their origins back to ancient foundations, mechanics institutes, Anglican teaching colleges, Colleges of Advanced Technology - all of which took a different route to university status. This year we have eased number limits and I hope as a result we will see at least 10 smaller institutions calling themselves universities for the first time - including alternative providers, so long as they are of the necessary standard.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, HMRC published a consultation on extending the VAT exemption to for-profit providers of HE. Currently, the majority of these providers cannot benefit from this exemption in the same way that not-for profit providers can. This potentially puts them at a competitive disadvantage in the market and runs counter to our vision of a more level playing field for all. I welcome this opportunity to review such treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-strategy-and-education-exports"&gt;Industrial strategy and education exports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Vince Cable launched our industrial strategy on Tuesday, we identified education as one of the key sectors of the future. Our universities, for one, are internationally recognised. We can do more to take advantage of our position.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are a great British export industry, and in a growing market - in 2000 there were just over 2 million students worldwide studying outside their own countries. Ten years later this had doubled to 4 million. By 2020 it is predicted to be around 7 million. Our education exports are already worth around £14 billion, and could rise to around £20 billion in 2020 and nearly £27 billion in 2025, representing an annual growth rate of approximately 5 per cent.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our key economic partners of the future like Turkey, Indonesia, Brazil are experiencing a surge in the number of young people. They are keen to invest in this generation through more HE at home and more opportunities abroad. That is why HE now has such an important role in our trade missions. Earlier this year, vice chancellors accompanied the PM and me to Asia. We’re going to Brazil later this month.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for UK education overseas extend significantly beyond teaching students. For example, other countries are attracted to the expertise that UK institutions can offer in governance models, professional development and curricular design; construction, management and financing. Some foreign education systems, particularly in emerging markets, have complex needs. For them, we are adopting a new approach, which we are calling “system-to-system” - facilitated and coordinated by the UK Government. Under this umbrella, the new UK Education Services will identify opportunities, then initiate and mobilise consortia to win the contracts. It could include higher education, further education and schools, as well as a range of non-education specific services. I am taking a delegation on a system-to-system education export mission to Colombia and Mexico later this year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system-to-system approach is not about replacing or duplicating the many excellent initiatives underway. But system-to-system supplements the bilateral opportunities already undertaken by many institutions and other organisations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overseas students travelling to the UK to study is just one way we can grow. Last year 400,000 overseas students came to the UK to study. But for the first time this was exceeded by the record 500,000 people who benefitted from British higher education while living abroad. I salute the trail blazers like Nottingham, Liverpool Reading, UCL and Newcastle with campuses abroad. On a recent visit to the US I was struck by the surge of activity in distance learning. We may be at a tipping point in distance learning as technology offers more efficient and more effective ways of online learning than ever before. We will be doing more work on this in BIS over the months ahead as I believe these forms of education are really going to take off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visas-and-the-situation-at-london-met"&gt;Visas and the situation at London Met&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few sectors of our economy with the capacity to grow and generate export earnings as great as higher education. Every overseas student on average pays fees of about £10,000 a year and spends almost as much while they are here. That means 400,000 overseas students bring in almost £8 billion a year. They make a big contribution to the economies of cities like Bradford and Exeter and Manchester, as well as London.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not allow the London Met issues to jeopardise this success story. I am grateful to the whole sector for its prompt, coordinated and effective response to the UKBA’s decision to remove London Met’s tier 4 sponsor licence. Both UUK and the NUS are playing a full role in the London Met task force that I set up within hours UKBA’s announcement. Individual universities are offering places for the mini clearing operation that goes live next Monday.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not lose sight of the individual students who are most affected by the current situation and we must maintain confidence across the world in the fair deal for overseas students. They may face costs of moving to alternative accommodation and costs of applying for a new visa. So I can announce today that we are setting up a £2 million fund to help legitimate overseas students at London Met who face extra costs through no fault of their own as a result of transferring to another institution. This will provide certainty to London Met students at what is a stressful and unsettling time.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope no other institution will face a similar situation in future. But it makes sense for the sector to plan now for how it would manage that risk if it did arise - we need to underline the message to students and potential students and their families that the UK is a safe and welcoming destination. There are examples of protection schemes in other countries and in other sectors - the ABTA scheme is one obvious example. So I very much welcome UUK’s willingness to develop proposals for a sector-led response to discuss with all its members. I look forward to seeing the results of that work.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must go further to protect our international reputation in the short-term too. We have already used Foreign Office posts to signal that we remain open to overseas students and I have agreed with your President, Eric Thomas, that we will jointly author an article to offer to key newspapers in our target markets explaining that overseas students are welcome here, and reminding them of what a great opportunity it is to study in UK.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year, countries around the world send their best and brightest here to learn. When they come, they bring with them the potential to add a rich and diverse cultural scene to many of our towns and cities. They bring a great opportunity to make our courses more international in scope and to contribute to enabling a well-rounded education for our home students. This is a globalised world, and our people should consider themselves privileged to be exposed to such talented people from all its corners. Without international students, we would not only be poorer economically - we would also be more boring, more insular, and more ignorant of the wider world.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why transparency in the immigration statistics is vital. We therefore want to publicise disaggregated figures so that the debate can be better informed. The ONS is planning improvements in its methodology so that in future it will be possible to better identify students in the emigration flows.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make clear the attitude of the government. There is no limit on the number of legitimate students from overseas studying at British universities. They have to have the language skills and the academic training to benefit from Higher Education here. It is in everyone’s interest to maintain our high standards. The vast majority of international students are here legitimately, study hard, contribute to our economy, and take nothing from us except a world-class education. Where things are working at their best, they also make us more cosmopolitan, sustain links between our communities with heritage in other parts of the world and those places, and make the higher education offer more diverse than it otherwise would be. It is crucial that we sustain and develop these advantages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition believes in our great higher education institutions. Whenever David Cameron is listing our great national assets, he puts our universities high on the list. We are proud of our international reputation. We are proud so many students from around the world want to come and study here. We are proud that the lives of so many British people are transformed by the opportunity to study at our great universities. And everything we know about our culture, the needs of our economy, and the aspirations of our young people tells us that our universities will have an even greater role in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://disqus.com/?ref_noscript=deptforbusinessinnovationandskills"&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="external" href="http://disqus.com"&gt;blog comments powered by Disqus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47126</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/london-metropolitan-universitys-licence-revoked"/>
    <title>London Metropolitan University's licence revoked</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;30 Aug 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 29 August 2012, the Tier 4 sponsor licence of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/sitecontent/newsarticles/2012/august/28-LMU-revoked1"&gt;London Metropolitan University (London Met) was revoked&lt;/a&gt; due to non-compliance with its sponsorship duties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision was made following a period of suspension and audits of the University’s student records by UKBA which identified a number of serious breaches of their sponsor duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Met students with a current valid visa do not immediately face a change in their migrant status. They will receive direct information from the UK Border Agency to inform them of changes to their status.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS are convening a task force to be lead by HEFCE, which will include UUK, UKBA and the NUS, to work with London Met to support affected students and enable genuine students to find another institution at which they can continue their studies in the UK. The task force will start work immediately to protect the interests of these students.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government recognises the important contribution that international students make to the UK, and is committed to keeping our education system one of the best in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome all genuine and legitimate students, and there is no cap on the number of international students who can be accepted to study in the UK. We fully appreciate the economic benefits and wider enrichment these students bring to the UK. We want to encourage students to come and study at our world-class academic institutions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities Minister David Willetts announced the formation of a task force to help overseas students affected by the decision:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is important that genuine students who are affected through no fault of their own are offered prompt advice and help, including, if necessary, with finding other institutions at which to finish their studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have asked HEFCE to lead a task force, which will include UUK, UKBA and the NUS, to work with London Metropolitan University to support affected students and enable them to continue their studies in the UK. The task force will start work immediately.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said that the decision affected only London Metropolitan University which had had its licence to sponsor non-EU students revoked. Britain remains a top class destination for international students, and welcomes them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognise that there are concerns for legitimate overseas students who will be affected and London Metropolitan University has set up a Help Centre to support and advise students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number is +44 (0) 20 7133 4141 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;UK Border Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Home Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmet.ac.uk/"&gt;London Metropolitan University&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47122</id>
    <published>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/a-level-results-and-the-start-of-clearing"/>
    <title>A-Level results and the start of Clearing</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;16 Aug 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/corporate/images/ministers/willetts-100x140.jpg?w=100&amp;amp;h=140&amp;amp;as=1" alt="David Willetts"&gt;“Congratulations to all those receiving their A-Level results today. I know how hard students have worked to achieve these results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Students are benefiting from a more diverse and competitive higher education sector. So there is a good choice of high quality courses. We have also introduced more flexibility into the system by allowing open recruitment of AAB students so that they can access the university of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Already more than 350,000 applicants have achieved the grades they need and are now off to university. For those who don’t get the results they had hoped for, there are still many other options out there. There are over 25,000 courses with vacancies in clearing so it is worth looking to see what is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Alternatively I would encourage students to consider studying part time or perhaps pursue an apprenticeship. You can also choose to reapply next year. Under our new reforms graduates will have to make a greater contribution towards the cost for their degree, but there will be more generous financial support available while you study and fairer repayment arrangements when you leave university.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/David-Willetts-congratulates-A-Level-students-67eb9.aspx"&gt;BIS press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/inthenews/inthenews/a00212869/nick-gibb-congratulates-students-on-their-a-level-results-"&gt;DfE press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ucas.com/about_us/media_enquiries/media_releases/2012/resultsdayupdate"&gt;UCAS press notice - Results day update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/EducationAndLearning/UniversityAndHigherEducation/StudentFinance/Typesoffinance/index.htm"&gt;Student finance 2012/13: what money can you get?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47116</id>
    <published>2012-07-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research"/>
    <title>Government to open up publicly funded research</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;16 Jul 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has announced that it will make publicly funded scientific research available for anyone to read for free, accepting recommendations in a report on open access by Dame Janet Finch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will likely see a major increase in the number of taxpayer-funded research papers freely available to the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science Minister David Willetts said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Removing paywalls that surround taxpayer funded research will have real economic and social benefits. It will allow academics and businesses to develop and commercialise their research more easily and herald a new era of academic discovery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This development will provide exciting new opportunities and keep the UK at the forefront of global research to drive innovation and growth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s decision is outlined in a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/science/docs/l/12-975-letter-government-response-to-finch-report-research-publications.pdf"&gt;formal response (PDF, 90 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; to recommendations made in the Finch Report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="better-access-for-the-public"&gt;Better access for the public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently most formally published research is only available behind restricted paywalls. Reforms will see publications opened up to a greater audience, providing more opportunities for research and development across a range of sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also support the commercial exploitation of research, contributing to the Government’s economic growth agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the recommendations that have been accepted by the Government are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving to deliver open access through a ‘gold’ model, where article processing-charges are paid upfront to cover the cost of publication. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walk-in rights for the general public, so they can have free access to global research publications owned by members of the UK Publishers’ Association, via public libraries. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the licensing of access enjoyed by universities to high technology businesses for a modest charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The details of how these measures should be developed will be worked on by funders in consultation with universities, research institutions, authors and publishers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Aug - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publishers.org.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=2299:finch-willetts-rcuk-green-oa-and-embargoes&amp;amp;catid=503:pa-press-releases-and-comments&amp;amp;Itemid=1618"&gt;Explanatory note on public Open Access policy by the Publishers’ Association&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Government-to-open-up-publicly-funded-research-67d1d.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Government to open up publicly funded research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/science/docs/l/12-975-letter-government-response-to-finch-report-research-publications.pdf"&gt;Government response to the Finch Report (PDF, 90 Kb) &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.researchinfonet.org/publish/finch/"&gt;Report of the Working Group on Expanding Access to Published Research Findings - the Finch Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/media/news/2012news/Pages/120716.aspx"&gt;Research Councils UK - RCUK announces new Open Access policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/news/newsarchive/2012/statementonimplementingopenaccess"&gt;Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE) statement on implementing open access &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hefce.ac.uk/news/newsarchive/2012/name,73613,en.html"&gt;HEFCE press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/science"&gt;Science policy at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55452</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/space-a-new-direction"/>
    <title>Space - A new direction</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning, everyone - and let me add a personal welcome to our distinguished guests today: Francesco Profumo, Enrico Saggesse, Vladimir Popovkin and of course Jean Jacques Dordain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be back at Farnborough as we celebrate 50 years of the UK in space. It was back in 1962 that the UKs first satellite, Ariel 1 was launched third after the USA and the then USSR. It was the start of a major home-grown industry and a true British success story. And I was delighted that, 50 years to the day, on April 26th 2012, the UK signed a £300 million contract to build the Solar Orbiter - a pioneering project to better understand how the Sun affects the Earth. It was the largest single contract placed by ESA with the UK space industry in two decades, and a great way to mark a half century of scientific and technological advancement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than surveying the past five decades, allow me to highlight some of the progress achieved in the UK since the formation of the UK Space Agency in 2011. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Agency has done a fine job carrying forward the Innovation and Growth Strategy agreed with industry through the Space Leadership Council. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Satellite technology is now an integral part of the Government’s policy for broadband delivery in rural and hot spot areas. Public investment of around £40 million in satellite broadband technologies has leveraged more than £500 million of capital funds from the market to deliver UK-owned and UK-operated services. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The space cluster in Harwell, the ESA facility is up and running - and the joint ESA/UK business incubator has met its first-year target of establishing 10 new companies. There are in fact 12 firms now located there, with a further three about to join them. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further evidence of UK progress came only yesterday, with the announcement that leading US company Aerojet is to create a facility in Northern Ireland - and several dozen new jobs - to build rocket thrusters for satellites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the research side, we’ve had the first results from Cryosat that quantify the polar ice sheets - a major step towards understanding the rate of long-term change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve just delivered to NASA the first instrument for the James Webb Space Telescope - the giant successor to Hubble. And, thanks to UK expertise, we can look forward to the Planck satellite delivering a detailed map of the echoes of the Big Bang - showing the first structures in the Universe more than 13 billion years ago.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, perhaps, the space sector continues to buck general economic trends. Today, we are announcing the latest update on the size and health of the UK industry - and it’s very encouraging. The report shows that growth remains positive at an average of 7.5 per cent over the latest period surveyed - with downstream business doing particularly well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sector was worth £9.1billion in 2010/11 - compared to £7.5 billion in 2008/09 - and is providing jobs for 29,000 skilled workers. Space is one of the UK’s key high-tech growth industries. I fully expect this growth trajectory to continue, as UK industry breaks into new markets and seizes more export opportunities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space-related technologies are advancing at a substantial pace - nowhere more so, arguably, than in launch systems. This is an area where the likes of Virgin Galactic and potentially the Skylon space plane being developed by Reaction Engines’s could be game changers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, it appears, is sticking with SpaceX’s traditional launcher model, while our Russian colleagues here continue to provide a valuable service through Soyuz. This presents an opportunity for us to seize the advantage in terms of both technology and regulation. Space tourism and commercial space are just beyond the horizon.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at present, in my view, Europe is not ready to grab this opportunity - and we must not lose out. We must formulate a regulatory framework that will allow reusable aircraft-type launchers to operate here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that Reaction Engines are making a significant announcement this afternoon regarding progress on their pre-cooler technology. Their SABRE engine already represents 30 years of incredible British R&amp;amp;D. It’s a remarkable world first, and the pace at which they’re advancing illustrates the urgency of laying the appropriate groundwork now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why i can announce today that I will be working with Justine Greening at the Department for Transport, to determine how the UK, indeed the whole of Europe, can best position itself to take advantage of space plane activities. We’ll be exploring the type of certification needed for space crafts and identifying the essential characteristics of an operational spaceport. Antonio Tajani, European Competition Commissioner has also agreed to pursue this matter with the European Air Safety Agency.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area where I’m keen to see further progress is at Harwell. Besides the positive news emerging from the business incubator, my department has funded the development of the International Space Innovation Centre, and last year’s £10 million investment in the National Space Technology Programme has brought in an extra £17 million from other sources. Some 50 new projects are underway as a result, from designing giant telecommunications satellites to testing “green” rocket propellants compliant with future safety requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m therefore delighted to announce today that the Satellite Applications Catapult will also be located at Harwell. The Catapult will give real impetus to commercial development from our space assets. Today we are also announcing the Technology Strategy Board delivery programme. From its £250 million budget for speeding up innovation in priority areas over the coming financial year, up to £10 million will be allocated to space.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture, of course, is making sure that space continues to be a key enabler of economic growth - and that’s the central goal of the revised Civil Space Strategy that I am publishing here today. The document, covering the next four years, focuses on creating new opportunities for industry, bolstering the role of space in the UK’s infrastructure and furthering the National Space Technology Programme. As such, it reflects the themes I’ve covered today, like regulating commercial space and improving knowledge of how the planet is changing, as well as addressing skills and training issues. It certainly captures the breadth of activity falling within the Space Agency’s remit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to security matters, I recently met with colleagues in France and we agreed that space situational awareness - addressing the small but growing risk of satellites crashing into each other or colliding with other debris - is a growing issue. This is an area where we’ve tended to rely on the USA for information, but the UK does need to consider taking responsibility for managing its own issues. This is important in the context of our own satellites and those we share with European partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the recent conclusion of the Wimbledon championships, I note that the smallest object we can currently track in low Earth orbit is equivalent to a spotting a tennis ball at a distance of 3,000 kilometres - making the undoubted powers of Hawkeye technology in SW19 seem rather humdrum by comparison. It’s vital that the UK has the capability to predict potential collisions with space debris or other satellites, and the Space Agency - together with other government departments - will be determining the scope of that capability in ways that are complementary to both our US and our European friends.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by looking forward to November, because 2012 is an important year for ESA, with the ministerial council taking place in Italy. The backdrop for the meeting is inevitably uncertain, given Europe’s current economic troubles. Nevertheless, as I await advice on the UK position from the Space Leadership Council, I hope we can reach a point that will see the role of ESA strengthened in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also several important European-wide programmes which will require attention - not least the ESA missions to Mars in 2016 and 2018, for which our council hosts are also our major European partner. I am pleased that we now have a viable way ahead for Exomars, following NASA’s withdrawal from the project last year. I repeat my gratitude to the Russians for stepping into the breach - and to the other ESA member states currently rethinking priorities so that this mission can proceed. From a UK perspective, I’m looking forward to saying that our export drive - courtesy of Astrium - has extended to other parts of the solar system.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only remains for me to hand you over to my co-chair on the UK’s Space Leadership Council, Andy Green.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47103</id>
    <published>2012-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/england-to-be-best-in-world-for-university-business-collaboration"/>
    <title>England to be best in world for university business collaboration</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;26 Jun 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the review of university-business collaboration by Professor Tim Wilson, David Willetts has announced new plans to strengthen that collaboration.  This will include improvements to the regime for sandwich courses, promotion of a new framework for business and universities to work together, and ensuring a better fit between graduates and jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s plans include:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting the Council for Industry and Higher Education (CIHE) to create a National Centre for Universities and Business. The centre will focus on strengthening the strategic partnership between universities and business with a view to driving economic growth and recovery. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stimulating student demand for sandwich courses by instituting a 15 per cent cap on fees for a sandwich year. This more reasonably reflects the costs of a sandwich place year and will encourage universities to invest in and expand sandwich course provision. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending the Graduate Talent Pool service for a further three years. This is a high-quality online resource that brings together graduates and businesses, and advertises internship vacancies, which now includes a strict quality assurance process. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with graduate employers to promote fair recruitment and the use of new more detailed records of student achievement.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/England-to-be-the-best-place-in-the-world-for-business-university-collaboration-67bdd.aspx"&gt;Read the Press Notice in full: England to be the best place in the world for business-university collaboration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/higher-education/docs/f/12-903-following-up-wilson-business-university-collaboration-next-steps"&gt;Government Response to the Wilson Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/further-education-skills/docs/w/12-610-wilson-review-business-university-collaboration.pdf"&gt;The Wilson Review&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
