<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/david-cameron</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/david-cameron.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon David Cameron MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-01T09:18:16+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60959</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:18:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:18:16+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-uks-g8-priorities"/>
    <title>The UK's G8 priorities</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK's G8 Presidency will be an economic G8 that deals with big issues in the global economy and prioritises trade, tax and transparency.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK takes over the one-year Presidency of the G8 today (1 January) and will hold the annual leaders’ summit in Northern Ireland on 17 and 18 June. As the chair of the G8, the UK has a unique opportunity to lead in shaping the outcomes of the summit and taking concrete action with other G8 countries to address some of the world’s most pressing challenges, including important economic and foreign policy issues of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has announced that he will focus the G8 in 2013 on 3 key areas: open economies, open governments and open societies to unleash the power of the private sector by advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="trade"&gt;Trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no greater stimulus for growth in the world economy than trade and no more important battle than the fight against protectionism. The G8 has collective responsibility to drive forward trade liberalisation. Among G8 countries work is already on going to prepare a free trade agreement between the EU and Canada and work will start next year to begin free trade negotiations between the EU and Japan and the EU and US. An EU-US free trade agreement would be particularly significant – the EU and US together make up nearly a third of all global trade and an ambitious deal between the two could provide an enormous boost to jobs and growth. The G8 leaders’ summit will be an opportunity to show the importance of this ongoing work and to agree how to accelerate progress across our common trade priorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="tax"&gt;Tax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will focus on strengthening international tax standards and working on greater international tax information exchange to tackle tax havens.  This will build on work that is already underway in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) and maintain the momentum set by the G20. And we will work with developing countries to enable them to collect tax that is due to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transparency"&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 has a long history of advancing the development agenda - and the UK’s G8 Presidency will be no different. The UK is meeting its commitment to spend 0.7 per cent of its gross national income on aid from 2013 and will hold other countries to account for their promises too. With this track record on aid, the Prime Minister plans to use the G8 Presidency to support the ‘golden thread’ of conditions that he sees as critical to the growth and prosperity of countries across the world. These include the absence of conflict, clamping down on corruption and ensuring strong and accountable government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency and accountability are vitally important to achieve these conditions. Too often, development at the G8 has been about rich countries doing things to poor countries. But at Lough Erne the G8 will focus on getting its own house in order and helping developing countries to prosper in the process. An example of this is mineral wealth. It’s important that developing countries rich in minerals see this as a blessing not a curse. The UK is already leading efforts in the EU that will require oil, gas and mining companies to publish key financial information for each country and project they work on. The UK’s G8 Presidency will push for greater transparency all around the globe so that revenues from oil, gas and mining are transparent. This should encourage greater accountability and ensure money doesn’t fuel conflict and corruption, but instead is used to provide better public services for citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined action on trade, tax and transparency during the UK’s G8 Presidency could lay the foundations of long-term growth and prosperity for generations to come and will support the development of open economies, open governments and open societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s G8 Presidency will also make progress across a range of vital global issues, including foreign policy challenges and supporting Arab Spring countries. The UK’s Presidency will also build on the Olympic Hunger Summit and the US’s New Alliance for Food Security and Nutrition, leading the way in the battle against hunger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this year the UK will also produce a comprehensive accountability report (CAR) that will show progress against key commitments made by the G8. The report is a concrete example of transparency and accountability at work, a central theme of the UK’s G8 Presidency, and an opportunity to hold G8 leaders to account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.linkedin.com/today/post/article/20121121130535-146036479-eyes-of-the-world-on-uk-again-for-g8-summit"&gt;Read the Prime Minister’s recent article on the G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60960</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:17:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue"/>
    <title>Lough Erne: G8 venue</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year's G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2013 the UK will hold the Presidency of the G8. As part of the year-long Presidency there will be a G8 Summit of the 8 global leaders in June. The Prime Minister has chosen to hold this year’s G8 Summit at Lough Erne, County Fermanagh, in Northern Ireland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing the G8 to Lough Erne will showcase to the world a modern Northern Ireland with huge potential for investment and tourism, demonstrating the growing confidence that exists in this part of the UK. It will highlight what Northern Ireland, its people and its businesses have to offer the global community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The venue of Lough Erne 2013 was also chosen because it creates the right conditions to encourage open and frank discussions between the G8 leaders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to welcoming my fellow leaders to Lough Erne and to showcase Northern Ireland to the world as a modern and dynamic part of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Northern Ireland’s transformation over the last 2 decades was made possible by the courage of so many people across sections of the community. Their determination and leadership has inspired the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60958</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:16:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/what-is-the-g8"/>
    <title>What is the G8?</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The G8 is a forum that brings together 8 global leaders to address global issues and tackle the most pressing global challenges.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The G8 (Group of 8) is made up of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Russia, the USA and the UK. The EU is represented by Jose Manuel Barroso, the President of the European Commission, and Herman Van Rompuy, the President of the European Council. The Presidency of the G8 rotates each calendar year and the country holding the G8 Presidency is responsible for hosting and organising the annual summit, with a number of preparatory meetings leading up to it. The summit is an opportunity for G8 leaders to have frank and open discussions about the important global issues of the day. In 2013 it will be the UK’s turn to shape the G8’s approach to these discussions with G8 leaders holding each other to account and agreeing concrete steps to advance growth and prosperity across the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="history-of-the-g8"&gt;History of the G8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1973 the world experienced its worst economic crisis since the Great Depression. The finance ministers of the USA, UK, France and West Germany met informally to talk about how they could solve the economic problems linked with the oil price shock. In 1974 Japan was invited to the meetings and in 1975 the French President brought these informal discussions to the leaders. He also invited Italy to what was the first G6 in Rambouillet, France. There was no army of political advisers in tow, just the leaders in a relaxed and private setting. This low-key formula was very successful and the leaders agreed to meet annually. A year later Canada joined and after the collapse of the Soviet Union, Russia became a full member in 1998. The EU has been part of the group since 1977, but does not hold a Presidency. Almost 40 years on, the G8 countries can provide guidance and stability in an unpredictable world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-presidency-involve"&gt;What does the Presidency involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 Presidency runs for 1 calendar year and rotates among the 8 member countries. The country chairing the Presidency is responsible for shaping the issues that leaders discuss at the G8 Summit and hosts a number of preparatory meetings leading up to the summit. It also acts as the spokesperson for the G8. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Presidency is an opportunity for the UK to influence the international debate on our global priorities, which include tax, trade and transparency. At the end of this year, the UK will hand over the Presidency to Russia for 2014. The Presidency will continue in its rotation to Germany in 2015, Japan in 2016, Italy in 2017, Canada in 2018, France in 2019, and the USA in 2020 before it returns to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-does-the-g8-do"&gt;What does the G8 do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G8 is a forum that provides the opportunity for its members to co-operate in addressing global challenges. The standards it sets, commitments it makes and steps it takes aim to drive prosperity and economic growth all over the world. Prime Minister David Cameron has said that this year the G8 will return to its roots, creating the right environment for frank and open discussions to promote growth and address global economic problems. There will be a short declaration aimed at holding G8 leaders to account and ensuring that good intentions become vital actions to advance growth and prosperity across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60961</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T09:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T09:14:59+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-events"/>
    <title>G8 events</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>During the UK G8 Presidency 2013 there will be events in addition to the leaders' summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="g8-foreign-ministers-meeting"&gt;G8 foreign ministers’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 and 11 April 2013, the Foreign Secretary William Hague will host his counterparts from the G8 countries. They will meet for the G8 foreign ministers’ meeting at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Foreign Secretary said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to the UK’s G8 Presidency making headway on the serious challenges facing our global community today. Today the Prime Minister explained that by supporting the development of open economies, open governments and open societies we can harness the power of the private sector for everyone’s benefit. Our G8 priorities of advancing trade, ensuring tax compliance and promoting greater transparency can only take place in an environment of political stability and peaceful international relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With my G8 foreign minister partners, I look forward to discussing and taking decisions on some of the most pressing foreign and security policy issues that we face. In particular I will be focusing on the Preventing Sexual Violence Initiative, a personal priority for me during the UK’s G8 Presidency and beyond, and ensuring that the G8’s Deauville Partnership provides the support needed by our partners in the Arab world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g7-finance-ministers-and-central-bank-governors-meeting"&gt;G7 finance ministers’ and Central Bank governors’ meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 10 to 11 May 2013, the Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne and the Governor of the Bank of England Sir Mervyn King will host a spring meeting of the G7 finance ministers and Central Bank governors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On announcing the meeting, the Chancellor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to hosting colleagues from the G7 to Britain in the spring. This group remains an important institution and a key forum in which to grapple with the challenges that face the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This meeting will be a significant opportunity for the UK and our partners to take on these challenges and to show leadership in the fight to tackle the ongoing ramifications of the global financial and debt crisis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="g8-leaders-summit"&gt;G8 leaders’ summit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The G8 leaders’ summit will take place on 17 to 18 June 2013 at &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lough-erne-g8-venue" title="Lough Erne Venue"&gt;Lough Erne in County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/topical-events/g8-2013"&gt;UK Presidency of G8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60310</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:50:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/david-cameron-visits-troops-in-afghanistan--2"/>
    <title>David Cameron visits troops in Afghanistan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The UK Prime Minister praised armed forces success during visit to Camp Bastion.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister flew into Afghanistan yesterday morning, 20 December. He visited Camp Bastion, where he met with military commanders before joining troops for an early Christmas dinner and a carol service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister’s visit came a day after he told &lt;abbr title="Members of Parliament"&gt;MPs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Parliament that troop numbers will almost halve to around 5,200 by the end of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron meets troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5805/PMmeetstroops.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;David Cameron visits Camp Bastion [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister told journalists on the trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is still a difficult and dangerous place but we’ve made real progress. It is tough, it is difficult, and we’ve paid a high price but their efforts have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Bob Bruce, Commander Task Force Helmand, reiterated confidence in the growing capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (&lt;abbr title="Afghan National Security Forces"&gt;ANSF&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is now absolutely appropriate we hand more and more control over to the Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Cameron met troops who he praised for their service in Afghanistan and thanked them for making the country “prouder than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a message to the armed forces, the Prime Minister said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well it is a good time to come to Afghanistan and say a really big thank you to our troops for everything they do, and particularly at Christmas time when they’re away from loved ones.  But I think it’s an opportunity to say to all our forces all over the world…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You make us incredibly proud; we’re always proud of you, and this year perhaps prouder than ever for your extraordinary work in Afghanistan, for the amazing things you do over the whole of Africa to keep us safe from terrorism and piracy, for the extraordinary things you did at the Olympics where the military stepped up, put a smiling face on the greatest show on earth, won a lot of medals too and made the country very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cameron added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our military really are the best of the best and we can’t thank them enough for what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60322</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T12:45:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/typhoon-for-oman"/>
    <title>Typhoon for Oman</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BAE Systems has signed a contract with the Sultanate of Oman for the supply of 12 Typhoon aircraft, associated support and 8 Hawk 128 aircraft. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.baesystems.com/home" title="BAE Systems website"&gt;BAE Systems&lt;/a&gt; released a statement confirming that the deal is worth some £2.5 billion and equips the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.omanet.om/english/government/defence.asp?cat=gov" title="Oman Defence web pages"&gt;Sultan’s Armed Forces&lt;/a&gt; with the most sophisticated aircraft on the market today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the deal the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This represents a further chapter in the historical and deep relationship between Oman and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Oman’s choice of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/typhooneurofighter.cfm" title="Typhoon aircraft"&gt;Typhoon&lt;/a&gt; recognises the capabilities of this versatile aircraft and its long term potential to stay at the forefront of military capability for many years. Oman will be a valued member of the growing Typhoon family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This sale is an important contribution to our race for growth providing significant revenue and protecting high value jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="RAF Typhoon aircraft in flight (stock image) [Picture: Senior Aircraftman Ash Reynolds, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5809/LEU-Unclass-20120912-0850-181.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;1(F) Squadron and 6 Squadron, based at RAF Leuchars, fly Typhoon aircraft over RAF Leuchars station and St Andrews town (stock image)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Sultan’s Armed Forces and those of the United Kingdom is enduring. This purchase of Typhoon will serve to strengthen further the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with the existing Jaguar and Hawk aircraft I am confident that Typhoon will provide many years of first class service to the Royal Air Force of Oman and maintain its long and fruitful relationship with the Royal Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Secretary Vince Cable welcomed the deal and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is obviously a very good day for BAE Systems, its suppliers and the broader Eurofighter supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has welcomed Sir John Holmes' review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56077</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T15:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T16:54:35+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/millies-heroes-honoured-at-awards"/>
    <title>Millies heroes honoured at awards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Last week, The Sun newspaper honoured courageous servicemen and women at their annual Military Awards. Here we feature two more winners.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h3 id="support-to-the-armed-forces-award"&gt;Support to the Armed Forces Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Army widow Nikki Scott won the Support to the Armed Forces Award for her charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.scottyslittlesoldiers.co.uk/" title="Scotty's Little Soldiers"&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers&lt;/a&gt;. The charity supports the children of men and women killed while serving in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki set up the charity in August 2010 after her husband, Corporal Lee Scott, was killed in Afghanistan in July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotty’s Little Soldiers aims to help as many children as possible up to the age of 18 by funding days out and paying for birthday and Christmas presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winning this is overwhelming but I’m very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Oliver handed Nikki her award and hailed her ‘wonderful spirit’. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a sacrifice beyond most people made not just by one family but by many families. As a dad of four, it’s probably the hardest award I’ve ever given. You can’t change what’s happened but what Nikki has done is really important. I’m so impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5432/PMand3rifles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prime Minister and his wife with members of 3rd Battalion The Rifles and their Best Unit Award [Picture: The Sun newspaper]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Praising the Millies, the TV chef said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s completely integral to pay our respects to the people that have done extraordinary things in extraordinary circumstances. There is not a job like it; we expect a lot and it’s really important that we give these guys a pat on the back and I think that’s what’s so brilliant about the Millies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="best-unit-award"&gt;Best Unit Award&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highly coveted award for Best Unit went to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/infantry/regiments/5974.aspx" title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3rd Battalion The Rifles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt;) for their work on Operation HERRICK. The unit were part of the Brigade Advisory Group mentoring the Afghan Army and Police. Prime Minister David Cameron and his wife Samantha presented the award to the unit, which is based in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer, soldiers from &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; took on the challenge of training the Afghan security forces. By building trust through shared dangers on the front line, they helped transform the capability of local forces. This approach was ably demonstrated on the day that Advisor 40 - a company of men that was part of &lt;abbr title="3rd Battalion The Rifles"&gt;3 RIFLES&lt;/abbr&gt; - risked their lives to save a badly injured Afghan soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of their arrival to mentor Afghan troops in Lashkar Gah, a rogue Afghan soldier from the base next door shot 2 British servicemen at the gates. Refusing to be cowed, despite the obvious risks, this event showed the dedication of the soldiers to the task at hand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 3 months later, 3 British troops raced over open ground under enemy fire to rescue an Afghan who had been shot, gave life-saving first aid, and then ran back, all under fire. This was just one example of the commitment and courage of the troops carrying out advisory roles in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warrant Officer Class 1 (Regimental Sergeant Major) James Mockridge said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Prime Minister"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt; thanked us and said he was really pleased with our achievements in moving the Afghan National Army forward in the campaign. Hopefully it has put us in a better place than when we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked whether it was the cherry on the cake to have the Prime Minister hand over the award, &lt;abbr title="Warrant Officer Class 1"&gt;WO1&lt;/abbr&gt; Mockridge said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most definitely! For our unit, the honour doesn’t get much higher than the Prime Minister giving us an award. It’s not only fantastic for us but for all the Riflemen back in Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/4685336/the-sun-military-awards-2012-roll-of-honour.html" title="Sun Military Awards roll of honour"&gt;The Millies&lt;/a&gt; awards ceremony on ITV1 at 2100hrs on Friday 14 December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16885</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T15:30:30+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:30:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mod-shines-at-the-civil-service-awards"/>
    <title>MOD shines at the Civil Service Awards</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The civilian Standing Joint Commander (UK) Olympics Team has won the Olympic Team Award at this year's Civil Service Awards.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Civil servants gathered together yesterday for the awards ceremony at Lancaster House in London. Hosted by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/" title="BBC"&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; TV presenters Jon Sopel and Sian Williams, the event honoured outstanding individuals and teams across government for their contribution to public services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/news/civil-service-awards" title="Civil Service Awards 2012"&gt;The Civil Service Awards&lt;/a&gt; celebrate and promote innovation and improvement across the entire breadth of central government. They recognise people who are leading the way in these areas and champion them as examples of best practice that can be applied across the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.civilservice.gov.uk/" title="Civil Service"&gt;Civil Service&lt;/a&gt;. This year 850 nominations were received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Awards featured 18 main categories. The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; was shortlisted in two of them. As well as the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s civilian Standing Joint Commander [&lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt;] (UK) nomination, Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie were nominated for the Achieving Better for Less Award. The judges accepted the fact that Defence has a unique &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; and opened the competition up to Service personnel as well as civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full citations and a list of all the winners can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://network.civilservicelive.com/pages/view/710933/civil-service-awards-winners-2012" title="Civil Service Awards Winners 2012"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video message at the event Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This summer we showed the world the best face of Britain and your efforts were a big part of that success. So I am very pleased to see a special category tonight recognising achievements in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Britain’s Civil Service is a great source of national pride. Your excellence, innovation and professionalism and your values, integrity and impartiality, honesty and objectivity are rightly respected around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the event, Sir Bob Kerslake, Head of the Civil Service, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s not often we have a chance to celebrate the excellent work we do in the Civil Service. What these nominations demonstrate is that it is a great place to work and what we do matters greatly to the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to sincerely thank all of you for your passion and dedication and innovation; it is truly impressive, it is truly great. You should all feel incredibly proud of your achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympic Team Award was a one-off category created for the 2012 Civil Service Awards to celebrate individuals, teams and volunteers who showed excellence in delivering the &lt;a href="London%202012" title="http://www.london2012.com/"&gt;2012 Games&lt;/a&gt;. Over 100 nominations were received for this category alone. The award was judged by a panel including the new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.teamgb.com/" title="British Olympic Association "&gt;British Olympic Association&lt;/a&gt; Chairman, Lord Sebastian Coe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video message played just before the winners were revealed Lord Coe said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The quality of the London Games was predicated almost entirely on the secure, robust relationships that we formed. And nowhere were those relationships more secure and robust than across government. There were 19 government departments that helped us deliver the Games. No organising committee alone can do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of you I know worked long and hard and put all sorts of things on hold to make sure these Games were the extraordinary success they were. Thank you for being such true and trusted teams to help us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting the award to the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team, Jonathan Stephens, Permanent Secretary at the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/" title="Department for Culture, Media and Sport"&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This summer was a summer like no other. It was a great opportunity to put on a show to the world. It was also only made possible by the very best of public service and Civil Service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Staff Sergeants Andy Laurie and Marc Smith" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1181/CSAwards01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Staff Sergeants Andy Laurie and Marc Smith from the Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers Training Wing [Picture: Crown Copyright/&lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team is made up of Angie Rogers, Sarah Williams, Kerry Kellett, Sheila Symes, Miles Tooke, Charlie Bird and Jo McKeegan-Brown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking moments after receiving their award, the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Olympics Team said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are really proud of what we have achieved. We worked so hard over the summer. It’s just recognition of that achievement. The award is not just for us, it’s for our families and friends who put up with us being away from them every weekend for six months and for supporting us when we worked long hours during the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces contribution to the Games was recognised throughout the summer but this award recognises the civilians too. It shows the &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; as a team, with civil servants and military working together. It doesn’t matter if it’s in Afghanistan or the UK - we can still do a good job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; team was up against Operation Stepchange from the &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-transport" title="Department for Transport"&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/a&gt;, which tested travel and business continuity plans across government in readiness for the Games; the UK Wide Operations Olympic and Paralympic Torch Team from the Department for Culture, Media and Sport, which co-ordinated the Olympic Torch Relay across the UK; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalparks.org.uk/" title="Royal Parks"&gt;Royal Parks&lt;/a&gt;, which hosted a number of the Olympic events watched by two million spectators. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Service Awards support the wider Civil Service reform plan. One of the plan’s main priorities is for all government departments to find new ways of delivering services. It aims to transform the Civil Service so that it will have a more innovative and less hierarchical culture, with a much sharper focus on outcomes rather than processes, and will be more flexible and corporate. Many aspects of the plan came from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/content/tell-us-how" title="Tell Us How"&gt;‘Tell Us How’&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/" title="Cabinet Office"&gt;Cabinet Office’s&lt;/a&gt; suggestion scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt; itself uses GEMS, its own staff suggestion scheme, to encourage innovation within Defence. The ideas scheme was launched in 1996 and is open to all Defence civilian and Service personnel, including ex-employees, anywhere in the world. It is the third most successful ideas scheme in the world. Those who make successful suggestions receive a financial reward. GEMS is a key part of Transforming Defence. It falls under the Behaviours and Business Improvement workstream, linking closely with the ‘Be A Leader - Think Defence - Do It Better’ behaviour change work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GEMS also glittered at the Civil Service Awards, showing the rest of Whitehall how we in Defence are ‘Doing It Better’. Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie, who were nominated for the Achieving Better for Less Award, earlier this week won the GEMS Idea of the Year Award and a commendation in the Most Operational Benefit category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Armoured Frame Electrical Layout is a training aid for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/reme/reme.aspx" title="Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers"&gt;Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers&lt;/a&gt; vehicle mechanics to fix electrical problems in protected mobility vehicles. This is currently a real problem in Afghanistan, and this innovation will help the mechanics in theatre to learn how to make faster repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two Staff Sergeants were up against the Respiratory Team from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/index.htm" title="Department of Health"&gt;Department of Health&lt;/a&gt;, which in the end won the Achieving Better for Less Award. The team retendered contracts for the regional Home Oxygen Service. The other nominee was the Property Asset Management Unit which is a shared service between the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.education.gov.uk/" title="Department for Education"&gt;Department for Education&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government" title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;Department for Communities and Local Government&lt;/a&gt;. It maintains the buildings for both departments at a significantly reduced cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff Sergeant Mark Smith and Staff Sergeant Andrew Laurie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although we didn’t win our category we were very pleased to be nominated. We work with civil servants quite closely and it was a privilege to come here and see the recognition they received. We felt the winning nomination deserved it, and we commend them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permanent Secretary Jon Thompson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My congratulations to the &lt;abbr title="Standing Joint Commander"&gt;SJC&lt;/abbr&gt; (UK) Team for their win, and to Staff Sergeants Smith and Laurie for their nomination. There was fierce competition from other government departments at the Civil Service Awards this year and the bar was set very high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Ministry of Defence"&gt;MOD&lt;/abbr&gt;’s strong performance at the Awards recognises our commitment to ‘Doing It Better’, and shows how highly our innovative work is regarded outside the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56230</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T13:59:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T13:59:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/life-sciences-strategy-one-year-on"/>
    <title>  Life Sciences Strategy: one year on</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Prime Minister David Cameron and Science Minister David Willetts have launched a report on the Strategy for UK Life Sciences.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report shows that the UK has generated more than £1 billion on industry and private sector investment within 12 months.  This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£500 million from GSK to build its first new manufacturing plant in almost 40 years at Ulverston in Cumbria and invest more in its two sites at Montrose and Irvine in Scotland as a direct response to the introduction of the Patent Box&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£25 million leveraged in from the private sector to bridge the ‘Valley of Death’ adding to a government commitment of £49 million to 64 projects through the Biomedical Catalyst&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£294 million through the UK Research Partnership Investment Fund (&lt;abbr title="UK Research Partnership Investment Fund"&gt;UK RPIF&lt;/abbr&gt;) from businesses and charities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Real progress has been made working closely with companies across the sector to ensure the measures in the strategy are making a real difference to their work and their decisions to invest in and remain in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes investing £1 billion per annum through the National Institute for Health Research, which includes £500 million in our translational research infrastructure in the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; to boost networks between academia, industry and the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="revolutionising-the-fight-against-cancer"&gt;Revolutionising the fight against cancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Cameron also announced that the UK will be the first country in the world to introduce to introduce high-tech &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; mapping for cancer patients and those with rare diseases, within the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt;.  Up to  100,000 patients over three to five years will have their whole genome – their personal &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; code –sequenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genome profile will give doctors a new, advanced understanding of a patient’s genetic make-up, condition and treatment needs, ensuring they have access to the right drugs and personalised care far quicker than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also help to develop life-saving new drugs, treatments and scientific breakthroughs, which experts predict could significantly reduce the number of premature deaths from cancer within a generation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has earmarked £100 million: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to train a new generation of British genetic scientists to lead on the development of new drugs, treatments and cures, building the UK as the world leader in the field. And train the wider healthcare community in harnessing this technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to pump-prime &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; sequencing for cancer and rare inherited diseases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to build the &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; data infrastructure to ensure that this new technology leads to better care for patients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="reaction"&gt;Reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for Science and Universities David Willetts said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life sciences is one of the most truly international sectors – so if we are to continue to be a world player and compete in the global race we must do everything we can to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past year, our initiatives have attracted more than £1 billion of private sector investment to the UK. We can see clear evidence the UK is succeeding in creating the right environment to attract global investment to our shores and continue to be world leader in life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am announcing today that we are committing a further £100 million to support this sector out of the extra money for science announced by the chancellor in his Autumn Statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/strategy-for-uk-life-sciences-one-year-on"&gt;David Willetts speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;Life Sciences at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/ols"&gt;a Strategy for UK Life Sciences: One Year On’ report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/dna-tests-to-fight-cancer/"&gt;Notice: &lt;abbr title="Deoxyribonucleic Acid"&gt;DNA&lt;/abbr&gt; tests to revolutionise fight against cancer and help 100,000 &lt;abbr title="National Health Service"&gt;NHS&lt;/abbr&gt; patients&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
