<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/don-foster</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/don-foster.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Don Foster MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-02T11:25:21+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60988</id>
    <published>2013-01-02T11:25:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-02T11:25:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cutting-red-tape-will-save-homeowners-240-on-diy-electrical-jobs-says-don-foster"/>
    <title>Cutting red tape will save homeowners £240 on DIY electrical jobs, says Don Foster</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government moves to scrap the requirement to get simple and low risk electrical works approved will save money for householders. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government moves to scrap the requirement for householders to get simple and low risk electrical works approved by their local council will save ‘DIYers’ £240 each, and in some cases even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduced just before Christmas, these changes will come into force in April 2013 and will avoid the need for householders to seek council approval for simple jobs such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding a socket to a kitchen, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;installing a new security light or a lawnmower socket in the garden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under current rules obtaining council approval for such jobs costs around £240 each time, or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riskier jobs such as work near baths and showers, installing new circuits and house rewires will continue to require approval from councils’ building control departments or be carried out by an electrician registered to approve their own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lots of people will have made it a new year resolution to fix or improve their home’s electrics, but they are often put off by the bureaucratic costs. I am cutting red tape to allow people to get on with making simple and safe improvements without having to spend hundreds of pounds on getting the council’s approval. Safety is the number one concern though and riskier jobs will always need to be signed off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also urged people to stay safe and continue using common sense saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I urge anyone who is either inexperienced at DIY or in doubt as to what they are doing to always consult a professional. Using a competent electrician is the simplest way to ensure you and your family remain safe. That’s why I’ll be working with industry and others to see what more we can do to get this simple message across.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster also acknowledged that many people - mainly married men like him - were going to lose an excuse for not getting on with their list of jobs around the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are part of a package of measures to clarify and update the building regulations that will also save businesses £50 million a year. Taking over 400,000 electrical jobs out of the system annually contributes to savings to electrical firms of around £14 million per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The changes to electrical safety were included in a package of deregulatory measures &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations" title="Written Ministerial Statement by Don Foster on changes to the building regulations regime in England"&gt;announced to Parliament&lt;/a&gt; on 18 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-electrical-safety" title="Consultation on building regulations -electrical safety"&gt;consultation in January 2012&lt;/a&gt; sought views on electrical safety.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The deregulation package also delivers other savings to business including:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;bringing together currently separate guidance on how to design stairs and ramps so they are both safe and accessible - saving £4.4 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;updating fire safety guidance for lighting diffusers - saving £26.3 million&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;making the building control system more efficient and to extending the scope of competent person schemes - saving £6 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57519</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/changes-to-the-building-regulations"/>
    <title>Changes to the building regulations</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written Ministerial Statement by The Right Honourable Don Foster MP on changes to the building regulations regime in England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am setting out today the changes that will be made to the building regulations regime in England to deliver an even better and more cost-effective way of ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable. The changes will deliver savings of around £50 million per year to business. In addition, legislation will also be laid before Parliament shortly to amend the Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations and to repeal unnecessary fire provisions of Local Acts which overlap national provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-access-statements-security-changing-places-toilets-and-regulation-7"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; issued by the Department for Communities and Local Government on 31 January this year contained a range of proposals to improve the building regulations regime. I am setting out today decisions on the deregulatory changes. I am also publishing today a document providing a factual summary of the responses received. The changes have been developed after active engagement with external partners and demonstrate the government’s ongoing commitment to ensuring that where regulation is necessary the impact on business is properly considered and the associated cost minimised. Decisions on the outstanding issues relating to the energy efficiency of buildings, on better targeting of radon protection measures and the referencing of British Standards for structural design based on Eurocodes will be set out in a further statement next year. We will also set out next year the outcome of the review of the framework of building regulations and local housing standards which I announced in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement with our external partners shows that they continue to value the national minimum standards provided by the building regulations. However, where any concerns do arise it is necessary to address them. That is why we listened to those that expressed concern with the costs associated with the electrical safety in the home provisions in Part P of the building regulations. Some have even advocated that Part P should be revoked as a burdensome requirement on competent electricians. We disagree - Part P has been a success - but we do recognise that there is scope to streamline the requirements by removing the requirement to notify smaller-scale, lower-risk electrical work to a building control body. Currently homeowners can face building control fees of upwards of £240 to have simple electrical work, such as an additional plug socket in a kitchen, approved by a local authority. This change will see the notification requirements focused on higher-risk jobs like the installation of new circuits, or work in the vicinity of showers and baths, which is the right approach. There will, of course, remain a duty for these non-notifiable works to comply with the safety provisions required by the regulations and which we have also updated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Part P seeks to achieve a reasonable balance of risk. We will continue to monitor indicators which can help identify the impact of the changes and keep this under review. But the key to ensuring electrical work is done properly is to employ competent electricians and so the department will continue to work closely with external partners to identify what more can be done to promote the importance of complying with the provisions of Part P through use of a suitably-qualified electrician. In addition, I will be bringing forward further regulations later next year that will introduce an alternative route to demonstrating compliance with Part P by allowing for third-party certification of electrical work. This will safeguard standards whilst providing a far cheaper way of verifying work is adequate - particularly for those carrying out DIY work. These changes will be accompanied by simpler, clearer and shorter guidance in a new Approved Document P that we will be publishing shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we will be making a number of other changes to the building regulations. We will amend the technical guidance in Approved Document B (Fire safety). In particular, we will update guidance in respect of lighting diffusers which has grown out-of-date as lighting technology has changed considerably. We will also, in relation to wall coverings, be taking forward changes to mitigate problems associated with how the European reaction to fire classifications work in practice. In effect, the changes will maintain the status quo, for example, allowing wallpapers that are currently used to continue to be so in the future. Both these changes have been supported by independent research which shows there are no adverse impacts on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be taking forward rationalisation of guidance supporting Parts M, K and N (Access, Protection from falling, collision and impact and Glazing respectively) to address areas of conflict and overlap, which again impose unnecessary costs. At the same time we will clarify the guidance on Access Statements in Approved Document M to promote a more proportionate, risk-based approach. These changes will be delivered by clearer guidance in a new Approved Document K and amendment of other Approved Documents which I will be publishing shortly. We intend that all of these deregulatory changes will come into force on 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the changes to the ‘technical’ provisions, we have also agreed a number of improvements to the building control system. These are relatively minor changes to benefit both local authorities and Approved Inspectors through changes to the procedures around completion certificates, statutory notifications and removal of the ‘Warranty Link Rule’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes to regulations also extend the scope for existing competent person scheme operators. This will allow more work to be self-certified and thereby avoid the need to notify a building control body or pay a building control charge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the building regulations, we will also be publishing shortly a new Approved Document 7 which provides updated guidance on adequate materials and workmanship for building work, in particular the implications of the full implementation of the European Construction Products Regulation on 1 July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated Energy Performance of Buildings Regulations will also be laid before the House shortly. These, in addition to consolidating the existing regulations, transpose the requirements of the recast Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2010 and remove unnecessary ‘gold-plating’. The Directive is an EU measure designed to tackle climate change by reducing the amount of carbon produced by buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new requirements will be introduced on 9 January 2013. The key measures include a requirement for property advertisements to include details of the Energy Performance Certificate rating where available; removal of the requirement to attach the front page of the certificate to any written material; exempting listed buildings from the need to have a certificate on their sale or rent; extending the current requirement for a display energy certificate in large public buildings, to public buildings above 500m² and; introducing a requirement for a certificate to be displayed in commercial premises larger than 500m² that are frequently visited by the public and where one has been previously issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given this statement relates to the regulation of buildings, I am informing the House that I will also shortly be laying regulations to repeal unnecessary fire provisions in 23 Local Acts. The decision has been taken in the light of previous consultation which found no evidence to justify maintaining requirements which go beyond the necessary protection already afforded nationally through the building regulations, and lead to differing and inconsistent rules even within fire and rescue authority areas. Evidence does not establish any statistically significant impact on life safety. These changes are intended to come into force on 9 January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be placing the revised guidance in the Approved Documents referred to above, along with the impact assessments that accompany all of these changes, in the Library of the House when they are published shortly and alongside the summary of responses that I am placing there today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17313</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T10:51:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/funding-boost-will-help-stop-the-rot-of-empty-homes"/>
    <title>Funding boost will help "stop the rot" of empty homes</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Don Foster has announced the opening of bidding for a share of £300 million. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funding will bring thousands of additional empty homes back into use across England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communities minister pledged to “stop the rot” that empty homes can bring to blighted neighbourhoods and said that he “wants to go much further” in tackling the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the scheme 5,000 empty, and in many cases derelict, properties will be refurbished and put back onto the market over the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="extending-the-governments-commitment-to-tackling-empty-homes"&gt;Extending the government’s commitment to tackling empty homes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest figures show the number of empty homes dropped from 300,000 in 2009 to 259,000 in 2012, and today’s new funding is in addition to the £160 million ministers have already committed to bringing empty homes back into use. The government has also given councils greater powers to tackle empty homes locally including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allowing councils to charge up to 150% of the normal Council Tax rate on owners of the most problematic neglected homes from April 2013 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;applying the ‘New Homes Bonus’ to empty homes, with government matching Council Tax proceeds from newly inhabited properties pound for pound, doubling councils’ revenue from these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the most severe cases, enabling councils to take over the most problematic neglected homes through the use of Empty Dwelling Management Orders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the beginning of Empty Homes Week Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Empty homes blight communities, attract crime and rats and deprive people of available housing. What’s worse this is a vicious circle - one derelict home brings an area down and can lead to more and in places whole communities have been destroyed. I am determined quite literally to stop the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This extra money will help communities refurbish empty and abandoned homes, bring in new residents, provide desperately needed extra affordable housing for families and regenerate communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This significant cash injection will help thousands of families in housing need, but will also support local economic growth by providing work for local building firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of organisations including councils, housing associations, community and voluntary groups as well as high street regeneration groups - prioritising the 27 ‘Portas pilot’ towns and 326 town team partners - will be able to bid for a share of the funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers are also considering future measures to bring not just homes but empty buildings generally back into use including making it easier to convert commercial into residential property and making more use of space above shops as homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TV presenter, architect, and Independent Empty Homes Adviser George Clarke said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Empty homes are a very serious problem for communities - they cause a loss of housing, produce an increase in crime and bring entire areas down. The government has shown it is equally serious about tackling this problem and I welcome this massive injection of extra cash that will help towns across the country tackle the blight of empty homes and regenerate communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Ireland, Chief Executive at the Empty Homes Agency, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The huge effort people have made this year to get empty homes back into use has been truly inspiring and created a major contribution to housing supply. This week we are celebrating what they have achieved and pushing for changes to make it possible for even more to be achieved next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homes and Communities Agency Chief Executive Pat Ritchie said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tackling empty homes remains a key priority for the Agency. I welcome this additional funding, which has an emphasis on helping to bring empty commercial and non-residential back into use as affordable housing, and will build on the work we are already doing to bring long-term empty homes back into use through our Affordable Homes Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will be working with our local partners to help meet local need and in doing so, support their efforts to tackle homelessness and regenerate neighbourhoods that are suffering from the blight of empty homes and help to prevent neighbourhood decline.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bidding guidance will shortly be published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk" title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;Homes and Communities Agency’s website&lt;/a&gt; for registered providers and at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.grantsadmin.co.uk" title="Grantsadmin"&gt;Grants admin&lt;/a&gt; for community and voluntary groups.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Empty homes figures can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/10605/1815794.xls"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government recently changed the threshold at which Empty Dwelling Management Orders take effect, maintaining councils’ powers to tackle the most problematic properties but preventing heavy handed use against homeowners. For more information see the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/pickles-acts-to-protect-the-rights-of-homeowners"&gt;news article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 150% council tax premium for empty homes is part of the measures within the Local Government Finance Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £300 million funding was part of the 6 September housing and growth package announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17053</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T15:57:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-empty-homes-conference-2012"/>
    <title>National Empty Homes conference 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Don Foster to the annual National Empty Homes conference.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Rachel Whiteread won international recognition for her cast of an empty room. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a striking piece. Conveying the sadness, the sheer tragedy of an unoccupied place - a place with no one to call it home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significantly, the artist’s name for that work was ‘Ghost’ and that really is the point. Homes are not pieces of sculpture. They are made to be occupied. An &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes"&gt;empty home&lt;/a&gt; is a phantom. A hole in the heart of a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know homes fall empty for all sorts of reasons. Some are renovated, some in probate, some are even second homes. But, wherever you find these haunted houses you’ll find blighted communities and lost neighbourhoods. Ambition abandoned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen how it happens. The empty edifice becomes an eyesore. The eyesore becomes a magnet for rats, vandals, drug dealing, squatters and prostitution. Neighbours are inconvenienced. Communities are damaged. Council and local emergency services stretched to breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistics prove the point. Research by The Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors suggests properties adjoining poorly maintained empty properties can drop by almost 20% in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in part we were reaping the whirlwind of the failed policies of the past. The destructive Pathfinder programme undermined once vibrant communities. Marooning people in appalling homes surrounded by a sea of derelict streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the legacy we’ve inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A legacy of almost three quarters of a million empty homes abandoned to the winds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re determined to say never again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to inhabit the absences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plug the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring ghost homes back from the brink to the land of the living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we afford not to do it? It’s a moral and financial imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 1.7 million families on housing waiting lists. Of those some are homeless forced to live in overcrowded B&amp;amp;Bs. And the country’s population is growing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, house building is really important, vital, as the Deputy Prime Minister’s recent housing announcement made clear. But, as George Clarke would say, it would be “a crying shame” if we couldn’t occupy these wastes of space. Make use of what we’ve already got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the government’s approach has been threefold. First, we’re making more funds available for bringing homes back into use. And we’ve committed £160 million to bring over 11,000 empty houses back into use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t about throwing money at a problem but making sure the money goes to the right places. Everyone who understands this area, knows there is no one-size fits all solution. Behind every empty home lies a myriad of social, historic and economic issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our approach must be to create local answers to local issues. Giving local communities the right incentives to take the lead. So they will no longer turn a blind eye. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than talk you through which fund comes from which pot, let me focus on the difference the money can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Habitat for Humanity in Dagenham, received financial aid to bring 35 houses back into use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redcar &amp;amp; Cleveland Borough Council used its cash to renovate 20 homes and help unemployed residents to learn new skills for employment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing Health Independence, out in my constituency in Bath, is bringing 18 properties back from the brink&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kingston upon Hull City Council has written to 500 owners of empty homes offering to resuscitate their property - more than three quarters have already said yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These organisations deserve all the praise they get. What can be better than giving someone a home?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our approach is not all about money. It’s about keeping empty homes on the agenda. That’s the second point I’d like to make today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be a case of out of sight out of mind. Often there are people who care passionately about the areas they live in but they haven’t a clue about what to do next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But thanks to George - the fastidious work of the Charity Empty Homes, the grass roots activities of local authorities and registered providers, the passion of community groups - ghost homes now have nowhere to hide. We’re stopping the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we’re taking the carrot and stick approach. There are now powerful incentives for all local authorities to tackle empty homes such as the New Homes Bonus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means local authorities can earn the same financial reward for bringing an empty home back into use as building a new one. And it has provided an income of £26 million to local authorities for bringing empty homes back into use over the past year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when advice and support isn’t enough? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those circumstances we’ll get tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to take action against individuals who just can’t be bothered, who refuse to see the problem, who feel it’s ok to abandon their homes to the elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve given local authorities the power to reduce or remove Council Tax relief for empty and unfurnished homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve allowed them local discretion to introduce a Council Tax premium on homes empty and unfurnished for more than 2 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next April, billing authorities will be able to charge up to 150% of Council Tax on such property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the Empty Dwelling Management Orders. These force owners to bring their properties back into use. And, last but not least, as a last resort, there is the compulsory purchase order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point about these things is not how many times they are used but the fact they are there at all. They are a deterrent against those who refuse to take responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our efforts these silent shells are vanishing before our eyes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we came to power the number of long term empty homes has fallen by 50,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This downward trend is continuing. The latest figures show a further decrease 20,000 in long term empty homes to 259,000 in 2012. And every house back in circulation, means a roof over the head of a working family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there is still a very long way to go. Yet what we’ve demonstrated emphatically is the power of collaborations. That it’s coalitions of organisations - registered social landlords and community groups, house builders and local authorities - that together will make the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These collaborations ensured the house in Oldham that stood empty for 14 years will soon be occupied. Oldham Borough Council and Aksa Homes brushed aside the cobwebs, hovered up the tumbleweed, rebuilt the pathways and put in new gates and fitted a new kitchen. A new home awakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s absolutely vital we harness the wealth of skill, experience, knowledge and application that these partnerships bring. So today I am inviting councils, housing associations, community and voluntary groups, and high street regeneration groups, prioritising our 27 Portas pilots to step forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In exchange for a share of £300 million I want them to tell me their plans to scatter the shadow of empty homes and bring thousands more back into the light. You’re the experts and it’s your innovative ideas I’m after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final thing. I’m keen to take our empty homes policy in a new direction. This shouldn’t just be about turning disused residential properties, those ageing apparitions, into inviting homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not turn empty offices into homes? Why not use the spaces above shops for housing? People who need a place to live don’t mind where it comes from. We’re making this easier to do. We’ve already introduced a whole host of policies to get rid of the red tape that gets in the way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know this type of project can be more challenging than a residential refurbishment. Typically, there are obstacles such as access and security to overcome. But they mustn’t stand in our way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minute you occupy an empty home, you start of an amazing chain reaction of events. You don’t just bring homes back to life, but neighbourhoods and communities. And businesses and jobs follow in their wake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re determined to exorcise ghost homes from the collective psyche. We’re straining every sinew to make them a myth not the reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up and down the country, there are people who dream of one day seeing neighbourhoods revive and redundant homes come back to life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have little doubt, that working together, we will grant them their wish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13585</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T11:33:48+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Don Foster welcomed a huge response from neighbourhood groups interested in using new powers to save local assets or take over services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/" title="Locality"&gt;Locality&lt;/a&gt;, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Don Foster said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as: the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; neighbourhood planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings; and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves, are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and town halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality Chief Executive Officer Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ’12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act which was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. Download &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate" title="A Plain English Guide to the Localism Act"&gt;A Plain English Guide to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently the Community Right to Bid came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/" title="my community rights"&gt;Community Rights&lt;/a&gt; website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14752</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-hails-localism-progress--2"/>
    <title>Don Foster hails localism progress</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Communities Minister Don Foster has welcomed a huge response from neighbourhood groups interested in using new powers to save much-loved local assets or take over services.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He told delegates at a conference on Tuesday that in just 3 months over 1,600 enquiries have been received by the Community Rights support website from groups interested in exercising the new powers and over £80,000 in grants have already been awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister was speaking at a gathering of over 500 community enterprise and social action practitioners held in Bristol by Locality, the UK’s leading network of community and social enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking to delegates, Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Localism is at the very core of what we are trying to achieve. Communities know their areas best and that is why we are not just talking about pushing power back to neighbourhoods - we are making it a reality and these figures show that it is happening where it matters, on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New initiatives such as the Community Right to Bid allowing people to step in and save the facilities and buildings that are important to them; Neighbourhood Planning, gives them a powerful tool to help shape their surroundings and the Community Right to Challenge, allowing them to challenge the way a service is run and even bid to run it themselves are all vital steps in moving power away from Whitehall and Town Halls and into the hands of local people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground, and today is a vital opportunity to share this knowledge and experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community organisations and activists from across the country will meet at the convention to discuss how local communities can play a greater role in shaping their areas and hear from those who have already delivered ground-breaking projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality CEO Steve Wyler said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Locality ‘12 will bring together the most inspiring community organisations in the country. Within our membership there is an extraordinary reservoir of talent, knowledge and experience which has never been more important than it is today. In these difficult times, community enterprise, community asset ownership and community-led delivery of services offers a beacon of hope for us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. Download an &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/localism-act-2011-overview" title="Localism Act 2011: overview"&gt;overview to the Localism Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-bid" title="Community Right to Bid"&gt;Community Right to Bid&lt;/a&gt; came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is available on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mycommunityrights.org.uk" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16909</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/independent-panel-to-help-government-cut-housebuilding-red-tape-and-boost-growth"/>
    <title>Independent panel to help government cut housebuilding red tape and boost growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New independent group of building industry experts to simplify the mass of rules imposed on developers and housebuilders.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today launched a new independent group of building industry experts, tasked with simplifying the mass of rules imposed on developers and housebuilders, to make them easier to understand and follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge,&lt;/a&gt; ministers have made clear they want to do everything possible to remove unnecessary burdens and bureaucracy imposed on developers to get much-needed new homes built, and support economic growth. The current, complex system of building regulations and housing standards will be targeted by a new Independent Challenge Panel, which will consider how these requirements work together and what potential there is to free up the system and make it work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel will for the first time bring independent experts together with government and it will report to ministers in spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mr Foster also made clear that essential safety and accessibility protections will remain untouched and that homes will always need to be built to high sustainability and quality standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="housing-standards-review"&gt;Housing standards review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the hundreds of standards that can be applied to new-build homes, some of which duplicate each other, a separate group will work alongside the new Challenge Panel to consider the specific issue of standards applied to housebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some of these standards are applied nationally across certain types of homes, such as affordable housing, others are made mandatory by individual councils for building in their area and some are entirely voluntary - resulting in confusion for local people and developers. Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the requirement for 2 phone lines in home offices, irrespective of need and in addition to broadband connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rules on window sizes that include a ‘dirty window factor’ - imposing bigger windows to allow for dirt on them, rather than assuming people will simply clean their windows&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a requirement that ‘drying space’ is designed and assessed when often this is nothing more complicated than a washing line over a bath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conflicting guidance on how to construct safe and accessible stairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;standards being assessed repeatedly by different people - such as planners, code assessors, building control officers - often looking at the same issues but coming up with different answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This new review, led by the Department for Communities and Local Government (&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt;) and to be conducted by a group of industry representatives, will look to avoid overlap and duplication in the system, helping ensure builders meet the high standards that aspiring homeowners rightly expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The current array of different housing standards used in different parts the country is complex and counter-productive, confusing local residents, councillors and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is why an urgent review has now started, bringing the government together with housebuilders, planners, councils and architects to establish what the unnecessary measures are that we can cut out of the system, while ensuring buildings are still made to exacting standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to see a simpler set of housing standards that people can easily understand and that free up developers and councils to get on with the job of building the high-quality new homes we so badly need to get more first-time buyers and families onto the housing ladder.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review was part of the government’s housing and growth strategy announced on 6 September 2012. It will result in a clear plan of action by next spring that will be put out to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Independent Challenge Panel members are:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy Von Bradsky (architect)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;David Clements (building control)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Paul Watson (planner)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kirk Archibald (developer)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Department for Communities and Local Government"&gt;DCLG&lt;/abbr&gt; is chairing and leading the housing standards review and has convened a group of members from representative industry bodies, comprising:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;House Builders Association&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;National House Builders Council&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Habinteg Housing Association&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Local Government Association&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Planning Officers Society&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Construction Products Association&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Building Control Alliance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Association of Chief Police Officers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;UKGBC&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Building Research Establishment&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Royal Institute for British Architects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Building Regulations Advisory Council&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Greater London Authority&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the housing standards that the review will consider include the Code for Sustainable Homes, Secured by Design, Lifetime Homes, Standards and Quality in Development and the Homes and Communities Agency’s Housing Quality Indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The review is taking place alongside the review of planning practice guidance which was announced on 16 October 2012, and both groups will be working closely together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15286/Published_ToRs.pdf"&gt;Download ‘Terms of reference for the housing standards review’ (PDF 53KB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comments and enquiries on the review should be emailed to &lt;a href="mailto:housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk"&gt;housingstandardsreview@communities.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Red Tape Challenge was launched by the Prime Minister in April 2011 and is systematically examining some 6,500 substantive regulations that the government inherited with the aim of scrapping or significantly reducing as many of them as possible. It gives business and the public the chance to have their say, by theme, on the regulations that affect their everyday lives. The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/housing-and-construction/"&gt;Housing and Construction Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; was open for comment from the 12 January until 17 February 2012. More information can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/home/index/"&gt;Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 10 September 2012 the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills announced that through the Red Tape Challenge at least 3,000 of the cross-government regulations examined will be scrapped or reduced. By ‘scrapped’, we mean that regulation is completely removed from the statute book. By ‘reduced’, we mean that regulations are reduced in number (eg a consolidation, making the rules simpler to find and follow); and/or in terms of the burden they impose (eg reducing who is caught by the regulation; removing domestic gold-plating of EU law; active renegotiation of EU law; simplifying requirements set by the regulation or in related guidance; or reducing the burden of inspection and enforcement arising from the regulation). Around 1,500 of the 3,000 changes will have a measurable financial benefit for business: this does not include consolidations of regulations without any changes to the content of those regulations. The Red Tape Challenge comprises regulation of UK origin and regulation that transposes EU laws. It does not include legislation or regulations falling within the responsibilities of the devolved administrations, tax and fees legislation or national security matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14739</id>
    <published>2012-10-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/more-green-flag-awards-for-great-local-parks"/>
    <title>More Green Flag Awards for great local parks</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Green Flag Awards - an annual ‘MOT’ inspection for parks on aspects like safety and cleanliness - are to continue as Communities Minister Don Foster announces that Keep Britain Tidy has been awarded the licence to run the scheme for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First launched in 1996 the scheme has rewarded thousands of flags over the years, with a record number 1,424 sites receiving the award this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As thousands of tourists during the Olympics saw for themselves we have some of the greatest parks in the world in this country and I want to keep the standard very high.  This is why the government is pleased to announce that Keep Britain Tidy will continue to run the scheme, awarding green flags to those parks that provide great spaces for local people.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Open spaces are essential in bringing people of all ages and backgrounds together, and are particularly important for the millions of people who do not have the luxury of their own garden to relax in or for their children to play in.  Green flags will continue to reward great parks across the country and challenge all the others to do even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as parks the green flag award scheme is open to any freely accessible public open space, including woodlands, nature reserves, allotments and cemeteries.  Judging is carried out by an army of volunteer judges and parks that receive lottery funding are required to achieve green flag status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking today at the UK Parks Summit in London, organised by the Heritage Lottery Fund and Big Lottery Fund, Don Foster is also welcoming additional lottery funding to support parks saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that £100million of extra lottery money will be going to support parks over the next three years, getting local people involved and protecting historic monuments.  With the continuing green flags scheme these new measures are a real boost for the country’s parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep Britain Tidy Chief Executive Phil Barton said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On behalf of the partners involved I’d like to say how thrilled we are to have won the licence to run the Green Flag Awards for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We know how important this scheme is to the army of professional men and women who manage our green spaces across the country. We also understand that, in these difficult financial times, these professionals are facing significant challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is only by working together that we can maintain the high standards set by the Green Flag Award and it is against this backdrop that we are delighted to be working with key partners who will help strengthen the scheme. Through this partnership, we will continue to spread best practice and raise the standard of our parks and green spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The new partnership believes the Green Flag Award is a model of how, by sharing good practice and celebrating and rewarding quality, we can raise the standards of public space in the UK, providing a range of benefits for local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Jenny Abramsky, Chair of the Heritage Lottery Fund said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted the Minister has made this commitment to the future of the Green Flags Awards scheme as it plays a vital role in inspiring local authorities and community groups to maintain their parks. Since 1996, the Heritage Lottery Fund and Big Lottery Fund have jointly invested over £640million to transform over 700 public open spaces.  The continuation of the Award - which we regard as a mark of quality all parks we fund must meet - will help safeguard our past investment along with our new commitment of £100million over the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Ainsworth, Chair of the Big Lottery Fund said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is great news and encouraging evidence of the government’s commitment to the quality of places and spaces where people live, work and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep Britain Tidy has been running the Green Flag Award scheme since 2009, with the contract expiring this year.  DCLG advertised the opportunity to run the scheme under licence and invited bids during the summer.  We are today confirming Keep Britain Tidy has been successful in its bid to become the licence holder for the scheme over the next five years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14715</id>
    <published>2012-10-05T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-community-shares-to-boost-local-services"/>
    <title>New 'Community Shares' to boost local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster today launched a new Community Shares Unit to help local people claim a stake and become part owners of much loved local assets and services such as their community pub, football club or even in the generation of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community shares let local people to take a more active in role in their communities by giving members - as part-owners - a direct say in their success, encouraging them to play an active part in their future. Most investors buy shares to help achieve a social good, however if the enterprise is successful they may also benefit from dividend payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dividends can be paid in money, but also in kind, with cheaper energy, cut-price pints, and local, fairly-priced food as possible incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backed by the Department for Communities and Local Government and run by Co-operatives UK and Locality - the country’s largest network of community led organisations - the new Community Shares Unit will enable more local enterprises to use share offers as a way of raising finance - in particular risk capital - to purchase buildings or get new projects up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the Community Development Finance Association annual conference, Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are shifting control away from Whitehall, handing communities the powers they need to run their own affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Across the country, communities are showing they have the ambition and determination to secure ownership of important local assets and get new projects off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We want to create the conditions in which social investment and community finance can flourish to make this happen. This new unit will give them the helping hand they need to take full advantage of the opportunity to do things their way, in the best interests of their area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new unit aims to grow the community shares market with the ambition of launching over 200 share issues over the next three years. It will also offer guidance and advice to investors seeking to understand more about the market, and support community enterprises, with services such as checking offer documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Mayo, Secretary General of Co-operatives UK, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re seeing more and more communities taking things into their own hands. They are investing co-operatively in local enterprises themselves, whether that’s football or farming, retail or renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Rolo, Director of Innovation at Locality, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that the Department for Communities and Local Government is supporting one of the fastest growing areas of social investment. Community shares generate the right kind of finance and act as a powerful lever to access other funding, allowing communities to develop fully sustainable enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since 2009, 15,000 people have invested in over 100 community share issues, raising over £15million. To find out more on community shares and the new Unit visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityshares.org.uk/"&gt;www.communityshares.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last three years Co-operatives UK and Locality have undertaken a Government-funded research project examining the potential of community shares and bonds as a way to increase community empowerment and grow social enterprises and attract investment from non-government sources. It investigated how members of the public can invest in enterprises that serve a community purpose. Ten projects tested the idea, looking at barriers that could restrict their growth and how they can be overcome. These include community retail stores, renewable energy and a football club. The outcome of the action research project confirmed that community shares not only help communities access funding directly but are also a good lever for accessing complementary grant and loan funding. They provide a viable option to the undercapitalisation of the community sector. The Department are funding Co-operatives UK in association with Locality, over three years, to establish the Community Shares Unit. To find out more about locality please visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://locality.org.uk/"&gt;www.locality.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link). To find out more about Co-operatives UK please visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/"&gt;www.uk.coop&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Community share offers are proving a lifeline for communities across the country. For example, Community enterprise organisation Bath and West Community Energy have, since 2010, raised funding to bring alternative sources of energy to their community, including the installation of solar, photovoltaic, hydro and wind technologies. With nearly 200 members, Bath and West Community Energy have raised £722,000 through a community share offer, exceeding their share target.  This in turn has helped them to secure £1million loan finance to fund 12 of their projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Localism Act which was enacted on 15 November 2011 and is opening up opportunities for community groups, including social ventures, to bid to run local services and assets. A plain English guide to the Localism Act is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month The Community Right to Bid came into force so communities can ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities such as post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Community Rights website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk"&gt;www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is also available on the My Community Rights website. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14713</id>
    <published>2012-10-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/don-foster-sees-community-spirit-in-action-in-bristol"/>
    <title>Don Foster sees community spirit in action in Bristol</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster is in Bristol today seeing how the local community are stepping up and stepping in to take charge of treasured local facilities and provide vital services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting the St Werburghs Centre, the Minister was given a glimpse of community spirit in action, meeting the local residents who rely on the centre on a daily basis for services as well as a meeting place that welcomes the whole community. The centre is home to over 180 member groups and five tenant organisations who are working with the local community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit comes two weeks after the Community Right to Bid came into force, giving communities the opportunity to ‘stop-the clock’ on the sale of valuable local assets and amenities like post offices, village shops or community pubs, giving them time to put in a takeover bid of their own and protect it for the wider community’s benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Right gives voluntary and community organisations and parish councils the opportunity to nominate an asset to be included on a list of ‘assets of community value’, pausing the sale of a successfully listed asset for six-months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Don Foster said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Communities know their local areas best and that is why we are pushing power back to neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The St Werburghs centre is a great example of community spirit in action and testament of the determination and appetite of the local community to improve the places where they live and shape their future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Community Right to Bid creates even more opportunities for people to step up and step in to save the facilities and buildings that are important to them, giving them the time to ‘stop the clock’ on sales so they have the time to get together a bid and ensure that prized local assets can live on, this time run by the local community for the local community”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locality, in partnership with The Social Investment Business and Local Government Association are helping to  support communities to take control of their local area. The My Community Rights advice service: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mycommunityrights.org.uk"&gt;www.mycommunityrights.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link) and online hub gives step by step advice, breaking down the legislation, with inspiration and ideas on using the new Community Right to Bid to make sure local amenities stay in the hands of those who care about them most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wyler, CEO, Locality said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Bid presents incredible opportunities for communities to retain land and buildings for local people - owned and used by those who value them most. Locality believes in community independence and will play a vital role empowering organisations and individuals to take control of their area.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We are working with local authorities to create registers of ‘assets of community value’ and encourage people to get in touch through the advice service so that we can help them navigate the path to saving their local shop, the sports or community centre, green spaces &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit coincides with the launch new advice for local councils to ensure they have all of the information they need to support local communities in their Right to Bid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
