<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/edward-garnier</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/edward-garnier.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Sir Edward Garnier QC MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8441</id>
    <published>2012-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/unduly-lenient-sentence-cases-referred-to-the-court-of-appeal-latest-figures"/>
    <title>Unduly lenient sentence cases referred to the Court of Appeal – latest figures</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General’s Office has released statistics for 2011 sentences which were considered too low - or unduly lenient - and referred to the Court of Appeal, which can quash a sentence and impose a higher one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, 117 sentences, from 78 cases, were referred to the Court of Appeal by the Law Officers. The Court considered 97 of them were unduly lenient (83%) and 94 sentences were increased (80% of the 117 referred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases are usually referred to the Attorney General by the Crown Prosecution Service, but it is open also to victims, their families, members of the public and MPs to ask for review. In 2011 the sentences passed on 377 offenders were drawn to the attention of the Attorney General and Solicitor General (the Law Officers), compared to 342 in 2010 and 369 in 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General, the Rt Hon Dominic Grieve QC MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The unduly lenient sentence scheme allows anyone to refer a sentence to me for consideration. In the vast majority of cases judges impose sentences which are appropriate to meet the justice of the case, but the scheme provides an important safeguard in those few cases in which the sentence falls significantly outside the proper range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sentencing is not a precise science. It requires judgments to be made about a whole host of different factors, including any aggravating and mitigating features, and how any relevant guidelines should be applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These statistics are only part of the story. Where there have been mistakes, in relation to the acceptance of pleas by the prosecution, these errors are followed up with the lawyers concerned to ensure they are not repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 377 sentences drawn to the attention of the AGO as being possibly unduly lenient in 2011, 299 fell within the scheme and were considered. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8440</id>
    <published>2012-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-tool-to-tackle-economic-crime"/>
    <title>New tool to tackle economic crime </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plans for a new tool to tackle economic crime have been published for consultation by Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC and Justice Minister Crispin Blunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Deferred Prosecution Agreements (&lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt;), companies would agree to publically admit wrongdoing, and meet tough conditions such as payment of substantial penalties, undertaking internal reform and submitting to regular review and monitoring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole process would be overseen by a judge and the threat of full prosecution would remain hanging over a company should they fail to comply with the agreement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we can encourage companies to self-report and come clean, pay penalties and mend their ways, the time and expense of investigations and prosecutions will be better spent elsewhere, enabling us to bring more individuals and companies to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An important aim of any &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; system would be to allow investigators and prosecutors to focus resources on those cases where a prosecution is in the public interest - and there will always be some where it is the only option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justice Minister Crispin Blunt said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Law enforcement agencies have told us that they do not have the tools they need to tackle increasingly complex economic crimes. Investigations can take several years and cost millions of pounds, with no guarantee of success, which means victims wait far too long for reparation. Or indeed receive no payback at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More clearly needs to be done. Deferred Prosecution Agreements will give prosecutors extra tools to tackle this type of crime and bring about a just outcome - which punishes the wrongdoer, ensures the surrendering of any proceeds and makes amends to victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic crime is increasingly complex, making it difficult to tackle effectively. As the complexity and size of commercial organisations grow, so too do the difficulties of identifying criminal activity and of bringing any organisation which commits such crime to justice. This is especially so in the case of organisations that operate, and so may have committed wrongdoing, in more than one country to which more than one set of laws can be applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DPAs would be available for prosecutors to use alongside existing methods, to give them the flexibility to secure appropriate penalties for wrongdoing, at the same time as achieving better outcomes for victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;abbr title="Deferred Prosecution Agreements"&gt;DPA&lt;/abbr&gt; is an agreement between a prosecutor and a commercial organisation that in return for complying with a range of conditions the prosecutor would defer a criminal prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An independent judge would oversee the development of the agreement to ensure it is fair, in the public interest and that the conditions properly reflect the nature of the wrongdoing. This will include the reparation made to victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, at the end of the deferral period, the prosecutor is satisfied the organisation has fulfilled its obligations, there is no prosecution on the charges laid. If, on the other hand, the commercial organisation fails to meet its obligations, further penalties are available and the original criminal proceedings could be revived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/8434</id>
    <published>2012-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/firearms-sentence-doubled-at-court-of-appeal"/>
    <title>Firearms sentence doubled at Court of Appeal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP has welcomed the doubling of the prison sentence originally given to 23-year-old Zephen Rollings for possession of a loaded firearm with intent to enable another to endanger life, from 5 to 10 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor had appealed the sentence to the Court of Appeal as possibly unduly lenient, arguing that as the supply and movement of dangerous weapons around the country was essential to the violent criminal acts committed with them, the punishment of the facilitators should reflect the gravity of the potential ultimate result of their activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Rollings, the weapon - a Smith and Wesson .357 calibre Magnum revolver loaded with hollow-point bullets, was particularly dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solicitor General said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In my view the original sentence of 5 years was unduly lenient and did not properly reflect the seriousness of the crime. It was truly shocking that a gun loaded with dum-dum bullets, which expand on impact, was being carried in broad daylight in a residential street. The Court of Appeal agreed and doubled the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The facts of this case painted a stark picture. Criminals carrying guns cause untold misery. The court clearly recognised the seriousness of this crime and I hope the increased sentence of 10 years sends out a clear message that gun crime will be dealt with severely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 6 July last year, police officers searched Zephen Rollings in a mini-cab outside an address in Brockley, South London. He was carrying a small leather bag which contained an American .357 Magnum calibre Smith and Wesson revolver. The gun was loaded with live ammunition which on test firing were found to mushroom on impact. He pleaded guilty to possessing a firearm with intent to enable another to endanger life and to possessing both a prohibited weapon and ammunition. On 10 November at Woolwich Crown Court, he was sentenced to a total of 5 years’ imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case was referred under the unduly lenient sentence scheme to the Court of Appeal and presented by the Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP. Giving judgment today, Lady Justice Hallett, Mr Justice Irwin and Mr Justice Nicol increased his sentence to 10 years’ imprisonment. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12331</id>
    <published>2011-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-2011-legal-wales-conference"/>
    <title>Speech to 2011 Legal Wales Conference </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Ladies and gentlemen, it is a pleasure to be here this afternoon to address the Legal Wales Annual Conference 2011. May I first thank my learned friend, the Chairman of the Legal Wales Standing Committee, Winston Roddick, for inviting me to do so? Whether you will thank him for doing so by the end of this talk is another matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am not Welsh, but I have been to Wales and to Cardiff on many previous occasions as a tourist, a barrister and a politician. My aunt lives in Powys, I have spent many happy days on the north Pembrokeshire coast on holiday with my wife and children, I successfully defended a libel action here in Cardiff some years ago brought against HTV by a caravan company, and masterfully failed to have another libel action brought against its Welsh language service by Daffyd Wigley moved from Caernarvon to English-speaking Mold or Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have conducted cases with and against the late, great Gareth Lord Williams of Mostyn, I have been to Her Majesty’s Prisons at Parc, Cardiff and Swansea, I have visited the South Wales &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, and I was lucky enough to watch England play Wales in the Millennium Stadium last December but 2 more facts connect me to Wales. My cousin, Crispin Masterman, is a circuit judge here in Cardiff although sensibly he is not here this week, and I was educated in that small but noisy part of Wales that sits between the Broad and the High in Oxford: Jesus College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let me tell you a little about my role as a Law Officer, the devolution landscape in Wales, and gazing at the horizon, the challenges for the Justice System in both England and Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="role-of-the-law-officers"&gt;Role of the Law Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The post of Law Officer is one of the most interesting posts for a lawyer to hold. It certainly has a colourful history. For example, one former Solicitor General, John Cooke, was responsible for prosecuting Charles I in 1649 for high treason in Westminster Hall, just a few yards from my own office in just off Central lobby. As we all know, the King was beheaded in Whitehall and went to his death with great dignity and Christian fortitude. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if Cooke though the death of the King and the abolition of the monarchy were the end of his troubles he was wrong - things caught up with the Solicitor General on the restoration of the Monarchy in 1660 when he became the first, and I hope, the last, Law Officer to be hanged, drawn and quartered. I am sure that all of us who practice in the courts of this jurisdiction will have had our good days and our not so good days in front of saintly and not so saintly judges but I trust that you, my audience, will let me get home today with that particular record still intact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney and Solicitor General have 3 main roles: as Chief Legal Advisers to the Crown and the Government, as the Government Ministers responsible for the Law Officers Departments and as guardians of the public interest. We are the political and legal heads of the Government Legal Service; we enjoy a special relationship with the lawyers in every other government department which entitles them to consult us on legal issues affecting their advice to ministers as well as where different departments have differing views on some issue that needs to be arbitrated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We seek to preserve the professional independence, and ensure high standards of advice and professional conduct in departmental lawyers. Of course, many of the legal issues that policy development gives rise to never come to the Law Officers but we remain the protectors of the rule of law and ensure that the government and its ministers conduct their business within the law and with propriety. And in that role we are ourselves lawyers but not just lawyers: as politically appointed ministers who are also lawyers we do not give advice or lead our lawyers with party-political bias nor do we adjust our advice to suit our party’s narrow political interests, but because we are appointed and accepted as fellow ministers, as fellow MPs, as elected politicians, we can speak to our colleagues in government, from the Prime Minister downwards with a confidence, a directness and with an understanding of the environment we operate within. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are there to speak truth unto power and if we do not do that we are failing in our job. It is a role that has taken on a new importance now that the Lord Chancellor is no longer the head of the judiciary but the head of a large spending and political department. The same goes for government lawyers in their departments but they have the comfort of knowing that if their advice is questioned or improperly criticised they can come to us for protection or may consult us if they have doubts about the propriety of any proposed course of action in a matter for which they have responsibility. This means that they can discharge a role in their respective departments that reflects ours at their head, not as politicians but as government lawyers who are also independent professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“From this position of strength they can advise Ministers on the legality of what they want to do, working up solutions when what is proposed collides with the constraints imposed by, say, the &lt;abbr title="European Court of Human Rights"&gt;ECHR&lt;/abbr&gt; or by our obligations under EU law. These things are matters of intense political controversy as we have been reminded this week at the conservative Party conference in Manchester and it is our job and our lawyers’ job to steer those politicians who are either over-excited, hasty or in need of a headline through the legal thickets and minefields that can destroy the unwary. Our job is not always to say “No” but to suggest they do it this way rather than that way; not to put up the red light but the amber one, to warn, to cajole and to ask, “have you thought about doing it this way?” which is, I guess, of course, what all good lawyers should do for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney General and I superintend and are responsible to Parliament for the Crown Prosecution Service, the Serious Fraud Office and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Inspectorate. We do not run these bodies, we do not micro-manage their day to day activities but we meet the &lt;abbr title="Director of Public Prosecutions"&gt;DPP&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Director of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Chief Inspector, as we do the Treasury Solicitor, the non-political head of the &lt;abbr title="Government Legal Service"&gt;GLS&lt;/abbr&gt;, to discuss the overall strategy of their organisations, we consider where in the most contentious cases the public interest lies and how it can best be served and we consent or not to those prosecutions that require our consent, and we refer to the Court of Appeal and frequently appear to argue about those Crown court sentences we consider to be unduly lenient as well as prosecuting contempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For my part, doing a job in government so closely associated with the law and the profession which has been such a big part of my life for the last 35 years is hugely rewarding. The life of the Law Officers, although circumscribed by limitations that a real politician would not tolerate, brings one to the very centre of power even if those at the centre do not realise it. It is not the dry and fusty world of the Dickensian lawyer’s office, still less the Office of Circumlocution. Of course, the public only see the capital ships, dressed fore and aft, steaming full steam ahead on the high seas, occasionally firing their guns - even at each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But below the surface and silently, and only known to a few in the law and in Whitehall, are the 2 submarines, HM Attorney and Solicitor. When we go on manoeuvres we do so to have an effect as the controversy over the Attorney General’s advice on Iraq in 2003 perhaps unfortunately reveals but there are happier examples of activities carried out in confidence for governments of both colours where the advice and restraining hand of the Law Officers has been both sensible and well received. When we surface it is usually to resign (or not), to apply to the courts in a contempt case, or to complain of an unduly lenient sentence. But my aim is not to end up like HMS Astute on the shingle bank off Skye, beached, powerless and inoperable; I am, like the man from the Inland Revenue here to help; I am but a humble seeker after truth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="devolution"&gt;Devolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government of Wales Act gives the Law Officers, along with the Counsel General for Wales (Theodore Huckle), the power to refer to the Supreme Court the question whether a Welsh Assembly Bill is within its legislative competence. So far there have not been any references but because we work closely with the Counsel General, the Welsh Government, the Assembly and the Wales Office, and they all with each other, there is no reason to expect references will be a frequent occurrence. In one sense that is a disappointment: as a member of the Bar I would relish the opportunity to argue a Welsh, Scottish or Northern Irish devolution point in the Supreme Court but by and large these difficulties are soluble without recourse to the courts. That is not to say that there may come a time when it will be sensible, indeed imperative, to ask the Supreme Court to arbitrate. No statute can anticipate every contingency so if either Wales or the United Kingdom does have to take a reference let us do so in a spirit of cooperation and willingness to hear each other’s arguments and as evidence of our willingness to make the devolution settlement work as parliament intended. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will act to clarify the limits of the devolution settlement, not to stultify political debate. We would do so to ensure that the boundaries of the devolution settlement here or in Scotland or in Northern Ireland are respected, not out of any desire to interfere with the policy behind devolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The devolution settlement itself has changed over the last 12 years - with powers shifting away from Westminster to Cardiff. In March this year, the referendum result meant further law making powers moving from Westminster to the National Assembly for Wales. The Assembly can legislate in all twenty areas covered by the original devolution settlement, including economic regeneration, education, health, transport and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a significant broadening of the Assembly’s powers, but all the areas not previously devolved remain reserved as the responsibility of the United Kingdom government and Parliament. This new constitutional landscape presents interesting challenges for us all in Westminster, Whitehall, the Welsh government and the National Assembly. We need to work together, talk to each other, correspond with each other and meet face to face to ensure that our working practices take account of the Assembly’s wider powers, understanding their new boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In July the Secretary of State for Wales announced plans to set up an independent Commission on Devolution in Wales. With the help of the Welsh government and cross-party support from the Assembly, we hope to establish the Commission this autumn. It will examine issues of fiscal devolution and accountability in Wales and will look to build a consensus around the recommendations it makes. It will take into consideration the work of the Welsh Government’s Holtham Commission, and will aim to report in the autumn of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Once the government has considered the Commission’s recommendations, it will turn its attention to looking at the boundary between what is devolved and what is not devolved in Wales, and specifically whether to recommend modifications to that boundary in light of the Assembly’s wider powers. The Commission will aim to report on this part of its work in 2013.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes---the-justice-system"&gt;Changes - the justice system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Despite all the constitutional reforms, criminal justice remains one area which is unaffected by the Welsh referendum. We are one jurisdiction. Reforms to our legal system and how we pay for it are implemented from Westminster and Whitehall but whether they came from London or Cardiff, in the current economic climate the Legal Aid reforms emanating from the Ministry of Justice will create real challenges. Publicly funded access to the law, to advice and to the courts is an essential prerequisite of any civilised and compassionate society and it will be even if to a different extent or in different ways than before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The work - work that has been carried out by hard-working, dedicated lawyers with a vocation to assist the less well off, the sick or the vulnerable for generations - will still be available but we must be adaptable and open to new ideas. Much as we would like to spend a growing percentage of public money on greater areas of legal work, we cannot afford to and thus we must face up to change and meet the challenge. It will not be easy, it may not be what we are used to or want, it has led and will lead to arguments and differences between individuals, chambers, firms, the professions, judges, and government as we seek to adapt to the new era of less public money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday ‘Alternative Business Structures’ became part of our life having been introduced by the last Government’s Legal Services Act. ABSs were not universally welcomed then and will not make us all dance in the street now but they will create opportunities by lifting the restrictions on the structure, ownership and management of businesses that provide legal services. They will allow lawyers and non-lawyers to work together in a single enterprise, providing clients with a service that recognises that the solution to at least some of their problems may not always involve recourse to the law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The external investment of funds into the legal services sector and competition will help stimulate growth which should help to maintain and even drive up the high standards of our already first class legal system. What they must not do is suborn professional standards or conduct, interfere with our duties to the court, our clients and to justice or skew our advice to please our financial masters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The role of the Law Society and the Bar Council and of the judges before whom we will appear will become all the more central to the maintenance of the highest standards but equally the independent firm of independent partners, large or small, the barrister in private practice will still have a vital and essential part to play in the justice system and one which I am determined to see survive and thrive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Other changes facing the profession include the introduction of a Quality Assurance Scheme for Advocates. The scheme devised by representatives from the Bar Standards Board, the Solicitors Regulation Authority and &lt;abbr title="Institute of Legal Executives"&gt;ILEX&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide a common and transparent assessment system for advocates in the higher courts whatever branch of the profession they are from. It will allow clients to pick the most appropriate advocate - whether barrister, solicitor or &lt;abbr title="Institute of Legal Executives"&gt;ILEX&lt;/abbr&gt; practitioner- to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There will inevitably be competition between solicitors and barristers for advocacy work but competition is at the heart of our two professions and neither should feel threatened by it. Competition, backed by high standards, properly assessed and regulated, is a good thing. Let us embrace it. These reforms bring into sharper focus the responsibilities of all of us in the legal professions to help shape the change and to adapt to change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The circuits have always been central to the professional and social life as well as the training and development of the Bar. It is through the circuit leaders and presiding judges that we talk to each other and to the judiciary. I am sure the Wales and Chester circuit will play its part in maintaining and enhancing the profession in Wales, and helping those in need of guidance and support as we navigate our way through these difficult economic times and this period of change. The Attorney and I take our roles as Leaders of the Bar seriously and we are there to help, to advise and to speak to government if needed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes---the-crown-prosecution-service"&gt;Changes - the Crown Prosecution Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms to the justice system will not only affect the private sector. The Crown Prosecution Service too is facing change. The inexorable rise in the numbers of in-house advocates at the expense of those outside has ceased as the Attorney and I have required the restoration of a proper balance between the private referral profession and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;. The comprehensive spending review touches every government department, ours included, as we implement the government’s agenda to reduce the massive budget deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This year the Crown Prosecution Service introduced a new scheme for the delivery of prosecution services in court. All advocates undertaking prosecution work from this month onwards must be members of new, quality-controlled &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Advocate Panels. The panels will be open to all barristers and solicitor advocates, and panel members will complement and work alongside &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; in-house advocates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although the overall number of advocates on the panels will be reduced, selected advocates will have more opportunity to undertake prosecution work. This initiative will help maintain the high standards of advocacy amongst prosecutors and ensure justice is delivered in Court. We will not tolerate poor advocacy from either private or employed advocates acting for the prosecution and those who cannot come up to scratch, be they in or outside the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, will not be offered the work - nor should they.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new Crown Prosecution Service Wales Area, as part of the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Senior Management Restructuring Plan, was introduced in April earlier this year. There will continue to be eight &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; offices across Wales (Wrexham, Colwyn Bay, Newtown, Camarthen, Swansea, Merthyr, Cardiff and Cwmbran) in order to ensure the effective delivery of services across Wales. We are, however, increasingly working in the digital age and the Wales is one of the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; areas leading the drive towards a more efficient and predominantly digitalised working environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For example, Dyfed-Powys was the first area to use a ‘digital file’. “Advance Information” is now provided ahead of first hearings in the Magistrates’ Court in electronic format both to the court and, where necessary, to Probation and Youth Offending Teams. This will make it easier and faster to get at information, reduce unnecessary adjournments and increase the overall efficiency of the administration of justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Crown Prosecution Service has also developed mechanisms for more effective cooperation with the police. Witness Care Units, for example now operate on a digital basis and have the capacity to move work between Units. Court files are now increasingly being prepared conjointly by the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and the police rather than wasting time and resources on creating multiple files which often never get read.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all facing difficult challenges in the current economic climate. Present circumstances have compelled us to look very hard at the current way of doing things. But reform would be needed even without an eye-watering budget deficit to worry about - to address some of the weaknesses present in the way that the Justice system operates, and to build on its strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s at times like this, when one has a difficult case to make, that I draw comfort from the strength and resilience of the traditional legal hack. Perhaps you know of the case in the Court of Appeal in which the appellant’s counsel was making heavy weather of a pretty hopeless criminal appeal. The presiding Lord Justice, beginning to lose patience but not his manners, stopped counsel in mid-stream.’Isn’t the difficulty you face, Mr Smith, that the evidence before the jury showed that your client was driving the van when it was stopped by the police, that in the back of the van was a large cardboard box all over which were found your client’s fingerprints and inside which was found a vast quantity of Class A drugs?’ Mr Smith replied, ‘Let me put it this way, my Lord. Here on the bench beside me is a copy of Archbold. It is my Archbold and I brought it here. But no one has ever suggested that I know what’s in it.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7968</id>
    <published>2011-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sentences-examined-by-the-attorney-general-in-2010"/>
    <title>Sentences examined by the Attorney General in 2010 </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Attorney General’s Office has released figures on Unduly Lenient Sentence cases which were considered too low – or unduly lenient - and referred to the Court of Appeal, which can quash a sentence and impose a higher one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;77 sentences were referred by the Law Officers. The Court considered 65 of them were unduly lenient (84%) and 60 sentences were increased (78% of the 77 referred)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2009, the sentences of 71 offenders were increased out of 108 reviewed by the Court of Appeal (66%). In 2008 52 sentences were increased out of 71 reviewed by the Court (73%).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 sentences passed on 342 offenders were drawn to the attention of both the previous incumbent, the Rt Hon Baroness Scotland QC, (from Jan to May 10,) and the present Attorney, the Rt Hon Dominic Grieve QC MP (from May to Dec 10) compared to 369 in 2009 and 274 in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dominic Grieve said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the Unduly Lenient Sentence scheme plays an important role in maintaining public confidence in sentencing as a vital tool in the criminal justice system, as well as being an important part of our role as guardians of the public interest. It is the only means by which anyone - especially victims or their families - can have an apparently unduly lenient sentence examined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC MP, added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unduly lenient sentences are rare. There are tens of thousands of sentences passed each year in the Crown Courts in England and Wales and in the vast majority of cases, the judge’s approach meets the justice of each case. The scheme provides an opportunity for the Court of Appeal to identify how sentencing in certain types of case should be approached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentencing requires judgments to be made about the weight to be attached to all the relevant considerations including aggravating and mitigating factors, and how any relevant guidelines should be applied. It may be reasonable to pass a sentence which is lenient, or which is harsher than the guidelines might suggest, on the particular facts of an individual case. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cases referred to the Court of Appeal in 2010 included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 3 March 2011, the Solicitor General presented 3 cases where the victims were sexually assaulted or raped in their homes or another place where they were entitled to feel safe. In 2 of the cases, the victims were subjected to the added humiliation of having pictures taken of the attack. The Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Henriques and Mr Justice Davis ruled that the sentences were unduly lenient, and issued guidance to sentencing judges that in a case where a violent sexual attack has been committed after or in the course of burglary in a home - even if there are no additional features beyond the rape and the burglary - the starting point will rarely be less than 12 years’ imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias Dawson, a 29-year-old offender, violently attacked his pregnant, estranged wife in a hospital car park. He knocked her to the ground and repeatedly kicked her to the head. The Attorney General, presented this case to the Court of Appeal on 9 December 2010 and the defendant saw his original sentence of 12 months imprisonment suspended for 2 years with a 2-year supervision order, quashed and replaced with one of 4 years’ imprisonment&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;49-year-old Maureen Cunniam visited the home of her near neighbours, an elderly couple, and carried out a sustained and violent attack on them with a baseball bat. She had her 3 and a half year sentence quashed and replaced with one of 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Offender “X” received a 7-year sentence for 6 counts of raping his wife which the Court of Appeal overturned and replaced with one of 11 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Charnley was jailed for 5 years for downloading and retaining 11,000 indecent images and 356 films containing indecent images of children aged between 2 and 17, over a period of 18 months. They included images of rape and sadism. In addition, on 35 occasions, over a period of 2 and a half months between June 09 and the date of his arrest, the offender had contacted adults in the Far East via the internet who, for payment, provided children aged from 2 to 12 years for the offender to view and record as he caused or incited the children to engage in sexual activity. Lord Justice Moses said that this court has a duty to pass appropriate sentences to deter others committing these types of offences; he then quashed the original sentence and replaced it with one of 12 years imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vasile Oaches and Vasile Maris received 30 and 24 months’ imprisonment respectively for trafficking into the UK for sexual exploitation and controlling prostitution for gain. The men met the 19-year-old victim in Romania and lured her and her friend to the UK with the prospect of a decent job. A third young woman was collected en route to the UK. Once there the women were required to work as street prostitutes and the offenders took their earnings. The victim was slapped and threatened by Oaches. She was also required to have sex with friends of Oaches, in lieu of payment for rent. The victim managed to escape with the help of another man she knew from Romania. The ULS hearing took place in September 2010 and the men saw their sentences increased to 4 and 3 years respectively. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7939</id>
    <published>2011-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/juror-and-defendant-sentenced-for-contempt-of-court-over-facebook"/>
    <title>Juror and defendant sentenced for contempt of court over Facebook </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a case brought by the Attorney General and presented by the Solicitor General, a juror and an acquitted defendant in a drugs conspiracy trial in Manchester Crown Court have been given custodial sentences (1 suspended) at the High Court in London for contempt of court over online discussions the 2 had engaged in during the trial. They were found guilty by the High Court on Tuesday 14 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joanne Fraill, the juror, and Jamie Sewart, the defendant, discussed the trial on the social networking site Facebook. Their activities led to the trial in Manchester Crown Court in 2010 being abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Ouseley and Mr Justice Holroyde, sitting at the High Court, heard how the pair discussed the deliberations of the jury of which Fraill was a member and which had acquitted Sewart but had yet to return verdicts on 3 other defendants. The trial, which had been running for 10 weeks, ended when the judge discharged the jury after learning of Fraill’s actions. Fraill was sentenced today to 8 months in custody and Sewart, to 2 months’ custody, suspended for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicitor General Edward Garnier QC MP, who presented the case in person, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Lord Chief Justice could not have been clearer. Joanne Fraill and Jamie Sewart’s conduct was a clear contempt of court. Jurors should take careful note and know that the Law Officers will prosecute those who commit contempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both of these women were well aware that they should not have been engaging in this discussion. The jury system is a cornerstone of our society and confidence in this vital part of our criminal justice system will crumble if jurors do not take their responsibilities seriously. Long before social networks, the courts have been in no doubt that discussions inside the jury room must stay there. The internet doesn’t make judges’ warnings not to talk about a case or research it any less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application to prosecute was made by the Attorney General, Dominic Grieve QC MP, for contempt of court at common law and under section 8 of the Contempt of Court Act 1981. The Attorney and Solicitor General are able to bring proceedings in their public interest capacity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12160</id>
    <published>2011-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-the-institute-of-international-and-european-affairs"/>
    <title>Speech to the Institute of International and European Affairs </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It is a great pleasure for me to have the opportunity of addressing you here in Dublin today. I feel very privileged to be invited to speak at the Institute of International and European Affairs - an organisation that has done a great deal to further research and discussion on important European and International developments and the implications these have for Ireland and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I cannot start my talk today without reference to Garret Fitzgerald whose recent death deprives us of a great statesman and thinker and one of the prime architects of the beneficent transformation in the relations between our countries from which we are all daily benefiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was indeed he who first made me aware of the Institute’s existence, when he presented me over 10 years ago with a copy of ‘Blair’s Britain, England’s Europe’, edited by Paul Gillespie, when I met him in the context of my interest in British-Irish relations which then led to my enjoying my years of membership of the British-Irish Parliamentary Body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think he gave me the book to challenge what he saw from our conversation as my regrettable Conservative euroscepticism and it was certainly a challenging if riveting read with its Irish dissection of the attitudes of the British body politic. But it made me realise just how much we might profitably learn from our mutual experience and I rejoice that I had the opportunity of knowing him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fortunately we find ourselves today nowhere near the more extreme developments of either end of the spectrum that the book considered. But as I realise in my office of Attorney General, we still do find ourselves in a very different Europe to the one our 2 countries joined in 1973 or indeed which prevailed in 2000. Nowhere is this more evident than in the field of Home Affairs and Justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is not just businesses, and our citizens who have benefited from freedom of movement and trade but also criminals who can now operate across borders with ease. They have adapted to this new Europe, and so have we through having to address improving judicial cooperation among Member States in an attempt to combat cross border crime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“EU criminal justice measures have moved on a great deal since work began over a decade ago to keep up with the constantly evolving nature of crime at national and international level. Crime today is increasingly complex, likely to transcend our national borders and therefore our approach to combating crime must be more flexible and involve cooperation between many agencies not just at national level but with our international partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A good example of how complex crime has become is fraud. Fraud is a real cross-border problem and, if it is to be tackled effectively and its perpetrators are to be brought to justice, it requires effective cross-border action. Globalisation of markets, internet trading and the free circulation of goods, services, persons and capital all mean that the United Kingdom cannot counter fraud in isolation. Key suspects and evidence - and key victims - may be anywhere in the world. The boundaries of national jurisdictions offer shields, not barriers, to the determined fraudster. This is an area where good co-operation at EU level can add real value. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Historically, both of our countries struggle at times with EU membership - both politicians and electors have challenged policies and decisions where they felt their national sovereignty has been threatened by Brussels and these challenges will continue. We have tried, however to work around these concerns by securing special positions for our countries under the Treaties to protect our interests in an attempt to balance our national needs and the protection of our sovereign discretion with the need to support and develop work in this important area of policy across the EU.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="justice-and-home-affairs-reviewed"&gt;Justice and home affairs reviewed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is a difficult balance to strike and as one can see by the perusal of Parliamentary debates in Hansard or the pages of our press there are plenty who believe we are getting it wrong and some who believe we should not participate at all. But I believe that any objective analysis demonstrates that work in the &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; field so far has done a great deal to arm us in the fight against cross border crime. We have some good if never perfect stories to tell. Within the last decade, a large number of EU criminal justice measures have been introduced and many of these measures have had a positive impact on our ability to prosecute cross border crime and protect our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most notable of the measures based on the mutual recognition principle was the introduction of the European Arrest Warrant Scheme in 2004. Although this is often viewed as a revolutionary new approach to extradition, it was not such an alien concept to the UK and Ireland who operated their own scheme for extradition based on the recognition of each other’s arrest warrants. This scheme was incorporated in UK law under the Backing of Warrants (Republic of Ireland) Act 1965. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“However, that process was not without its difficulties, which have been entirely ironed out under the &lt;abbr title="European Arrest Warrant"&gt;EAW&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme that is now in force and has played a key role in enabling us to secure the swift return of suspects to the UK for trial. Between January 2004 and April 2010 the &lt;abbr title="European Arrest Warrant"&gt;EAW&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme has allowed the UK to extradite over 1900 alleged or convicted offenders to other Member States. During the same period, it has resulted in 447 suspected offenders being surrendered to the UK to face justice. Most significantly it allowed for the swift return of 1 of the 21 July bombers, Hussein Osman, from Italy to the UK in 2005. In the past this may have taken quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have also seen the establishment and development of the European Judicial Network (&lt;abbr title="European Judicial Network"&gt;EJN&lt;/abbr&gt;) and Eurojust, which are both organisations that can effectively support practitioners involved in cross border cases. The role of Eurojust has been strengthened even more this month with the coming into force of the Council Decision agreed on 16 December 2008. This decision is designed to strengthen and improve Eurojust and introduces a number of changes, which include: the requirement for national desks to provide 24-hour cover to respond to requests for urgent assistance, setting out the tasks of Eurojust acting as a college (eg when to intervene in conflicts of jurisdiction), establishes a national co-ordination system in each member state and sets out new rules on information that member states should provide to Eurojust in relation to complex cross-border cases involving more than 2 member states. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Another important tool for criminal justice practitioners, introduced by the EU are Joint Investigation Teams (&lt;abbr title="Joint Investigation Teams"&gt;JITs&lt;/abbr&gt;), set up on the basis of an agreement between two or more member states and/or parties such as Europol, for a specific purpose and limited duration. This type of co-operation can be more beneficial than working through traditional mutual legal assistance channels as it allows prosecutors and law enforcement officers to work directly with their opposite numbers in the participating member state or states with support from Eurojust and Europol. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK has been involved in a number of &lt;abbr title="Joint Investigation Teams"&gt;JITs&lt;/abbr&gt;, including “Operation Golf”, which was particularly successful. The team was set up in September 2008 and was the first ever JIT to receive full EU funding amounting to 1 million Euros. Operation Golf’s activities centre on tackling organised crime groups who traffic predominantly Roma children to the UK to work as beggars and exploit the UK benefits system for criminal gain. This JIT achieved the first UK conviction of Trafficking of Human Beings of a child, and rescued 5 further victims of child exploitation, as well as uncovering evidence of systematic and widespread benefit fraud. This is an excellent example of what we can achieve when we work together with European partners using the measures that are available to us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-uk-approach-to-jha"&gt;The UK approach to &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what is the UK’s approach to &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt;? In policy terms, this government’s approach is one of full engagement in the EU, whilst being careful to safeguard our national sovereignty. To quote from the Coalition Agreement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government believes that Britain should play a leading role in an enlarged European Union, but that no further powers should be transferred to Brussels without a referendum. This approach strikes the right balance between constructive engagement with the EU to deal with the issues that affect us all, and protecting our national sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK recognizes that Title V of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, which sets out EU cooperation in Justice and Home Affairs, can help to enhance our security and provide opportunities for practical cooperation and capacity-building work on immigration, organised crime and judicial cooperation. With that in mind, the Coalition Government has undertaken that all proposals will be assessed on a case-by-case basis. We will put the national interest and the benefits to our citizens and businesses at the heart of our decision making. The government has committed to make a written statement to Parliament on each opt-in decision to ensure that Parliament is fully informed of our decision and of the reasons why it believes its decision is in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But as an issue of principle, the Government will not opt in to proposals concerning a European Public Prosecutor and has no intention of joining Schengen measures that involve the abolition of border controls. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe that our approach to &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; policy is pragmatic, measured and proportionate, having proper regard to Britain’s wider interests. We want to ensure that we participate in measures that are in the best interest of our businesses and citizens and that our decisions are informed by the views of Parliament and on rigorous assessments of each measure against a set of criteria. These criteria include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;potential impact on the integrity of the UK’s justice systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;national security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;effects on civil liberties and rights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the potential regulatory impact of the measure and wider impacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="protecting-national-interests-post-lisbon-the-eu-bill"&gt;Protecting national interests post-Lisbon: the EU Bill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having spoken in general about the UK approach to &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; I would next like to talk to you about the steps the UK Coalition Government is taking to provide more accountability for the decisions it takes in relation to how the EU develops, and to ensure that there is no further transfer of sovereignty or powers over the course of the next Parliament. The Government’s Bill on the EU, currently going through the House of Lords will require that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Any proposed future EU Treaty, agreed to by all EU member states’ governments, including the UK government, which seeks to transfer areas of power or competence from the United Kingdom to the European Union would be subject to a referendum of the British people; and,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) The use of ratchet clauses or passerelles (which are provisions in the existing EU Treaties allowing the powers of the EU to be modified or expanded without the need for a formal treaty change), would require an Act of Parliament before the government could agree to its use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It additionally includes a clause underlining parliamentary sovereignty; making clear that EU legislation has effect in the UK only because, and for such time as, Parliament wills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For measures in the &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; area, the Bill introduces specific provisions that a referendum would be required to remove the requirement for unanimity to use any of the following powers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) to approve UK participation in any proposal to create a European Public Prosecutor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) to approve UK participation thereafter in any subsequent proposal to expand the powers of a European Public Prosecutor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) for any decision under Article 4 of the Schengen Protocol (Protocol 19) that removes border control of the United Kingdom and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d) for any amendment to the Treaty that would move &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; legal bases from unanimity to QMV&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;e) for any treaty change that would remove or amend the emergency brake mechanisms contained in Articles 82(3) and 83(3) of the TFEU&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ‘emergency brake’ available to all member states is an important protection mechanism available to us. The Bill will make it clear that any attempt to change the Treaties so as to remove these emergency brakes from this or future treaties would be subject to a UK referendum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Both for the emergency brakes and for the measures listed other Member States could of course go ahead without the UK. However the referendum stops a UK government joining in such a change unless the UK public have confirmed that they support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Bill additionally provides that an Act of Parliament must approve any UK decision to use the &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; ratchet clauses contained in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Article 81(3) TFEU to permit the application of ordinary legislative procedure in place of special legislative procedure in family law&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Article 82(2)(d) TFEU to add to the list of criminal procedures on which EU directives may be made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) Article 83(1) TFEU to add to the list of serious crimes with a cross-border dimension on which directives may be made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These ratchet clauses would apply a lesser voting requirement to measures in family law areas, or, for areas relating to criminal law, enable an expansion of the issues over which the EU has competence, for example as crimes develop that simply did not exist until relatively recently, like cybercrime. For instance, there are indications that the Commission will wish to propose adding female genital mutilation and/or violence against women to the list of serious crimes with a cross-border dimension on which the EU can act in Art. 83(1)TFEU. If that were the case, and the government indicated that it would wish to support this proposal, an Act of Parliament would be required to approve the UK’s adoption of any proposal to add these offences to the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government made further comments in the Written Ministerial Statement of 20 January this year, which set out a package of measures to strengthen Parliamentary scrutiny of EU business, reinforcing the government’s commitment to honour the Ashton commitments providing for enhanced scrutiny over European Justice and Home Affairs matters, but highlighting that the government would undertake further extensions to those parliamentary scrutiny arrangements. Thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) The government now commits to a Written Ministerial Statement on each opt-in decision, or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) where appropriate and necessary, Ministers will make this Statement on an opt-in decision orally to parliament&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) The Written Ministerial Statement outlined that the Government actively urges the House of Commons and Lords Scrutiny Committees to take full advantage of their existing rights under the Ashton Commitments, including the right to call a debate on an amendable motion on any opt-in decision&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Committees have thus far exercised this right only twice; the Commons called a debate on the Cross border enforcement road safety offences directive and the Lords called a debate on the Minimum Standards on procedures in Member States for granting and withdrawing refugee status and on the minimum standards for the qualification and status of third country nationals or stateless persons as refugees or as persons who otherwise need international protection and the content of the protection granted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d) The Government also expressed its willingness to set aside Government time for a debate in both Houses on a motion on the Government’s recommended approach to the opt-in on issues where there is strong Parliamentary interest in the Government’s decision whether or not to opt in to such a measure. The Government has already committed itself to holding a debate on the 2014 opt-out decision&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What the EU Bill does not cover is the ordinary use of the UK’s opt-in protocol. This falls outside the scope of the bill, because it was agreed under the Lisbon treaty, and it is considered that it would be contrary to the UK’s interests to lose flexibility here.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="stockholm-the-future-of-jha"&gt;Stockholm: the future of &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whilst it is very important to us to have the safeguards I’ve mentioned to you in place we also consider that it is important to be as fully engaged in &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; work as possible, particularly in the context of Stockholm. The UK has worked hard to feed into the new &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; work programme that replaced the Hague Programme earlier this year. The Stockholm Programme sets out what it considers should be the priorities in all &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; areas for the next 5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“More specifically, on criminal justice, the Programme, as you will be aware, envisages the extension of the principle of mutual recognition for all stages of criminal procedure, including measures to protect victims and witnesses, and disqualifications arising from convictions. The training of prosecutors and judges is seen as an essential element in increasing mutual confidence and the EU envisages more work in this area. Evaluation is also highlighted as a priority, to improve the implementation of legislation. Five key areas of organised crime will be targeted, human trafficking, sexual exploitation of children, cyber crime, financial crime and drug trafficking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Judicial co-operation will also be strengthened, with priority given to work to improve the exchange of criminal records and enhanced mechanisms to exchange evidence, accompanied by work on strengthening the rights of defendants in criminal proceedings. This is an important area of work that the UK supports subject to detailed scrutiny of the proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have already seen some important measures issued at EU level since the introduction of Stockholm, which include the European Investigation Order (EIO), the Proposal for an EU Directive on the Right to Information in Criminal Proceedings, EU Directive on Combating the Sexual Exploitation of Children and Child Pornography, the European Protection Order and the Cybercrime Directive. The UK has opted-in to all these proposals. In addition the UK is awaiting parliamentary approval on a recommendation to participate in the Human Trafficking Directive post-adoption and we are currently considering whether to opt-in to the recently published Victims’ Directive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although all these proposals for EU criminal justice measures are important, the EIO is likely to have the most impact on criminal justice practitioners when it is eventually introduced across Europe. It will streamline the process of Mutual Legal Assistance (&lt;abbr title="Mutual Legal Assistance"&gt;MLA&lt;/abbr&gt;) between EU countries. UK practitioners frequently describe the current system as fragmented, confusing and subject to delays. The EIO seeks to simplify the Mutual Legal Assistance system amongst EU Member States through introducing a standardised request form, by providing formal deadlines for the recognition and execution of requests and by replacing the majority of &lt;abbr title="Mutual Legal Assistance"&gt;MLA&lt;/abbr&gt; instruments with a single instrument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK government carried out a consultation with Police and other UK law enforcement agencies, prosecutors, private practitioners, academics, the Law Society of England and Wales, Criminal Law Solicitors’ Association, Fair Trials International, Justice and many others. The majority view was that the UK should opt in. While there were some anxieties expressed that it could lead to the forced harmonisation of criminal procedure, we have decided to do so.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="meeting-the-challenges-of-operating-post-lisbon"&gt;Meeting the challenges of operating post-Lisbon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As you are all aware, all these new proposals introduced under Stockholm are subject to the post-Lisbon procedures. Protocol 21 on the Position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in Respect of the Area of Freedom, Security and Justice has secured important safeguards for our 2 countries, and introduced a process that allows us to decide whether or not to opt-in to any proposals or initiatives presented to the Council pursuant to Title V of Part Three of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union. Although this is a new process for criminal justice measures (and civil matters) it is not a new concept for us as we have been operating a similar process for asylum and immigration matters for many years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is important to have secured an opt-in process for &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; measures, however, it does pose additional challenges for practitioners and policy makers. As you know, under the Protocol, our countries are allowed 3 months in which to consider whether we wish to participate in a new measure. This is a relatively short period of time to analyse the impact of the measure at national level and to allow for Parliamentary scrutiny of the proposal to take place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The latter is particularly challenging if the proposal is issued during a period of Parliamentary Recess. I have already spoken about the requirements introduced by the Written Ministerial Statements of 20 January 2011, which means that Parliamentary scrutiny of &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; measures post-Lisbon is much more thorough than it was for previous Third Pillar instruments subject to unanimity. I understand that Ireland has also experienced difficulties in scrutinizing &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; measures. Detailed scrutiny of these measures will be a continuing challenge for our policy makers and parliaments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although, our ability to choose whether we participate in &lt;abbr title="Justice and Home Affairs"&gt;JHA&lt;/abbr&gt; measures or not sets us apart from other Member States we must not forget the most notable difference that distinguishes us from the majority of our European partners and which dates back much further than any special arrangements introduced by the EU Treaties. That difference is our shared common law legal tradition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Again, this isn’t a new challenge and we have frequently faced these hurdles together during the negotiation of measures with countries which do not share our common law tradition and misunderstand concerns we have because our criminal justice process is different. The most notable areas that are misunderstood are the investigative processes in common law jurisdictions and the very different role that victims and witnesses play during our proceedings. If any such points arose, pre-Lisbon we could be reassured that unanimity would offer us the protection if our civil law partners were unable to understand any concerns we had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now, post-Lisbon, we may frequently find ourselves in situations where any concerns resulting from our different legal systems are shared only by a minority of Member States. If the measure is of key importance to European judicial cooperation we are then faced with the dilemma of whether to opt in to a measure containing provisions we may not be confident we can to amend under QMV or opting out of an area of work that could potentially benefit us in tackling cross border crime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an area where we need to work together to give our civil law partners a greater understanding of our different legal systems and the very specific issues we face as a result of our common law jurisdictions. However, I am encouraged by recent proposals issued under the Stockholm Programme, which seek to respect and accommodate the different legal traditions operating among all European partners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope that in this talk I have been able to set out for you something of the principles with which the UK will seek to approach the undoubted opportunities but also the challenges of the development of the EU’s Home Affairs and Justice policies. We are determined not to take a blinkered approach and very conscious that we should look to our European and International partners, who meet common standards of human rights and justice, for cooperation in combating crime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This of necessity requires pragmatism and a willingness to share powers to achieve sensible goals. But we will ensure that we only participate in measures that are in the interests of our businesses and citizens and our decisions will be informed by the views of Parliament and on rigorous assessments of each measure against a set of established criteria. We believe that this balance can allow us to be fully engaged in an important area of work at European level, while preserving our national sovereignty and the civil liberties of our citizens and upholding the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In striving to achieve this I know that we will wish to look to you here in Ireland, where your national legal traditions are so close to our own and the challenges so similar, yet perspectives may at times be quite different, for a dialogue and mutual critique of how best we can approach these matters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our ability to do this for each other appears to me to be one of the best of the many good legacies of the efforts of Garret Fitzgerald and many others in both our countries in transforming our bilateral relations in the last quarter century. We must strive to ensure that we build on their good works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank you, again, for the invitation to speak here today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12159</id>
    <published>2011-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-annual-conference-of-the-institute-of-money-laundering-prevention-officers"/>
    <title>Speech to Annual Conference of the Institute of Money Laundering Prevention Officers </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I want to begin with a brief overview of the organisations involved in dealing with economic crime, reporting to or superintended by different government departments. There are several of them and when I first looked at the question of how best to investigate, prosecute and deter complex economic crime 18 months ago when in opposition it all looked to me very much like alphabet soup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney General and I are the government’s ‘Law Officers’. We are both Ministers of the Crown, politicians appointed by the Prime Minister to be part of the political government. We can also get sacked or moved by the Prime Minister just like any other minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We vote with the government and we accept collective responsibility with our colleagues, but in some major respects we are quite different to other ministers by virtue of the office we hold. Harold Macmillan told Peter Rawlinson on his appointment as Solicitor General in the early 1960’s that his first loyalty was to the rule of law; his second was to Parliament and only in third place came his loyalty to the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is because we are not jobbing political ministers but Law Officers to the Crown and just like lawyers in private practice we spend a good deal of time advising and acting for our main client, the government in its many guises. We are by statute interchangeable, each can carry out each other’s work and since there are only 2 of us, it frequently happens that one of us will be away, abroad or out of London, even occasionally on holiday, so we need to be able to step into the other’s shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Put shortly, we exercise a number of functions in the public interest, such as the power to bring contempt proceedings to protect criminal trials and the administration of justice. We appear in the courts of England and Wales, in the European Court of Justice and the European Court of Human Rights on behalf of the government or to assert the public interest. We also superintend the Law Officers’ departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Two of these are of direct relevance to your conference and are concerned with economic crime: the Serious Fraud Office (&lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;) and the Crown Prosecution Service (&lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is the independent government department that investigates and prosecutes serious or complex fraud, and corruption, with jurisdiction in England, Wales and Northern Ireland. The Director of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is appointed by and accountable to the Attorney General. The key factors that the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; considers before taking on a case are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;does the value of the alleged fraud exceed £1 million?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is there a significant international dimension?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the case likely to be of widespread public concern?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;does the case require highly specialised knowledge, eg of financial markets?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is there a need to use the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s special powers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“By taking on appropriate cases, investigating them and bringing them to a successful conclusion as quickly as individual circumstances allow, the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; contributes to bringing financial criminals to justice; to the reduction of fraud and corruption and their cost to the public, our economy and our national reputation; and to the maintenance of confidence in the United Kingdom’s business and financial institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Other economic crime is investigated, but not prosecuted, by the police. The City of London Police is the national lead force for fraud. The Serious Organised Crime Agency (&lt;abbr title="Serious Organised Crime Agency"&gt;SOCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) tackles serious organised crime that affects the United Kingdom, including fraud and money laundering but of course its remit takes in human and drug trafficking as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Local police forces are responsible for investigating less serious fraud in their areas - and by that I mean frauds that can be measured in hundreds of thousands of pounds, as opposed to multi-millions, and although perhaps less significant in terms of each individual case when looked at from the centre, these cases represent a huge loss to the country and to individual victims. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Home Secretary is the Minister responsible for the police, and for the criminal law on money laundering. The Treasury leads on what I would loosely call the City and the financial services sector, dealing with the regulatory framework and industry guidance, and through what is presently called the Financial Services Authority, but will before too long become the Financial Conduct Authority, disciplines the financial services sector and prosecutes financial crime, for example, insider trading, market abuse, and boiler room scams. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="Financial Services Authority"&gt;FSA&lt;/abbr&gt; is accountable to Treasury Ministers and, through them, Parliament, but is operationally independent of government and funded entirely by the firms it regulates and, like the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;, is an integrated investigator-prosecutor. HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs, the Office of Fair Trading and a number of industry bodies supervise compliance with the Money Laundering Regulations by businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Financial crime investigated by the police (or HM Revenue &amp;amp; Customs) is prosecuted by the Crown Prosecution Service. Within the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, the Central Fraud Group prosecutes all cases of direct tax, indirect tax, excise duty and tax credit fraud. This work used to be done by the Revenue and Customs Prosecution Office but that has now been merged within the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; through the Central Fraud Group. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is also responsible for prosecuting cases involving export control, illegal arms trafficking and sanctions violations, together with money laundering offences where any of the above appears as the trigger offence. The Group prosecutes fraud cases where the value of the fraud is in excess of £1 million or, if the case is considered to be complex, sensitive or to have a potentially high media profile. Other fraud cases are prosecuted by &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government has made crime reduction a top priority and this includes reducing the amount of economic crime. All crime, but particularly complex economic crime, is expensive both in time and money to investigate and to prosecute but its effects can be as devastating to its victims as violent or other acquisitive crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most cost-effective way of cutting crime is prevention. Individuals and organisations need to recognise that they have to take responsibility for protecting themselves from fraud and the consequences of other economic crime, but the state has a duty to ensure that there is an effective criminal justice system that can respond quickly, proportionately and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need therefore to ask ourselves whether the current system does what it should, to see whether it working?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All the agencies I have mentioned can point to notable recent successes but in January this year the National Fraud Authority (&lt;abbr title="National Fraud Authority"&gt;NFA&lt;/abbr&gt;) published its Annual Fraud Indicator, which estimated that fraud is costing our national economy over £38 billion a year. The breakdown by sector was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;public - £21 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;private - £12 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;individuals - £4 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charity - £1.3 billion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Fraud not only has serious consequences for individuals, businesses and public services: it is also often used to fund serious crimes, such as terrorism, drugs or human trafficking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The estimated cost of organised crime to the UK economy is £20-40 billion a year. The importance of tackling organised crime through disruption of criminals, plots, conspiracies and crime itself cannot be overstated. Money, and particularly tax-free access to other people’s money, both motivates criminals and constitutes the reward for the risk of conducting criminal activities and it provides the capital available to invest in future scams and conspiracies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Organised criminals may accumulate wealth in cash and assets or spend their profits sustaining a lavish lifestyle, and the profits from crime are used to buy the goods and services needed to fuel future criminal activity. Criminal finances run through and link all aspects of organised criminality, from burglaries committed locally to pay for drugs, to supporting the networks needed to smuggle the same drugs across international borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what are the government and the relevant agencies doing, and going to do, to bear down on economic crime?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“First, we need better to coordinate the work of the alphabet soup of organisations already referred to. The infrastructures underpinning criminal finances are as varied, complex and sophisticated as the methods of criminality employed by the gangs and individuals who operate locally, nationally and internationally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Money laundering shifts resources between fraud and financially-motivated organised crime and most criminals will be involved to some extent in laundering their criminal proceeds, to hide their true origins and to legitimise them. They will go to great lengths to hide or disperse their ill-gotten gains so that they cannot be recovered by the police or stolen by some other crook. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They will use more than one money laundering method at a time, from relatively low level laundering such as investing in property, putting the cash through front companies, foreign exchange dealing and using false accounting, to more sophisticated methods such as layering and online money transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we need to be ahead of them, more sophisticated than they are and more resolute to catch them than they are to avoid. The government made clear in our Coalition Programme, published a year ago, that we take white collar crime as seriously as other crime, and that to achieve success and to avoid duplication and gaps in our criminal justice system that could be exploited by criminals we would create an Economic Crime Agency to take on the work of tackling serious economic crime that is currently spread between the Serious Fraud Office, the Financial Services Authority and the Office of Fair Trading. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This was a project that was being worked on by both the Treasury and my own department but last autumn, the government decided that criminal prosecution powers in relation to market abuse should for the time being remain with the &lt;abbr title="Financial Services Authority"&gt;FSA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s successor body, the &lt;abbr title="Financial Conduct Authority"&gt;FCA&lt;/abbr&gt; thus ensuring that the &lt;abbr title="Financial Conduct Authority"&gt;FCA&lt;/abbr&gt;’s markets unit will have powers to both regulate and prosecute market abuse. The legislation that will bring about the reorganisation of the Bank of England’s role and those of the &lt;abbr title="Financial Conduct Authority"&gt;FCA&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Consumer Protection and Markets Authority will be introduced later this year but it meant that consideration of the way we deal with non-City specific economic crime, whilst remaining with my department transferred from the Treasury to the Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Home Secretary, the Law Officers and other relevant colleagues are currently considering options for delivering this commitment, and we hope, ending the piecemeal approach to tackling white-collar crime. The economic crime landscape, to use the Whitehall jargon, is diverse, and it is complicated so all our efforts need to be focused not on creating structures but on attacking the very thing that causes us all to be concerned: that hydra-headed monster which is complex economic crime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to deploy the right resources, the right skills and the right intelligence against the several types of economic crimes currently bedevilling us. In this, the Home Office is working closely with the Attorney General’s Office and others including the Ministry of Justice, the Treasury and the Cabinet Office. It is important to get this right, and we are giving careful consideration to all the issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How can we improve the international and high end work we presently do through the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; in investigating and bringing to justice foreign-based and British-based criminals who attempt to corrupt and undermine our economy and those of countries overseas, to use our top FTSE companies without their knowledge as cover for international crime, who work across national and continental boundaries to achieve their criminal ends? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How can we ensure that the City of London Police can better lead and coordinate our investigative effort with international partners and, within this jurisdiction, with county police forces whose focus tends, quite properly, to be on drug dealers, burglars, and Friday night city centre violence, rather than on those conducting medium-size frauds and financial crimes on the domestic stage? How do we ensure that cases that are not big enough or lack a sufficiently international dimension for the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; are taken up by the police, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; Central Fraud Group or by the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and are not left un-investigated and not prosecuted so that those who have committed crime get away with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One organisational consolidation that will improve our ability to fight economic crime is already in place. From 1 April, the Home Office took over responsibility from the Attorney General’s Office for the National Fraud Authority (&lt;abbr title="National Fraud Authority"&gt;NFA&lt;/abbr&gt;), which leads on combating fraud across the public and private sector through research and public dissemination of knowledge and good practice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is hoped that this change will strengthen the country’s ability to crackdown on fraudsters by building closer links with those engaged in the wider fight against organised and cyber crime. At the time, the Home Secretary commented: ‘The government is determined to give greater focus to tackling both serious and economic crime… the move of the &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Authority"&gt;NFA&lt;/abbr&gt; to the Home Office… will forge even closer links with our key partners in the police, Serious Organised Crime Agency and other law enforcement agencies.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Secondly, to improve our response to economic crime, we need to ensure that the criminal justice system, at every stage, prioritises economic crime and has the powers to deal with it effectively. Economic crime is not a ‘victimless crime’, but includes, for instance, stealing from pension funds. The public expects the police and prosecutors to combat fraudsters as much as other villains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many of the necessary operational and legal weapons are already in place. Our law enforcement agencies already have formidable powers for investigating criminal finances and recovering assets from criminals under the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002 (&lt;abbr title="Proceeds of Crime Act"&gt;POCA&lt;/abbr&gt;). These powers provide robust and valuable means by which to detect, disrupt and deter criminals, and the amount of criminal finances disrupted since the introduction of &lt;abbr title="Proceeds of Crime Act"&gt;POCA&lt;/abbr&gt; has gone up every year. We can and should do more though to recover the proceeds of crime, criminal assets and to return to victims the money they have lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So we need to encourage all police forces, not just the City of London Police, to have a real focus on fraud and money laundering. The effective investigation of money laundering helps in the recovery of stolen assets and disrupts funding for terrorism and for human and drug traffickers. There is not a police force in the country that is not facing organisational change and financial constraints, but the Home Secretary has said that despite this they should be able to deal with their main activities, including the investigation of financial crime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, to identify and investigate economic crime, the police need good intelligence. The private sector has a key role to play here. I know that some of you may have concerns about the regulatory burden of Suspicious Activity Reports. But &lt;abbr title="Suspicious Activity Reports"&gt;SARs&lt;/abbr&gt; are a crucial information and intelligence resource for law enforcement action against money launderers and fraudsters. &lt;abbr title="Serious Organised Crime Agency"&gt;SOCA&lt;/abbr&gt; receives over 200,000 &lt;abbr title="Suspicious Activity Reports"&gt;SARs&lt;/abbr&gt; a year, the majority of which come from the financial services industry. I understand that the Treasury is currently reviewing how the money laundering regime works in practice, and will issue a response to that review shortly. No doubt you will hear more about that from Hugh Burns, who is speaking to you later this afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also aware that difficulties can arise about what officers in the regulated sector can tell clients while awaiting &lt;abbr title="Serious Organised Crime Agency"&gt;SOCA&lt;/abbr&gt; consent to complete a reported transaction, or for the moratorium period to expire. Section 333 of the Proceeds of Crime Act is not an easy provision to understand both as to its offences, its exceptions and its defences so I appreciate that nominated officers have genuine concerns about whether their conduct, either through omission or commission, could lead to their being implicated in or prosecuted for the offence of tipping off contrary to section 333. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“However, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; is of the view that if tipping off happens inadvertently, the nominated officer would have a viable defence. Under the Code for Crown Prosecutors, a prosecution for any offence requires, first, enough evidence to provide a realistic prospect of conviction, and, secondly, that the prosecution is in the public interest. In cases of minor harm or where the offence under sections 330-332 or 336 of &lt;abbr title="Proceeds of Crime Act"&gt;POCA&lt;/abbr&gt; has been committed as a result of a genuine mistake or misunderstanding, the public interest may be better served by referring the matter to the relevant regulatory or supervisory authority to deal with, rather than by pursuing a criminal prosecution or a caution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Moving on to the prosecution of economic crime more generally, the Attorney General and I are concerned to ensure that prosecutors and the courts have all the tools and powers they need. We are discussing this with our ministerial colleagues in the MoJ. Should the government decide to take any changes forward to legislation it will consider whether there is a need for consultation on specific issues but the areas we are considering making changes have to do with, for example, deferred prosecution arrangements and more effective use of civil remedies and asset recovery, more effective indications of sentence under the Goodyear principles and pre-conviction changes in disclosure requirements. In the longer term, we also plan to look at whether the law on corporate criminal liability needs to be readjusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Turning to the sentencing of convicted offenders, fraudulent conduct can come within a variety of common law and statutory offences such as conspiracy, money laundering, handling, theft, corruption or bribery, all with different maximum or likely sentences. In 2009, the Sentencing Guidelines Council produced a Definitive Guideline on Sentencing for statutory offences of fraud which addressed this issue. And its successor the Sentencing Council, chaired by Lord Justice Leveson, has recently agreed to consider the scope for a guideline on bribery and corporate or financial crime, and will begin work on this in the current financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One of the our powers as Law Officers is to ask the Court of Appeal to review sentences which we consider to be “unduly lenient” - not less than we would have sentenced or another judge could have sentenced but so far below what is manifestly correct that a judge could not reasonably have given that sentence. Only certain cases are eligible: the more serious crimes which can be dealt with only in the Crown Court, including all conspiracy charges and cheating the Revenue; and some other specified offences (none of which relate to economic crime). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Any such referral has to be made within 28 days of the passing of the sentence. Anyone can alert us to an unduly lenient sentence, and we consider all such cases personally. If we refer a case, and if the Court of Appeal agrees the sentence was unduly lenient, it can increase the sentence. These powers have been used in a ‘missing trader’ fraud case in 2006, in which the Court of Appeal increased the sentencing levels for this kind of crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Last but not least, when financial and other criminals are brought to justice, it is important to try to recover the proceeds of their crimes. The &lt;abbr title="Proceeds of Crime Act"&gt;POCA&lt;/abbr&gt; powers are being used increasingly effectively as agencies become practised in their use, and internationally we are seen as world leaders in asset recovery. When used to their full effect these powers have dramatic consequences, and common sense and police intelligence tell us that many organised criminals are far more concerned about losing their (or more accurately, other people’s) money than spending time in prison. But no matter how good we get at recovering the proceeds of crime there will always be a huge number of crooks who have the means and the wherewithal to stay one step ahead of the police so we need to make their lives uncomfortable and their ambitions less global.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why the government will soon publish an Organised Crime Strategy, which will set out how we will increase our ability to hit a far wider range of criminal finances in particular through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increasing the effectiveness of asset recovery activity and unblocking our bureaucratic systems, including stepping up our ability to recover and disrupt criminal finances held overseas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognising and broadening the use of asset denial &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stepping up work to target conspirators, back-room crooks and money launderers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Thirdly, we need to recognise the importance of international cooperation in combating economic crime. The volume of financial business in London means it can be used by criminals to move money quickly and easily into other markets and jurisdictions through the international financial community. To counter this international cooperation between police forces and prosecutors is vital. Criminal activities are now more often transnational, exploiting the deficiencies, particularly failures in cooperation and mutual assistance. Criminals and their professional advisers know how international cooperation works and they know how to exploit its weaknesses to stay ahead of the law enforcement authorities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is President of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (&lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt;) Task Force on tax crime and other crimes (including money laundering) and influential in providing training on money laundering to &lt;abbr title="Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development"&gt;OECD&lt;/abbr&gt; member countries. The &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; has extensive strategic and operational experience of working with overseas law enforcement agencies and jurisdictions in fraud and corruption cases, through mutual legal assistance and via Europol, Eurojust and Interpol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Its relations with the US Department of Justice are close and mutually advantageous as I was able to confirm with the US Attorney General last week when he was in London. The &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is the evaluator for the Council of Europe’s Group of States against Corruption (GRECO), looking at other countries’ legislation and operational methods and recommending improvements at the Council of Europe in Strasbourg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; also has good experience of working with overseas partners in economic crime cases. By its nature, &lt;abbr title="Missing Trader Intra-Community"&gt;MTIC&lt;/abbr&gt;, ‘missing trader’, or ‘carousel’, fraud in particular cannot be prosecuted without law enforcement and prosecutors working effectively with their overseas counterparts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A recent example was Operation Duma, which involved the prosecution of 7 defendants for conspiracy to Cheat the Public Revenue, relating to a £45 million missing trader fraud concerning the purchase and sale of mobile phones. The investigation focused upon the activities of 6 companies operated by the defendants. Important evidence was provided by investigators in a number of European countries and the Far East. All 7 defendants were convicted over the course of 2 trials and each received sentences of between 4 and 15 years imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope I have shown you that the government is determined to increase the salience of economic crime within the justice system, to demonstrate that we Law Officers are determined to play our part in leading the campaign against it and to help enhance and make more efficient the efforts of our criminal justice and law enforcement agencies. To do this we need the support of the private sector, and close working relationships with our overseas’ counterparts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is our mission to bring these crooks to justice, to take their ill-gotten gains from them and to see them sentenced in such a way that they will be deterred from trying it again and that those who think this an easy way to make a living come to see it as a quick and certain way to prison.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12161</id>
    <published>2011-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/speech-to-the-annual-retail-fraud-conference"/>
    <title>Speech to the Annual Retail Fraud Conference </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Thank you for inviting me to speak to you today. I see this is the 8th Annual Retail Fraud Conference, but I understand I’m the first Law Officer to address one, so I will start by saying a bit about our role.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-law-officers"&gt;The Law Officers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Attorney General and I are the Government’s ‘Law Officers’. To most people nowadays (perhaps even to some Law Officers) the Law Officers are something of a mystery. The Office of Attorney General is an ancient one, though much changed over the years. Legal historians like to argue about who the first Attorney General was though given the way that the role has changed it is debatable whether the “first” Attorney was in any meaningful sense like the Attorney of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am not even sure whether my ancestor, William de Grey, who between 1762 and 1781 was successively Solicitor and Attorney General and then Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas, would recognise the office today. He suffered so badly from gout in his hands and fingers that he could not hold a quill to take a note of the evidence or the arguments and yet as a judge delivered extempore judgments after lengthy civil trials that better historians and lawyers than I tell me would pass muster in today’s higher courts. I have inherited his pride in being a Law Officer and gout - but not his intellect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But what history has bequeathed us is an Attorney General who is a Minister of the Crown and Chief Legal Adviser to the Government. He is not a member of Cabinet though he will attend when his advice is required or when matters within his responsibility come up for consideration. He also exercises a number of functions in the public interest, such as the power to bring contempt proceedings to protect criminal trials and the administration of justice. He superintends the ‘Law Officers’ Departments’, including the Crown Prosecution Service and the Serious Fraud Office. He also oversees the Government Legal Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So, as Law Officers, the Attorney General and I are politically appointed and members of the government, but we are not only political ministers like other members of the government; we are also lawyers. (In my case, I have been a Barrister for 35 years, a QC for 15 of those, and worked as a Recorder - a part-time judge - in the Crown Court since 1998.) The core function of the Attorney General is to make sure that government, that Ministers, act lawfully, in accordance with the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course the public only see the capital ships, dressed fore and aft, steaming full steam ahead on the high seas, occasionally firing their guns, but below the surface and silently, and known only to a few in the law and in Whitehall, are the 2 submarines, HM Attorney and Solicitor. When we go on manoeuvres we do so to have an effect. There are many examples of activities carried out in confidence for governments of both colours where the advice and restraining hand of the Law Officers has been both sensible and well received. When we surface it is usually to apply to the courts in a contempt case, or to complain of an unduly lenient sentence. But so much of our time is not spent just saying, “No, but have you thought about doing it this way?” which is what all good lawyers should do for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As I have said, one of the Departments the Law Officers superintend is the Serious Fraud Office (&lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;). The &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt;’s forensic accountants, professional investigators and lawyers investigate and prosecute the most serious or complex instances of fraud and corruption, in England, Wales and Northern Ireland. By bringing criminals to justice they help maintain confidence in the UK’s business and financial institutions. The Director of the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; is appointed by and accountable to the Attorney General, who is responsible to Parliament for the &lt;abbr title="Serious Fraud Office"&gt;SFO&lt;/abbr&gt; and the other Law Officers’ Departments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-role-of-the-cps-within-the-criminal-justice-system"&gt;The role of the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; within the Criminal Justice System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The largest of these Departments is the Crown Prosecution Service (&lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;). The &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; was set up in 1986 as an independent authority to prosecute criminal cases investigated by the police in England and Wales. It is headed by the Director of Public Prosecutions (&lt;abbr title="Director of Public Prosecutions"&gt;DPP&lt;/abbr&gt;), and its role includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;advising the police during the early stages of investigations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;determining the appropriate charges in more serious or complex cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keeping all cases under review and deciding which should be prosecuted, by applying the ‘Code for Crown Prosecutors’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The key principles of this Code are that a prosecution should only go ahead if there is enough evidence to provide a realistic prospect of conviction, and, if so, where a prosecution is needed in the public interest. If a prosecution does go ahead, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; then has to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prepare cases for court, and either prosecute them by in-house advocates, or instruct agents and/or counsel to present cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide information and assistance to victims and prosecution witnesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, to over-simplify:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Home Secretary is responsible for the police, who investigate crime, and can deal with offences without them going to court&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Law Officers are responsible for the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; and other agencies who prosecute offences in court&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Lord Chancellor is responsible for the courts that try cases and the prison and probation services who take charge of convicted offenders” &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="the-partnership-approach-to-preventing-retail-crime"&gt;The partnership approach to preventing retail crime&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, the ideal is to make this system redundant, by preventing crimes being committed in the first place. This government has put cutting crime at the centre of our ambition, and this includes crimes against business and retailers. We believe a strong partnership approach is needed to tackle retail crime, and we are firmly committed to working alongside business and trade associations to find effective solutions and responses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="national-retail-crime-steering-group"&gt;National Retail Crime Steering Group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Retail Crime Steering Group, set up by the Home Office with the British Retail Consortium, embodies this partnership approach at the national level. It brings together many of the key organisations involved in the fight against retail crime: the government, the police, major retailers and trade associations. The Steering Group, co-chaired by the Home Office’s Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Crime Prevention, James Brokenshire, provides a forum to discuss and devise strategies for tackling crimes of concern to retailers, including shop theft, violence against staff and the growing threat of e-crime. At this national level, the government will work with industry and businesses to broker solutions that cannot be solved by local action alone and will promote the sharing of effective practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Part of the Steering Group’s role is to support businesses to do more to help themselves, through both greater crime prevention activity by designing out crime, and taking more corporate social responsibility, to deny opportunities for criminals to commit crimes. Effective crime prevention advice is available for businesses, and the Home Office is making it a priority to share good practice examples of businesses working together, and in partnership with the police and other law enforcement agencies, to tackle retail crime locally.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="local-partnerships"&gt;Local partnerships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The key local partnerships for working to cut crime are Community Safety Partnerships (&lt;abbr title="Community Safety Partnerships"&gt;CSPs&lt;/abbr&gt;). &lt;abbr title="Community Safety Partnerships"&gt;CSPs&lt;/abbr&gt; already have a duty to seek the views of the public and people who represent the interests of many different groups, which should include the business community. Whilst it is for each partnership to determine whether business crime is a priority that needs to be addressed in their local area, the Home Office would expect businesses to engage with their &lt;abbr title="Community Safety Partnerships"&gt;CSPs&lt;/abbr&gt; where possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="police-and-crime-commissioners"&gt;Police and Crime Commissioners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“From May 2012, the government is replacing bureaucratic police authorities with directly elected Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs). The Home Office will give them the maximum control over their resources so they can decide how best to tackle crime at a local level. I understand there is a concern that PCCs may consider business crime a low priority. But they will have to respond to the needs of the local community as whole, including businesses, and the government would expect PCCs to engage with all their principal local partners, so that they can identify and focus on the key priorities across their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a real opportunity for the police to be more accountable to their local communities and businesses, and for businesses to influence the local policing agenda. I understand that the British Retail Consortium will be producing guidance for PCCs which will assist them with the issues of crimes affecting business, which is a positive step.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-purpose-of-the-criminal-justice-system"&gt;The purpose of the criminal justice system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But crime reduction will sadly only take us so far. Before I turn to the 3 types of retail crime I’ve been asked to speak to you about, I want to say something about what the criminal justice system is for. Its purposes include securing justice for victims, punishing offenders, protecting the public, and reducing re-offending. This government will always provide enough prison places for those whom the courts judge should receive a custodial sentence. But the criminal justice system is not simply a numbers game, about how many people are locked up. It is about the right response to stop people committing crime, from preventing offending in the first place to stopping reoffending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most recent figures show that, for adults discharged from custody or starting a court order under probation supervision, 43 per cent are reconvicted within one year, 55% within 2 years; 68% within 5 years; and 74% within 9 years. The government is committed to reducing this level of re-offending, and that entails taking into account the effectiveness of various punishments in getting offenders to desist from crime. It is significant, for instance, that (in 2007) court orders under probation supervision were more effective (by 7 percentage points) at reducing one-year proven reoffending rates than custodial sentences of less than 12 months, for similar offenders. As retailers, I quite understand that your concern may simply be that people who commit crime against you should be severely punished. But government, and indeed all of us as members of society, must also be concerned to prevent further offending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="retail-crime-in-london"&gt;Retail crime in London&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The partnership approach I referred to earlier can also make a vital contribution to bringing offenders to justice. For instance, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; here in London has been working closely with the New West End Company (the Oxford Street retail association). You don’t need me to tell you that there is a lot of shoplifting in West End stores but, recently, the offending has become more serious and more organised. We are not only talking about theft by individuals for themselves, but also that by organised criminal gangs. Both the police and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; have had to respond to this development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There have been a number of notable successes in smash and grab cases. For instance, following some brave and enterprising evidence gathering by members of the public and an off-duty police officer, the police and the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; were able to bring to justice 5 of the 6 members of a gang who had carried out a smash and grab raid on motorcycles, at Ernest Jones jewellers in Oxford Street. These 5 received custodial sentences of between 4 and 6 years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="shoplifting"&gt;Shoplifting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to assure you that the government regards shoplifting as a serious problem. After all, The British Retail Consortium’s recent survey of retail crime showed that theft by customers is the largest component of such crime, both in terms of value of stolen items (estimated at over £750 million 2009/10) and the proportion of incidents (over 95%). In 2009/10, there were 3,490 incidents of customer theft per 100 outlets, thankfully down 10.6% from 2008/09. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like all crime, retail theft requires a proportionate response. When the police arrest someone, they have a range of ways of dealing with the offence, using their professional discretion, including ‘out-of-court disposals’. These allow the police to deal quickly and proportionately with certain kinds of (often first-time) offending, which does not require prosecution at court. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This frees the police to spend more time on frontline duties. Realistically, it also means that offences that might previously never have been sanctioned on account of pressure of other demands now receive a formal penalty. Using an out-of-court disposal also frees the police - and retailers - from possibly having to attend court as witnesses. And last but not least, it frees up prosecutors’ resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or, the police may decide, on &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; advice if necessary, that the circumstances of the offence or the offender (perhaps a persistent offender who has already received more than one out of court disposal) require him or her to be charged and taken to court. &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt; records do not identify retail crime as a separate category, but figures for the prosecution of all cases of theft and handling show that, in 2009/10, the &lt;abbr title="Crown Prosecution Service"&gt;CPS&lt;/abbr&gt;’s success rate in securing convictions in these cases was impressive, approximately 93%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Following a conviction, the sentence is a matter for the court. You may be aware that in 2008 the Sentencing Guidelines Council issued a guideline on ‘Theft and burglary in a building other than a dwelling’. This covers theft from a shop. It makes clear that organised activity by a gang or the use of intimidation and threats will be treated as a more serious offence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It indicates that it will be an aggravating factor if the thief was already banned from the shop, whether this is a court imposed ban or a ban imposed by the shop owner or manager. The guideline also indicates that it will be an aggravating factor if the theft is committed against a particularly vulnerable victim - for example small independent shops, or if high value goods are targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the offender does not go to prison, a fine may be used to hit them where it really hurts - in the pocket; or the offender may receive a non-custodial penalty. This is no soft option, but will be rigorously supervised by the Probation Service. As I said earlier, such orders have been shown to be more effective at reducing reoffending than short custodial sentences. They include requirements aimed at dealing with the causes of the offending behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the case of a shoplifter, this may well be drug addiction. (64% of all newly sentenced prisoners report using a drug during the four week period before custody; this reflects what I have seen myself in visiting many prisons.) A court order under probation supervision may be the best opportunity to enable an offender to overcome the drug habit they have been stealing to feed; and simply to give them the will and the ability to find and hold down a job.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="assaults-on-staff"&gt;Assaults on staff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Shop workers and those serving the public do an important job and it is only right that they are able to do so without the risk of physical and verbal assault from customers and others. The British Retail Consortium’s survey I mentioned earlier showed 14 incidents of violence against retail staff per 1,000 employees. Although these figures have thankfully shown a strong downward trend over the last 6 years, this remains an unacceptably high level. The government strongly believes that any act of violence or abuse against retail staff is unacceptable and should not be tolerated. Tackling such offences is a key theme for the National Retail Crime Steering Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government also welcomes what a number of businesses are doing to counter such violence, for instance by providing staff with conflict resolution or violence prevention training. We also want to see major retailers continue to demonstrate commitment and support to smaller businesses in tackling abuse and assault against staff, as part of both their responsibility as good employers, and their corporate social responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I mentioned earlier how partnership working can also support a criminal justice response. Last October, a joint initiative between Crimestoppers and the Association of Convenience Stores was launched, which established financial rewards for information leading to a conviction for cases in relation to violence against those working in the retail sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And as I said about shoplifting, after conviction, sentencing is a matter for the courts. Last month, the independent Sentencing Council released revised definitive guidelines for sentencers on assault offences. These aim to ensure a consistent and proportionate approach to sentencing in these cases, so that it reflects both the harm convicted offenders have caused their victim and their culpability. The guidelines restate the Sentencing Council’s view that judges and magistrates should consider it an ‘aggravating factor’ if an assault is committed against those working in the public sector or providing a service to the public - which the Council has made clear includes those who work in shops and the wider retail business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fraud"&gt;Fraud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The National Fraud Authority’s most recent Annual Fraud Indicator, published in January, indicates that fraud against the retail, wholesale and distribution sector costs £2.7 billion a year. The British Retail Consortium’s survey found that retail fraud specifically accounted for over 10% of retail crime by value - that is, over £110 million - in 2009/10. The largest single category of fraud attempts (40%) were attributable to card-not-present transactions. But the largest category of retail fraud by value (60%) was refund fraud, which had increased since 2008/09.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These figures are a serious cause for concern, particularly as a large amount of fraud is not reported. In the past, not having a centralised body to co-ordinate fraud intelligence made it easier for criminals to operate undetected and free to re-offend. This problem was addressed last year, by the launch of the National Fraud Intelligence Bureau (&lt;abbr title="National Fraud Intelligence Bureau"&gt;NFIB&lt;/abbr&gt;). The &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Intelligence Bureau"&gt;NFIB&lt;/abbr&gt; was developed and overseen by the City of London Police as part of its role as the national lead force for fraud. The &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Intelligence Bureau"&gt;NFIB&lt;/abbr&gt; database is populated from a large number of organisations within the public and private sectors, representing industry, commerce and government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Intelligence Bureau"&gt;NFIB&lt;/abbr&gt; employs analysts from both law enforcement and private sector backgrounds to sift through the raw intelligence, searching for distinct patterns of fraudulent activity and behaviour. Once a trend has been spotted, such as organised crime groups associated with fraud, an intelligence report will be dispatched to the relevant police forces to be used in their investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Members of the public and small and medium sized businesses are able to provide the &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Intelligence Bureau"&gt;NFIB&lt;/abbr&gt; with information about fraud by using the newly developed national fraud reporting centre, Action Fraud, which is run by the National Fraud Authority. I would encourage all businesses to report fraud to, and if necessary get advice from, Action Fraud. Larger businesses can report directly to the City of London Police. As with any other crime, if fraud is not reported, law enforcement authorities cannot build up the intelligence they need to inform an effective and targeted response. But I know that Stephen Harrison from the &lt;abbr title="National Fraud Authority"&gt;NFA&lt;/abbr&gt; is speaking to you later today, so I won’t say any more about fraud.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope I have assured you that the government takes all forms of crime against retailers seriously. We and the criminal justice agencies want, and need, to work with you, ideally to prevent retail crime, or to ensure an effective response when it occurs.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/7772</id>
    <published>2011-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-guidance-from-court-of-appeal-following-a-reference-by-the-solicitor-general"/>
    <title>New guidance from Court of Appeal following a reference by the Solicitor General </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Court of Appeal has increased the sentences of 3 offenders who sexually attacked women during burglaries in homes they were entitled to regard as ‘safe havens’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal court judges also issued guidance to sentencing judges that the use of photographs taken by mobile phones or digital cameras, increasing the hurt and humiliation of the victim, is to be treated as a seriously aggravating factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their original sentences were referred to the court by the Solicitor General, Edward Garnier QC MP, to the court as possibly unduly lenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Chief Justice Lord Judge, Mr Justice Henriques and Mr Justice Davis ruled that the sentences were unduly lenient. In 2 of the attacks the offenders took pictures of their victims. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming the judgment, the Solicitor General said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Court of Appeal has now made clear that sexual assaults and rapes committed during the course of domestic burglaries will attract a far higher sentencing starting points than previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These 3 cases were important on their own facts. Each of them was unduly lenient. But, more broadly the Court of Appeal said that the victims sexually assaulted or raped in their own homes suffered not only the attack but also the destruction of the sense of security and safety they were entitled to feel in their own homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Chukudi Anigbugu had been sentenced to 8 years’ imprisonment at Wood Green Crown Court, London for 2 offences of rape and 4 years concurrent in respect of 2 offences of sexual assault by penetration. His sentence was raised to 15 years. 
Hyung-Woo Pyo had been sentenced to 8 years’ imprisonment at Leicester Crown Court for offences of rape, robbery and possession of a bladed article. His sentence was also raised to 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark McGee had been sentenced to 6 years’ imprisonment with an extended licence period of 6 years for an offence of sexual assault by penetration. He was also sentenced to 3 and a half years’ imprisonment concurrent for an offence of robbery at Truro Crown Court (therefore 6 years in total). His sentence was raised to 14 years, 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Judge said the home should be ‘our safest refuge’ and that the taking of photos during sexual assaults for blackmail or humiliation was a ‘pernicious new habit’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
