<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/edward-davey</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/edward-davey.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Edward Davey MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2011-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18317</id>
    <published>2011-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-midata-vision-of-consumer-empowerment"/>
    <title>The midata vision of consumer empowerment</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The businesses, consumer bodies and regulators involved are all committed to working with Government to achieve its vision for midata, launched today. And all are endorsing the key principle that data should be released back to consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;midata is a voluntary programme the Government is undertaking with industry, which over time will give consumers increasing access to their personal data in a portable, electronic format. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals will then be able to use this data to gain insights into their own behaviour, make more informed choices about products and services, and manage their lives more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement marks the first time globally there has been such a Government-backed initiative to empower individuals with so much control over the use of their own data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the midata vision, Consumer Affairs Minister, Edward Davey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the way the world is going and the UK is currently leading the charge. We see a real opportunity here, but others, including the US and EU, are also showing real interest in the programme and the economic benefits it can deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So if we want to continue leading the way, we need to develop a platform upon which the innovation and services that drive growth can be built. midata aims to do just that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://blogs.bis.gov.uk/blog/2011/11/03/giving-consumers-the-midata-touch/"&gt;Read Edward Davey’s blog on the launch of midata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="midata"&gt;midata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall aim of midata is to benefit the economy, by stimulating innovation and growth, as well as companies and consumers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;For the economy&lt;/strong&gt; - midata will encourage sustainable economic growth by boosting competition between companies in terms of value and service, and driving innovation. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;For business&lt;/strong&gt; - midata will create opportunities for businesses through improved dialogue with consumers and increased trust, and the opportunity to provide innovative new personal information services and tools. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;For consumers&lt;/strong&gt; - midata will allow consumers to access their data in a safe and secure way and make better decisions reflecting their personal wants and needs. New services made possible by midata will further assist consumers, whether it be in getting the best deal on their mobile phone contract or energy tariff, or managing their lives more efficiently. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="who-is-involved"&gt;Who is involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and organisations that have so far committed to working in partnership with Government to achieve the midata vision are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMEE &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoco Secure &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;billmonitor &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;British Gas &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Callcredit &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EDF Energy &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;E.ON &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Garlik &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lloyds Banking Group &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MasterCard &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moneysupermarket.com &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mydex &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;npower &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RBS &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scottish Power &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scottish Southern Energy &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The UK Cards Association &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following consumer groups and regulators are working with midata to represent consumers’ interests and concerns. As well as working towards potential benefits, their input plays an important role in identifying potential risks and helping determine how these can be addressed: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citizens Advice &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communications Consumer Panel &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumer Focus &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OFCOM &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office of Fair Trading (OFT) &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421869&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Government set out its plans for midata in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment"&gt;consumer empowerment strategy Better Choices: Better Deals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18307</id>
    <published>2011-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cutting-accountancy-and-reporting-fees-for-smes--2"/>
    <title>Cutting accountancy and reporting fees for SMEs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 100 thousand UK businesses could save in excess of £600 million in accountancy and administration costs every year under proposals to reduce financial reporting requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/audit-exemptions-and-accounting-framework"&gt;The consultation on Audit Exemptions and Change of Accounting Framework&lt;/a&gt; sets out plans to allow more small companies and subsidiaries to decide whether or not to have an audit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It covers the whole of the UK and will close on 29 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current EU rules mean a company must comply with two out of three criteria in order to be classified as ‘small’ for accounting purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No more than 50 employees. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A balance sheet total no more than £3.26 million. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No more than £6.5 million in turnover. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, to obtain an audit exemption in the UK, small companies must fulfil both the balance sheet and turnover criteria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new proposals, UK SMEs would be eligible for audit exemption by meeting any two of the three criteria, saving them an estimated £206m per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister responsible for Corporate Governance, Edward Davey, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Audit is very valuable for many companies. But the proposals we’ve published today are aimed at removing EU gold plating and freeing up enterprise, which ultimately benefits the whole UK economy and will help put us on the path to long-term, sustainable growth. So I encourage businesses to read the consultation document and share their views with us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cutting-gold-plating"&gt;Cutting gold plating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is also proposing to introduce legislation in 2012 to exempt most subsidiary companies from mandatory audit, provided their parent is prepared to guarantee their debts. Savings are estimated at £406m per year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, removing this EU gold plating could save UK businesses £612m per year. These moves are part of the Government’s wider focus on cutting red tape and reducing unnecessary burdens on business, in particular addressing the impact of European legislation.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, following the consultation by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/asb/"&gt;UK Accounting Standards Board &lt;/a&gt;on changes to UK Generally Accepted Accounting Principles (UK GAAP), the Government is also seeking views on whether to allow companies which currently prepare accounts under International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) more flexibility to change their accounting framework to UK GAAP. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011 the Chancellor and Business Secretary published The Plan for Growth. One of the Plan’s ambitions is to ensure the UK ranks among the best places in Europe to start and grow a business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve this, the Government is committed to removing regulatory burdens and improving corporate governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421482&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-law/accounting-auditing-reporting"&gt;Audit, accounting and reporting at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.frc.org.uk/"&gt;Financial Reporting Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.companieshouse.gov.uk/"&gt;Companies House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18302</id>
    <published>2011-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-10-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tackling-employment-law-red-tape--2"/>
    <title>Tackling employment law red tape</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the next three weeks &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.redtapechallenge.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/themehome/employment-related-law/"&gt;the Red Tape Challenge&lt;/a&gt; will focus on more than 160 different cross-Government employment related regulations that businesses have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign asks how regulations can be improved, simplified or even abolished, whilst also ensuring that the current standard of employment rights for employees are maintained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister David Willetts said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Businesses regularly tell us that the burden of regulation is too high. So today we are giving them a chance to tell us exactly which rules they think need to be reformed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So they are fit for purpose and easier for businesses to understand, examples of regulations you can comment on include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules on collective redundancies. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Employment agencies. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Immigration checks. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Minimum Wage. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statutory sick pay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister Edward Davey said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We often hear from businesses that employment related regulation holds them back from growing their firms and employing more people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whether it is the filling out of endless forms when you hire your first member of staff, the complexities of letting somebody go, or simply manage staff on a day-to-day basis, we want to review these regulations with the aim of giving business more confidence in employing people and creating more jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/employment-matters/employment-law-review"&gt;The Employment Law Review&lt;/a&gt; is a Parliament long review looking at all aspects of employment law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A discussion paper, entitled &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/assets/biscore/employment-matters/docs/F/11-1308-flexible-effective-fair-labour-market"&gt;‘Flexible, effective, fair: Promoting economic growth through a strong and efficient labour market,’&lt;/a&gt; has also been published today. This paper sets out the principles that are guiding our approach to reform of the labour market framework along with a number of thematic questions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Davey added: “We are determined to tackle unnecessary, burdensome red tape that harms job creation and means employers spend less time running their business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But this does not mean this will result in a watering down of employee rights. Today we are launching a real debate with employers and employees, to listen to their thoughts and act on what regulations can be simplified, merged and abolished. This is your time to get involved and have your say on your employment law bugbears.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government will publish the results of the employment related law Red Tape Challenge theme later this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421440&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/employment-matters"&gt;Employment policies at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?topicId=1073858787&amp;amp;furlname=employingpeople&amp;amp;furlparam=employingpeople&amp;amp;ref=&amp;amp;domain=www.businesslink.gov.uk"&gt;Business Link guidance on employment law and skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/Employment/index.htm"&gt;Directgov guidance on your employment rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18294</id>
    <published>2011-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/building-a-mutual-post-office"/>
    <title>Building a mutual Post Office</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postal Affairs Minister Edward Davey announced the plans today in a Government consultation, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/pomutualisation/"&gt;‘Building a Mutual Post Office,’&lt;/a&gt; which sets out options to move the Post Office from Government ownership to a mutual model.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postal Affairs Minister Edward Davey said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Post Office sits at the heart of our communities and I am determined to make sure that it becomes a successful and profitable business.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With this in mind we want to explore how those with an interest in the Post Office could be given a real say in how it is run.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The consultation, Building a Mutual Post Office, published today, sets out the different options for how we might enable subpostmasters, employees, post office customers and local communities, to have a real stake in the future of the Post Office.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Combined with our major investment programme and Post Office’s ambition to become the ‘Front Office for Government’, a mutualised Post Office could help link a new commercial focus with an even stronger community purpose.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why I really want everyone with an opinion on the future of the Post Office network to tell us what they think of our proposals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-mutual-model"&gt;The mutual model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation builds on a detailed and independent report for Government led by Co-operatives UK. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk.coop/press-release/new-report-explores-options-post-office-mutualisation"&gt;Published in May this year,&lt;/a&gt; their report was positively received by Post Office’s stakeholders.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes that Post Office Ltd could be ideally suited to a mutual model, with those that know it best working together, giving them a greater say in how the business is run, as well as a stake in its success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing Post Office Ltd - the national company which sets the strategy for the post office network and operates some of the larger branches - to a mutual would not affect the ownership of the thousands of privately-owned post office branches up and down the country.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A move to a mutual would not of course be possible until the business is on a more financially sustainable footing. The Government has committed to provide £1.34 billion of funding to the post office network over the spending review period to modernise the network and safeguard its future.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government believes that the Post Office could be on a clear path to mutualisation by the end of this Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=421260&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18270</id>
    <published>2011-07-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-07-07T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/european-ministers-meet-to-talk-about-growth"/>
    <title>European ministers meet to talk about growth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim of the meeting at Lancaster House was to build on recent European Council agreements regarding the creation of a fully-functioning digital single market, reducing the regulatory burden and maximising the potential of EU services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the Government’s pamphlet &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Mar/eugrowth"&gt;Let’s Choose Growth&lt;/a&gt; setting out why it’s time for growth in Europe.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group consisted of Ministers from Member States that have expressed support for the EU growth agenda and its focus on the single market, trade, innovation and reducing regulatory burdens. Today’s meeting was convened to help turn the high level political support for the agenda into real progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew McClelland, Chief Operations and Policy Officer at the Interactive Media and Retail Group also attended the meeting and presented a paper on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/corporate/docs/e/delivering%20eu%20growth%20%20imrg%20slides%20presentation%20by%20andrew%20mcclelland.pptx"&gt;Digital Single Market and the Challenges Facing the EU. (PPTX, 791 Kb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business minister Edward Davey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The strategy of positive engagement with our European partners is beginning to show real results.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s meeting confirms how an increasing number of Member States share Britain’s view on the need for an ambitious Europe wide growth agenda, and how we are co-operating more closely than ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU Single Market already adds €600 billion a year to the economy. Further liberalisation of services and the creation of a digital single market could add €800 billion more - the equivalent of making the average European household almost €4,200 better off each year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 12 per cent of EU online trade is cross-border. By creating a genuine digital single market, European businesses will have access to larger markets, and consumers will find it easier to buy the products they want from neighbouring countries, providing them with more choice and cheaper prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/europe"&gt;BIS European work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18606</id>
    <published>2011-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/chatham-house-competition-policy-conference"/>
    <title>Chatham House Competition Policy Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for inviting me to speak today. I am pleased to be here; particularly as the subject of the conference “The role of Competition Policy in building a new economy” is one that will be occupying my mind over the coming months. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Budget earlier this year, we set out our Plan for Growth, which clearly recognised that competition underpins economic growth, by driving efficiency and innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are taking a number of steps to ensure vigorous competition remains at the heart of our economy, and helps create the right conditions for business to start up, invest, grow and create jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are undertaking far-reaching long-term reforms to reshape the whole of the competition and consumer landscape. In April, we launched a strategy focused on empowering consumers - looking at how we can “nudge” people to make better choices. This is critical, because informed, empowered consumers demand choice, which stimulates competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, we published a consultation on reforming the consumer landscape. It looks at how we can streamline the current array of consumer bodies and create a single, clear advocate for consumer education and information in Citizens Advice. It also set out our plans to strengthen consumer protection by proposing a beefed up role for Trading Standards, supported by more resource and better co-ordination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I want to concentrate on the consultation we have run on Competition Reform, which closed on June 13. We have had over 114 responses and I know that many here today took part, helping us debate the issues and hear a wide range of views. Thank you for your input. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to give you a flavour of what we have heard during the consultation, and the issues we will explore further as we start to make decisions in this important area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="creation-of-the-cma"&gt;Creation of the CMA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of our plans is the creation of a strong single Competition Markets Authority, promoting effective competition in the interest of consumers. Whilst there is quite a lot of support for such a move, it’s fair to say that we haven’t yet managed to convince everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I do understand why this is. In the current environment I can see that such a change is seen as risky. Both the Office of Fair Trading and the Competition Commission are world-class, and of course a merger of any sort brings with it a degree of uncertainty and disruption which, if not handled well, could undermine our very objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here I really do think we need to be ambitious and look to the future. And whilst I understand the view that some of our proposals could, at least in theory, be achieved without a merger, I think this stance underestimates the benefits and synergies a merger will bring - which could not otherwise be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe there are three particularly strong arguments for creating the CMA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it will build more predictability and a more streamlined approach into decision making, through strong oversight of the end-to-end case management process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, a CMA will be a single powerful advocate to speak for competition across the economy, in Europe, and globally. That is much more difficult in present conditions, where we often have two different competition authorities’ representatives, each representing their own views and reflecting the role of their particular part of the competition regime, rather than the whole picture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - let’s be frank - public money is short. A single authority will be able to focus resources on addressing the most important competition problems of the day. It will also allow more efficient use of resources across the whole of the system. It makes absolutely no sense to have overstretch in some part of the competition regime, and under utilisation of resources in another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for business time is money. The time they have to spend understanding the concerns of two quite different authorities, with different cultures and objectives, is time that generates additional costs for the business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there are concerns about the ability of a single authority to preserve independent decision-making and, where relevant, the separation of decisions into two phases within a single body. I am considering this very carefully - but I strongly believe it is possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cma-framework"&gt;CMA Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarifying the CMA’s purpose and vision will be very important here. As will preserving the independence of the authority’s decision-making from Government, while ensuring accountability for the public money it spends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am attracted to setting out in legislation the primary duty of the CMA to promote competition in the interests of consumers. This will mean the purpose and duties of the CMA will be set out for all to see and judge its performance against. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reflects the approach used for most sector regulators. Indeed, the Chancellor announced last week that the Financial Conduct Authority will have a new primary duty to promote competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also considering whether it would be useful for the Government to set out our view of how the CMA will, within the competition framework, support long-term economic growth. This could be a long term, high level and non-statutory statement designed to make transparent the relationship between the Government and the Authority. It would help reinforce the independence of the CMA’s day to day decision making role in individual cases, while strengthening the democratic accountability of the regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mergers"&gt;Mergers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to the issue of mergers - while there is consensus the UK’s regime works well in most respects, the consultation looked at a spectrum of options for addressing some problems identified with the current voluntary notification regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, business has been very concerned that any move to a mandatory notification regime could create additional costs and regulatory burden. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand these concerns and I will keep them in mind as I consider the next steps. However, I do believe it’s important that we address the issue that the competition authorities investigate a high proportion of completed mergers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reduces the effectiveness of the competition regime as when these mergers are found to be anti-competitive they can sometimes be difficult to undo and it can also be difficult to apply the right remedies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as I weigh up the options an important issue for me will be whether strengthening the voluntary notification system through stronger hold separate powers will adequately address the problem of completed mergers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="markets"&gt;Markets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The markets regime is an unusual in global terms, and generally well regarded feature of the UK’s competition framework. Between 2007 and 2010 OFT and Competition Commission’s combined market work have saved consumers an estimated £345 million a year. This is a huge achievement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, like most things it could still be improved further. Responses to the consultation have shown that that the biggest weakness of the current regime is the length of time taken to conduct market investigations. To date, market investigations have taken up to 67 months to complete. Delays like this cause uncertainty for business and are detrimental to consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single authority will have an incentive to resolve any problems at the most appropriate stage in the process. But this alone will not be enough. We need to give businesses more certainty about how long cases may take, so I am considering introducing shorter, statutory timescales, across more of the process, with enough flexibility to allow the CMA to conduct investigations well and agree remedies at the right stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="concurrency"&gt;Concurrency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Consultation also looked at how we can strengthen general competition law in the regulated sectors by ensuring vigorous enforcement by the sector regulators and the new CMA, thereby avoiding an excessive reliance on detailed sectoral regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to recognise that sector regulators have a range of objectives, which go beyond just promoting competition. And in many cases, they may be required to use their regulatory tools, or these may be faster and cheaper to use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is clearly scope for improvement. I am examining the idea of applying the kind of duty Ofcom has - to consider its competition act powers before using its Broadcasting powers - more broadly to other sector regulators. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would need to ensure, of course, that this did not conflict with the regulators’ wider duties or their freedom to apply the most appropriate tools to deliver their objectives - which is, after all, one of the key Principles for Economic Regulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also carefully considering whether to give the CMA an oversight role, similar to that of the EU Commission in the European Competition Network - including the power to take cases from sector regulators in appropriate circumstances. In doing so, I am focusing on what the right balance should be between the CMA and other authorities with competition powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="anti-trust"&gt;Anti-trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Merger and Markets, the UK regime is generally considered to compare very well with regimes in other countries so only marginal changes may be needed. But on anti-trust many respondents to the consultation felt more could be done to improve the quality of the decisions taken and to reduce the length of time taken to resolve cases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firmer signals need to be sent to markets that cartel behaviour and abuses of dominant positions will be discovered and will be punished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, that’s where the consensus ended, and forceful arguments were made in favour of a number of different solutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OFT, the sector regulators and some law firms said that incremental improvement in the current arrangements was the best way forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others, including the City of London Law Society, some academics, and the Competition Commission, saw the need for an enhanced decision-making processes, such as the adoption of the CC’s own panel structure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third group, including the CBI, and the Joint Working Party of the Bars and Law Societies of the UK, considered that a move to the CMA prosecuting cases before the Competition Appeal Tribunal would be the best solution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, this is an area where we need to undertake a thorough analysis of all views and evidence. We also need to balance the potential for long-term benefits against any short-term disruption in a change of regime. I have not yet formed my own view and am considering the best way forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decision-making"&gt;Decision making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to talk a bit about decision making within the new CMA. Clearly this is will be crucial to the success of the new regime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very clear that respondents want to retain the strengths of the current regime. In particular, they want separate phase one and phase two decision-making to continue for markets and mergers. It won’t come as a surprise to learn that respondents want fair and robust decisions to be prioritised over speed - although there should be real efforts to make them as quickly as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;he consultation paper set out a base case for decision making, which included independent panels for phase two decisions. The great majority of stakeholders prefer this option. The panels will bring a second pair of eyes to cases and provide confidence that decisions are independent of government, the phase one process and the institutional interests of the competition authority. Continuing with the Panel system will allow us to preserve independent decision-making, while realising the other benefits of a move to a single authority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, we are currently working through a wide range of issues as a result of the consultation. My Department is still doing a great deal of work analysing responses and considering the evidence. We hope to be able to publish the Government response in the autumn and to introduce a Bill in the next session of Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is very much work in progress, so now I am happy to take questions and hear your views on these issues. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18262</id>
    <published>2011-06-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mary-portas-makes-first-town-centre-visit"/>
    <title>Mary Portas makes first town centre visit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/business-sectors/images/retail/portas-conversation.jpg?w=500&amp;amp;h=313&amp;amp;as=1" alt="Mary Portas meets retailers in Rugby"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visits are the first of a number of engagement events Mary will undertake across the country as part of her review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During today’s visit Mary Portas will speak to high street businesses, local authorities and shoppers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Edward Davey said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The High Street should be at the heart of every community, bringing people together, providing essential services and creating jobs and investment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I am delighted that Mary Portas will today make her first town centre visits to Rugby and Sparkbrook which are regarded by the Association of Town Centre Managers as exemplars of best practice.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to seeing Mary’s final report which will identify what government, businesses and local communities can do to develop more prosperous and diverse high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Portas said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am visiting town centres across the country to find solutions for the problems that are blighting our high streets.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Rugby and Sparkbrook are good examples of suburb towns that face tough competition being on the doorstep of a big city but have found innovative solutions to attract business.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope to draw on the creativity of everyone involved in high streets whether they are independent shop owners, chain store managers, bookmakers, librarians or town centre managers.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With town centre vacancy rates doubling over the last two years, the need to take action to save our high streets has never been starker.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-sectors/retail/high-street-review"&gt;independent review&lt;/a&gt; will seek to identify what government, local authorities and businesses can do to promote the development of more prosperous and diverse high streets.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also form part of the Government’s wider &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth/growth-review"&gt;Growth Review&lt;/a&gt; which is examining how it can remove the barriers to achieve strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420042&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/business-sectors/retail/high-street-review"&gt;High street review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth/growth-review"&gt;Growth review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18256</id>
    <published>2011-06-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/empowering-and-protecting-the-consumer"/>
    <title>Empowering and protecting the consumer</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumer Minister Edward Davey announced today new proposals to simplify the confusing and overlapping provision of consumer protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new consultation &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//Consultations/empowering-and-protecting-consumers"&gt;‘Empowering and Protecting Consumers’&lt;/a&gt;, ministers want to see a new simplified ‘consumer landscape’ with public funding concentrated on two bodies that consumers trust and already turn to for advice - &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/"&gt;Trading Standards &lt;/a&gt;and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/"&gt;Citizens Advice service&lt;/a&gt;. It is proposed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Citizens Advice service to become the single service that consumers can turn to for information and advice. It will also act as their champion across a range of sectors. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To strengthen the leadership and coordination of Local Authority Trading Standards Services in tackling difficult cases that cross local authority boundaries. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation will run for 14 weeks until the end of September and government is keen that consumers, the voluntary and private sectors share their views on the proposed reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer Minister Edward Davey said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government believes in giving more power to people. Our consumer policy is all about empowering consumers to make the right decisions for themselves when they buy goods and services.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we also need to ensure we have the right system of help, advice and protection when consumers need support. For too long people have been faced with a confusing landscape of different, public, private and voluntary consumer bodies, with overlapping roles and responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is not always clear where to turn for trusted advice and information which consumers need to make good choices or a champion to support them when they have been ripped off.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The proposals which I have published today seek to put an end to such confusion and make sure consumers are empowered and have champions. The Citizens Advice service has for a long time offered trusted advice, information and advocacy. So it’s right that it sits at the heart of our plans.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Likewise, Trading Standards are trusted by the public to do a good job in enforcing consumer law and standing up for consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But there are barriers which get in the way of effective responses to rogues who operate across authority boundaries. Our proposed reforms will strengthen their hand in tackling these threats to consumers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strengthening consumer power helps drive competition, making businesses more efficient and innovative. Reforming the consumer landscape was a key part of the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/growth/the-plan-for-growth"&gt;Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt;, published at the time of the Budget, and its focus on creating the right conditions to deliver strong, sustainable balanced economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420025&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/consumer-issues"&gt;Consumer issues at BIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment"&gt;Better Choices Better Deals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/Governmentcitizensandrights/Consumerrights/index.htm"&gt;Directgov - consumer rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18603</id>
    <published>2011-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/trading-standards-institute-conference"/>
    <title>Trading Standards Institute Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon and thank you for inviting me here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I made my first speech at your conference as the new Consumer Minister. I am glad to be invited back to speak to you all again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am here to make an announcement that I believe will put Trading Standards on a stronger footing for the future, and will help all of you meet the increasingly complex challenges you face in protecting consumers from being ripped off. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am very pleased to launch our consultation on reform of consumer institutions.  It sets out our plans to establish Citizens Advice as a one-stop-shop that consumers can turn to for advice, information and education about their rights.  And it outlines our proposals to bolster the Trading Standards Service, so it is better equipped to protect consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because your service plays a critical role. Helping honest business grow and protecting consumers from rogue traders is essential to creating the safe and prosperous communities we all want to live in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why Trading Standards sits right at the heart of our plans to reform the landscape of consumer protection and improve the provision of enforcement and advice, education and advocacy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I have done a lot of listening. We have crafted our proposals to take account of what you have been telling us. I know about the financial pressures you are all facing and the tension between your local funding and yet the fact that you must address threats which go beyond local authority borders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want you to continue to meet local threats under the control of local authorities. But this should be better allied with regional and national organisation and, yes, more funding for you to work collectively to enforce the law against threats that don’t fit neatly within convenient local boundaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the consultation sets out a new model for national leadership of the service. But rather than describing this in detail today, I would rather sketch out for you a vision of the Trading Standards service I would like to see in a few years’ time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a service with effective national and regional leadership, with a much greater capacity to understand where threats to consumers are coming from, and to prioritise enforcement action to meet those which cause the greatest harm to the greatest number of consumers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Consumer Direct will reach far more consumers by being available online and by incorporating existing information from Citizens Advice. This will provide a much richer evidence base for you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want this to be combined with regional intelligence officers in every region, and collaboration with Citizens Advice, Which?, and the new Competition and Markets Authority, so Trading Standards can point exactly where consumers are suffering and can focus on the biggest targets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to see a service with high standards of professional competence, using leverage and influence as well as investigation and prosecution to deliver real results. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I envisage greater collaboration, with regional investigative teams supporting the smaller authorities and greater flexibility over who brings individual cases. These will be backed up by specialist national squads, located around the country, looking after the most complex cases in particular fields such as unfair contract terms or internet enforcement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want a service that helps good people to move between local, regional and national teams, rather than having to leave to get promotion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want a more confident Trading Standards service, able to quantify and demonstrate the huge benefits that we all know you deliver for consumers in the UK. One that uses this information to celebrate your achievements, raises your public and media profile, and showcase the enormous contribution you make to public welfare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to see a strong national Competition and Markets Authority, specialised in understanding why markets have structural failings and with the determination to make markets work well. I see this CMA interacting with TS in a true spirit of partnership, seamlessly complementing TS efforts to pursue individual businesses with wider action against structural problems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to see a better balance, over time, between local and national funding.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consultation is exactly that - nothing has been set in stone at this point. There is a lot of support for our proposals, but I realise that not everyone agrees with the direction of travel. There are some issues which have not been resolved and questions which still need answers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we need to think clearly about accountability and where to host specialist expertise. We need to work out corporate structures and governance and sort out finance and the costs of change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is your chance to shape the future structure of your profession and develop a consumer landscape which is fit for modern consumers and a modern economy. So I am urging you and your colleagues to respond to the Consultation and tell me what you like, what you don’t, what will work, what won’t - and the reasons why. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that times are tough at the moment, and the Trading Standards service is being asked to meet some big challenges - but that is often when inspiring ideas lead to the greatest advances. I want to hear all of your ideas in the months ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18251</id>
    <published>2011-05-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/creating-a-modern-workplace"/>
    <title>Creating a modern workplace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today launched &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/modernworkplaces/"&gt;a consultation on plans to introduce a new system of flexible parental leave from 2015 &lt;/a&gt;as part of its plans to create a modern workplace for the modern economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the proposals, once the early weeks of maternity and paternity leave have ended, parents will be able to share the overall leave allowance between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the current system this leave could be taken in a number of different blocks and both parents could take leave at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-being-proposed"&gt;What is being proposed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible Parental Leave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18 weeks maternity leave and pay - in one continuous block around birth. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Four weeks of parental leave and pay exclusive to each parent to be taken in the first year. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;30 weeks of additional parental leave available to either parent - of which 17 weeks would be paid and can be broken in blocks between parents. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible Working&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extending the right to request for all workers who have been with their employer for 26 weeks. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Government will consider publishing a statutory Code of Practice for businesses. It will propose that employers should be allowed to take into account employees individual circumstances when considering conflicting requests. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are no plans to alter the current 8 business reasons for a business to turn down a request. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Government recognises that legislation is not the only answer to promoting flexible working practices. Non-legislative measures are being developed to promote flexible working opportunities both for those with a job and for those looking for one. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;**Equal Pay **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employment Tribunals that have found an employer to have discriminated on gender in relation to pay, will order the employer to conduct a pay audit and publish their results (except in some circumstances, such as where an audit has already been conducted). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our proposals will encourage greater choice by giving employees and their employers the flexibility to find arrangements to suit them both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New parents should be able to choose their childcare arrangements for themselves, rather than being dictated to by rigid Government regulation as is currently the case. And employers should be encouraged to come to agreement with employees on how work and family responsibilities can be met simultaneously.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These measures are fairer for fathers and maintain the existing entitlements for mothers - but crucially give parents much greater choice over how to balance their work and family commitments.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course I’m mindful of the need to minimise the costs, bureaucracy and complexities on businesses. This has been at the forefront of my mind throughout the development of our proposals. So we will ensure that businesses will still be able to take into account their needs when agreeing how leave can be taken. But I’m also confident that we have a good case to make on the wider benefits to business - not least from a motivated and flexible workforce and we will be making this case to employers over the next few years before these changes are introduced.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419503&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/modernworkplaces/"&gt;Modern workplaces consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/employment-matters"&gt;Employment matters at BIS&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
