<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/eric-pickles</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/eric-pickles.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Eric Pickles MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50196</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish community has made, and continues to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17574</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;'There but for the Grace of God'. Picture: Rob Boler&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and the other winners and finalists in the competition can be found on the awards and highlights section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ftal.staged.ws/awards-highlights-from-2012/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Together in Service event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632131148440/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17739</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets--2"/>
    <title>Community Budgets</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I don’t want to talk about the ins and outs of community budgets, or the finer points of cost benefit analysis. I want to talk about their impact on people’s lives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why it’s a scandal that agencies in Doncaster, faced with more than 100 events involving children, failed to co-ordinate any realistic attempt to prevent what happened in the Edlington case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why so few children are getting their teeth checked in parts of Newcastle, that more and more are ending up having emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why in West Cheshire 1 woman faced 30 incidents of domestic abuse before feeling able to turn to an agency that might help her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to talk about my own area, Essex, and why some people still feel able to let a young father from that neck of the woods get caught up in a Kafkaesque nightmare - “Meeting upon meeting with different organisations” - just to get a bit of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that these are the types of service failure that the pilots themselves are addressing. Because if these initiatives were just about money, we’d rightly be accused of a lack of ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, we’re all having to live with less. And, given the waste, given the inefficiency, given the duplication that went on before, the purpose of this is to use less to deliver a better service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t just looking for these pilots to just patch things up. To mend and make do. To think about ‘service improvement’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people-at-the-centre-of-the-system"&gt;People at the centre of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems. Even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m glad to see that is what has been happening. The tri-borough initiative - part of the Whole-Place pilots - is proposing to reduce unplanned admissions to hospital. Putting the donkey work into helping older people with longer term conditions before they get to an acute stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got the greater Manchester pilot working with parents of children at risk so they don’t pass on the bad habits likely to hold kids back for the rest of their lives. The idea to ensure kids get a fresh start and can stand at the school gates on their first day ready with great excitement to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve got pioneers in West Cheshire making sure families with complex needs now have an advocate who’s going to stick with them through thick and thin. Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family at a staggering cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets. But we’ve worked out, if you get people together in a room - if you focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the re-offenders, the long-term unemployed and all those with dependencies - you can usually start taking dependence out the system. You can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth so they can lead independent lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re going to keep working with these 4 areas to make sure our plans really are do-able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we’re going to help other areas to learn from their experience. We know our colleagues across government are up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the way we’ve managed to bridge the old Whitehall, local government, voluntary sector fault lines has been one of the great success stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier on today we heard Norman Lamb speak about the pilot’s positive approach to health and social care integration. And we’re working with the Treasury, Work and Pensions, Education, Home Office and the Ministry of Justice to ensure we’re all on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="neighbourhoods-on-track"&gt;Neighbourhoods on track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know, as we’ve heard today, that our neighbourhood community budgets are on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ilfracombe to Haverhill they’re making sure their communities are involved in making the most of their resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critically, local folk are backing them. 89% of people surveyed in Poplar felt citizens should ‘do their bit’. While more than half wanted to be involved in turning their neighbourhood around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we’re seeing community budgets turning their irrepressible energy, their boundless enthusiasm, to that eternal question of reducing waste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilfracombe, for example, knows that nationally an estimated £300 million per year of NHS money is wasted through over prescription of medication. Imagine all those pills and potions sitting in the cupboard never being taken away. So Ilfracombe is tracking down that waste with the help of its local people to stop the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because what’s driving Ilfracombe, what’s driving us all is the priceless prize for getting this right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just savings of millions of pounds, but hearing from the young girl of the father in Essex I mentioned earlier talking about how she’s been; “changed… around”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing from the man who’d fallen on hard times describe how, by becoming a mentor, he now has; “something to get up for to make him feel better about himself that he is helping others”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is more than money. It is the prize. And the prize relates to people. There’s a real opportunity here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said it was brave, fool hardly, silly even, to try this. They said it was bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve been really impressed with how all the different organisations have risen to the challenge. We’ve always known these problems existed. Now we have the chance to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what fires you up and me up and Bob up is not the cost benefit analysis. It is the fact we can make a difference to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a noble cause. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just a case of government knows best. People must understand they too have a sense of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t lose that fire in your belly. Be innovative, be bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and I can make a difference. And together you and I will set us on course to make a difference for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17338</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-value-of-parishes"/>
    <title>The value of parishes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently JK Rowling’s new novel doesn’t paint parishes in a flattering light. It’s as fictional as the boy wizard himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we love our parish people. You are localism’s magic wand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Local Government Act of 1894, you’ve been providing unrivalled help, to the smallest of villages, the largest of towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the principles you embody are hardwired into the social DNA of every hometown, every village, in every era of our history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because you care about your areas, because you are rooted in the places you love, you are prepared to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="good-works---floods-and-jubilee"&gt;Good works - floods and Jubilee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent days, as floods have drenched our towns, we’ve seen parishes, from Oxford to Devon, coming to the rescue again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laying sandbags, battening down the hatches, working with police and fire crews, doing everything they can to save their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in this great year of the Jubilee, we’ve seen parishes, stepping into the spotlight, organising Big Lunches and street parties, helping the celebrations go with a swing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, wherever I find a new parish in a rural or urban area, like Queen’s Park in Westminster, I cheer it to the rafters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because our local services are at their best when they are run by local people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me say to &lt;abbr title="National Association of Local Councils"&gt;NALC&lt;/abbr&gt;, that the role you continue to play, championing local people, ensuring their voice resounds loud and clear in the corridors of power, is absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="putting-parishes-in-charge"&gt;Putting parishes in charge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we all know parishes, have the credibility to lead their communities. So we’ve made sure you’re calling the shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve cut through the jungle of red tape that tied you up in knots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve scrapped the Standards Board that summed up everything that was wrong with local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of wasting taxpayers money on petty squabbles, we’re letting the sunlight of transparency shine through. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Localism requires local accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some councillors are concerned about publishing their business interests. The names of their spouses. Pictures of their pet goldfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as our light-touch guidance explains, only one of the above has to be on record. I won’t tell you which one. That might spoil the surprise. But here’s a clue - it’s just common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for bullies and liars, they must expect the full force of the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, local people should trust the public. You put decent people in and if they get it wrong they don’t get elected next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call it minimalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-powers-new-rights"&gt;New powers, new rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standards Board apart, we’ve also got rid of the childish power of well being which died a death every 4 years. And we’ve given you the General Power of Competence instead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils can now do anything an individual can do unless it’s specifically ruled out. These days you don’t have to get things signed-off in triplicate, if you want to, for example, back community composting, or transform a village pub into a wi-fi hotspot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of competence means you’re only limited by your imagination and your ingenuity. And when it is combined with new community rights - that let you bid to control local services like street cleaning or step in to save a much love community asset like the local pub - the implications are far reaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, some parishes will need training in the art of power. But no need to dust down your copies of Sun Tzu’s ‘The Art of War’. Just log onto the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/"&gt;my community rights website&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I strongly suspect, the more power you grab, the more power you’re going to want. That’s why we’ve also introduced neighbourhood planning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of the slim-line National Planning Policy Framework, the days of wasting time on the amount of projection of a window are gone. So too the pettifogging bureaucracy and the master planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve put local people at the heart of the system. So they get to decide where new homes, new shops and new offices should go. And which green spaces to protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your chance to remould your area in your own image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="frontrunners"&gt;Frontrunners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our neighbourhood frontrunners are already blazing a trail in Upper Eden. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seventeen parishes are beavering away in the most sparsely populated area of the country to provide housing for farmers and rural businesses. They’re hoping to hold the first ever neighbourhood plan referendum in March. I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also pretty excited about what’s going on in the City to Ripon - where they’re working out how to allocate land for 160 homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="over-to-you---the-precept"&gt;Over to you - the precept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve thrust genuine power into the hands of local people. Now it’s over to you to get your parish in order; to build proper neighbourhoods, to choose activism not nimbyism. And to make sure you’re not overburdening hard working folk with increased taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn’t escaped my noticed that, at a time when most districts are freezing their council tax, the average parish precept has gone up by 3%. And the trend is seeing parish increases outstripping the rest of local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made it clear. We would look at again at the council tax referendum principles. But, as a general rule of thumb what you really need to ask yourself is this; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can you square any rise with your electorate? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can you really look your local folk in the eye?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have you really done everything you can to manage your resources, work with others, make the most of what you’ve got…?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood-budgets"&gt;Neighbourhood budgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last point is critical because if there is one thing neighbourhood budgets have shown it’s the advantage of looking beyond your borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in Ilfracombe in North Devon where they’re digitally mapping their resources. Or Haverhill in Suffolk where they are bringing local business and public agencies together to equip young people with the skills local businesses need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know where to begin my department is here to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re proud of our parishes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re out there in your communities revolutionising public services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing your civilising influence to bear on all around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve given you the power but now we’re looking for you to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So be vigorous, be innovative, be independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all never forget the people you serve and you won’t go far wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17013</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lancashire-flag-flying-high-above-whitehall"/>
    <title>Lancashire flag flying high above Whitehall</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag features the iconic red rose of Lancaster, which is the county flower of Lancashire, on a background of golden yellow - the livery colours of the county. The red rose is a symbol for the House of Lancaster, immortalised in the verse “In the battle for England’s head/York was white, Lancaster red” referring to the 15th century War of the Roses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic county of Lancashire dates from the 12th century and emerged during the industrial revolution as a major commercial and industrial region. The county encompassed several hundred mill towns and collieries. By the 1830s, approximately 85% of all cotton manufactured worldwide was processed in Lancashire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles holding the flag of Lancashire with two Lancashire MPs" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1207/lancashire_flag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles is joined by Lancashire MPs Eric Ollerenshaw OBE and Mark Menzies&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2 years flags for all the English counties have been flown outside the department, to celebrate the important place counties play in the nation’s cultural heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of other flags has also been hoisted above the building to recognise national days of significance such as the Red Ensign flag for Merchant Navy day, the Armed Forces flag for Armed Forces Day and the flag of the Falkland Islands to mark the islands’ liberation day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also published a new, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/flying-flags-a-plain-english-guide"&gt;Plain English guide to flying flags&lt;/a&gt;’. This will make it easier than ever before for individuals, businesses and community groups to fly their chosen flag without incurring costs of up to £335.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide provides a clear summary of the new liberalisation of controls over flag flying that were recently introduced by the Secretary of State. It is a simple way of knowing which flags can be flown without the consent of the local planning authority so that communities can continue to fly them with joy and pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“England’s counties continue to form an important part of our cultural and local identity in this country and many people remain deeply attached to their home county. This sense of pride and shared identity is one of the things that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been celebrating this patriotic pride by flying a range of flags outside my department over the past couple of years. The new plain English guide will make it easier than ever to do this, so I look forward to seeing more flags flying around the country with the relaxation of these rules.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Dawson from the Friends of Real Lancashire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Successive governments have confirmed the boundaries of Lancashire, and we welcome their further confirmation by this government, which demonstrates the valuable part that traditional counties play in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We hope that the flying of traditional county flags outside the department’s office will lead to further measures to promote the identity of Britain’s traditional counties. We welcome the flying of the Lancashire flag in celebration of Lancashire Day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geoff Drive, Leader of Lancashire County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re very pleased that the Department for Communities and Local Government is flying the Lancashire flag to celebrate Lancashire Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lancashire is a county with great history and tradition and a bright future through industries such as aerospace and advanced manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2012 has been an extraordinary year for Lancashire, with the Open Golf Championships at Royal Lytham, royal visits for the Diamond Jubilee, the Preston Guild and welcoming the Olympic torch relay. Flying our flag at the heart of government will be a fitting end to a tremendous year for our county.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relaxation of regulations for flying flags came into force on 12 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/spirit-of-the-summer-realised-with-relaxation-of-flag-flying-rules"&gt;Spirit of the summer realised with relaxation of flag flying rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17061</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/weekly-collection-saved-as-government-scheme-delivers-for-6-million-families"/>
    <title>‘Weekly collection saved’ as government scheme delivers for 6 million families </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is thanks to the government’s £250 million &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-sure-council-tax-payers-get-good-value-for-money/supporting-pages/bins-and-waste-collection"&gt;Weekly Collection Support Scheme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best 90 projects, from 85 councils, have today been selected from an over-subscribed scheme to share in the funding. Ministers are concerned that without the fund weekly bin collections could have all but disappeared by 2015, as is happening in other parts of the United Kingdom, such as Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Disraeli’s Public Health Act 1875 which first introduced a duty on local authorities to collect rubbish; this duty was enhanced by the Public Health Act 1936 obliging councils to collect household waste weekly. Weekly collections were the norm for decades, but started disappearing from 2000 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, 41 schemes will offer genuine rewards (such as shopping vouchers or loyalty points) for recycling so more families can go green without facing punitive fines and taxes, meeting an important coalition agreement pledge. It is hoped that such new schemes will encourage further take-up across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund was set up in February to support comprehensive and cost effective weekly collections that harness innovation, use new technology and spread reward schemes to increase recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils already receive funding for bin collections through central government formula grant and from the money raised locally via Council Tax: in total, council spending will be £114 million this year. A further 4 million households continue to provide weekly collections outside the support scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. Another survey found that two-thirds of the public thought government should mandate weekly collections; that weekly collections were better; and that problems with flies and smells were much worse with fortnightly collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government has already scrapped bin taxes plans via the Localism Act; reversed Audit Commission rules which marked down councils for not adopting fortnightly rubbish collections; and abolished Whitehall targets which created perverse incentives to downgrade waste collection services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department will continue to work with Defra to spread best practice on weekly collections, challenge poor procurement or unpopular approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every Englishman has a basic right to have their household rubbish taken away each and every week - it is the most visible council service people get. Yet under the previous administration weekly bin collections halved while their Council Tax bills doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over 6 million families will breathe a sigh of relief tonight because we have put a stop to the fetid fortnightly rot and saved many weekly collections from extinction, all while increasing recycling rates by hundreds of thousands of tonnes to boot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Weekly Collection Support Scheme encourages councils to focus on 4 things: better weekly collections, cost effective bids, environmental improvements and better use of innovative ideas or technology that help residents to recycle more and do their bit for the environment. 118 councils submitted final bids. For more information, see the &lt;a rel="external" href="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/15038/Weekly_Collection_Support_Scheme_-_successful_bids.xls"&gt;list of 90 winning bids&lt;/a&gt;, which gives a short description of what each of the schemes will do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence: opinion research they carried out actually found that two-thirds of people think frequent and regular rubbish collections are the most important feature of the waste service. (Ipsos-MORI, ‘Weekly or fortnightly: Public attitudes to waste collections’, July 2008.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fortnightly collections rose from just 13 councils across the United Kingdom in 2000 to 225 in 2008 (Alternate weekly collections conference, aspects of alternate weekly collection, July 2008). In Northern Ireland, as of 2010 to 2011, 92% of local authorities offer a fortnightly collection; in Scotland 72%, and Wales 77% according to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.wrap.org.uk/" title="WRAP"&gt;WRAP’s&lt;/a&gt;, local authority waste and recycling information portal, statistics for 2010 to 2011. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Sauce-Icaro attitudes to waste and recycling in Great Britain, December 2011 found that two-thirds (67%) agreed with the statement the government should mandate weekly collections. Weekly collections had higher satisfaction levels than fortnightly (83% compared to 74%). Reports of problems with flies and smells for fortnightly collections were more than double that for weekly (14% compared to 6%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What next: in the weeks to come the department will begin working with councils, the Local Government Association and Defra to support them to work together to procure the best deals as consortiums or groups to ensure value for money for the taxpayer. This means the department has provided a synopsis of each successful bid, but will not be disclosing further specific bid details as this would have an adverse effect on competition between prospective companies and potentially put local authorities in a disadvantageous position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16804</id>
    <published>2012-11-22T12:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-22T12:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-visits-hidden-homes-in-wandsworth"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles visits ‘Hidden Homes’ in Wandsworth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles visited the Rollo housing estate in the London Borough of Wandsworth today (22 November 2012) to see how £3.6 million of government funding is helping the council provide more affordable homes for local families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the final 38 affordable new homes of the Hidden Homes initiative that celebrates its 10th anniversary this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Eric Pickles with Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1168/Rollo2-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wandsworth Council Leader Ravi Govindia and Councillor Paul Ellis welcome Eric Pickles to the borough to officially unveil the new Hidden Homes&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Offering excellent value-for-money, the cutting-edge programme converts vacant and disused spaces on housing estates - from boiler rooms to storage areas - into modern and attractive affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme has delivered 238 homes in Wandsworth over the past decade. These have been allocated to local families and first time buyers, often on a shared ownership basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hidden Homes approach has provided more affordable homes, and at the same time prevented these redundant spaces from becoming eyesores or potential havens for anti-social behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles praised the borough for boosting housing delivery that, in the 12 month period to March 2012, was the highest in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said the Wandsworth scheme was a lesson to other councils for delivering more affordable housing, despite the tough economic circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects like Hidden Homes also provide valuable economic regeneration, creating jobs and boosting the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is committed to delivering more affordable homes that families need. Our £19.5 billion investment is delivering 170,000 affordable homes, and our FirstBuy and NewBuy schemes are helping families take the next step on the property ladder with just a fraction of the normal deposit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But we also want more councils to do more, and adopt innovative solutions like those being pioneered in Wandsworth. Using government and council funding, these Hidden Homes are making a fantastic contribution to the affordable housing landscape and giving families and first time buyers the chance to have their own home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabinet Member for Housing at Wandsworth Council, Councillor Paul Ellis said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Hidden Homes scheme has played a really major role in increasing the supply of affordable housing over the past decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As well as proving incredibly cost effective, it has also helped create jobs in the construction sector and been the key to regenerating redundant land on housing estates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the secretary of state will today unveil its biggest single scheme, and that as a result, 3 dozen families in housing need will be able to move into brand new high quality homes”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding for Hidden Homes builds on the options available for aspiring homeowners who want to get onto and up the housing ladder. This includes the NewBuy Guarantee and the reinvigorated Right to Buy, which will give thousands of council tenants the opportunity to buy their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632071654509/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
