<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/eric-pickles</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/eric-pickles.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Eric Pickles MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57535</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T11:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-pop-up-shop-to-showcase-high-street-entrepeneurs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens pop-up shop to showcase high street entrepreneurs</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s efforts to regenerate high streets and encourage entrepreneurs, the shop is being opened in time for final Christmas present buying this week by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk, with the support of national enterprise campaign StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To directly support enterprise and showcase Britain’s best new retailers, ministers have set up the pop-up store inside their Victoria-based office building to act as a blueprint for high streets across the country to emulate through schemes such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cutting the ribbon on the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5697/ribbon-cutting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles cutting the ribbon with Mark Prisk and Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the first ever Whitehall pop-up shop with ‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell. Every fortnight six new British start-up businesses will move into the shop, sharing costs and trialling their exciting ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop will be open to the public for at least a year and will offer affordable retail space to over 150 small start-up businesses. The department is not seeking any financial return from the shop, which is being supported by sponsors Intuit, John Lewis, SNR Denton and StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5698/shop-floor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The first 6 pop-up tenants are NANUKK, Milla &amp;amp; Arti, Arthur &amp;amp; Henry, London Mummy, Morrow’s Outfitters and The English Tee Shop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe pop-ups are a great way to get empty spaces used and could be easily replicated in other town centres across the country. Mr Prisk has written to the British Property Federation to urge landlords to get on board. He said that, starting in January, all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Town Team partners will receive support to facilitate new pop-ups in their empty high street premises, which could support thousands of new businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to rejuvenating the high street. A multi-million pound strategy is backing local partnerships such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams to breathe new life into their town centres. This includes a doubling of small business rate relief; mentoring from retail experts; and workshops to address town centre challenges. A guide to opening a pop-up will be published soon and StartUp Britain has published a tool kit today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is providing over £80 million of start-up loans for young entrepreneurs, which could create over 30,000 new businesses. Ministers are also changing planning restrictions so that landlords can alter how an empty shop is used for up to two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these steps will make it easier for start-ups to find other low-cost stores to set up in. Last year 450,000 people set up new businesses and almost two thirds of new start-ups say they would benefit from trading on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are absolutely determined to support the high street and we know pop-ups are a great way to bring empty shops back to life and get new businesses going, so we thought ‘why not open one right here in the department?’. It will also showcase how we can unleash more of our best and brightest young entrepreneurs onto the country’s high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The PopUp Britain model gives retail entrepreneurs an affordable opportunity to scale up their businesses and become a part of their own high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing record numbers of people setting up businesses and they are starting out small and online. They are the driving force of the economy. This initiative offers them a chance to physically test out new markets as well as get their products in front of consumers and big buyers in a way that has never been available to them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By actively encouraging local authorities to give start-ups access to empty shops across Britain, we hope it will help accelerate British enterprise as well as providing a vibrant addition to the local British shopping experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real appetite in our town centres to get them revitalised so they remain attractive places to visit. And it’s not just talk: there are many extremely capable and serious people with some superb ideas; but they need a bit of help to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up shops are a superb way for all sorts of entrepreneurs to test their ideas. So I’m delighted that this department is opening the first pop-up shop in Whitehall and I look forward to inviting all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Towns Teams here to see how they could replicate this model across the country in the new year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a brilliant idea and it is great to see the government actively supporting business in this way. For many aspiring and growing enterprises, having access to a retail unit where new propositions and ideas can be tested directly with customers can be the catalyst to increase sales. I hope other landlords follow this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the Bright Ideas Trust, where we invest in businesses started by young unemployed people, we see many business struggle to secure retail space as they grow out of their bedrooms and away from their kitchen tables.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=neKNqnTu6qY"&gt;Pop-up shop event video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="startup-britain"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startupbritain.co/"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/a&gt; is a national campaign by entrepreneurs for entrepreneurs, harnessing the expertise and passion of Britain’s leading businesspeople to celebrate, inspire and accelerate enterprise in the UK. The campaign was founded by eight entrepreneurs and was launched in March 2011 by the Prime Minister. It has successfully run pop-up stores in Richmond, Surrey, which opened in July and which have already helped 42 businesses get access to the high street. Four in five of the tenants said the experience had been good for their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-six-pop-up-britain-victoria-tenants"&gt;First six pop-up Britain Victoria tenants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established 6 months ago by 27-year-old Shrewsbury-based designer Sarah McLeod, silk scarf company &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nanukk.com/"&gt;NANUKK&lt;/a&gt; features beautiful pieces of Art printed onto silk fabrics. All the scarves are made in England. Sarah has been labelled as one to watch, after she was awarded the River Island Graduate Fashion Week Award in 2008. 
Sarah said: “It will be great to have a physical presence in the marketplace at last! So far I’ve only been online. People will love the feel of my silk scarves and I hope it will make them buy. I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millaandarti.co.uk/"&gt;Milla &amp;amp; Arti&lt;/a&gt; was set up by product design consultant Deborah Reyner 18 months ago. Her British-made homeware collection includes bespoke lavender hearts for weddings, patchwork kits, gift ties and ribbons, collars and bows. 
Deborah said: “This is a wonderful opportunity for Milla &amp;amp; Arti and to talk about my products which are made by the British seaside and get people interested in making and doing themselves. I haven’t been able to sleep for a week before this, I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brother and sister Mark and Clare Lissaman named their ethical organic cotton men’s shirt company after their grafting grandfathers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.arthurandhenry.com/"&gt;Arthur &amp;amp; Henry&lt;/a&gt; was developed after ethical consultant Clare noticed there were no ethical formal shirts on the market. “I was at the World Congress on Organic Cotton a few years back and realised that although all the men attending were passionate about organic cotton - none were actually wearing any as they were all suited up and couldn’t find proper smart shirts in organic cotton,” Clare, from Islington, said. “So we thought we’d make some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re thrilled and delighted to have this opportunity. For a newly established, ethical menswear brand, this is an amazing opportunity to meet customers face-to-face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single mum and former interior designer Esther Gibbs, from Chiswick, created &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmummy.com/"&gt;London Mummy&lt;/a&gt; after people kept asking her where she bought the cushions and accessories she had made herself. All her products are now either made in England – some by Esther herself - or by women’s collectives in China. Her handpicked selection includes retro bed linen, colourful crochet animals, quirky kids’ stationery, classic toys and games, funky lunchboxes, wall art and more. Esther also makes beautiful children’s fabrics, which she sells in store too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther said: “I sell online but I’ll sell much more in the shop. Once people understand what the shop is about and what it’s doing for small British businesses, it will be a great asset for the high street and small businesses. I’m delighted to be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sock entrepreneur Philip Morrow, 25, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.morrowsoutfitters.com/"&gt;Morrow’s Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; last year as a way to re-establish his great-grandfather’s former gentlemen’s outfitters shop that operated in Liverpool between 1912 and 1987. His range of Loughborough-made cotton socks come in over 40 designs and colours. 
Phillip said: “Pop-up shops make a great deal of sense for small online businesses such as mine. I’m over the moon about getting the opportunity to come into PopUp Britain in Victoria.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-time English teacher and designer Alia Qadir, 30, from Ealing, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theenglishteeshop.com/"&gt;The English Tee Shop&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to combine her passion for fashion and love of grammar! All her cotton is English-made and printed. She sells online and runs her business part-time from home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia said: “Until now I have relied on my online presence to sell my brand. But my T-shirts are made from a really good quality, soft jersey, and that doesn’t come across online. I’m really delighted about this new pop-up adventure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-town-team-tool-kit"&gt;New Town team tool kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the prototype shopping concept comes a newly-developed pop-up-specific tool kit for Town Teams to implement, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a national pop-up lease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a central website with information about the initiative for town teams and new businesses interested in applying for a slot at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.popupbritain.com"&gt;www.popupbritain.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to free pop-up payment equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a step-by-step guide for setting up a PopUp Britain shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PopUp Britain branding to make the shop recognisable to the consumer as a place where they can support British enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review, the department is running a number of high street Town Team Portas Pilots in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs. Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams in May, and 15 more in July, with three from London, bringing the total to 27. They each receive up to £100,000 of funding plus support from Government and retail expert Mary Portas. More detail can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"&gt;Improving high streets and town centres pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-teams"&gt;Town Teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 330 Town Team Partners support includes: an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management; special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and support from industry experts and trade bodies including an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice; regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas; and ‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work. All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919132719/www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;List of Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="statistics"&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key statistics and evidence on start-ups in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 saw a record high for start-ups: over 450,000 people set up a company
 and became their own boss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a StartUp Britain poll revealed 82% of start-ups found the pop-up experience was valuable for their business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the UK, there are 4.8 million private sector companies employing an estimated 23.9 million people with a turnover of £3,100 billion. Small and medium-sized enterprises also account for almost half of the net growth in jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to the latest figures from the British Retail Consortium, 11.3% of shop premises in UK town centres are now vacant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to research from StartUp Britain, 63% of businesses not already on the high street think their business would benefit from a high street presence and, of these, 88% believe funding is the biggest barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="additional-quotes"&gt;Additional quotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Johnson, Chairman of StartUp Britain, former Pizza Express boss and Chairman and part-owner of Patisserie Valerie and Giraffe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new high street name that will become synonymous with buying British and supporting small British enterprise is a fantastic idea. I’m sure PopUp Britain will be embraced by town planners and local government as a way to offer tangible support to their own high streets and start-up communities.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Russell, Chief Executive of WeArePopUp, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-ups are ideal incubators for the next generation of entrepreneurs. It’s very encouraging to see the Government opening a national showcase in a high-profile location such as Cardinal Place in Victoria. Pop-ups can change the fortunes of local communities and we look forward to this support encouraging more landlords to open up their empty shops and become part of the solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosie Cann, Director at Popupspace, a property consultancy that specialises in pop ups, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find space for lots of established retailers, but the challenges for new businesses wanting to open shops are much wider. What we have here is a unique offering to smaller start-ups looking for affordable space to sell, but also for business support and a high profile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Little, UK Managing Director of Intuit, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up tenants need to be able to accept card payments but it can take weeks to get set up, the equipment and transactions can be expensive and require long-term contracts. Intuit is proud to support PopUp Britain with Intuit Pay, giving start-up retailers a way to get set up in minutes to securely take card payments on their smart phone or tablet – with no commitment and no contracts. With Intuit Pay anyone can now accept card payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the shop are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269606220/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56690</id>
    <published>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T00:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/louise-casey-calls-for-family-intervention-approach"/>
    <title>Louise Casey calls for family intervention approach</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a look at the academic evidence, alongside consultation with practitioners and families themselves, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/louise-casey"&gt;Louise Casey&lt;/a&gt; today published a new report that shows the life-changing results that good family intervention can have on even the most challenging households, along with a guide to best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;‘Working with Troubled Families’ report&lt;/a&gt; outlines that family intervention reduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;involvement in anti-social behaviour by 59%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;involvement in crime by 45%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;truancy, exclusion, bad behaviour at school by 52%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also points to the 5 key features of effective family intervention being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dedicated worker, dedicated to a family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ‘hands on’ support &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a persistent, assertive and challenging approach &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;considering the family as a whole - gathering the intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common purpose and agreed action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louise Casey is now calling on councils to review their own ways of working with troubled families and adopt these principles in order to ensure that the significant momentum that has built up behind the programme - with all eligible local authorities in England on board and committed to working with over 40,000 families in this financial year - continues in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to push on with this work and make further progress towards the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around the lives of 120,000 troubled families by 2015, the Department for Communities and Local Government will also be holding a series of training academies for local authorities in the new year to help share best practice on family intervention and provide masterclasses from some of its leading exponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head of the government’s Troubled Families programme Louise Casey said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My last report was about listening to troubled families themselves and some of the stories from families were truly appalling. However these were families successfully going through family intervention and the results were impressive - so I wanted to ensure that this practice is adopted as widely as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This report makes a strong case about what works - family intervention that involves one dedicated worker for each family, providing tough but persistent challenge and support, has a dramatic impact, not just on the life chances of those within the families, but on the communities around them who suffer from the effects of truancy, youth crime and anti-social behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This important piece of work is a crucial step towards building a wide campaign of support behind the work we are doing to break an inter-generational cycle of misery and failure with these families. It will put rocket boosters under the Prime Minister’s pledge to turn around 120,000 troubled families by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Effective family intervention also demonstrates that savings can be made for taxpayers by putting families back on the right track for the long run, rather than wasting money on simply reacting to their problems. We must have aspiration for every family and this work will reach all corners of the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dame Clare Tickell, Chief Executive of Action for Children, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Since developing the initial model, we’ve seen how family intervention can really help vulnerable families facing multiple difficulties in their lives. It works by forming effective relationships with families and building on their strengths. This timely guide is a welcome resource, which will help people understand the key features of the model, learn what really works and ensure that projects are delivered to a high quality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/working-with-troubled-families-a-guide-to-evidence-and-good-practice"&gt;Working with Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, December 2012&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/listening-to-troubled-families"&gt;Listening to Troubled Families report&lt;/a&gt;, July 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All eligible local authorities are running troubled families programmes in their area and between them have committed to start work with 41,835 families across England by the end of this financial year, over a third of the 120,000 the Prime Minister wants to see turned around by the end of this parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Communities and Local Government is today also publishing management information on the work of family intervention projects and services in England up to 31 March 2012. This reports the latest data at a national level for all participating family intervention services. It includes information on the families worked with and the percentage of families considered to have a successful outcome in relation to family functioning and risk, crime/ anti-social behaviour, health and education/ employment. This data was collected by the National Centre for Social Research (NatCen) which ran a secure web-based information system into which family intervention project staff recorded details of the families they worked with between 2007-2012. It can be found at Annex B of the ‘Working With Troubled Families’ report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56381</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T17:04:38+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T17:04:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/no-hidden-costs-to-home-improvement"/>
    <title>No hidden costs to home improvement</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government today announced that anyone looking to improve their home through measures such as building a conservatory will not be subject to any rules requiring them to carry out additional building works on other parts of the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals for ‘consequential improvements’ - whereby work on one part of a home would trigger a requirement to carry out energy efficiency improvement works throughout, such as the installation of loft or cavity wall insulation - would in fact deter many people from having any work done in the first place, ministers believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Having consulted carefully, the government has noted the potential danger that introducing consequential improvements would, in fact, discourage people from undertaking home improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This measure ensures that it will remain straightforward for hard-working homeowners to undertake small-scale home improvements and conservatories.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January this year the Department for Communities and Local Government published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; on reforms to building regulations in England, aimed at providing significant savings to business, whilst ensuring buildings remain safe and sustainable. The consultation asked for views on whether to require ‘consequential improvements’ to the energy efficiency of a home when other building work such as the creation of extensions, large conservatories, loft and garage conversions was undertaken, or when boilers or a number of the home’s windows were replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most conservatories would not have been affected by such proposals ministers have carefully considered responses to the consultation, as well as research of the effects on homeowners and building professionals by the Energy Saving Trust and AECOM respectively. The Energy Saving Trust research indicated that over a third of households would be put off from doing home improvements if they had to undertake consequential improvements as well. The research also revealed concerns that there was greater potential for cowboy builders to mislead customers over what consequential improvements would be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the government’s growth agenda and the proposed lifting of planning rules to make it easier for people to carry out sensible extensions and improvements to their home Ministers have decided it would be inappropriate to place an additional cost on building owners. The Green Deal will continue to provide financial incentives to homeowners looking to improve their home’s energy efficiency, cut carbon emissions and reduce their long term energy bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minor-consequential-improvements"&gt;Written statement on minor consequential improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-l-proposals-for-consequential-improvements-in-existing-homes-report-of-focus-groups"&gt;Changes to Part L of the building regulations: proposals for consequential improvements in existing homes - report of focus groups&lt;/a&gt;, AECOM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.energysavingtrust.org.uk/Publications2/Corporate/Research-and-insights/Building-regulations-and-Green-Deal-research-report"&gt;Exploratory Research into Building Regulations in relation to the Green Deal&lt;/a&gt;, Energy Saving Trust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56280</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minor-consequential-improvements"/>
    <title>Minor consequential improvements</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, the Department for Communities and Local Government published a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/building-regulations-conservation-of-fuel-and-power"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; on reforms to building regulations in England. The proposals contained a strong deregulatory element which seeks to deliver real and significant savings to business, whilst ensuring our buildings remain safe and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department will shortly publish details of some of the deregulatory reforms stemming from that consultation. However, I wanted to inform honourable members of the government’s conclusion on one aspect that attracted significant public and media attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation sought views on whether to require ‘consequential improvements’ to the energy efficiency of a dwelling when other defined building work was undertaken, such as (a) extensions or increases in habitable space (ie loft and integral garage conversions) and (b) the replacement of a boiler or a percentage of the home’s windows. Such proposals were coined as a ‘conservatory tax’, although it should be noted that most conservatories would not have been affected by such proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers have carefully considered the responses to the consultation. We have also taken into account quantitative research work by the Energy Saving Trust of householders and qualitative analysis by AECOM of building professionals, which I have today placed in the library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Energy Saving Trust research found that consequential improvements, even with Green Deal finance in place, would put off 38% of households from going ahead with building work on their property that they were otherwise planning (Energy Saving Trust, ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.energysavingtrust.org.uk/Publications2/Corporate/Research-and-insights/Building-regulations-and-Green-Deal-research-report"&gt;Exploratory Research into Building Regulations in relation to the Green Deal&lt;/a&gt;’, p.37).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AECOM focus groups found that the majority of the installers registered with Gas Safe Register or members of competent person schemes were very negative towards the idea of being responsible for informing homeowners of the consequential improvement requirements. They observed that given the current economic climate, increased costs would make it harder to win work - homeowners may be deterred from getting the work done or delay commissioning the work. There was concern that by leaving the responsibility to inform homeowners to the installer, it could increase dishonesty in the market. It would potentially present rogue traders with an opportunity either to not inform homeowners of the requirements (to keep costs down), or to inflate the requirements and ‘rip people off’ (AECOM, ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/building-regulations-part-l-proposals-for-consequential-improvements-in-existing-homes-report-of-focus-groups"&gt;Changes to Part L of the building regulations: proposals for consequential improvements in existing homes - report of focus groups&lt;/a&gt;’, p.5). There were also concerns about non-compliance, with homeowners facing prosecution and £5,000 fines, leading to widespread problems with enforcement (p.44).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these concerns point to the danger that introducing consequential improvements would, in fact, discourage people from undertaking home improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having considered all the representations and evidence, including the public reaction, I can inform the House that we will not be going ahead with such regulatory proposals in any way at this point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding, there is significant scope to promote take up of the voluntary Green Deal, which allows householders - if they choose - to improve the energy efficiency of their home without any upfront cost. We intend to work with the industry and local authorities to help increase awareness of the Green Deal amongst householders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, it is my department’s stated policy (as outlined in my &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201213/cmhansrd/cm120906/wmstext/120906m0001.htm"&gt;statement of 6 September 2012&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 29WS) to make it easier for householders to undertake small-scale home improvements and conservatories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cancellation of the council tax revaluation (as outlined in my &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmhansrd/cm101011/wmstext/101011m0001.htm"&gt;statement of 11 October 2010&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 1WS) has also avoided the imposition of higher council taxes on home improvements. As explained in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201212/cmhansrd/cm120430/text/120430w0002.htm#1205012000001"&gt;answer of 30 April 2012&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Official Report’, Column 1105W, we have also discontinued the revaluation database and ceased the intrusive collection of data on the scenic views, gardens and patios of families’ homes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50131</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/first-regional-strategy-to-be-abolished"/>
    <title>First regional strategy to be abolished</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be achieved when East England’s regional strategy becomes the first to be formally abolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-down approach of regional strategies from the last administration imposed centrally set building targets on communities rather than giving local people the powers to plan. The regional strategies coincided with the lowest peacetime levels of housebuilding since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning and housebuilding works best when it is locally-led and from 3 January 2013 councils and local people across the former government office region for the East of England once again have control of deciding and shaping development in the places where they live. An order to abolish the strategy was laid in Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abolition of the East’s regional strategy reinforces the importance of the local plan, produced with the involvement of local communities, as the keystone of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Regional planning built nothing but resentment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is the next stage in the abolition of the whole tier of regional government in East England. We are devolving power from unelected regional quangos down to elected local councils and to local communities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government made clear its commitment to return decision-making on housing and planning to local councils and to end the era of centrally-imposed targets which build resentment to development, and is introducing powerful incentives to ensure communities benefit from development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Localism Act 2011 legislated to provide powers to abolish the last administration’s regional strategies. European Union law requires strategic environmental assessments to be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yesterday (10 December 2012) the government announced councils who welcomed new development in the last year will share £661 million from the New Homes Bonus scheme, which pays a cash bonus for every new home built or brought back into use. Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share in the cash payout after delivering 142,000 new homes in the last year, including 58,000 affordable properties, and bringing a further 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In addition the government is getting Britain building and has: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invested £19.5 billion of public and private funding in a programme to deliver 170,000 affordable homes, which is on track and exceeding expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the FirstBuy scheme, which will help 27,000 first time buyers purchase a new build home, and the NewBuy Guarantee, which will help tens of thousands of aspiring homebuyers take their next step on the housing ladder with a fraction of the normal deposit, as little as 5%; leading house builders have recently praised these schemes for boosting the sales of new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identified enough formerly-used, surplus public sector land to support 100,000 new homes, and already sold enough of this land to deliver 33,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduced the £1.3 billion Get Britain Building and Growing Places schemes which will unlock stalled housing sites across the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The government’s reform package is working. The latest housebuilding figures show starts on new homes are up by 18% compared to the previous quarter, and year on year completions are up by 6%. Housing starts are 52% higher than 2009, and recent housing supply figures also show net supply is at the highest level since the tail end of the unsustainable housing boom in 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘Strategic environmental assessment about revoking the East of England regional strategy: post adoption statement’ is available &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/strategic-environmental-assessment-of-revoking-the-east-of-england-regional-strategy" title="post adoption statement"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The written ministerial statement on the revocation of the East of England regional strategy can be found &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-vote-office/December_2012/11-12-12/5-DCLG-EastOfEngland.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50196</id>
    <published>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-ministers-wish-the-jewish-community-a-happy-chanukah"/>
    <title>Communities ministers wish the Jewish community a happy Chanukah</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want to take this opportunity to recognise the huge contribution the Jewish community has made, and continues to make, towards British society and culture. We have seen some marvellous examples of this throughout the year such as Barnet and District Synagogue joining a food collection with their local church as part of ‘A Year of Service’. The annual triumph of ‘Mitzvah Day’ has also seen thousands of people across the globe volunteer - from improving the local environment, working with the homeless or visiting care homes - these activities have all made a real difference to their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw this first hand when I recently attended a multi-faith volunteering event organised by a local synagogue in St Albans. It was terrific to see how so many people gave their time to help the wider community, and come together with those of other faiths at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to wish the whole Jewish community a very happy Chanukah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As each candle is lit over the next eight nights during the Festival of Lights, I want to wish all Jewish communities a very happy and peaceful Chanukah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lighting of the menorah candles remind us of the persistence of hope and endurance through difficult times and I want to acknowledge the role that the Jewish community play within our wider society. I work closely with many Jewish groups in my role as Minister for Faith and Communities and particularly enjoyed visiting a ‘Mitzvah Mummies’ event - a volunteering project where mothers and their babies visited residential care homes - earlier this month. It was wonderful to see the joy this brought the residents and it showed how faith can bring people together and have such a positive impact on the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Happy holidays to you all.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17574</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/winners-announced-for-faith-based-photography-competition"/>
    <title>Winners announced for faith-based photography competition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This annual competition uses photographs to celebrate how faith is present in communities throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel of judges, headed by award-winning photographer Don McCullin, chose the winning photographs from 3 categories which were: moments of faith, community spirit against the odds and A Year of Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Year of Service, supported by the department, was a new category included in the competition this year. It aims to celebrate social action and to mark the practical contribution that faith groups make within their neighbourhoods to improve the lives of those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each faith in turn has hosted a day, or days, of volunteering throughout the year and those taking part were encouraged to send in photos that captured the inter-faith volunteering projects they had been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They say a picture is worth a thousand words and I was delighted to see A Year of Service really come alive in some terrific photos that perfectly captured the strength of our faith communities and the commitment they make to their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This has been a memorable year of social action so thank you to all the budding photographers who entered and congratulations to the winners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith Minister Baroness Warsi said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These photos really illustrate what can be achieved when communities join together, so it was fantastic to see all of the photographs that were submitted for the competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to all those who took part, it is great to have a permanent record of A Year of Service events - here’s to another successful year of faith volunteering and social action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winning photograph for A Year of Service was entitled ‘There but for the Grace of God’ and was taken to coincide with the theme of giving during the Harvest Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="A man giving food to a homeless woman" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1245/grace_of_god_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;'There but for the Grace of God'. Picture: Rob Boler&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This photograph and the other winners and finalists in the competition can be found on the awards and highlights section of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://ftal.staged.ws/awards-highlights-from-2012/"&gt;Faith Through a Lens website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baroness Warsi was speaking at the Coin Street Neighbourhood centre where she gave a key note address at Together in Service, a national celebration for A Year of Service. The event, organised by the department was opened by Communities Minister Don Foster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attendees including faith leaders and representatives of faith-based organisations, were also invited to contribute to a piece of art work which will be donated to the Evelina Children’s Hospital, a part of Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Painting of children planting a peace garden" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1246/art_work_picture.JPG"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Baroness Warsi with the painting to be donated to Evelina Children’s Hospital&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene includes 9 children planting a peace garden - each of the children representing 9 different faith groups. Attendees of the celebration were invited to create flowers which are included in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Together in Service event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632131148440/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ayearofservice.org.uk"&gt;A Year of Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17220</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-budget-pilots-transforming-public-services"/>
    <title>Community budget pilots transforming public services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles announced how the pilots can save the taxpayer millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, 4 Community Budget pilots in Essex, London, Manchester and Cheshire, with support from Whitehall, were given free reign to track local public expenditure to see where it was being spent and whether it was being put to best use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilots discovered that a large proportion of budgets and services were focused on entrenched problems where small numbers of people were repeatedly involved in local services costing the taxpayer hundreds of millions of pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues included how to reduce repeat offenders; how to support older people with chronic health conditions so they are less likely to end up in hospital; helping victims of domestic abuse earlier; and identifying and helping children facing disadvantage from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking radical steps that set up better locally-integrated early intervention services between all agencies the pilots could save the 4 areas hundreds of millions over the next 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a conference about Community Budgets to an audience of public service experts, Communities and Local Government Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I wasn’t looking for these pilots to patch things up, to mend and make do, to think about service improvement I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family, at cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000, our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’ve also worked out, if you get heads together in a room. Focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the reoffenders, the long-term unemployed and those with dependencies you can actually start to take dependence out the system and you can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are all on the same page now. The pilots are bringing services together with an appreciation of the real prize for getting this right and is not just savings of millions of pounds it is changing people’s lives too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="health-and-social-care"&gt;Health and social care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester it is estimated that 750,000 hospital bed days a year are occupied by older people with multiple long term conditions, costing £800 million to £1.2 billion annually. Two per cent are aged over 85 but they account for 10% of emergency admissions and 18% of all hospital bed days. They estimate that they can reduce emergency admissions and days spent in hospital beds or care homes. The 3 West London boroughs found that 20% of residents who had the highest health and social care needs accounted for nearly 80% of spend on these services. This represented almost £25,000 for a person with very high needs compared to £250 for people with very low needs. West Cheshire expect to make a £26 million saving from a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="domestic-abuse"&gt;Domestic abuse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex has 29,000 incidents of domestic abuse causing costs of £86 million in the county every year. Four in 5 victims visit GPs before going to police. Essex’s plan will see a single hub streamlining the current system where 1000 locations, 116 phone numbers and in excess of 80 agencies deal with domestic violence, bringing agencies together with common goals and aligned budgets. It will focus on prevention and early intervention will save over £100 million by reducing reoffending and domestic abuse, supporting 17,000 victims by creating a single contact point to help with issues like accommodation and dealing with perpetrators. West Cheshire found that almost all of the £20 million spent on dealing with its 9,000 cases of domestic abuse was reactive. They expect to save £17 million by providing earlier support for victims and dealing with perpetrators sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reducing-reoffending"&gt;Reducing reoffending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Westminster, Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham found that half of those given short sentences were likely to reoffend within a year. That group totals 9% of all offenders but two-thirds of all prison admissions and releases. They are establishing a bespoke service to co-ordinate help that is expected to save £25 million. They are cutting the time care proceedings take to go through the courts. Half of all crime in Essex is committed by someone with a record. Two thirds of boys with a convicted father go on to commit crimes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supporting-children"&gt;Supporting children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greater Manchester, about 40% of young children - 16,000 each year - are assessed as not school ready. Early years services are fragmented and often miss the wider factors that influence a child’s development. These services cost the area £300 million a year but we spend far more than that addressing the subsequent failure. This approach is expected to secure £215 million savings over 25 years on a cohort of children born in particular years for an investment of £38 million. West Cheshire plan to introduce a children’s investment unit and single family assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people in Essex are not choosing vocational and skills courses that give them the best chance of a quality career with skills to offer employers. The council are making training employment led through an Employment and Skills Board to address the mismatch between skills of residents and young people and needs of businesses. Directing money in the right way will act as a catalyst for more apprenticeships, creating a more streamlined pathway from education to work and fewer NEETs (not in education, employment or training) by setting out clear choices and opportunities for young people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17739</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/community-budgets--2"/>
    <title>Community Budgets</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I don’t want to talk about the ins and outs of community budgets, or the finer points of cost benefit analysis. I want to talk about their impact on people’s lives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why it’s a scandal that agencies in Doncaster, faced with more than 100 events involving children, failed to co-ordinate any realistic attempt to prevent what happened in the Edlington case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why so few children are getting their teeth checked in parts of Newcastle, that more and more are ending up having emergency treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about why in West Cheshire 1 woman faced 30 incidents of domestic abuse before feeling able to turn to an agency that might help her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to talk about my own area, Essex, and why some people still feel able to let a young father from that neck of the woods get caught up in a Kafkaesque nightmare - “Meeting upon meeting with different organisations” - just to get a bit of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that these are the types of service failure that the pilots themselves are addressing. Because if these initiatives were just about money, we’d rightly be accused of a lack of ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, we’re all having to live with less. And, given the waste, given the inefficiency, given the duplication that went on before, the purpose of this is to use less to deliver a better service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t just looking for these pilots to just patch things up. To mend and make do. To think about ‘service improvement’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="people-at-the-centre-of-the-system"&gt;People at the centre of the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted them to put people at the heart of the system and get to the root cause of entrenched problems. Even if that means throwing away the rule book and starting again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m glad to see that is what has been happening. The tri-borough initiative - part of the Whole-Place pilots - is proposing to reduce unplanned admissions to hospital. Putting the donkey work into helping older people with longer term conditions before they get to an acute stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got the greater Manchester pilot working with parents of children at risk so they don’t pass on the bad habits likely to hold kids back for the rest of their lives. The idea to ensure kids get a fresh start and can stand at the school gates on their first day ready with great excitement to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve got pioneers in West Cheshire making sure families with complex needs now have an advocate who’s going to stick with them through thick and thin. Instead of an average of 68 separate interventions per family at a staggering cost to the taxpayer of up to £92,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pilots have discovered that if you simply follow the money you’ll usually find different cash flowing through different pipes to different agencies with different targets. But we’ve worked out, if you get people together in a room - if you focus on the elderly and the vulnerable, the troubled families, the re-offenders, the long-term unemployed and all those with dependencies - you can usually start taking dependence out the system. You can actually begin to help people recover their sense of self-worth so they can lead independent lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re going to keep working with these 4 areas to make sure our plans really are do-able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why we’re going to help other areas to learn from their experience. We know our colleagues across government are up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the way we’ve managed to bridge the old Whitehall, local government, voluntary sector fault lines has been one of the great success stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier on today we heard Norman Lamb speak about the pilot’s positive approach to health and social care integration. And we’re working with the Treasury, Work and Pensions, Education, Home Office and the Ministry of Justice to ensure we’re all on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="neighbourhoods-on-track"&gt;Neighbourhoods on track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know, as we’ve heard today, that our neighbourhood community budgets are on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Ilfracombe to Haverhill they’re making sure their communities are involved in making the most of their resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critically, local folk are backing them. 89% of people surveyed in Poplar felt citizens should ‘do their bit’. While more than half wanted to be involved in turning their neighbourhood around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we’re seeing community budgets turning their irrepressible energy, their boundless enthusiasm, to that eternal question of reducing waste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ilfracombe, for example, knows that nationally an estimated £300 million per year of NHS money is wasted through over prescription of medication. Imagine all those pills and potions sitting in the cupboard never being taken away. So Ilfracombe is tracking down that waste with the help of its local people to stop the rot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because what’s driving Ilfracombe, what’s driving us all is the priceless prize for getting this right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just savings of millions of pounds, but hearing from the young girl of the father in Essex I mentioned earlier talking about how she’s been; “changed… around”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing from the man who’d fallen on hard times describe how, by becoming a mentor, he now has; “something to get up for to make him feel better about himself that he is helping others”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is more than money. It is the prize. And the prize relates to people. There’s a real opportunity here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said it was brave, fool hardly, silly even, to try this. They said it was bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve been really impressed with how all the different organisations have risen to the challenge. We’ve always known these problems existed. Now we have the chance to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what fires you up and me up and Bob up is not the cost benefit analysis. It is the fact we can make a difference to people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a noble cause. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not just a case of government knows best. People must understand they too have a sense of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t lose that fire in your belly. Be innovative, be bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and I can make a difference. And together you and I will set us on course to make a difference for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
