<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/gerald-howarth</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/gerald-howarth.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Gerald Howarth MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-08T10:30:12+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18766</id>
    <published>2012-05-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T10:30:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-02-smarter-and-greener-defence"/>
    <title>2012/05/02 - Smarter and Greener Defence</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at the Nordic Defence Industry Seminar, Copenhagen on Wednesday 2 May 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning. And thank you Kristian, (Danish MOD Deputy Permanent Secretary for International Policy) for that kind introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great honour to be asked to address NORDEFCO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective defence calls for effective collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group is a good model for us all when it comes to practical hands on commitment and delivery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are also very much on the front foot when it comes to pursuing a new and radical approach to achieving a Smarter and Greener Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be talking a little later about these two issues which, focusing as they do on the crucial issue of resources, are essentially both sides of the same coin. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I speak on behalf of the others when I say it is a particular privilege that you have also invited to this seminar colleagues from the wider Northern Group..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group which encompasses the Baltic nations, Germany, Poland, the Netherlands. And of course the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s fair to say that previous British Governments have not placed  the same value on building relations with our fellow Northern European nations as we do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister with the lead for defence diplomacy, I’m very clear that the nations of Northern Europe comprise a group of countries bound together with a shared history and shared values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In NORDEFCO you have, of course, recognised that for many years. It’s just the rest of us who have taken a little longer to wake up to the issue. Perhaps we in Britain took too long to recover from the Vikings, the only people successfully to have invaded the UK in 1,000 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Norway, and the work they are doing around the clock to guard NATO’s North Eastern flank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Norway earlier this year at the invitation of the Norwegian MOD State Secretary, Roger Ingebrigtsen, I had the privilege  personally to take the controls of a the P3 Orion and fly over the Polar ice cap. It gave me a very real appreciation of the sheer scale indeed, loneliness, of this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an area which is going to become increasingly important, as the Northern Sea Route - which almost halves the transit time between Europe and the Far East - is likely to be open for several months of the year within the next 10 years. Within that time the retreat of the ice will mean the opening of energy supplies and passage of shipping which is potentially game changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norway’s work in safeguarding these routes is of vital strategic importance to us all - and it’s important we begin to think ahead about the challenges presented by climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Group provides such an opportunity to bring us together to discuss issues of relevance to our mutual security, without reference to any particular institutional framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very obvious to me that we as neighbours should work together to secure our own region, to keep our trade routes open, and together face threats as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming here to Copenhagen is - for me - therefore very much a neighbourhood visit. And a wonderful opportunity to get together with like-minded friends and partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like minded friends and partners who, in common with the UK, are outward facing, aware that defence is also an international business, and with whom we have served on operations across the world stage in recent years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On last year’s Operation Unified Protector over Libya, for example.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s decision to maintain a stunningly high level of sorties (double the coalition average) throughout August proved critical to bringing an end to Qadhafi’s tyrannical regime.  We much appreciated Danish Defence Minister Gitte Bech’s willingness to extend Danish operations.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the invaluable contribution of the Royal Norwegian Air Force, which flew more sorties than at any time since the Second World War.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was privileged - on my visit there in January - to have the opportunity to meet some of the commanders and pilots who spearheaded Norway’s contribution.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An operation which also saw Sweden step forward to help enforce the No Fly Zone over Libya with eight of its Gripen aircraft and a C-130.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first time in over 60 years that Sweden - a non-NATO nation - had conducted an out-of-area operation with an offensive air capability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there were times when the Swedish Air Force was providing something in the region of 40 per cent of the entire coalition air picture; an extraordinary contribution.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Northern Group are also heavily engaged in counter piracy operations off the coast of Somalia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Denmark’s counter piracy effort involves providing a naval contribution for six months of every year, plus an MPA contribution for up to two months of every year.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in Afghanistan where UK Forces have fought - and are fighting - alongside forces from Denmark, Sweden, Norway, Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Latvia, Poland, Germany and the Netherlands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many have very sadly lost their lives: a tragic total of 594 across all twelve Northern Group countries, of which the UK has suffered 410 losses.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to say something very briefly here about the contribution of Denmark and Estonia, who have been closely involved with us in Helmand Province.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both countries have borne a particularly high proportion of casualties in the light of the number of forces deployed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now been to Afghanistan 6 times, and had the privilege of meeting the Danish and Estonian military on a number of occasions when visiting our troops in Helmand. I am always impressed by their professionalism and commitment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan has taught us all a lot about collaboration and the concept of everyone maximising each other’s strengths and capabilities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on that note, I’d like to take this opportunity to say how much we are looking forward to working with Denmark in developing the Afghan National Army Officers Academy.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a crucial contribution to Afghanistan’s future security, and we are delighted to be working on it with our close comrades from Helmand Province.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that NORDEFCO members are adamant that this is an initiative which isn’t about new military or political alliances.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What NORDEFCO is about is sharing resources, driving down costs and enhancing interoperability. Doing more with less.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are a pragmatic and proactive group already leading the way on Smart Defence - or to use the EU term, ‘pooling and sharing’.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some here today are members of NATO, but not the EU. And vice versa. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What matters to me is that all countries wanting to contribute to collective defence and security are able to do so without constraint by institutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, the UK has developed - and will shortly see enter service - a major enhancement to our air-to-air refuelling capability. This will give Europe a significant enhancement in an area which has a critical shortfall. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we didn’t wait for the EU or for NATO to tell us to develop that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t plan to wait for either of these organisations to find us potential partners with whom to share the spare capacity we anticipate having when the system is fully in service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact under David Cameron’s government the UK has been actively driving forward bilateral and small group cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe it offers a practical way in which the international community can respond to the strategic and financial challenges of the twenty-first century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the publication of our Strategic Defence and Security Review in October 2010, we have signed no fewer than three Defence Treaties and 27 Memoranda of Understanding, including with Norway.  And more of these bilateral agreements are under negotiation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working hard to ‘bottle’ the superb collaboration shared by the UK, Denmark and Estonia in Helmand Province. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly when it comes to sustaining the logistics relationships which have proved so fundamental to our success together in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next month my own Policy Director will chair a meeting of Northern Group MOD Policy Directors to consider the Group’s role in delivering further Smart Defence and Pooling and Sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And next year we look forward to working with Latvia and Lithuania and others on the UK-led EU Battlegroup. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we recognise that the EU has a complementary role to play in supporting NATO, I want to take this opportunity to emphasise that as far as the UK is concerned, NATO will remain the cornerstone of our security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because the Alliance continues to be a community prepared to back principles with military fire-power, as we saw last year in its implementation of the United Nations Security Council Resolution on Libya. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that when it became clear that sustained multi-lateral action was required, NATO was the only realistic co-ordinating structure prepared for - and with the mechanisms to deliver - joint and combined operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the Alliance does need to be revitalised. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya was very successful, but as Robert Gates said just before he stepped down as US Defence Secretary last year: ‘NATO’s serious capability gaps and other institutional shortcomings were laid bare by the Libya operation’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that we all need to think - and act - Smarter.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart Defence isn’t a random concept with a catchy title.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is it a shiny new strategy to be launched with a couple of Press Releases, posted on a website and quickly forgotten about.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it must certainly not become an excuse for individual countries to reduce national defence expenditure, which in many cases are already too low.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart Defence needs to become the basis on which we  collectively shape our defence capabilities in the future.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why we are actively supporting NATO’s Smart Defence initiative, which will be an important focus of this month’s Chicago Summit.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embedding Smart Defence in the Alliance requires it to be clearly tied into the NATO Defence Planning Process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also need common standards. Because the reality is that multinational military operations still suffer from poor interoperability.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also - and I think all of us here today are very aware of this -  about driving forward cultural changes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the NATO Secretary-General observed to NATO Chiefs of Defence earlier this year, Smart Defence is essentially about changing mindsets.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About getting nations to think in a more collegiate way, and take an objective approach about capabilities which many of us are more used to thinking of as sovereign.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to understand the challenges faced by nations such as the UK, who cannot risk relying on an unreliable partner to provide a key capability.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smarter defence is actually about future proofing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to make sure our resources go further.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK, we are currently going through a process of transformation, getting our budget back under control and putting the management of Defence on a sustainable footing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There also remains far too much inefficiency in both NATO and the EU. Too many headquarters, for example - and too many staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us here can afford it - and we must address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course one very important way of boosting our efficiency and being Smart, which is relevant to this conference, is to adopt a new approach to the way defence uses energy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a fact that the military have been - and will for the foreseeable future - be dependent upon energy for battle wining capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy is a critical enabler - but, we need to make sure that it does not constrain us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our experience in recent operations has highlighted this as a potential vulnerability.  And just to put this into context - according to US military figures - a soldier in World War 2 used one gallon of fuel per day. Today the average American soldier on operations takes up 22 gallons every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And take for example Afghanistan, where most of the fuel we use has to be imported and forms the bulk of the long logistics tail from Karachi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those convoys have to be protected - and we have taken casualties in doing so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tandem, not only is the global price of diesel going up, but the cost of bringing it into theatre can be ten times the original price. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these convoys are vulnerable to disruption, such as the closure of international borders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of which impacts on our military effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find ways of reducing the amount of energy we use, and you will shortly be hearing more about the UK approach from Admiral Neil Morisetti, the UK Climate and Energy Security Envoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d just like to mention a couple of examples of work the UK has been taking forward in this area: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have funded Qinetiq’s development of the Zephyr - an amazing solar powered high altitude long endurance UAV which has successfully completed a world-beating three and a half day flight. This is a tremendously exciting capability with a huge amount of potential. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also have a plastic bottle recycling plant in Camp Bastion &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And we’ve also been looking at a range of energy management techniques to be deployed in forward operating bases - particularly in a harsh environment like Afghanistan. You’ll be hearing more about this MOD project - known as PowerFOB -  over the course of the seminar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all cases this has been achieved by working closely with our industrial partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The military will always require a hard edged war fighting capability -and for the foreseeable future that means using fossil fuels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, through energy efficiency and by opting - where appropriate -   for alternative sources of energy, we can sustain operational effectiveness and  address the wider issues of climate change, and the risks that poses to global stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, you can be smart and green.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are challenges we will - and must - face together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they call for effective collaboration and strong partnerships. I know this is something this group can - and will - deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18763</id>
    <published>2012-04-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T10:10:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-04-17-putrajaya-forum"/>
    <title>2012/04/17 - Putrajaya Forum</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at the Putrajaya Forum, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia on Tuesday 17 April 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chairman, fellow Defence Ministers, Ambassadors, High Commissioners, Chiefs of Staff, Ladies and Gentleman, I am delighted to be here in Kuala Lumpur, my second visit to Malaysia in four months and hot on the heels of my Prime Minister, David Cameron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron said: “Malaysia is now a real economic heavyweight and an influential actor in the region, in the Commonwealth and beyond.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His visit here has been part of a determined re-engagement with Malaysia and countries in this region. As he made clear, the era of “benign neglect” is over.  Britain is back and is ready to do business in this region. This will be good for all our economies, and for the region’s security interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delegation he led - of some of Britain’s top business people, including representatives of UK Defence Industries - is just one of many delegations from Britain to this part of the world over the last 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I am leading a delegation of around 40 British defence &amp;amp; security companies, many involved in joint ventures with Malaysian companies or businesses from other countries in the region, at DSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade links reinforce security relationships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="britain-in-asia"&gt;Britain in Asia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is here to do business - to re-invigorate old friendships and to build new partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many countries we have a shared history which brings us together. That is particularly the case here in Malaysia, with which the UK shares a relationship stretching our two centuries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As PM Najib reminded us earlier this week “we should celebrate these historic ties, both big and small, between our nations and to renew them for this generation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make sure we have a great future too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that future includes security co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the operation to bring peace and stability to Afghanistan, to the routine presence of Royal Naval vessels, to Ghurkhas in Brunei, Britain has a significant Defence footprint in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our recent Strategic Defence and Security Review was designed to maintain Britain’s strategic reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is bolstered by our permanent membership of the United Nations Security Council, and by our membership of NATO, the EU, and the Commonwealth.  In this region we remain a committed partner in the Five Power Defence Arrangements, an alliance which celebrated its 40th Anniversary last year, further enhanced by our strong bi-lateral partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course all this is underpinned by the 4th largest defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I from the United Kingdom Ministry of Defence have held high-level talks with many in this region and our Military Service Chiefs have engaged widely with their counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 18 months, we have signed three Defence Treaties and 33 Memoranda of Understanding, including with traditional partners like Australia and New Zealand but also with Asian powers such as India and new friends in this region such as Vietnam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this last week has shown, we intend to continue this process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strengthening Defence ties with Malaysia as our Prime Ministers’ agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving towards a new Defence Cooperation Memorandum with Japan and exploring Defence industry collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this action is a measure of the importance the UK places in our engagement in the region as a whole and reflects our determination to build a new calibre of partnership for a new age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="old-friends-new-partners"&gt;Old Friends, New Partners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an age of uncertainty, volatility and change as events in the Arab world are showing;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An age of emerging powers, not bi-polar as in the Cold War, but multi-polar where no single region or small group of countries can call all the shots; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And an age where we are more connected than ever before - our economies, our people, our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also an age when countries have united to tackle oppression by Governments against their own people.  In some instances the weight of world opinion combined with internal outrage has thankfully been sufficient to achieve change relatively peacefully, as in Tunisia and Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, most recently in Libya, the crimes being threatened against part of the population have required external, UN-authorised, assistance to protect civilians from the worst excesses of their own Government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Syria, today, we watch closely to see if a UN-brokered peace deal will bring that country back from the brink. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wait to see also if international pressure, combining sanctions and diplomatic engagement, will persuade Iran that it must submit to the will of the international community and accept that only the peaceful use of nuclear energy is acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, we welcome the emergence of this region as one of the centres of global power.  You have twice as many of the world’s top 30 richest cities than has Europe; and growing populations with rising ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This growth brings with it great developmental benefits to the people who live here - but it also brings new responsibilities to those who govern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron argued last week, those who benefit from increased trade and prosperity in an interdependent global economy have a responsibility, indeed an obligation to help maintain global security.  It means standing up and being part of the solution to insecurity wherever it emerges and not just being an onlooker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the United Kingdom welcomes the fact that countries here in Asia are playing an increasingly strong role in maintaining the international stability and security required to sustain growth and global prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Gulf, off the Horn of Africa, here and elsewhere - our navies operate together in international waters, protecting vital trading sea lanes from piracy - Forces from Malaysia, Japan, China, India, Singapore, Thailand and the Republic of Korea to name just a few, besides traditional partners such as Australia and New Zealand work regularly and well alongside the EU, NATO, and other national forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This co-operation is a recognition that very few nations, no matter how rich, can hope to provide for the security of their people by working alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most, therefore, partnership is necessary, not optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility of power calls for a responsibility to collaborate and find shared solutions to shared problems. Despite the obvious challenge, this is precisely what Britain and France are doing in the European context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you could explore similar opportunities in this region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the continents of Asia and Europe rely on being able to trade with one another, and with other regions beyond, to grow economically.  We therefore have a major stake in keeping open the trading links between us and facing down those who threaten them for their own national interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="multi-layered-security"&gt;Multi-layered Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can this region manage the inevitable tensions which may arise when growing prosperity, growing defence budgets and the growing strategic interests of countries in the region collide?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition is healthy, but it has to be ordered by alliances, treaties and recourse to international law, or else aggressive competition for resources or strategic advantage will ultimately threaten security, stability and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would be a lose-lose situation for everyone - instability, insecurity - and all threatening economic growth and development &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer has to be to find the right multi-national security structures and organisations which can best provide for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the United Nations, its Security Council and other global organisations exist for that purpose, but regional security solutions to regional security problems are preferable -  particularly where the issues straddle borders. As the Gulf states have shown through the Gulf Co-operation Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about giving up national power or about ceding sovereignty; it is about solving problems by coming together and working out the best way to avoid conflict and ensure that each country’s rights and economic interests are properly respected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mature organisation, designed to promote co-operation, ASEAN has the potential to be a platform for developing consensus and helping to drive regional security collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the political will of its members to build capacity which is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the United Kingdom stands ready to provide practical help in the development of a cohesive and proactive ASEAN if requested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do not believe that security is served by an approach of putting all your eggs in a single basket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that an approach which provides for multi-layered security - multilateral organisations like ASEAN supported by smaller group co-operation and bi-lateral relationships which can be swifter to act, more flexible in approach and generating real deployable capabilities in a crisis situation - offers the most practical solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in Europe, we sometimes struggle to co-operate effectively, so I know how difficult it can be for sovereign nations with different cultures and different political systems to find common ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if sufficient political will exists to tackle a problem, you will find solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategic challenge for ASEAN is therefore whether its member states continue to act unilaterally or whether they have the desire, and sufficient common national interest, to pool military resources for the betterment of regional and global security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a question I believe ASEAN could have asked itself even a decade ago.  But I firmly believe it can ask of itself now.  Do you want to help shape global security, or merely observe the actions of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the key question I pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, I am proud and honoured to be representing the UK in Malaysia at the Putrajaya Forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleague and fellow Minister of the crown, Lord Astor, spoke at the Jakarta International Defence Dialogue last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Britain will send a high level delegation to the Shangri-La dialogue in June, as we have done for successive years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are here as long standing friends, as partners, to collaborate and to co-operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Malaysia you have a saying: If it is heavy, we carry it together on our shoulders; if it is light, we carry it together in our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is here with our hands, and with our shoulders, to help carry the load, to work with you to find the best solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18756</id>
    <published>2012-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T11:12:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-13-smart-power-in-defence"/>
    <title>2012/03/13 - Smart Power in Defence</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at the Royal College of Defence Studies, London on Tuesday 13 March 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January this year, a carrier-group, led by the USS Abraham Lincoln, with escorts from the UK and France, sailed through the Strait of Hormuz in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sailed quietly - and at night - but its passage was noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of Iranian threats to close the Strait to shipping, a powerful message was being sent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this merely a 21st century display of 19th century gunboat diplomacy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it certainly was a show of formidable military force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying a big stick has an effect all of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes, it was the use of hard power assets - warships - to deter Iran - and to reassure allies in the region that the international community would not allow the Strait to be closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in reality, it was just one more turn of the screw by the International Community to put pressure on Iran over its pursuit of nuclear weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a struggle where we are deploying all the clubs in the golf bag - economic, diplomatic, military, political, legal, and cultural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ‘smart power’ is about is picking the right club, or the right combination of clubs, for the right occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about forging traditional soft and hard power assets - from development aid to defence diplomacy - from sanctions to air-strikes - into a comprehensive strategy focussed on the fulfilment of national objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="smart-power"&gt;SMART POWER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have always been intrinsic connections between the levers of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government has recognised, much more so than its predecessor, the inextricable link between economic strength and national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic clout is the number one weapon in the smart power arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because from economic strength flows our ability to influence the global environment in which we operate, our standing with our allies, and the calculations of our adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides us with a powerful voice in international institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides the long-term investment required to maintain modern, high-tech military forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it provides the funds for diplomatic reach and depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dealing with this country’s fiscal difficulties - the deficit, the national debt, and economic growth - has to underpin any realistic national security strategy - and has to be the basis for the UK’s application of ‘smart power’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Paul Cornish defined it for us earlier, power is: “the ability to get what is wanted, or to produce desired change”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power is, of course, relative not absolute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the Cold War and the rise of globalisation have unleashed the dynamism of capitalism in countries like China, India, Brazil - galvanising whole regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, relative power is shifting from mature economies in the West towards the swiftly growing South and East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain does continue to have a large economy and a high-tech military - we are unique in our historic ties, the talents of our people and our geopolitical position - but we are not omnipotent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this multi-polar world, we are one of a number of influential global powers at different stages of development and maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fact that power is more dispersed does not mean that Britain has to accept strategic shrinkage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed the Foreign Secretary has made just that point on a number of occasions, while in opposition and now in Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we have to use our power wisely - to adapt and operate differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be more canny, to use a Scottish expression - which translated into English means, of course, smart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is what we are doing - using all the levers of power to leverage influence in a world of multiple power centres and multiple tensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-stability-overseas"&gt;BUILDING STABILITY OVERSEAS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to this is a proper cross-government strategy for building stability overseas - helping to prevent conflicts and building international, regional and local capacity to deal with problems as they emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are improving our ability to anticipate conflict, to act rapidly when a crisis emerges to prevent escalation, and, most importantly to build up in susceptible countries strong, legitimate institutions to manage tensions peacefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the example of Afghanistan - we are not in Afghanistan to create a perfectly functioning western liberal democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are there to prevent the return of the terrorist threat operating with impunity from Afghan territory as it did before 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to limit the ungoverned space terrorists can exploit requires a government able to manage inter-ethnic and tribal tensions without recourse to civil war - that means it has to have the legitimacy and capacity to act on behalf of all the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having visited Afghanistan a few weeks ago, I am encouraged by the progress being made by ISAF in training the Afghan National Security Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am encouraged by the fact that the Karzai Government recognise that success will be achieved by good governance and political effect too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the integrated approach which we are applying in Afghanistan - marrying security with development, governance and political efforts - is a model from which we are learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conflict Pool, jointly managed by DfID, the MOD and the FCO, provides us with the resources to take strong and well-funded conflict prevention actions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be long-term, like the rebuilding of national security structures in Sierra Leone through an International Military Advisory and Training Team - or immediate, like building up the training for the African Union forces in Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But conflict prevention in far away places can only be successful if we are engaged in the world, we have strong ties with allies and partners and understand the very complex issues which spark bloody violence in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why our Building Stability Overseas strategy is supported by cross-government activity which deepens our ties with existing allies and forges new links with new partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="expeditionary-diplomacy"&gt;EXPEDITIONARY DIPLOMACY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as our military posture is expeditionary, so must be our diplomacy and other tools of soft power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would have thought that by definition - diplomacy is expeditionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, over the years, we have allowed some relationships to wilt through a lack of attention, and we have not explored fully the benefits of deeper relations with countries rising in global importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we do need to rediscover Britain’s expeditionary zeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only in the physical world we need to be expeditionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have the capacity to take action in cyberspace to protect and promote our interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not only Government which needs to be more expeditionary - power is not just wielded by Government - that is one of the many lessons of globalisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is wielded by civil society too - from universities attracting the best candidates, to businesses exporting the best products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are all representing the United Kingdom - and benefiting from Britain’s reputation abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With globalisation, more than ever before civil society has to think and act globally too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Government the integrated strategies we have for key countries are a classic example of smart-power thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are linking the work of DfID, the FCO, the MOD and our intelligence and security agencies with other organs of state who deal with issues such as energy and exports to produce a framework of mutually supporting action in each country and each region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about drawing together all the instruments of national power, so that the sum of the British effort is much bigger than its component parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we can all agree that Tom Croft scything through the French line, provoking a stern look on the face of the French President, was a pretty powerful strike for English esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence engagement is an absolutely critical part of these strategies because Defence can leverage disproportionate influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skill, professionalism and reputation of our military, the quality of British equipment, and the links we have through NATO - makes us a partner of choice for many countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have myself visited 17 countries in all quarters of the globe since taking on the role of Minister for International Security Strategy - building defence ties, promoting exports and spreading the message that Britain is back and interested in strong bi-lateral relations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the 18 months since the publication of the SDSR, we have signed three Defence Treaties and 33 Memoranda of Understanding, including with NATO members like France and Turkey, and emerging powers such as Brazil and India. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other soft power Defence tools, such as training, visits, Defence attaches, and technology sharing contribute to the generation of significant influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a huge supporter of the work of our Defence attaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no substitute for having someone on the ground who knows the people and knows the politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is very important that he or she must be equipped with the language skills necessary to engage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally important is a network of people who know Britain - who perhaps studied at Sandhurst, Cranwell or Dartmouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these places, and others such as Shrivenham and here at RCDS, we have strategic assets whose value to the UK extends far beyond the education they provide for our own Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application of soft power to build good relations is complementary to the application of hard power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot operate mine counter-measures vessels in the Gulf without a port to base them in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t fly a military aircraft over another country’s territory without seeking its permission or ‘diplomatic clearance’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t maintain troops on operations in Afghanistan without ground lines of communications through neighbouring countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why Defence Diplomacy isn’t just an add on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It forms one of the 7 Military Tasks of the Armed Forces - the key activities which the Government asks our Armed Forces to fulfil and plan for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modest investment in Defence Diplomacy provides disproportionate advantage for the country as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at a time when money is tight, being focussed and targeted is a must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specific UK Defence Engagement Strategy, complementary to cross-government efforts, is in the final stages of preparation and will guide our future efforts and resource commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion, ladies and gentlemen, let me leave you with this thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is made abundantly clear to me, time and again, by our allies, by our partners and potential friends, that the might of our military forces matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can talk as much as we want, but the power of our military means we are listened too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Defence and Security Review sets out the vision of formidable, flexible and adaptable Armed Forces; equipped with some of the best and most advanced technology in the world; and able to project significant power to almost any part of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuing ability of UK forces to apply that formidable hard power if required - within international law - and alongside allies wherever possible - makes Defence assets ideally suited to the application of smart power in support of expeditionary diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, Defence is as much about preventing wars as it is about winning them - that surely is the message of the Cold War and, indeed, our ultimate hard power weapon, the nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a world in which we will need to rely on these assts more, not less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not advocating a return to the gunboat diplomacy of the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think we all need to recognise that the world we inhabit has much more of a 19th century feeling to it - competitive, multi-polar, and in a state of flux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new era, Britain remains a force to be reckoned with -  supported by the 4th largest Defence Budget in the world and possessing a history and knowledge bank to which others cannot hold a candle and which also commands respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can, and will, use all our unique assets, welded together as smart power, to ensure that our citizens are secure and prosperous in this new era, and we continue to play an influential role on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18752</id>
    <published>2012-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:07:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-01-23-european-defence-and-security-2012"/>
    <title>2012/01/23 - European Defence and Security 2012</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at Chatham House, London on Monday 23 January 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Caroline [Wyatt, BBC] for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence and Security in Europe is at a critical juncture.  As relative economic power moves South and East we are beginning to see the geopolitical impact.  As President Obama indicated in his speech at the Pentagon on 5 January, the Pacific region will consume a great deal more of the attention of the United States.  European countries will have to take more responsibility for collective security whether the challenges are within Europe’s borders, on the periphery, or at a distance.  Furthermore, the fiscal position of many countries in the North Atlantic region is driving a reduction in public spending, including in Defence budgets.  It means European countries have to do more with less.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is not all doom and gloom.  Whilst there are weaknesses, we should not be blind to our strengths.  Our greatest strength is the shared security agenda and shared values embodied in NATO - the cornerstone of our collective security, made up of inviolable sovereign nations.  Another great strength is the range and depth of high technology residing in European Defence companies.  Our greatest weakness, however, is that - even in NATO - European countries are falling short of the capability, commitment, and resources which the maintenance of our collective security surely requires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet I see this as an opportunity.  If European countries can rise to the challenge of deploying meaningful capability, we shall have no stronger ally than America.  To aid us, those institutions and arrangements which are proven and strengthen Europe’s Defence and Security should receive our full support to make them work even better.  But those which merely duplicate or distract are a dead weight on Europe, draining our increasingly scarce resources while the US looks on increasingly concerned.  These themes will dominate your discussions over the next two days -as well as NATO’s Chicago summit in May - and I’d like to set the scene this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strategic-shift"&gt;Strategic Shift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there was ever any doubt that we live in a volatile world, this was surely laid to rest in the last twelve months.  Bin Laden and Gaddafi were removed; we had the earthquake and tsunami in Japan, and financial crisis in Europe; we saw long-surviving regimes across North Africa swept away, challenging long-held strategic calculations in Western capitals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this year bring?  What will be the consequences of the political unrest in Syria; dynastic succession in North Korea; an assertive and nuclear determined Iran?  How will newly developed economies assert themselves?  How will mature economies respond? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the United States is being forced to re-think its posture and prioritise like the rest of us.  Its Defence budget will be cut by at least 500 billion dollars…  Its Armed Forces will be leaner, though (unlike many European countries) fully deployable.  And it has chosen to reflect the growing importance of the Asia-Pacific region in its strategic posture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, US and European vital interests regularly coincide outside the North Atlantic area.  This includes the Pacific region where it is in all our interests that the emerging powers become responsible members of the international community and help provide stability to the global system.  But this should not mean that the historic trans-Atlantic alliance is no longer of vital interest to both the US and the rest of NATO - far from it.  Nor does the importance of the Pacific region in the coming decades lessen the requirement to co-operate elsewhere.  Syria, Iran, and Afghanistan are not to be found in the Pacific. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nato"&gt;NATO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this should compel us to strengthen North Atlantic bonds -in particular, the European strand - rather than weaken them.  For the British Government, this means NATO above all else when it comes to Defence and Security.  NATO is the best vehicle to advance our shared security agenda - it is established, proven, and based on shared values.  It remains the cornerstone of North American security as well as Europe’s:  NATO borders the Pacific as well as the Atlantic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it remains the organisation which many other countries look to.  When the United Nations Security Council passed Resolution 1973 on Libya, who did they think would implement it?  When sustained multi-lateral action was required, NATO had the only realistic co-ordinating structure prepared for joint and combined operations.  Most importantly, NATO remains a community of Allies with values - willing to back principles with power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Libya showed that the Alliance as a whole, and the contribution of some of the Allies, fell short of what NATO’s Strategic Concept demands.  Let us be very clear.  Despite the limited nature of the campaign, the nations of Europe could not have undertaken the operations over Libya without the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unsurprising therefore that the United States is asking whether it’s sustainable for the US to subsidise the Defence of those who could invest more but choose not to.  Why can NATO only generate a fraction of the capability nominally available to it? And it has reaffirmed wider concerns that a two- or multi-tier alliance is starting to emerge with some allies less willing to participate in operations than others.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of these issues - finance, capability, and political will -  demand a proper response from Europe, using all the tools at our disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="finance"&gt;Finance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, finance.  As the Soviets found to their cost, the lesson from history is that you cannot be secure if you’re broke.  In Britain, we see debt as a strategic issue.  It’s also undeniable that European defence spending has fallen by 24 billion euros in the last three years.  This is set to get worse.  We have to prove to a sceptical electorate that the threats to our security are genuine and that we’re making every pound count.  In Britain, we’ve already made difficult decisions to bring our fiscal position -  including the Defence programme - under control.  Others will have to follow suit.  So in such challenging times, we need to make the case for Defence spending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in these austere times, NATO’s 2% of GDP target for Defence spending should be achievable.  As the former US Defence Secretary, Robert Gates, said just before he retired, “If current trends in the decline of European capabilities are not halted and reversed, future US political leaders - those for whom the Cold War was not the formative experience that it was for me - may not consider the return on America’s investment in NATO worth the cost.”  So it is frankly depressing that 25 out of 28 currently fail to meet the 2% target, despite reaffirming their commitment to it only last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As politicians, we are acutely aware of the need to carry public opinion with us.  Spending priorities, in many respects, reflect the politicians’ perceived assessment of public opinion.  Those of us who understand the volatility of the modern world, and the dramatic shifting of the tectonic plates, do have a duty to ensure that those we represent understand the gravity of the situation so that they are in a position to re-prioritise.  All the investment in our schools and hospitals - or indeed welfare - could be set at naught if we fail to provide adequate defence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capability"&gt;Capability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, what we spend individually is only part of the story.  As resources are squeezed, we need to spend more smartly and with a much clearer view on the collective capabilities the Alliance requires.  Making cuts in capability on the assumption that someone else will take the strain is not a viable long-term strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simply have to find ways of re-balancing who generates and pays for capability, as well as who demands it.  In Libya, the shortage of ISR capability could only be met by the US, and only 12 of 43 air-to-air refuelling aircraft came from other Alliance members.  The shortage of strategic lift capability is a real constraint on the deployability of EU battlegroups.  NATO’s Smart Defence and the EU’s Pooling and Sharing initiatives go to the heart of this issue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that capability has to be additional and deployable without breaking the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I welcome NATO’s continuing efforts to remove or disinvest in non-essential capabilities and avoid duplication in national inventories.  It should help to reduce waste and prevent an uncoordinated rush to an as yet undefined bottom line. NATO must also highlight the worrying capability gaps across Europe which are being created as a result of budget reductions in almost every country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this work fails to grab political attention because it is seen as being too “in the weeds”.  We need to raise it up and give it a real political push.  So we need to develop a far more clear-sighted focus on what we really need in terms of our core military capabilities to maintain our collective security.  And set that against an even more objective and sophisticated assessment of how good we really are now.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="political-will"&gt;Political Will&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third issue facing European nations is the political will to commit force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, NATO has demonstrated considerable flexibility by incorporating countries from as far afield as South Korea, Georgia, and Tonga.  While in Libya, NATO’s swift and impressive agility in incorporating Arab states and other non-NATO countries such as Sweden was pretty remarkable.  We should capitalise on this experience by making it even easier for non-NATO nations to contribute to NATO-led operations - to fight as well as facilitate - often without the caveats which some Alliance members insist on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with 10 NATO allies choosing to opt out of Libya and only six participating in air strikes, it reminds us that NATO is an alliance of sovereign states.  Alliance solidarity - in respect of the Article V commitment - must remain sacrosanct.  Outside Article V, I entirely accept the right of individual sovereign nations not to act if they believe their national interests are not served by doing so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if NATO is going to remain relevant in the 21st century, is consensus at 28 essential when like-minded Allies wish to operate together within the framework of NATO to implement the will of the wider international community?  Non-NATO nations can invoke the ‘Berlin-plus’ arrangements to use NATO’s SHAPE HQ and assets on EU operations.  Yet when some NATO Allies don’t want to participate in certain operations, those who want to use elements of the NATO Command Structure (which they pay for and man) are not allowed to do so.  Should we consider a ‘Berlin-minus’ arrangement where the few can use Alliance assets on behalf of the many?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-defence-and-security-arrangements"&gt;Other Defence and Security Arrangements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve focused on NATO this morning, as I firmly believe in its enduring role as the bedrock of European Defence and Security.  But that doesn’t mean we should ignore the other components of multi-layered Defence.  We should encourage bi-lateral partnerships and regional groupings to flourish, not least where doing so could add value to the capabilities of the Alliance as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the newly-formed Northern Group of nations, which includes the Baltic and Nordic countries, Germany, Poland, and the Netherlands - as well as Britain - is part of this process for us.  So is the UK-France Treaty, which commits us to working together, and we would encourage others to do the same. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we are to meet the challenges of a volatile world, we need the full array of economic, developmental, and security levers at our disposal. This means a deployable and interoperable military capability married to a Comprehensive Approach which is designed to encapsulate the civil and military engagement which I have just mentioned.  Here the EU’s Common Security and Defence Policy - CSDP - can complement NATO through its unique set of stabilisation tools, and in promoting further capability development.  This allows it to play a useful role in crisis management.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But talking up the EU as an alternative route and adding additional new structures does not address diminishing Defence budgets.  And there is absolutely no point attempting to duplicate structures which already exist or capabilities we already have.  With two million men under arms in Europe -  more manpower is not the issue.  What Europe needs is manpower and capability it can deploy.  Focusing on process and institution building while struggling to find a medic to support the European Training Mission for Somalia does not cast EU priorities in a positive light - to put it mildly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Defence Agency has a role in driving forward the EU pooling and sharing initiatives which I endorsed at the Steering Board on 30 November.  I pay tribute to Claude-France Arnould’s efforts in these areas - in particular, the EDA Helicopter Training Programme to which Britain has signed up.  I know that, under her leadership, the EDA will concentrate on practical programmes such as this.  These are good examples of collaboration within a small multi-lateral agreement to deliver capability with real operational benefit.  But co-operation with NATO, not competition, should be the watchword on every European’s lips. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, this is indeed an important moment for European Defence and Security.  European countries need to bring more to the table if NATO is going to remain relevant in what many are calling the “Pacific Century”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Gates was clear about this when he said, “In the past, I’ve worried openly about NATO turning into a two-tiered alliance: between members who specialise in ‘soft’ humanitarian, development, peacekeeping, and talking tasks, and those conducting the ‘hard’ combat missions.  Between those willing and able to pay the price and bear the burdens of alliance commitments, and those who enjoy the benefits of NATO membership - be they security guarantees or headquarters billets - but don’t want to share the risks and costs.  This is no longer a hypothetical worry.  We are there today.  And it is unacceptable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know more money is not going to be the answer.  The challenge is to maximise the capability we can squeeze out of the resources we have.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must ensure that NATO’s Smart Defence and EU pooling and sharing initiatives are mutually reinforcing.   As our new Defence Secretary, Philip Hammond, has said, “We must prioritise ruthlessly; specialise aggressively; and collaborate unsentimentally.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States will be watching us closely.  So too will our adversaries.  The Chicago Summit provides the perfect opportunity to show them all that - when it comes to Defence and Security - Europe remains committed, capable, and solvent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18736</id>
    <published>2011-10-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:45:30+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-10-19-heli-power-conference-exhibition"/>
    <title>2011/10/19 - Heli-Power Conference &amp; Exhibition</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at FIVE, Farnborough Airport, Hampshire on Wednesday 19 October 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kevin [Jones, Director Air &amp;amp; ISTAR, ADS] for that introduction.  May I also thank ADS more widely and the Shephard Group for organising this impressive conference and exhibition.  It’s appropriate that we’re here in Farnborough - not just because it happens to be my constituency(!) - but also because it’s the birthplace of British aviation and the host to Europe’s largest aviation trade show.  In addition, we meet opposite the headquarters of AgustaWestland International located on the other side of the runway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been said that in some ways the helicopter is the ultimate in aviation.  Back in 1908, Thomas Edison was asked for his opinion on the Wright brothers’ aeroplane.  The electrical wizard pooh-poohed the Wrights’ achievement.  “No aeroplane would be good”, he said, “until it could go straight up and down.”    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite holding a pilot’s licence since 1965, I would have disagreed with Edison until recently - I’ve always felt that a propeller should be in front of you, not on the roof!  Yet about two years ago, Eurocopter introduced me to the art of rotary and earlier this year I was allowed to fly the Merlin from HMS BULWARK to Yeovilton. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am something of a convert to the rotary world.  And it’s with this genuine appreciation that I want to talk about the major role which Rotary Power has in current operations and in our future plans for Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Power - of which Rotary is an important component - remains critical to the Defence of Britain and the safety of our people.  Yet there is a severe lack of understanding in some quarters about the critical nature and complexity of Air Power and the contribution which Rotary makes.  It is the ultimate in versatility.  I hope that the recent operation in Libya, which was overwhelmingly an air operation with a maritime component, will have driven home the message.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge of operating helicopters in different environments is extremely complex, and requires exacting standards and realistic training.  And although a no-fly zone may trip lightly off the tongue, an enormous range of tri-Service assets is required to deliver that effect across the battlespace, not least 42 air-to-air refuelling tankers off Libya.  There, Army Air Corps Apache helicopters - operating from the deck of HMS OCEAN - have enhanced their already superb operational reputation by winning their first littoral spurs, and in the process achieved the milestone of 100,000 flying hours since entering service.  It’s a reputation which has clearly drawn Prince Harry’s gaze. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, the first ever operational deployment of Lynx Mark 9a followed the Apaches in building a fierce reputation for tackling insurgents on the ground, generating real fear in the hearts and minds of the enemy.  Royal Navy and RAF Merlin helicopters - celebrating 10 years on the front-line - are heavily committed around the world, at sea and from the sea, as well as on land operations.  And last year, the RAF’s CH-47 Chinooks transported almost 100,000 people plus their kit and supplies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, our Chinook-borne Medical Emergency Response Teams (MERT for short) - operating out of Camp Bastion - have developed an awesome reputation in a league of their own.  On the CO’s office wall is a map with Bastion in the middle surrounded by concentric circles.  Each circle shows the distance a MERT can cover in a set time to reach a casualty.  The first boundary is ten minutes - five minutes out, and five back again.  And every minute matters - the ‘platinum 10 minutes’ after injury when most battlefield deaths occur rather than the ‘golden hour’ of earlier campaigns.  Without helicopters, this life-saving level of response couldn’t be delivered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at home, almost 100 people every month have good cause to be thankful for the skill and bravery of our Search and Rescue crew - not least the commitment of the Duke of Cambridge - and for the Sea Kings they fly.  This has particular resonance today as the Cambridge Military Hospital, named after his Royal Highness’s forebear, lies less than a mile from here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all of these examples show is that delivering Rotary Power is truly a Joint affair. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, the catastrophic state of the public finances we inherited from Gordon Brown’s disastrous administration has forced us to review all major equipment and support contracts to ensure that the future programme is coherent with future Defence needs, and, crucially, is affordable.  Although the previous government undoubtedly delivered some fine UOR kit, it has been rightly lambasted for failing to ensure the core equipment budget was coherent and affordable.  We’re trying to rectify that mistake by conducting a Defence Rotary Wing Capability Study - known colloquially as ‘DERRICK’ - to ensure that we have the right structures and forces in place to deliver the plans outlined in the SDSR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t pre-empt the findings, but I believe there are reasons to be cautiously optimistic.  We are committed to increasing the planned MoD equipment budget by over £3 billion - or 1% a year in real terms - after 2015.  And the SDSR clearly laid out plans for a helicopter fleet based on four core platforms from 2025 -Apache, Merlin, Wildcat, and Chinook.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased we were able to announce a £1 billion contract for 14 Chinooks in August because our reforms have given us confidence that the money to pay for them will actually be there.  It means we can sign contracts which will deliver genuine capability, genuine value for money, and genuine economic benefits to the British economy.  So I’m confident that the plans for our future rotary wing mix will bring 21st century capability to our Armed Forces - in the right numbers, with the right support, and at prices we can genuinely afford. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking at how we buy and support equipment as well as what we buy.  In particular, we hope that our White Paper will offer the greater clarity and predictability which industry seeks.  Again, I can’t pre-empt the White Paper, but I think most of you understand the general thrust of our intentions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use the market where we possibly can while protecting our national security and sovereignty requirements (although we expect these to be limited).  Only to use the Defence budget for necessary and affordable Defence capability.  To provide strong support for technology investment, SMEs, and exports while creating the right conditions for growth.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course we’re looking to boost economic growth and stimulate innovation in the wider economy.   That’s why BIS announced £32 million of government investment in helicopter production, research, and development - which, among other things, will help AgustaWestland to introduce the civil AW169 aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, we will define our needs, be consistent in our application of policy, and transparent in how our business is done.  I’m certain that most of you in this room will have no argument with that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let me say a few words about exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to sustain UK Defence and Security jobs in the long-term is to widen the customer base through enhanced Defence exports.  We’re providing unprecedented levels of Ministerial support across government for some excellent rotary wing opportunities - particularly the AW101 and Super Lynx, while interest in Wildcat is beginning to develop.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re examining other ways to support exports.  For instance, we are working hard to accommodate the likely interest from customer nations in UK flying training.  But we look to you in industry as well to offer some innovative arrangements which can enhance our ability to support exports in this critical area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, Rotary Power is a critical component of Air Power.  It ensures freedom of movement, supports logistic sustainment, and provides essential close combat support to front line troops, together with a highly responsive medical evacuation capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most recent operational honours list for Afghanistan, I was struck that every single award in the air environment was made to rotary wing aircrew.  Indeed, the first DFC ever awarded to a woman went to Flight Lieutenant Michelle Goodman for flying her Merlin into Basra under intense fire to rescue a seriously wounded casualty.  This is not to doubt the bravery of other personnel in the air or the support all airmen receive on the ground - not least from you in industry.  But it does shine a welcome light on the magnificent effort which our helicopter crews are putting in - day in day out - in the face of a determined and co-ordinated enemy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their role in military operations - now and in the future - is quite simply indispensible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18733</id>
    <published>2011-10-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:36:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-10-13-hms-anson-keel-laying-ceremony"/>
    <title>2011/10/13 - HMS ANSON Keel Laying Ceremony</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at Barrow-in-Furness, Cumbria on Thursday 13 October 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, it is a great pleasure to be here today to lay the keel of the fifth Astute Class submarine - ANSON. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submarine is the seventh British warship and the first submarine to bear this title, and is being named after the Admiral of the Fleet George Anson, who was one of our greatest First Lords of the Admiralty and noted for his circumnavigation of the globe, as well as his role overseeing the Royal Navy during the Seven Years War.  During Anson’s time in the Admiralty, his reforms reached into every aspect of the Navy, from shipbuilding and technological developments, to training and discipline, and command and control.  His work transformed our naval power into a global asset, and it laid the foundations for the naval victories of his era and the generation that followed.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that we lay the keel for Boat 5 of our new attack submarine flotilla as we ourselves continue through a planned course of Defence Reforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last October, we confirmed our commitment to build a class of seven Astute Submarines.  ANSON will now join her sister boats, AMBUSH, ARTFUL and AUDACIOUS in construction here at Barrow.  Indeed, behind me you can see the great progress being made with ARTFUL and AUDACIOUS as they are welded together, fitted out and tested, and in essence ‘brought to life’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, many of you here today will recall the rather wet and blustery November day in 2009 when the first of class, HMS ASTUTE, sailed from Barrow to begin a programme of extensive and rigorous sea trials and training, which are demonstrating the boat’s capability.  I am pleased to report that ASTUTE is on track to begin her operational service around the end of 2012.  I was also delighted to learn that, the second of the Astute Class, AMBUSH, has successfully completed her first dive in the shipyard’s basin.  This is a critical milestone ahead of the boat’s planned exit from Barrow early next year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are clear that the Royal Navy has a requirement for nuclear powered submarines.  Royal Navy submarines have made, and will continue to make, a vital contribution to the defence of the UK and interests overseas.  What many people do not appreciate is that they are perform a wide range of unique and essential military tasks, including global reach and endurance, and conduct unsupported operations in hostile environments whether operating close to the coast or deep in the oceans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I don’t need to tell you that the Astute Class provides a step change in anti-submarine and anti-surface warfare, protecting our Nuclear Deterrent, land attack, and intelligence gathering.  They have an improved capability for world-wide operations, much greater firepower, better communications, and crew accommodation than in-service submarines.  With advanced stealth technology, the Astute Class has been designed to be quieter than any of her predecessors and thus very hard to detect.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructing nuclear submarines is one of the most complex projects that our maritime industry - indeed any industry - undertakes.  The Royal Navy often say that the Astute Class is more sophisticated than the space shuttle and, for this reason alone, I pay tribute to the thousands of skilled people at BAE Systems Submarine Solutions and in the supply chain, as well as in the Royal Navy and the Ministry of Defence, who will be involved not just in ANSON’s construction journey but who have been and will be involved in the production of the Astute Class of submarines as a whole.  Being here today, in the very heart of the UK’s centre for excellence for submarine design and building, I can clearly see why each and every one of you are rightly proud of the contribution you are making in building the most powerful and advanced attack submarines ever delivered to the Royal Navy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Government has provided assurances for the Astute Programme and also confirmed the long-term future of the Submarine Programme with a commitment to Continuous At Sea Deterrence and the Successor SSBN Programme.  However, given the challenges faced in balancing the Defence budget, such a commitment is predicated on the delivery of significant future efficiencies - in fact £900 million worth of efficiencies over the next 10 years.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work strand is known as the Submarine Enterprise Performance Programme (or SEPP), and we are engaged with the British submarine industry to improve efficiency and optimise to expected demand its capacity to build and support submarines &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since last year, the Ministry of Defence has been working collaboratively with BAE Systems Submarine Solutions, Babcock Marine, and Rolls Royce to transform the way the submarine programme is delivered and managed.  We want a Submarine Enterprise that is efficient and effective, and that offers sustainability in terms of skills, facilities and infrastructure.  I believe that we can deliver the SEPP objective of: “Performance Up, Cost Out, and Sustainability In” by developing a value for money submarine enterprise - built on long-term commercial arrangements - that recognises the contribution of each of the key industrial participants and provides the necessary programme stability for benefits of long-term partnering to be realised.  Through SEPP, the Ministry of Defence has established new collaborative ways of working in which joint MOD-Industry project teams have been pooling skills and expertise to ensure that the submarine programme is managed effectively; this unprecedented level of collaboration can only be good for all of us committed to the delivery of these fine boats.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEPP is the key to transformation in the Submarine Enterprise and I have every confidence in the joint team to deliver what we expect.  As you heard John Hudson say a few minutes ago, BAE Systems Submarine Solutions believe they will deliver ANSON in twenty percent less time than ASTUTE.  With SEPP at the helm of the Astute Submarine Programme - and indeed the Defence Submarine Programme as a whole - this is a transformation promise of which Admiral Anson himself would be proud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, let me say again how pleased I am to be here today.  Together we are witnessing the next step in this important programme that will deliver Defence capability and help ensure security for us all for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18728</id>
    <published>2011-09-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:58:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-09-12-nato-allied-command-transformation-act-industry-day"/>
    <title>2011/09/12 - NATO Allied Command Transformation (ACT) Industry Day</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at the Grosvenor House Hotel, London on Monday 
12 September 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, distinguished guests, partners, on behalf of Her Majesty’s Government, it’s a real pleasure to welcome you all to NATO’s Allied Command Transformation Industry Day here in London. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d particularly like to welcome General Abrial [Supreme Allied Commander Transformation] and thank him for his kind introduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let me add my welcome to the NATO Secretary General, Anders Fogh Rasmussen.  We are grateful for your strong leadership in Afghanistan and Libya, and for working hard to make NATO’s Strategic Concept a reality.  We are also hugely supportive of your efforts working with Baroness Ashton and Claude France-Arnauld to reduce the amount of duplication between NATO and the EU, as we must.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let me welcome Admiral Di Paola, Chairman of the NATO Military Committee.  Admiral, you’ve said on many occasions that NATO is all about defending the shared values of friends, and preserving the vital link between North America and Europe.  I could not agree more, and today’s Trans-Atlantic audience is testament to that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, we live in a volatile world where the pace of change is staggering.  Some risks appear timeless: conflict born of competition between states, or of out and out aggression, has not been abolished.  Nuclear proliferation continues to be a concern.  The value of NATO as the ultimate guarantor of territorial defence remains undiminished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this new world requires us to continue to think and adapt to new threats and new pressures.  A world in which competition for natural resources will increase.  A world in which cyberspace requires us to think differently about how we defend ourselves.  A world in which no nation can hope to meet all of its national security concerns acting on its own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would have thought, as they were eating their Christmas turkey that within months Bin Laden would’ve been killed and Mladi? put on a trial, or a mass uprising across North Africa and elsewhere? And Libya is proof, if ever it were needed, that the pursuit of our national and collective security cannot be confined to the Euro-Atlantic area.  All this as the international community continues to support the Afghan government, while bringing the transition of security responsibility to the Afghans ever closer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This era has been called the ‘Age of Uncertainty’, with the relative certainties of the Cold War far behind us.  Already, it’s 20 years since the abortive coup in Moscow against President Gorbachev which would ultimately pave the way for the collapse of the USSR - a totemic moment.  At the time, Gorbachev was under pressure from his hardliners to be more conservative and aggressive militarily.  And he was under pressure economically as the weight of military spending eventually made the Soviet economy buckle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the current Prime Minister arrives in Mosocw it is perhaps appropriate to recount the British Prime Minister at the time, Sir John Major, who recalled Gorbachev wryly recounting a joke.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There was a food shortage in Moscow and people were queuing for bread. They were queuing for a long time and they were getting very irritated.  One man turned in the queue to his neighbour and said, ‘I’m fed up with this, I blame Gorbachev, I’m going to kill Gorbachev,’ and off he went.  He came back two days later and the people still queuing said, ‘Did you kill Gorbachev?’  ‘No,’ he replied ‘The queue was just too long’.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good story, but it also underscores a message which should resonate loud and clear at this conference today.  A weak economy, as the Soviets discovered, is itself a threat to national security liability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That truism has not been lost on the US Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Admiral Mullen who said recently that, “Growing debt remains the single biggest threat to our national security.”  That’s why here in Britain, as elsewhere, Defence is having to play its part in tackling our national deficit. The US looks like following suit.  Some painful yet essential decisions have been taken, and more may follow. At the same time, my colleague, Liam Fox, and I, are both hawks on fiscal rectitude and hawks on strong national defence.  It’s a painful position to be in, but we are committed to strength in both.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also face up to some uncomfortable truths about our security architectures, not least the future of our most potent and cherished military alliance - NATO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it has for over 60 years, NATO continues to be the bedrock of our security.  20 years have passed since the original defining mission of NATO - defence against the Warsaw Pact - came to an end.  But NATO has defied the sceptics who questioned, “Whither NATO?” at the end of the Cold War.  It’s perhaps best illustrated by the remarkable transformation NATO has undergone since that other totemic moment of our times - 9/11 -whose 10th anniversary, we sombrely marked yesterday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of 9/11, NATO invoked Article V for the first time in its history.  It embarked on its first truly out-of area mission in Afghanistan.  In Libya, NATO has again proved that it is has adapted beyond all recognition from its Cold War stance.  It was to NATO that the UN turned to implement Resolution 1973.  It was a NATO-commanded operation which saved Benghazi from a brutal attack by Gaddafi’s forces. And NATO has been sufficiently agile to accommodate two Arab states and a neutral one, Sweden, in support of Libyan operations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an instrument of policy and security, NATO has proved its worth once more.  But with 10 Alliance members choosing to opt out of Libya, it reminds us that all is not well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why just before he retired in June, the former US Defence Secretary, Bob Gates, gave a forensic and discomforting analysis of the challenges facing the Alliance.  He highlighted three areas where NATO must transform: finance, capability, and political will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Soviet threat was at its height, the US spent roughly the same on defence as the rest of the Alliance combined. Now, the US contribution heavily outweighs the rest. Furthermore, Secretary Gates was clear that the gaze of Congress is increasingly fixed on the emerging powers in Asia.  And when the US, like many of us, faces the serious pressure of balancing budgets, it can no longer justify producing security for those who merely consume it.  In 2001 US indebtedness to China stood at $78 billion; today, it is more than $1,100 billion.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just about money.  It’s about having meaningful capability, and the will to deploy it.  For example, air-to-air refuelling for Libya is overwhelmingly provided by the United States - only 12 of 43 aircraft come from other Alliance members. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless NATO members address the issues of finance, capability, and the political will to commit to missions of collective security we all agreed in the Strategic Concept, I am afraid that I agree with Bob Gates that a ‘dim and dismal future’ may fall upon it.  Rectifying these deficiencies in the Alliance is within our means.  The question is, as I’ve said before, will NATO cross its Rubicon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO rose to the challenge of assuming relevance in the aftermath of the fall of the Berlin Wall, and I believe it can rise to this challenge again because it must. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference is an important part of that process, because we simply have to find ways of sharing the burden of collective Defence more equitably.  We need innovative approaches to developing affordable capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where General Abrial’s organisation and all of you in industry have such a vital role to play. I’m delighted that so many of you could come from near and far, and I hope you will visit DSEi at the Docklands this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, this will mean allocating more, as we have done in Britain with an additional £650 million to strengthen our understanding, our resilience, and our defences in cyber space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, this will mean spending differently.  For example, some European countries have punched well above their weight by focusing on deployability or on assets which are of greatest utility to the Alliance as well as their national defence.  At the risk of singling out any one programme, the acquisition by the NATO Airlift Management Agency of Boeing’s C-17 aircraft is an excellent example of multinational pooling and sharing, with nations co-operating to deliver capability which they couldn’t individually afford.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, quite frankly, this will mean spending less on areas as we configure forces fit for the 21st century.  The European Defence Agency should also have a role to play here, but it must do so in close co-operation with NATO.  Talking up the EU as an alternative route and adding new institutional structures does not address diminishing defence budgets.  As my colleague, Liam Fox, has said, “Double hatting doesn’t increase capacity or capability. It doesn’t create one more bullet, one more gun, one more plane.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the challenge facing NATO, and therefore industry, is how to generate and develop the capabilities necessary to meet contemporary and future tasks without breaking the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coherent and co-ordinated action will be required to address ‘common’ shortfalls - for example, in areas like Counter-IED, medical support, and increasing the availability of heavy lift helicopters - as we in Britain have done recently with the purchase of 14 new Chinooks.  I welcome NATO’s continuing efforts both to remove unnecessary duplication from Allied inventories and highlight the worrying capability gaps across Europe which are being created as a result of budget reductions in almost every country, including, I accept, in the United Kingdom.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But many other questions need to be answered.  For example, how can we do more with less? How can NATO and industry collaborate to deliver the Secretary General’s ‘Smart Defence’ initiative and fill these critical capability gaps?  And how can we maximise the chances for you in industry to think outside the box?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I think General Abrial put his finger on perhaps the central issue earlier this year - interoperability.  The perfect solution is always attractive.  But as the General has said, “Sometimes the 80% solution is better because you can have it faster, because you can have it cheaper, and because you can share it [and, I would add, export it] better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, in these austere times it is tempting to defer the cost, pass on the burden, and recoil from change.  But our approach to NATO - on money, on capability, and political direction must change.  Industry has a major role to play and as the world of Defence comes to London to be part of one of the world’s largest Defence exhibitions - DSEi - my challenge to you is this: seize the opportunity to put the principles we discuss today into practical effect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And help NATO - the world’s greatest military alliance - to be the viable, powerful, and relevant force we all want, and need, it to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18724</id>
    <published>2011-07-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:23:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-07-26-1958-uk-us-mutual-defence-agreement-stocktake"/>
    <title>2011/07/26 - 1958 UK/US Mutual Defence Agreement Stocktake</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at 1 Carlton Gardens, London on Tuesday 26 July 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, Churchill once remarked about a London dinner, “It would have been splendid: if the wine had been as cold as the soup; the beef as rare as the service; the brandy as old as the fish; and the maid as willing as the duchess.”  Happily, I’m confident that tonight’s fayre will be as splendid as the company; I’m grateful to the Government Hospitality team - particularly Annette Moore, and the Government Butler David Allen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also thank Professor Mark Welland - the Chief Scientific Adviser - and his staff for organising this dinner to mark the 35th Stocktake of the 1958 Mutual Defence Agreement - surely one of the most historic and enduring Treaties between Britain and the US; indeed between any nation.  I gather you have had a very successful day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over 50 years, the MDA has ensured that our nuclear deterrence programmes remain aligned and mutually supportive.  It has allowed us to discuss and plan aspects of our national nuclear deterrence in the finest detail. That’s indicative of the depth of the relationship between the United States and Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even now, the technical challenges faced by our scientists and engineers are immense - from maintaining a nuclear stockpile beyond its originally envisaged lifespan to the certification of warhead safety, security, and performance in the absence of explosive nuclear testing.  Indeed, maintaining a cadre of suitably qualified and experienced people is itself no small challenge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my sincerer thanks you all for what you do on our behalf.  You’re part of a complex and largely invisible web of day-to-day interactions between Britons and Americans deep inside each other’s establishments, laboratories, and headquarters.  I’m delighted that Britain with its nuclear technical experts is making such a positive contribution to that relationship.  The current level and depth of collaboration is unprecedented.  Although they may not know it, when people talk of the ‘Special Relationship’ they’re talking about you.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because your unique skills are as essential as ever.  This year’s events alone remind us what a volatile world we live in.  Financial uncertainty - not least the prospect of the US defaulting on its debt next Tuesday - tumultuous unrest across North Africa and the Middle East, ongoing operations in Afghanistan and Libya, and the death of Bin Laden are a sharp riposte to those who have failed to acknowledge this fact.  My friends, we are living in unprecedented times.  So it’s right to take stock of our approach to Defence and Security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Cold War far behind us, some have argued that the deterrent effect of nuclear weapons has less relevance than ever.  Certainly, the main theme in recent headlines has been disarmament.  In Britain, this was backed in our Strategic Defence and Security Review by the reduction in our requirement for operational nuclear warheads.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while we will continue vigorously to pursue multilateral global disarmament, I think we have to look at this from a wider perspective and more profoundly.  We should remember the fundamental lessons which we applied during the Cold War, and which are equally applicable in the 21st century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of you may know, I had the privilege of serving as Margaret Thatcher’s Parliamentary Private Secretary.  Her indomitable belief in the power which economic, and thus military, strength bestows on a nation was one of her defining qualities.  She understood the importance of a rules-based international system in our armoury.  And she grasped as well as anyone that warfare is not, and never has been, solely about the art of war-fighting.  It includes having the national resilience and political determination to face down threats; accepting the risks to life and limb which that entails; and having the self-belief, patience, and will to stay the course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She brought these core beliefs to bear when the Falkland Islands were invaded.  She did so again when - along with one of America’s greatest Presidents, Ronald Reagan - the West faced down the tyranny of the Soviet Union.  And as Saddam Hussein would discover, she knew that if the international community backed down in the face of unprovoked hostility it would be a betrayal of our values and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, her faith in the power of deterrence was resolute from first to last.  Nuclear weapons can not be dis-invented and we are seeing today both vertical and horizontal proliferation.  For example, Iranian possession of nuclear weapons would accelerate proliferation elsewhere in the region as others refuse to countenance a nuclear-armed Iran.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, in an unpredictable world, Britain’s position must remain unchanged.  We are committed to the concept of a “minimum credible deterrent”, long-championed by us in opposition and now in government through the SDSR - and most eloquently by my Parliamentary colleague, Dr. Julian Lewis.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have acknowledged the different position of our coalition partners, and will review the costs, feasibility, and credibility of alternative systems and posture to a continuous at sea deterrent, based upon a ballistic missile submarine.  But our bottom line remains that Britain will continue to maintain a minimum credible nuclear deterrent, and our commitment to the 1958 MDA is as strong as ever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not mean we can rest on our laurels.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and the US must be in the vanguard of shaping an international environment which minimises the risks of diversion, and inadvertent or unauthorised use of nuclear materials.  We must - as President Obama has said - enhance the safe, secure, and effective management of the nuclear capabilities which we have at the moment.  Our co-operation in this field is, I hope, as strong as the deterrent itself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also provide better value for money where possible, not least through collaboration.  That’s why the British and French Governments have agreed to design and build a joint hydrodynamics facility at Valduc which meets both nations’ sovereign requirements.  Engagement between the P3 nations on nuclear deterrence is likely to become increasingly active.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And closer collaboration will help us to make progress on a Fissile Material Cut-Off Treaty; deliver the commitments we signed up to in last year’s NPT Action Plan; and determine the future of NATO’s nuclear defence and deterrence posture. It also applies to areas which fall under the NPT, including a focus on nuclear arms control verification research - in which the US and the UK are world-leading. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, those who drew up the 1958 MDA were far-sighted indeed.  Just as the US and the UK, working together, led the world into the nuclear age in the 1940s, the MDA can help us to lead the world towards our long-term goal of a world without nuclear weapons.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But until the threats we face are gone, Mrs. Thatcher’s equally far-sighted words still hold true: “A world without nuclear weapons would be less stable and more dangerous for all of us.”  Your help in balancing progress on disarmament with keeping our deterrent credible and safe remains a key task of our time.  Long may you continue to be able to provide the support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18722</id>
    <published>2011-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:15:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-07-15-royal-international-air-tattoo-riat-gala-dinner"/>
    <title>2011/07/15 - Royal International Air Tattoo (RIAT) Gala Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at RAF Fairford, Gloucestershire on Friday 15 July 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, distinguished guests, good evening.  I realise that many of you came here tonight expecting to hear the Secretary of State.  I apologise as you have got me instead.  You don’t get a refund, but at least I speak English.  Of course, I’m delighted that Sir Stephen [Air Chief Marshal Sir Stephen Dalton, Chief of the Air Staff] invited me.  He offered me some advice: no politics, not appropriate.  That’s a bit like asking Joanna Lumley not to talk about the Gurkhas, Jamie Oliver not to talk about school dinners, and Gordon Brown not to talk about… Gordon Brown. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did hear a good political joke this week, however, by Nick Clegg.  What’s the difference between Ed Miliband and Ryan Giggs? One’s a fading left winger who’s upset his brother. The other’s a footballer…    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, no need to talk about politics when you can talk about journalists…  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pilot, I am particularly honoured to address this, the premier social event in the aeronautical calendar, to celebrate RIAT’s 40th birthday.  The first Air Tattoo was staged at North Weald airfield in Essex with just over 100 aircraft taking part.  It was the brainchild of Tim Prince, Paul Bowen, and World War II ace, Air Marshal Sir Denis Crowley-Milling, who twice escaped from occupied France: once by Hurricane and once on foot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reputation of RIAT was assured when they managed to secure a Spit Mk9 at that first Tattoo.  It was piloted by former Red Arrows leader and legendary aerobatics display pilot, Ray Hanna, of whom Tim would later say: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I can still recall the cold sweat I felt when Ray made his first approach: he was so low the tips of his propeller seemed to be touching the ground. But Ray went on to perform fantastically in MH434 and he helped cement the Air Tattoo’s reputation for staging spectacular aerial displays.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the relentless and increasingly absurd efforts of the “elf ‘n’ safety” merchants, RIAT continued to attract practitioners and spectators of some of the finest feats of flying skill. In 1996 Her Majesty the Queen conferred the title of ‘Royal’ on the show which from 1993 had become an annual event.  It is a truly international affair and I extend my personal welcome to so many friends from India, Ukraine, Oman, Saudi Arabia, and Chile.  In tribute to its status as an international event, in 2004, Fairford was one of the few select venues chosen to mark the 100th anniversary of the historic Anglo-French Entente Cordiale.  Fellow RIAT founder, Paul Bowen, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The friendly understanding contained in this historic document has helped both nations focus on the fact that there is a lot more that unites our two countries than divides us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, Paul did not live to see the event - nor indeed our new Defence Co-Operation Treaty with France last year - but was justly proud of how RIAT had grown from its small beginnings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also owe a big thank you to our close friends in the United States Air Force for making this base available to us.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget that RIAT simply couldn’t be held without the tireless work of nearly 4,000 volunteers - from air traffic controllers to engineers; from medics to firefighters, not forgetting the Air Cadets, who this year celebrate the 70th Anniversary of their formation, nor the UASs.  They are the backbone of the Air Tattoo.  All give voluntarily of their time.  So many have told me they do it to give something back.  Tonight, we should show our appreciation for all that they do.  Whilst none of us can calculate with any certainty how many young people’s love of aviation was first sparked here at RIAT or one of the many other air shows, my guess is that they have played a key part in fostering air-mindedness, attracting our young people to careers in the RAF or civil aviation and aerospace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of industry, let me thank some of the RIAT sponsors, beginning with the very best of British - BAE SYSTEMS and Rolls-Royce - who fly the flag at the cutting edge of the global aerospace business.  But in the true spirit of the Royal International Air Tattoo, thanks are also due to our international friends Northrop Grumman whose Cyber Test Range I was pleased to open last October.  Lockheed Martin, whose C-130s are playing such a vital role on current operations.  And EADS who play a key part in Eurofighter Typhoon.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also like to mention MBDA - who are not sponsors - but whose performance in support of current operations demonstrates the flexibility of the joint working approach implemented between MoD and MBDA, and the overall importance of the relationship between the MoD and industry, and the value of having domestic sovereign capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I came here, I decided to look back to this day - 15 July - in 1940, when the Battle of Britain had just begun in earnest.  There was very little enemy activity, probably owing to bad weather, though a few raids took place nonetheless.  What really stood out for me, however, were the Air Intelligence Reports that day.  A confirmed report was received that among the German troops there was “a healthy respect for, coupled with a fear of, the RAF due to the ferocity of their fighters and the accuracy of their bombers.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those men would be proud that their successors today uphold that superb reputation.  As it was in 1940, Air Power today remains a critical component of the Defence of Britain and the safety of our people.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to rehearse all the arguments advanced at CAS’s Air Power conference this week - you can all read Liam Fox’s excellent speech on the MoD website - but there is a lack of understanding in some quarters about the critical nature and complexity of air power.  A no-fly zone may trip lightly off the tongue but an enormous range of assets is required to deliver that effect.  In Libya, coalition Air Power has stopped the forces of the Gaddafi regime from using the skies to brutalise his own people and is degrading his ability to do so from land and sea.  The RAF alone has damaged or destroyed over 500 military targets.  The state-of-the-art MBDA Brimstone missiles and Raytheon’s Enhanced Paveway bombs allow us to minimise civilian casualties and take out non-civilian targets in urban areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya is also showing that the matchless Typhoon has come of age as a multi-role aircraft, flying over 1,700 hours to date.  Tornado GR4s and Typhoon have flown well over 1,000 sorties.  Last month also saw Tornado pass the 1 million flying hours milestone underlining what a magnificent servant this aircraft has been over many years.  Here, I must thank our Italian friends for the tremendous support they have given us, particularly at NATO’s air operations centre in Poggio and its airbase at Gioia del Colle.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time air operations continue unabated in Afghanistan.  In 2010, the RAF’s Chinook helicopter fleet in Afghanistan transported almost 100,000 people plus their kit and supplies.  In May this year alone, over a million kilograms of freight was moved over the airbridge to Afghanistan.  Air Power provides real-time information crucial to commanders.  And it can make the difference in a humanitarian disaster.  Last August, DFID called on the RAF to help provide urgently-needed shelter for thousands of people driven from their homes in southern Pakistan, which had been hit hardest by severe floods.  Within days, C17 mercy flights - supplemented by a C130 Hercules - delivered desperately needed shelter, food, and medical supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at home, the RAF defends UK sovereign and NATO-monitored air space around-the-clock.  Our Typhoons scramble approximately once a month to intercept aircraft which cannot be identified by any other means, a protection largely invisible to the majority of our citizens who don’t live near RAF stations.  As an aside, I’m delighted that the Typhoon is now operational on QRA in Saudi Arabia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More visible perhaps is the fact that the RAF’s Search and Rescue helicopters are scrambled almost every day - as indeed they have for the past 70 years.  Around 100 people every month have good cause to be thankful for the skills and bravery of the SAR crews and for the Sea Kings they fly - not least the commitment of the Duke of Cambridge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the core burden of delivering Air Power on operations falls on the RAF, it is not exclusively.  So just as the RAF Regiment is made up of gunners who have a special understanding of the air environment, so the Fleet Air Arm is made up of airmen who have a special understanding of the maritime environment and the Army Air Corps is made up of airmen who have a special understanding of the land environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not just the pilots.  It’s the technicians which keep the aircraft flying; it’s the controllers who send the aircraft off and bring them down again; it’s the analysts who bring to bear their unique skill sets to analyse ISTAR data; it’s medevac crews with their heroic life-saving skills; and it’s the weapons engineers making sure the ordnance is ready. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are brilliant, committed, brave people - among the best in our Armed Forces - united by their understanding of the utility of Air Power.  As the Secretary of State said in his speech on Wednesday, “There have been times in our history when the light blue was the only thing which stood between us and defeat… The people of this United Kingdom know that the Royal Air Force will never let them down.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three Services rely on the equipment and support provided by dedicated and talented men and women who make up the aerospace industry.  The industry is important not just for our Armed Forces - and by extension our national security - but for our country as a whole.  The industry employs around 100,000 people directly in the UK and indirectly supports over 200,000 more.  These are good jobs with average salaries over 40% higher than the national average.  It drives innovation spending almost £1.8 billion annually on R&amp;amp;D.  And it is a dynamic global industry - despite the difficult financial circumstances - looking to expand partnerships around the world, sharing technology and skills.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s export figures have just been announced today and they show that the UK has maintained its position as the second largest defence exporter with sales approaching £6 billion, increasing its market share from 18% to 22% whilst security exports grew by 8% to around £2 billion.  Over the past five years, sales of Typhoon and Hawk alone have accounted for almost £7 billion of orders or around 20% of British Defence exports.  And that approximately three-quarters of all British Defence exports are expected to have derived from the air sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even in these testing times there is much to celebrate.  But these are testing times.  Budget deficits around the world are being seen as threats to national security in themselves, so tackling the UK’s £150 billion deficit we inherited last year has inevitably led to some tough decisions, few of which we had wanted to make and which more benign circumstances would have spared us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a package the Strategic Defence and Security Review has ensured that we will remain in the premier league of military powers, supported by the 4th largest defence budget in the world.  The MoD will be spending around £50 billion on equipment and support over the next four years.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for the RAF that means new Typhoons, A330 Voyager tankers, A400M Atlas transporters, JSF and UAVs. But the circumstances mean that - now more than ever - we have to make every penny count.  The long-term prosperity of British industry will depend on being competitive and market sensitive to increase export prospects while delivering better value for money to the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me offer one word of caution, as a politician.  We can not, nor should we, rely on our American friends to act as our substitutes for the things we must all do as sovereign nations.  In Europe, unless NATO members are willing to pay their premiums, the validity of their insurance policies must be in serious doubt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me end pretty much as I began. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aviator, I have to say that RIAT is just the most magnificent gathering of airmen and women - a veritable aeronautical garden party; and of proponents and exponents of Air Power. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one of the most unexpectedly astute views on Air Power I’ve come across was by Field Marshal Montgomery.  Monty said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Air Power is indivisible. If you split it up into compartments, you merely pull it to pieces and destroy its greatest asset - its flexibility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Power is, quite simply, mission critical, and I’m quite sure it will play as strong a role in the future Defence of our respective countries and our interests as it has done, so remarkably, in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for giving me the supreme honour of addressing you, this gathering of the clan, this band of aviator brothers, my friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18718</id>
    <published>2011-06-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:43:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-06-29-shaping-nato-s-reform-agenda-conference"/>
    <title>2011/06/29 - ‘Shaping NATO’s Reform Agenda’ Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for International Security Strategy at Cercle Gaulois, Brussels on Wednesday 29 June 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Giles [Merritt, SDA Director] for that kind introduction, and to you and Jaap [de Hoop Scheffer, former NATO Secretary General &amp;amp; SDA Co-President] - together with the Konrad Adenauer Stiftung - for hosting this timely event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this session is ‘Equipping NATO for different threats and new tasks’.  Recent developments around the world have once again shown the volatility of the world we live in, and the pace of change we need to manage and respond to.  In just the last six months, bin Laden has been killed; Mladi? put on trial; the leaders of Tunisia and Egypt swept away by a tide of change which is washing across the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Afghanistan and Libya are proof, if ever we needed it, that the pursuit of our national and collective security cannot be confined to the Euro-Atlantic area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is the world just a geographic entity anymore - it is networked and virtual.  Recent cyber attacks on diverse organisations like Lockheed Martin and the IMF are a foretaste of what is to come.  And some threats are still with us - no-one can be certain that state-on-state conflict has been abolished, and nuclear proliferation remains a growing threat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we have a range of different threats and new tasks before us is not in question.  Our challenge is how to tackle them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it has for over 60 years, NATO continues to be the bedrock of our security.  The 28 NATO Allies set themselves an ambitious vision of NATO’s role in the world when they agreed the new Strategic Concept last year.  But questions are being raised again about NATO’s funding, capability, and political will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hugely impressed with Bob Gates’s forensic dissection of the challenges facing the Alliance earlier this month, and I congratulate the SDA on hosting that event.  It was both a warning, and a clarion call for pressing on with NATO reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Soviet threat was at its height, there was roughly a 50:50 split in funding between the US and the rest of the Alliance - a reasonable share of risk and reward.  Now, America contributes some 75% of the funding, while Europe’s percentage has roughly halved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in times of plenty, this is a questionable imbalance.  But Secretary Gates was clear that the gaze of US lawmakers is being held ever more tightly by the increasingly capable and global Armed Forces of emerging powers in Asia.  And when the US, like many of us, faces the serious pressure of balancing budgets in a time of austerity, it can no longer justify producing security for those who merely consume it.  It was a clear warning to Europeans to take this imbalance in NATO seriously. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not just about money.  Not all members can contribute meaningful capability, and not all those who have such assets choose to do so.  Events in Libya have underscored this starkly.  &lt;br&gt;
So unless the rest of NATO strengthens its finances, its capabilities, and its political will to commit to missions of collective security we all agreed in the Strategic Concept, the ‘dim and dismal future’ which Bob Gates spoke of will be upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rectifying these deficiencies in our Alliance is well within our means. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But will NATO cross its Rubicon? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to look at all three components today - finance, capability, and political will - and their influence on internal NATO reform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know how tough the financial situation is.  In Britain, we have had to make some difficult decisions to bring balance to our Defence budget because we inherited a massive national budget deficit which, unless addressed, would itself constitute a threat to our national security.  We also believe that investment in security is insurance for future prosperity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why our recent Strategic Defence and Security Review reaffirmed that we will continue to meet the NATO 2% of GDP target throughout our current spending period.  Yet, although our allies also reaffirmed their commitment to this target as recently as March, it is very depressing that 23 out of 28 allies currently fail to meet it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is imperative that we find ways of sharing the burden of collective Defence more equitably.  In some cases this will mean spending more, which we in Britain acknowledged by allocating an additional £650m to strengthen our understanding, our resilience, and our defences in cyber space.  In some cases this will mean spending differently.  For example, some European countries have punched well above their weight by focusing on deployability or on assets which are of greatest utility to the Alliance as well as their national defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are quite clear that talking up the EU as an alternative route does not address diminishing defence budgets.  As our Defence Secretary, Liam Fox, has observed, “Double hatting doesn’t increase capacity or capability. It doesn’t create one more bullet, one more gun, one more plane.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This places even greater emphasis on spending our scarce resources wisely by targeting our most pressing capability needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to identify and reduce areas of duplication among the Allies - and NATO’s Allied Command Transformation has an important role to play here in advising Allies to help deliver the Secretary General’s Smart Defence initiative and fill critical capability gaps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anglo-French Defence Treaty is a model of how this could evolve.  It will also make us stronger partners with our NATO and EU allies.  Indeed, we hope that our example will encourage other partners to seek better value for money and improve capability through co-operation with each other.  However, such arrangements would have to be pragmatic and have clear military utility at their core - like the future Combined Joint Expeditionary Force - or they are, at best, political symbolism.  So we view our collaboration with France as a strategic imperative; as natural as it’s necessary.  Indeed, the US has long argued that Europe as a whole needs more effective, operationally viable forces.  I agree, though this has to come with improved access to US technology, and research and development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to be clear that while pooling and sharing, and collaborative working is an important tool for delivering better value for money, it is not a panacea.  And it’s no good complaining, for example, about multiple shipyards or armoured vehicle manufacturers in Europe unless you are clear about the capability you are prepared to give up or collaborate on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the question of political will.  NATO’s teeth, not its tail, have made it the most successful military alliance in history.  But NATO’s success in securing more than 60 years of peace and ending the continent’s Cold War divisions means far less to younger generations than to those of us who lived through those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media and public opposition to military intervention has increasingly tested the resolve of all European governments; in some cases they have been found wanting.  Of course, politicians must be sensitive to the views of their electors, and we must be more adept at communicating the relevance of threats to the lives of our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot duck our responsibilities: Defence of the realm is the first duty of the British government and, I would trust, all Allied Governments.  We must articulate the cost of inaction: threats don’t disappear because we choose not to confront them.  On the contrary, history tells us that they grow when this happens.  So we believe that countries should look forwards and outwards - not backwards or inwards.  And while they should understand their history, they should not be governed by it.  Ultimately, as a military alliance, if we agree on the need for force we must be willing to deploy force.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO’s Strategic Concept offers the blueprint for the future, and Liam Fox has set out three important reasons why full and speedy implementation is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - it reaffirms the centrality of Article 5 and the pledge to defend one another, whether large or small, old or new allies - it is the very foundation upon which the Alliance and Europe’s security is built. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also recognises - and this has been reinforced by Afghanistan and Libya, and is consistent with our own SDSR - that European security today means much more than sitting at home, hoping to be able to repel attacks, however unexpected and from whatever quarter.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the emphasis on deployability for both Article 5 and non-Article 5 activities is central to the effectiveness of NATO in preserving our security in the future.  That is why, for example, we place a priority on Force Generation and the delivery of deployable capability and force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - as our experience in Afghanistan has shown and the Strategic Concept acknowledges, NATO needs better capabilities in linking civilian and military effect when undertaking these kinds of missions.  That civilian capacity should predominantly come from NATO’s partners - the UN and the EU - and from the Allies themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But NATO needs to be able to develop its own plans as it works with these partners and operate alongside them, so we need to get a civilian planning capability in NATO up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would add a fourth reason - public legitimacy.  The Strategic Concept was right to address internal reform and transformation.  &lt;br&gt;
So I welcome the decision to streamline the Command Structure, and the recent agreement on where the Commands should be - in particular the Maritime Command in Northwood.  The decision, when implemented, should deliver the effective, leaner, and affordable Command Structure which the NATO Secretary General has championed.  We need to apply similar rigour to reform other parts of NATO: the Headquarters (including International and Military Staffs), and the Agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO’s End to End Review of Capability Development highlights duplication taking place across numerous areas: we need to stop these wasteful, self-serving working practices and will be looking for concrete recommendations for Defence Ministers.  Co-locating the Brussels Headquarters’ 1,600 civilian and military staff would also be a first step towards more effective ways of working.  And we believe NATO’s Committee structures need to be re-examined and, where appropriate, outsourcing of support services should be considered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, although progress has been made, it strikes us as odd that the Secretary General does not have more control over the way his own HQ is run.  For example - and Jaap, you may have some thoughts on this - the post remains extremely limited in how it can flex manpower to meet peaks and troughs in work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when difficult decisions are being made across the alliance on the affordability of military capability, we should consider carefully whether the generous terms for NATO appointments -  such as average tax-free salaries of 95,000 euros, substantial housing allowances, and paying for dependents’ education up to the age of 26 - real world requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these austere times, it is tempting to defer the cost, pass on the burden, and recoil from change.  But Europe needs to reflect on the fact that it is in large measure the US taxpayer who has provided the shield which since 1945 has enabled the continent to recover its prosperity.  It’s not simply a question of thanks.  It’s not simply a question of money.  It’s equally about deployability, and the political will to do so, which only the US and a few of the more capable and willing allies possess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me end on a positive note.  Writing in The Economist in 1996 about NATO’s future, Brian Beedham wrote that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The chief task of the new NATO will be to support western foreign policy in areas outside the Alliance’s own territory.  Its purpose will be power projection.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He excluded large parts of the world but concluded: “this still leaves to the new NATO’s zone of responsibility a huge stretch of territory -South-West Asia and much of Africa - which also happens to be the most unpredictably explosive part of today’s world…  Out of this turbulent region could come, in the next 20 or 30 years, a dozen requirements for power projection.  The Atlantic countries will need to preserve their access to the region’s oil…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Their conscience may insist that they act to stop the worst outbreaks of ethnic or dictatorial brutality. They may even, when they judge it can be done without too much difficulty, try to open the door to democracy for some of the area’s imprisoned peoples.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perceptive stuff indeed, but surely Afghanistan and Libya - and as your old friend George Robertson reminded me last night, Kosovo -  have illustrated that NATO has matched up to the challenge foreseen 15 years ago. In particular, the speed with which NATO was able to offer its proven structures and systems to implement UNSCR 1973 is testament to NATO’s ability to generate and deliver capability, although we do need to remind ourselves that Libya is not a NATO operation but a NATO commanded operation, and as Secretary Gates rightly pointed out, a mission which does not involve ground troops under fire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want the world’s greatest military alliance to remain viable and powerful, but that requires reform - right here, right now. As former winner of the Nobel Peace Prize, Rene Cassin, once remarked, “Building for the future is a very difficult thing to do; we cannot hope to complete the work in one generation; all the more reason to begin at once.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
