<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/grant-shapps</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/grant-shapps.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Grant Shapps MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14694</id>
    <published>2012-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/safety-net-against-homelessness-continues-to-2015"/>
    <title>Safety net against homelessness continues to 2015</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support secured for those facing homelessness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding to help those facing the real and frightening prospect of homelessness will continue to the end of this Parliament, Housing Minister Grant Shapps said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2208882.jpg" alt="StreetLink poster"&gt;A preview of the new StreetLink poster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils across the country are set to receive a share of £160million over the next two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister also confirmed that a new website and telephone line, where anyone anywhere looking to get help for someone sleeping on the streets can go to, is on track to be available by Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also offered a first-look at a new campaign aimed at encouraging people to seek help for rough sleepers in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="funding-support"&gt;Funding support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps announced that councils across the country would receive £160million over the next two years in Homelessness Prevention Grants - offering certainty that homelessness services will be funded to the end of this Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is on top of the £160million that has been allocated to councils over this and last year, which has been used to offer support to those facing the threat of homelessness, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing rent deposit schemes to enable homeless people to get accommodation in the private rented sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mediation services to help prevent relationship breakdown leading to homelessness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;outreach services to help get rough sleepers off the streets and into accommodation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Latest figures show that 199,000 households were last year given help to stay in their homes or find new places to live - stopping them from facing losing their home and, potentially, a life on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="streetlink-support"&gt;StreetLink support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Mr Shapps also confirmed that plans for a new website and national phone line are on track to be available by Christmas, so that anyone will be able to ring if they are looking for help for someone sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;StreetLink, to be run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway, will include a national telephone line, and website accessible via smart phone, so anyone anywhere can provide details of someone sleeping rough in their neighbourhood so they can be found and connected to local services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A series of posters will be released in December alongside these new tools, so residents, charities and councils can all work together to ensure as few people as possible face spending this Christmas on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister released the first images from a campaign due to start in the run-up to Christmas to encourage members of the public to come forward and seek help for local rough sleepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All too often, we see people sleeping rough on our streets and don’t know what to do for the best, where to turn to get them help and whether offering a handout really does offer them help out of homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;That’s why I’m delighted that this December, StreetLink will offer a solution, with members of the public able to ring a national helpline or use a website accessible by smart phone to help ensure someone sleeping rough can be found and connected to local services.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And to ensure that we shore up the strongest safety net in the world, I can today confirm £160m funding right up to the end of this Parliament, giving councils the means to continue their strong work in preventing homelessness in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A preview of what StreetLink, the new national rough sleeping campaign, will look like, can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208862.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf.2208862.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 435kb).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the £160m Homelessness Prevention Funding, which will be awarded to councils in 2013/14 and 2014/15, are published today and can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208843.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/pdf/2208843.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 89kb).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14692</id>
    <published>2012-08-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-31T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/major-clampdown-launched-on-beds-in-sheds"/>
    <title>Major clampdown launched on 'beds in sheds'</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Action to tackle suburban shanty towns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers today launched a major clampdown on rogue landlords to bring an end to suburban shanty towns that trap vulnerable people in dangerous living conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2208223.jpg" alt="Beds in sheds"&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps and Immigration Minister Damian Green outside a shed being rented out illegally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps and Immigration Minister Damian Green launched new guidance to councils making clear the wide range of powers at their disposal to shut down so-called ‘beds in sheds’ that blight entire neighbourhoods and take action against other bad practice by landlords such as overcrowding and poor maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps and Mr Green saw the evidence for themselves when they attended an early morning visit on a suspected rogue landlord’s properties, and witnessed the squalid conditions the ‘tenants’ paid hundreds of pounds a week to live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While visiting six properties, officials from Ealing Council and the UK Border Agency encountered 39 individual tenants, 22 of whom were illegal immigrants:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;of those 22 illegal immigrants encountered, &lt;strong&gt;19 were detained&lt;/strong&gt; (three were required to report to a Reporting Centre because they were a couple with a young child);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of those 22 encountered, &lt;strong&gt;14 were found in the outhouses&lt;/strong&gt; (this includes the two adults with the young child). The remainder were found in the houses;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of those 19 detainees, 16 were Indian nationals and three were Pakistani nationals;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of those 19 detainees, nine entered the country without leave, eight were overstayers, one was a failed asylum seeker and one was working in breach of his visa conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="power-to-tackle-rogue-landlords"&gt;Power to tackle rogue landlords&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new guidance highlights the range of actions councils can take to clamp down on rogue landlords once and for all. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;proactively identifying problem properties and effectively working through complaints;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking action using a full range of legal powers to stop rogue landlord activities;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with other organisations including the police and UK Border Agency to tackle linked criminal behaviour;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prosecuting landlords who persistently let illegal property;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing evidence of landlord’s earnings to magistrates to ensure they receive an appropriate level of fine for offences;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;naming and shaming prosecuted landlords by publicising successful cases;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working with the new national taskforce which has been set up between Whitehall departments, the police, the UK Border Agency and local government. The taskforce is exploring all possible options for closing down ‘beds in sheds’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of sheds and outbuildings are being rented out illegally to vulnerable migrants by ruthless landlords who charge them extortionate rents to live in cramped conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘tenants’ can often find it difficult to return home quickly with some having destroyed their passports to avoid removal often leaving them to either live in these outbuildings or face living on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s simply unacceptable that people are living in squalid, unsafe accommodation provided by landlords more interested in a quick profit rather then their basic responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The actions of these rogue landlords are helping fuel illegal working and benefit fraud and creates a shadow housing market that carries dangers to peoples health as well as community relations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I want to see all agencies from councils to the police and the UK Border Agency using the full range of powers at their disposal to work together on a national clampdown towards ridding our communities of this problem once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immigration Minister Damian Green said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Operations like this show our determination to do whatever is necessary, working alongside local authorities and police, to enforce our laws against those who are in the UK illegally.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The UK Border Agency continues to gather intelligence about those illegally in the country. Those with no right to be in the UK must leave the country. If they need help to leave the country voluntarily we will offer it but if they refuse we will enforce there removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s guidance is backed up by the recent allocation of £1.8million to councils earlier this year to tackle the issue and flush out those landlords renting out ‘beds in sheds’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=109615" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All images are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157631320683000/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dealing with rogue landlords: a guide for local authorities&lt;/em&gt; is published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/roguelandlordsguide"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/roguelandlordsguide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Magistrates’ warrants were issued ahead of the dawn raid, granting Ealing Council the legal power to enter the premises without notice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps allocated £1.8million to the nine councils in areas worst-affected by Beds in Sheds. Details can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2143332"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2143332&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The National Taskforce on Beds in Sheds was announced in April this year. Details can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2137365"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2137365&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14691</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/put-our-towns-first-and-revive-the-nations-high-streets"/>
    <title>Put our towns first and revive the nation's high streets</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Town Team partners to benefit from multi-million pound support&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPs returning to Parliament next week can put their towns first by putting their local high streets forward for a package of Government support and help make them the beating hearts of their communities once again, Local Government Minister Grant Shapps said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/2082239.jpg" alt="High Street Illustration (Dermott Flynn)"&gt;Illustration by Dermott Flynn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister urged MPs whose towns missed out in the Portas Pilot competition to apply now for their town centres to become &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/townteampartners/"&gt;Town Team partners&lt;/a&gt; and benefit from help available, including support from the Government and access to advice and support from leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also called on towns across the country to apply to be considered for the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/x-fund/"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund&lt;/a&gt;. Those town centres that show they have made the greatest improvements will win a share of the £1million prize on offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having witnessed the overwhelming response from over 400 towns to our search for Portas Pilots, I’m determined that the energy and enthusiasm they displayed is not lost, and that every area has the opportunity to breathe new life into their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It’s time to put ‘Our Towns First’. That’s why today I’m calling on MPs to apply for their towns to become Town Team partners, so that communities can put their plans into action with the backing of retail experts as well as learning the lessons from other town teams from across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And for those who make the greatest improvements to their high streets, I look forward to awarding them with a share of the £1million Future High Streets X-Fund so that they can continue their sterling work to bring their town centres back to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="no-high-street-left-behind"&gt;No high street left behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This package of support comes after an overwhelming response to the competition to find 27 Portas Pilots. With over 400 town teams submitting bids, Mr Shapps is clear that none will be left behind in the campaign to breathe new life into the nation’s high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those MPs that apply to be Town Team partners will be making a commitment for their town team to take forward key elements of their original plan for reviving their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In exchange, they will have access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management, as well as key informative events;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct mentoring and visits from a range of retail experts;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regular meetings with other Town Teams to share lessons learned, tips and ideas; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an online community to receive advice and information from retail experts; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Already Portas Pilots across the country are taking steps to bring their high streets back to life. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market Rasen’s Portas Pilot, who attracted 35 new traders to the town in July putting the ‘market’ back into Market Rasen and enticing thousands of new visitors into the town. Going forward, they are now looking to run their next BIG Market event on 1 September with the theme, ‘Say Goodbye to Summer’;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton’s Portas Pilot, who are already achieving their goal to connect local businesses to the range of events taking place in the local high street. For example, for the 25th anniversary of Stockton’s International Riverside Festival, local restaurants were offered their own gazebos, banners and leaflets to serve their food to visitors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dartford’s Portas Pilot, which has opened a community shop to be used by a range of community groups as a place to meet and socialise. The Pilot have also been generating more Sunday trading through a ‘My Sunday’ marketing campaign that promotes the towns businesses, market, parks and free parking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="future-high-street-x-fund-open-for-business"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund open for business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps also called for nominations for town centres to be considered for the £1million Future High Street X-Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prize will be shared among the high streets that show the greatest improvements. Towns will be judged by an independent expert panel, for the inventiveness of their schemes and the impacts they can evidence, such as increased footfall or turnover, or improved skills and employment levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towns will also need to explain how they plan to use their prize money to further support their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MPs representing towns whose Portas Pilots bids were unsuccessful will today receive an application form to put forward their towns to be Town Team Partners. The deadline for submitting forms is 16 September 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Town First: Future High Street X-Fund - Prospectus&lt;/em&gt; is published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/x-fundprospectus"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/x-fundprospectus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent expert panel of judges will include representatives from Alliance Boots, the Association of Town Centre Management, Civic Voice, Locality and Yellowdoor (Mary Portas’s retail and brand communication agency).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14690</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plans-for-thousands-of-homes-unlocked-by-historic-deal"/>
    <title>Plans for thousands of homes unlocked by historic deal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New agreement will get work started on thousands of new properties&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plans for thousands of new homes that have been stuck on the drawing board for a decade are to finally get the go-ahead thanks to an historic deal reached between ministers, councillors and developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal will unlock around 22,600 much-needed homes over the next 20 years - delivering as many as 60,000 jobs - and brings a brownfield site back into use. The first phase at Eastern Quarry, Ebbsfleet, in Kent will deliver 1,500 homes as part of wider plans for Kent Thameside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers Land Securities have invested over £100million in developing the site. However, plans have been delayed amid concerns over the cost and the need for further investment in transport improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, after work by Housing Minister Grant Shapps and Transport Minister Mike Penning with Kent councils and the developers, builders could be on site as early as next Summer with the first homes set to be completed by December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="historic-deal-reached"&gt;Historic deal reached&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kent County Council and Dartford and Gravesham Borough Councils worked closely with the Department for Transport and the Highways Agency to reduce costs of the transport programme and to agree how funding could be unlocked. Under the arrangements agreed, the Department for Transport and Highways Agency will begin development work on two major junction improvements and will work with Kent County Council and the Kent Thameside partners in managing the transport investment programme necessary to deliver the new developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dartford and Gravesham Borough Councils will ensure that contributions from Land Securities and other sites are provided to support the transport improvement programme, and that they and Kent County Council use a proportion of their New Homes Bonus payments to contribute to the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal reached between these three councils and Land Securities on the specific planning obligations - known as a Section 106 agreement - will enable work to start. Land Securities will contribute nearly £25million towards the Homes and Roads Programme, through to completion of 4,500 homes on the site by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps said that this illustrated the benefits of Government, local authorities and developers working together to unlock progress on stalled larger sites and signalled that he was keen to build on this approach in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s frustrating that while the need for homes in Kent and the surrounding area has continued to grow, the Kent Thameside development - offering the opportunity for tens of thousands of new homes - has been stuck on the drawing board for a whole decade.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’m delighted that we’re finally taking steps forward to get builders on site and work finally started. This historic deal offers a double benefit to the local area, a commitment to improve the road network but also to deliver over 22,600 properties over the next 20 years - with the first homes set to be completed in little over a year from now.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;After such a delay, like local residents I look forward to seeing the properties being built, the jobs being created and, in the near future, the first families moving into their new homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Mike Penning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government has been clear about the need to maintain a pipeline of future transport infrastructure improvements given their importance in delivering economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;By agreeing to carry out the necessary preparatory work for potential future junction improvements on the A2, we have been able to show our commitment and give the confidence needed by private sector developers to allow them to begin the delivery of the ambitious new housing programme in Kent Thameside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Carter, Leader of Kent County Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Getting this significant development underway and built out signals our continued intent to increase construction activity in Kent. We have real growth ambitions and this site signifies our intent to unlock the potential of the Thames Gateway. Where sites are stalled we will talk to developers about ways of releasing sites in the short term. However we will only work with those that are intent on accelerating development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Jeremy Kite, Leader of Dartford Borough Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It has been a long road but this finally seems to be our opportunity to build a great community and top quality housing for a new generation of Dartford families. Housing for sons and daughters of local people is a real responsibility and Eastern Quarry provides a great setting for young people to build their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colette O’Shea, Head of London Development, Land Securities said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are pleased that a way forward has been found to unlock the potential at Eastern Quarry and we will now sit down with our housebuilding partners and press ahead to start delivering homes and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first phase of 1,500 homes at Eastern Quarry are expected to be completed by 2020, with a further 3,000 homes expected to be completed by 2030-31. Eastern Quarry forms part of longer term plans which are expected to unlock the development of 22,600 homes and around 1million m2 of commercial development across the Kent Thameside region over the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency has already invested £13million in the supporting transport investment (the Homes and Roads Programme), and is committed to working with all parties to identify other future funding sources as work progresses on the development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kent Thameside Strategic Transport (Homes and Roads) Programme is a £116million investment in transport improvements covering both the Strategic and Local Road Network aim at enabling the planned level of development to be realised.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Roads Programme is a package of the following seven schemes:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A2 Ebbsfleet Junction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A2 Bean Junction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A226 London Road/St Clements Way Junction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dartford Town Centre Improvements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rathmore Road Link, Gravesend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A226 Thames Way Dualling, Ebbsfleet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Urban Traffic Management and Control Measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key partners involved in the development, management and delivery of the Homes and Roads Programme include:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dartford Borough Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department for Transport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gravesham Borough Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highways Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homes and Communities Agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kent County Council&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Land Securities is the UK’s largest commercial property company and a member of the FTSE 100. The company owns and manages more than 29 million sq ft of property, from shopping centres to offices. For more information see &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.landsecurities.com/"&gt;www.landsecurities.com&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14688</id>
    <published>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-28T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-3-million-to-hand-power-back-to-tenants"/>
    <title>£1.3 million to hand power back to tenants</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New programme will give social tenants voice to challenge local decisions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Housing Minister has unveiled a new fund of £1.3m to help give more power to communities over their social homes. Grant Shapps hopes the scheme will help bring the passion of the Olympic volunteers and last year’s broom armies to local communities by giving housing association and council tenants a voice to lead change in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps said the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/housing/socialhousing/tenantempowerment/"&gt;Tenant Empowerment Programme&lt;/a&gt; would offer a “springboard for success” to communities across the country who want to see their local needs reflected in the services they receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be by helping tenants learn the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords; forming tenant panels to come together to demand the best value-for-money services; or even to take control of local services themselves if they feel that they could deliver more for less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister also highlighted the benefits to landlords of getting their tenants involved, from community involvement in scrutinising new repairs contracts or tenants working together with local authorities to tackle anti-social behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="giving-tenants-the-confidence-to-invest-in-their-community"&gt;Giving tenants the confidence to invest in their community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister invited charities and benevolent societies to submit their ideas for delivering a national programme that will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encourage the creation of more tenant panels - groups of tenants who can challenge landlords, shape services and get involved in local decision making; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;help individual tenants engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new Community Cashback scheme will also be at the heart of the Tenant Empowerment Programme - allowing groups of tenants who choose to take on the management of services, such as maintenance and repairs, to reinvest any savings they make from running these services themselves into other community priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past 12 months we’ve seen the power of local people in action, from the ‘broom army’ clean-ups after the riots to the Olympic volunteers helping this country put on the greatest show on earth. I know that tenants in communities across the country have that same passion.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This £1.3m programme will be a real springboard for local success, giving tenants real power, whether they choose to take local services over completely or merely challenge their landlords to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We’re bringing communities together and giving them the knowledge, skills and confidence to build their own Big Society in their back yard. And by helping them to ensure their area’s unique needs are being met I hope they will inspire more tenants across the country to lead change in their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applications are being sought from charities, benevolent societies and philanthropic institutions, as defined by the Charities Act 2006, for grant funding to deliver a tenant empowerment programme to tenants living in social housing.
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/tenantempowermentprospectus"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/tenantempowermentprospectus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grant funding of up to £1.32m will be made available from the £8m Tenant Empowerment Programme, announced in February 2011 to deliver two separate programmes. Applicants can choose to apply for one or both programmes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This funding is intended to support activities over and above those that landlords should provide as part of their regular responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The importance of developing local solutions to tackle tenants’ problems, including an enhanced role for tenant panels, was identified in the Government’s &lt;em&gt;Review of Social Housing Regulation&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/socialhousingregulation"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/socialhousingregulation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14682</id>
    <published>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/montague-plan-offers-boost-to-private-rented-sector"/>
    <title>Montague Plan offers boost to private rented sector</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian publishes proposals to encourage greater investment in build-to-let&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures aimed at boosting professional investment in good quality, privately rented homes and to help meet the nation’s housing demand are published today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Grant Shapps welcomed the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/privaterentedhomesreview"&gt;report by Sir Adrian Montague&lt;/a&gt;, saying it offered, “a blueprint” for encouraging more institutional investment into the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of private-rented homes in this country are managed by individual landlords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Sir Adrian’s report highlights the “real potential” for investment in large-scale development of homes built specifically for private rent by professional organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report finds that a combination of recent tax changes and wider market conditions have cleared the way for this sector to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian’s report makes a series of recommendations to speed up the timescale for building the private-rented homes needed to meet existing and growing demand. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That councils use flexibilities in the planning system to plan for and enable developments of privately rented homes where they can meet local need. This could include waiving affordable housing requirements on new developments of homes specifically for private rent, or reviewing stalled sites to see whether some of the new homes planned could be made available to rent rather than sell;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That a task force be set up to encourage and support build-to-let investment from the private sector, and to develop voluntary standards that future landlords would meet and tenants could expect;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That the Government look to provide a number of targeted incentives to encourage the development of Build-to-Let business models, which could include sharing development risk in the short-term to get spades in the ground and building started;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That the Government allocate some of the redundant, formerly used public sector land and buildings being released for housebuilding to build-to-let development, and publish data on how this is done; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That the Government work with councils and the Greater London Authority to identify a number of sites where there is good demand for rental housing and make them available to developers on the grounds that a proportion of the homes built be let out to tenants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s report is the conclusion of Sir Adrian’s review, which was commissioned as part of the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/housingstrategy2011"&gt;Housing Strategy&lt;/a&gt; in November. The Government will issue a formal response later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re determined to encourage greater investment in the build-to-let market and boost the country’s Private Rented Sector, which plays an integral role in meeting the nation’s housing needs and aspirations. In the past it’s often been seen as the Cinderella of the housing market, but when over three million people rely on this sector for their home, this is clearly no longer the case.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A major part of this is to attract and encourage new players to the market, while at the same time avoiding the excessive regulation that would force up rents and reduce choice for tenants.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian Montague’s findings offer both a blueprint for achieving this goal, and for setting the standards of accommodation that people should expect. I will be considering his recommendations very carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian Montague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s clear we must encourage investment in the private rented sector, which has gone through a period of rapid growth and is now relied upon by millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My review shows that the rental housing sector offers potential investment opportunities of interest to institutional investors. But real momentum has been inhibited by constraints affecting the supply of stock, the treatment of rented housing schemes under the planning system and the need to create confidence among investors.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The recommendations in today’s report are designed to challenge this, and remove the barriers that prevent the kind of investment that our private rented sector needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian Montague’s report, &lt;em&gt;Review of the barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes&lt;/em&gt;, can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/privaterentedhomesreview"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/privaterentedhomesreview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ministers are concerned that unrealistic agreements negotiated between councils and developers at the height of the housing boom are stalling too man developments, resulting in no regeneration and no community benefits at all. Earlier this month, Communities Secretary Eric Pickles announced a fresh drive to re-examine these deals and get workers back on sites. Details can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2197690"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/news/newsroom/2197690&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent review of barriers to institutional investment in private rented homes was announced in the Government’s Housing Strategy published in November 2011. Terms of reference for the review can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/housing/pdf/2057113.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/housing/pdf/2057113.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sir Adrian Montague is non-executive chairman of 3i, Michael Page International plc, Anglian Water Group Ltd and CellMark Investments AB of Gothenburg, and a non-executive director of Skanksa AB of Stockholm.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;He was a member of the Housing Finance Group established by the Homes and Communities Agency in the wake of the credit crisis, and also chairs an advisory group reporting to Business Secretary Vince Cable on the establishment of a Green Investment Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14679</id>
    <published>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/sir-terence-conran-joins-drive-to-build-higher-quality-homes"/>
    <title>Sir Terence Conran joins drive to build higher quality homes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housebuilders challenged to prove the quality of new-build homes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star of the British design industry Sir Terence Conran is to work with the Government to help create a new competition to give communities a chance to design their own neighbourhoods, Housing Minister Grant Shapps announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes as Sir Terence and the Minister call on housebuilders to involve local people as early as possible in the design of new homes - helping to encourage communities to say yes to new housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The competition will be launched at a forthcoming summit this Autumn with communities invited to submit their designs for Sir Terence and other design industry stalwarts to judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes as Mr Shapps lays down the gauntlet to developers to tackle the mistaken belief among too many people that new-build properties are potential ‘homes from hell’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="designing-with-local-needs-in-mind"&gt;Designing with local needs in mind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the forthcoming summit, Sir Terence and Grant Shapps will urge developers to get the public involved in their design process from the very start - ensuring the homes they want and need are built in their area, meeting local demand and making them easier to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mr Shapps will argue there is another benefit to community involvement - proving to sceptics that new-build properties are well-built and of good quality design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister will say that all too often, tales of badly designed ‘homes from hell’ give new developments a bad reputation before they even get off the ground - when in fact many new build homes are at the height of modern design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polls have shown that a significant number of prospective buyers believe that new-builds are badly designed and built. And three-quarters of people would embrace more housing in their area if they knew it was better designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps will say it is unfair to tar all newly built homes with the same brush, and will call on developers to “prove the pessimists wrong” by taking more responsibility to get local communities back on side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted that Sir Terence Conran, a leading light of the design industry, is helping us launch this competition, which will harness the creativity of communities up and down the country as they consider how they want their local areas to look.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But this is part of a wider point about the need to build more homes, which can’t happen without getting local people onside and turning NIMBYs into YIMBYs (Yes in My Back Yard). To do this, residents must be involved in the design of new developments from the outset - helping to build the homes communities want and need and meeting demand from local buyers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And by doing this, housebuilders can finally tackle the belief that new-builds are potential ‘homes from hell’, proving the pessimists wrong and clearly demonstrating how well-designed and built their properties really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Terence Conran said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The design of an area has a significant and lasting impact on the quality of life of its residents - it’s therefore vital that local people have a say over how their communities look and feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I want the competition to inspire communities up and down the country to really think about the places in which they want to live, what they want to see and how they can make a difference. I look forward to launching it later this year, and seeing how creative Britain can be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is putting the framework in place for developers to engage their neighbours early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New &lt;strong&gt;local plans&lt;/strong&gt;, introduced in planning reforms, encourage people’s active involvement in neighbourhood planning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new &lt;strong&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/strong&gt; allows communities to approve local developments without the need for the normal planning process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/strong&gt; raises funds from new developments to build the public infrastructure the neighbourhood wants, like park improvements or a new health centre.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/strong&gt; lets communities see the benefits of local growth by rewarding new developments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the Home Builders Federation Customer Satisfaction Survey can be found at: [www.hbf.co.uk/fileadmin/documents/Customer_Satisfaction/Cust_Satisfaction&lt;em&gt;2012.pdf](http://www.hbf.co.uk/fileadmin/documents/Customer_Satisfaction/Cust_Satisfaction&lt;/em&gt;2012.pdf)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 2010 Public Attitudes Survey by the former National Housing And Planning Advisory Unit (NHPAU) said found that just under three out of four (73 per cent) said they would support more homes if they were well designed and in keeping with the local area. Further details can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/507390/nhpau/pdf/16127041.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/507390/nhpau/pdf/16127041.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. And the 2011 YouGov poll showed that 31 per cent of people would not consider buying a home built in the last 10 years, or would only consider it as a last resort. Of these, 60 per cent said it was because the rooms are too small, 46 per cent said they lack style, and 45 per cent were concerned about the lack of outside space.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14678</id>
    <published>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tenants-take-back-power-to-choose-their-own-home"/>
    <title>Tenants take back power to choose their own home</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;HomeSwap Direct searches set to hit 1.5 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social tenants who have been stuck in homes that no longer meet their needs are seizing the opportunity to up sticks through the &lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; scheme, boosting their chances of getting a job, living nearer to family or simply improving their quality of life, Housing Minister Grant Shapps announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister welcomed latest figures showing that there are nearly 6,000 searches a day conducted on &lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; - an online scheme that shows social homes available for swaps across the country. The total number of searches since it launched in October 2011 is shortly expected to hit the 1.5million milestone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time &lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; has allowed tenants to easily look outside the service provided by their own landlord and be given a choice about where they live. With the scheme being online, it has made advertised swaps much more accessible for all tenants and the possibility of moving house just a click away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme has transformed the way in which tenants can look for properties and boosted their prospects of moving - whether for work, to be closer to family or for a property better suited to their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, tenants wanting to move were restricted to swapping properties through a scheme chosen by their landlord - effectively meaning only a partial swap scheme existed. &lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; gives tenants access to a much wider selection of properties than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the success stories of &lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syvie from Coventry found a job in London. She registered on House Exchange in March and moved in June. It would have been too expensive for her to commute to her new job and says the service meant she didn’t have to “live temporarily with family members”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claudia had lived in her small village home in Norfolk for 12 years but needed to reduce her car journeys. She was able to swap with a family in Norwich looking for a more rural setting. “I’m delighted with my new home, there was such a large selection, but I know I’ve got the right one for me.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark had been living in Greenwich for 14 years and wanted to move out to nearer his family in Kent. With his mother Anne’s help, Mark moved four months later. “I was able to help Mark find his exchange with the benefit of HomeSwap Direct which made it much easier” she said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For years, social tenants were stuck in the ridiculous situation where they didn’t have the same freedom of choice as everyone else and could only swap homes with those using the same service as their landlord - or face competition from those higher up the waiting lists.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; has challenged this lazy consensus that trapped people in their homes. Instead, tenants are taking power back to arrange their own home swap by viewing properties available not just in their neighbourhood, but across the whole country.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And with nearly 6,000 searches every day, and nearly 1.5million since the its launch, this successful scheme is clearly opening doors that were simply closed to social tenants, giving them a chance to improve their job prospects, live closer to family or simply move to a home better suited to their changing needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HomeSwap Direct&lt;/em&gt; brings together four internet-based providers of mutual exchange services (HomeSwapper, House Exchange, Abritas and LHS (Locata)) to offer tenants more choice over where they live.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A membership agreement which has been developed by Government and joined by these providers is available on the Department for Communities and Local Government website. This sets out the framework under which information will be shared by providers, the technical requirements of the scheme and the processes by which new members can apply to join. A copy can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/corporate/pdf/2200950.pdf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/corporate/pdf/2200950.pdf.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A new Tenancy Standard came into force on 1 April 2012 and places a requirement on social landlords in England to subscribe to an internet-based mutual exchange service. The provider of the service must be a signatory to an agreement such as HomeSwap Direct under which tenants can access matches across all (or the greatest practicable number of) internet based mutual exchange services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14677</id>
    <published>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-20T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-response-to-the-policy-exchange-report"/>
    <title>Government response to the Policy Exchange Report</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the publication of the Policy Exchange report &lt;em&gt;Ending Expensive Social Tenancies: Fairness, higher growth and more homes&lt;/em&gt; the Government sets out its position in the following statement by Housing Minister Grant Shapps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is common sense to use social housing stock as efficiently as possible, especially since housing waiting lists almost doubled between 1997 and 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Where social landlords have houses which are worth millions, they are able to sell them and build more affordable homes to help more ­vulnerable people come off the ­waiting list. Many independent housing associations have already done this, but councils have been slower to seize the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This Government is investing £19.5billion of public and private funding into an affordable housing programme to deliver 170,000 homes, and has given councils the flexibility to offer fixed term tenancies to new tenants to ensure social housing goes to those in greatest need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Councils looking to sell vacant social housing can now keep the receipts to invest in affordable housing, regeneration or paying down housing debt in their area. And the reinvigorated Right to Buy is helping existing council tenants realise their dream of home ownership with increased discounts of up to £75,000, with a new commitment to replace additional council homes sold with new affordable homes for rent on a one for one basis nationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14674</id>
    <published>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prevention-is-best-cure-for-homelessness"/>
    <title>Prevention is best cure for homelessness</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government commits to early help for those at risk of losing their home&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new report today sets out a cross-Government approach to ensuring that anyone at risk of homelessness gets help at the earliest possible stage to prevent them from losing their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/makingeverycontactcount"&gt;Making Every Contact Count report&lt;/a&gt; details clear commitments from Government to stop the slide towards homelessness in its tracks and ensure that this country’s strong safety net of support for those without a roof over their head remains an absolute last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this Housing Minister Grant Shapps reaffirmed ongoing efforts to ensure no-one has to spend more than one night on the streets, with a further £3.5 million for more homelessness help and to roll out the No Second Night Out initiative across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-every-contact-count"&gt;Making every contact count&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Shapps said that today’s report would give councils, charities, health services and the police a blueprint to work together to ensure that families and vulnerable people at risk of homelessness are offered help early, no matter who they turn to first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets out the Government’s clear commitment to helping them achieve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;earlier support for young people, former prisoners, and patients with mental health, drug or alcohol problems;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better cross-service work between the voluntary sector, councils, health services and the justice system;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;financial advice and jobseeking support through the voluntary sector, Jobcentre Plus and the work programme;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new funding mechanisms, including the Government’s innovative new payment-by-results scheme; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new homelessness ‘gold standard’ that all local services should aim to achieve, setting the benchmark for services across the country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minister said that this early intervention approach is backed up today by new statistics which show that 199,000 households were last year given help to stay in their homes or find new places to live. This vital support, such as repossession, tenancy or debt advice and re-housing services, can set many people back on track before they face losing their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="more-support-for-rough-sleepers"&gt;More support for rough sleepers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further £3.5 million to 21 homelessness charities will support help and accommodation schemes for rough sleepers and extend the No Second Night Out initiative to eight more areas - Manchester, Plymouth, Great Yarmouth, North Devon, Taunton, Gloucestershire, Chichester and Worcestershire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First introduced in London, the No Second Night Out project works with members of the public to quickly identify people sleeping rough locally and provides them with the support they need to get themselves off the streets Mr Shapps wants to see the initiative rolled out across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s funding will support:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two ‘Nightstop’ emergency accommodation service for young people prevent them from living on the streets, or living long-term in B&amp;amp;Bs;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Housing First accommodation for ex rough sleepers help them rebuild their lives and get into long term housing rather than hostels;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a No Second Night Out project and a supported private rented homes scheme for rough sleepers in Plymouth;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a No Second Night Out team at Worcestershire’s St Paul’s Hostel to work with rough sleepers and support those moving to long term accommodation; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving co-ordination and information sharing between day centres and voluntary services in Manchester’s Day Centres, including a No Second Night Out service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grant Shapps said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have some of the strongest protections in the world to safeguard people from homelessness, despite trying economic times, with homelessness in this country lower than for 28 of the last 30 years. But more can always be done.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;No single voluntary service, government agency, council or government department can prevent homelessness alone - but working together we can make a big impact. Every single contact these vulnerable people have with our public services - from council drop-ins to healthcare visits - should be made to count, turning prevention into the cure for anyone facing the real and frightening prospect of sleeping on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And for those who still fall through the cracks, a further £3.5 million of Government money to help rough sleepers and roll out our No Second Night Out pledge across the country means that anyone facing losing their home and sleeping rough will get the support they need and deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today’s gold standard on tackling homelessness is contained within the second report from the Ministerial Working Group on Homelessness, &lt;em&gt;Making Every Contact Count&lt;/em&gt;, which is published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/makingeverycontactcount"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/housing/makingeverycontactcount&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Annual homelessness prevention figures are published today and can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/homelessnessprevention201112"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/corporate/statistics/homelessnessprevention201112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
