<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/greg-clark</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/greg-clark.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Greg Clark MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:05+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14689</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-communties-supporting-neighbourhood-planning"/>
    <title>Cash boost for communties supporting neighbourhood planning</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New funding to help communities bring jobs and homes to their neighbourhood using improved planning powers was announced today by Planning Minister Greg Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go and the type and design of development that can be granted automatic planning permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £10 million fund is now available to help councils ensure their communities are able to finalise people’s plans for homes, businesses and facilities in their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 200 communities are already using the new planning powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans that can, for example, decide the location of new homes and decide the green spaces communities are keen to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils are today invited to apply for grants of up to £30,000 for each scheme to help pay for the costs of getting plans in place. Payments will be paid to councils to help them support and advise groups taking forward neighbourhood plans and to pay towards the examination of plans and a local referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have seen enormous enthusiasm from communities around England, jumping at the chance to be in the driving seat of deciding the future vision of their neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This fund will give councils and community groups working on plans a big boost in getting their vision in place as soon as possible to ensure people can enjoy the benefits sooner rather then later.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is making sure local residents are, for the first time, centre stage in helping decide their neighbourhood’s future. It is giving people the chance to plan positively and will help deliver the homes and jobs their communities need to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="eden-valleys-plan-a-step-closer"&gt;Eden Valley’s plan a step closer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Upper Eden Community Plan Group has their plan well underway after the enthusiasm of residents to be at the centre of decision making ensured they were one of the first areas to use these new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area covering 17 parishes in and around Kirkby Stephen in Cumbria has already been designated a neighbourhood plan area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan that focuses on how and where to provide new housing, affordable housing for older people and better broadband connectivity has now been passed to the Eden District Council for a formal consultation. Local people and businesses will be invited to comment before a final referendum is held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Payments will be made in two payments. The first, of £5,000 will be made once a neighbourhood area has been designated. The second payment of £25,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning independent examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details of the Upper Eden Community Plan can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uecp.org.uk/"&gt;www.uecp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14624</id>
    <published>2012-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:40:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/community-right-to-challenge-comes-into-force"/>
    <title>Community Right to Challenge comes into force</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;From today more communities will be able to bid to take over local services they think they can run differently and better as the Community Right to Challenge provisions come into effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Challenge hands more power back to communities, allowing voluntary and community groups, parish councils and local authority staff to express an interest in taking over the running of local authority services, making services more responsive to local needs and delivering better value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also from today a range of specialist support is being put in place to help community groups wanting to take greater control of their community through every stage of the process - from setting up a group and developing a proposal right through to the delivering services on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Social Investment Business, in partnership with Locality and the Association of Chief Executives of Voluntary Organisations will deliver a three year support programme worth £11.5million. The programme will include a dedicated advice phone line where support and information will be available. It will also include grants to help groups to use the new right and bid to run local public services, resources, and case studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of community groups already providing excellent local services include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bulky Bob’s&lt;/strong&gt; - a social enterprise that has contracts with Liverpool City Council and others to collect, reuse and recycle bulky household waste. 70 per cent of the furniture and white goods collected are recycled or reused, helping over 34,000 low-income families gain access to affordable, ‘pre-loved’ furniture and a huge saving for councils in landfill tax.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shiney Advice and Resource Project (ShARP)&lt;/strong&gt; - is an independent welfare rights advice centre based in Sunderland. Run as a charity it provides basic advice on debt, welfare benefits, housing and employment. Many of ShARP’s users are vulnerable adults or people in stressful situations. Sunderland City Council has recently renewed its contract with ShARP to provide key advice to the Shiney Row, Houghton and Hetton wards of Sunderland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Minister Andrew Stunell said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Challenge gives communities another opportunity to be the driving force in the future of their local services. As the people who know their communities best and use and rely upon local services it makes sense, that where they feel they can run services better, they should be encouraged and supported to step in and do exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Already we have seen some excellent achievements from local people taking the reins, and with these revolutionary rights now in place we can look forward to more communities getting involved in making their local areas better places to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralisation Minister Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Challenge paves the way for communities to play a bigger part in shaping excellent local services around their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Councils do not have to have a monopoly over the best ideas and the most creative are already welcoming innovative ideas from communities about how services can be reformed and improved to better meet local need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This marks the next step in returning power back to citizens, communities and local groups to manage their own affairs free from Whitehall interference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Jenkins, Chief Executive, Social Investment Business said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Right to Challenge presents a fantastic new opportunity for social ventures to grow through increased revenue, and therefore build their capacity to secure further investment - all with the goal of being able to reach more beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Wyler, Chief Executive, Locality said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are delighted that the Community Right to Challenge is coming into force, having pushed hard to make the Localism Act a reality. The Community Right to Challenge will give communities the impetus to suggest and put in place new ways of delivering services - meeting the needs of residents, employing local people and creating resilient community enterprises. Locality supports local people to run local services as the best way to deliver economic and social change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mohamed Aslam MBE, BEM, Director, Himmat Limited a community-led organisation based in Halifax said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At Himmat, we have expanded from our original base of Halifax to deliver services elsewhere in West Yorkshire. As a community-led organisation, we have been successful in being awarded contracts to run services such as with the local Youth Offending Team. It hasn’t been straightforward establishing ourselves - we’re lucky to have strong relationships with our local authority. The new Community Right to Challenge will make it easier for community organisations to suggest new ways of running council services. The 95 per cent attendance record at our Youth Offending Team programme is evidence that community organisations deliver results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Right to Challenge was introduced by the Localism Act 2011 which was enacted on 15 November 2011. Regulations were laid in Parliament on 30 April and 17 May 2012. &lt;em&gt;A plain English guide to the Localism Act&lt;/em&gt; is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/localgovernment/localismplainenglishupdate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the Community Right to Challenge, relevant authorities (county, district and London Borough councils and fire and rescue authorities) must consider expressions of interest and, where they accept an expression of interest, carry out a procurement exercise for the service.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Community Rights website has been launched to give people more information about the new powers and opportunities available to them. The website will continue to grow and expand as more of the Rights come into force. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk"&gt;www.communityrights.communities.gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical help and guidance for those wishing to use the Community Right to Challenge is also available on the My Community Rights website. The site can be viewed here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/"&gt;http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/community-right-to-challenge/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The dedicated advice phone line for support on Community Right to Challenge can be reached on 0845 345 4564.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Social Investment Business has been awarded a contract to deliver a Community Right to Challenge support programme. The programme will be provided in partnership with Locality and the Association of Chief Executives of Voluntary Organisations and supported by a wider partnership of Social Enterprise UK, National Association of Local Councils, Urban Forum, National Council for Voluntary Organisations, ACRE and Community Ventures and Pulse Regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Locality is also providing support for those using the Community Right to Build.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More details of the grants element of the Community Right to Challenge support programme will be announced soon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12631</id>
    <published>2012-05-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T18:01:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/tory-minister-labour-mayor-we-fight-together-for-liverpool"/>
    <title>Tory minister, Labour mayor: we fight together for Liverpool</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Economic growth does not happen in the abstract - it happens in particular places where existing employers expand their production or new firms are attracted to locate for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain is one the most urban countries in the world. So, unless our cities are places which foster and attract enterprise, investment and job creation then Britain itself will not return to growth with the strength that is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we have joined forces - a Conservative Minister and a Labour Mayor - to represent the UK at the New Cities Summit in Paris this week. We are meeting, together, potential investors of global significance, and the leaders of cities around the world with a successful track record of attracting international investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our united message is that Liverpool isn’t just open for business, but is committed to a course that will restore its position as a world-beating centre of trade, culture and innovation. It is an ambition that begins at the top, with a UK mayor who will provide the primary point of contact for inward investors, and the political leadership needed to unlock each and every barrier to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not solely out of faith in the enterprising potential of the city - it is also a matter of practicality. These are tough times and the days when we could just rely on an ever-expanding public sector to provide jobs are over. The same goes for the old culture of debt-fuelled consumerism and destructive speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cold, hard reality is that Britain - and each of its cities - has to earn its way. Moreover, we must do so sustainably. Other parts of the world may compete by exploiting their people and their environment, but to maintain our standard of living and our quality of life, we must compete on what makes us great as a nation: our inventiveness, our creativity, our cultural vitality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These resources are at their most concentrated in our cities. The challenge is to make the most of them. In the past, it is a task in which we have sometimes failed as a nation. Worse still, we have drawn the wrong lessons from each setback, by depriving our cities of the confident self-governance that made them so great in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is perhaps no clearer example than Liverpool. Few would claim that, in the era of Militant, the city showed its best side to the world. However, those events were a trigger for a mistake on the side of the political divide: a further wave of centralisation in which power was locked away in Westminster and Whitehall, adding to the steady accumulation of top-down government control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yet, Liverpool is also where the tide of centralisation began to turn. Michael Heseltine - an early advocate for decentralisation and now a proud Freeman of the City of Liverpool - helped Liverpool find its way back from the brink. Looking back, we can the see the groundbreaking regeneration projects of that time as a milestone in the long revival of our cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the time has come to move into a higher gear. We need to rebalance the economy away from the public sector and towards the private sector - and away from high finance and towards a much broader range of activities in which all our cities can excel. In pursuing this goal, policy makers must remember that we are not job creators - at least, not directly. Rather, our task is to provide the best possible conditions for those who are - the entrepreneurs who create jobs on the basis of productivity not subsidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For cities, the highest priority must be to attract these entrepreneurs. To become the place where the most mobile and dynamic people in the world choose to live and work. Doing this successfully surely requires an in-depth knowledge of the people and places each city brings together. That is why policies for growth cannot be, and have never been, exclusively led by the centre. Cities themselves must take the lead. And for this they need leaders with power and authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Labour Mayor and Conservative Minister, we are working together through the City Deals programme to negotiate the return of power to local people. Liverpool was, in fact, the first City Deal to be announced, but this is just the start of a process that will be widened and deepened in the months ahead. Not least, in Liverpool itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reversing decades of centralisation and driving growth in our cities is not easy - but, for urban Britain, it is essential. Our needs are too great - and our hope are too high - to tolerate the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12595</id>
    <published>2012-03-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T14:26:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-planning-policy-framework--2"/>
    <title>National Planning Policy Framework</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker I would like to make a statement about planning policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted today to be publishing the National Planning Policy Framework and our response to the Communities and Local Government Select Committee Report of the 21 December 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our reforms to planning policy have 3 fundamental objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To put unprecedented power in the hands of communities to shape the places in which they live;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To better support growth to give the next generation the chance that our generation has had to have a decent home, and to allow the jobs to be created on which our prosperity depends; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To ensure that the places we cherish - our countryside, towns and cities - are bequeathed to the next generation in a better condition than they are now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To achieve these objectives reform is sorely needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade of Regional Spatial Strategies, top-down targets and national planning policy guidance that has swelled beyond reason to over 1000 pages across 44 documents, has led to communities seeing planning as something done to them, rather than &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as the planning system has become more complex, it has ground ever slower. In 2004 Parliament required every council to have a plan - eight years on, only around a half have been able to adopt one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last decade - starting long before the financial crisis - we built fewer homes than in any peacetime decade for 100 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average age of the first-time buyer is approaching 40, and rising rents mean that families have to spend more and more on housing, and less and less on themselves and their children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t allow this to go on. To do so would be to deny our responsibility to young families - to tell them that the property-owning democracy was for our generation but not for yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of this is down to sclerosis in the planning system, but some is. The Chambers of Commerce have said that the planning system has become;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;too complicated, too costly, too uncertain. It discourages investment, creates mistrust and holds back our recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not as if what has made it through has made up in quality what it lacks in quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too much development in recent years has been mediocre, insensitive and has detracted from the character of the areas in which we live and work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many of our habitats have been degraded and nature driven out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect has been that much of the public have come to assume that any particular change to our built environment will be negative - that it will tend to impair beauty, damage the environment and make our lives worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a disastrous state of affairs in a country which is home to some of the most talented designers, and the best architects and craftsmen in the world, and which has over the years constructed villages and cities and buildings - like the one we meet in - that people cross the world to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our reforms to the planning system take on each of these challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They enshrine the local plan - produced by local people - as the keystone of the planning system;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They make planning much simpler and more accessible, reducing over a thousand pages of often impenetrable jargon into around 50 pages of clearly written guidance;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They establish a presumption in favour of sustainable development that means that development is not held up unless to approve it would be against our collective interest;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Framework guarantees robust protections for our natural and historic environment, and goes further by requiring net improvements to put right some of the neglect that has been visited on us;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It raises the bar on design standards so that we have the most exacting requirement for design that the English planning system has ever contained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, I have always regarded reforming the planning system as a serious responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start I made it clear that Parliament should be central to the development of the policy, we have had three full debates in this House and in the House of Lords - and I asked the Communities and Local Government Select Committee to consider the draft National Planning Policy Framework and to give me its considered advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put on record my thanks to the chairman and members of that Committee and to Environmental Audit Committee for the seriousness and thoughtfulness that they brought to the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to tell colleagues that of the Committee’s 35 recommendations, I have been able to accept 30 in whole or in part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular the final framework:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes it clear that the local plan is, as the Committee put it, the keystone of the planning edifice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is crystal clear that sustainable development embraces social and environmental as well as economic objectives and does so in a balanced way;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refers explicitly to the five principles of the UK Sustainable Development Strategy;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goes further than ever before and is clear that councils should look for net improvements on all dimensions of sustainability;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes explicit that the presumption in favour of sustainable development works through, not against, local plans;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes it clear that relevant policies - such as those protecting the Green Belt, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, National Parks and other areas - cannot be overridden by the presumption;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognises the intrinsic value and beauty of the countryside (whether specifically designated or not);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes explicit what was always implicit: that councils’ policies must encourage brownfield sites to be brought back into use;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Underlines the importance of town centres, while recognising that businesses in rural communities should be free to expand;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Takes a localist approach to creating a buffer of housing supply over and above 5 years, and in the use of windfall sites;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows councils to protect back gardens - those precious urban oases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensures that playing fields continue to benefit from that same protection that they do currently;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final framework has been strengthened by the contributions of everyone who has taken the trouble to submit their views and I am very grateful for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always been my intention that councils who have done the right thing and either adopted, or have made good progress towards adopting local plans, will not be disadvantaged by the change to new policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, I have introduced transitional arrangements suggested by, and agreed with, the Local Government Association. They accord weight to plans according to how advanced they are. However, I have gone further in two respects. I have allowed 12 months from today for existing plans to be adjusted to be in complete conformity with the new framework, and made clear that weight can be given to emerging plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Mr Speaker, this House has a particular role to play in safeguarding the interests of our successors. Having shaped the development of the new framework, I will ensure that Parliament supervises the implementation of the policies starting with a debate on the floor of the House soon after we return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, the purpose of planning is to help make the way we live our lives tomorrow better than it is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This National Planning Policy Framework will help build the homes the next generation needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It supports growth to allow employers to create the jobs our constituents need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It protects what we hold dear in our matchless countryside and in the fabric of our history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does so by taking power away from remote bodies and putting it firmly into the hands of the people of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I warmly commend it to the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="related-publications"&gt;Related publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h4 id="national-planning-policy-frameworkhttpwwwcommunitiesgovukpublicationsplanningandbuildingnppf"&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/nppf"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Published: 27 March 2012&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Site: Planning, building and the environment&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9730</id>
    <published>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-mayors-cabinet-to-provide-cities-with-a-voice-in-government--2"/>
    <title>New Mayors Cabinet to provide cities with a voice in government</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new Mayors Cabinet that will ensure elected city mayors have a voice at the heart of Government was announced today by Prime Minister David Cameron and Cities Minister Greg Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cabinet will provide city mayors with a direct route to the Prime Minister and other senior Ministers and provide a forum for cities to exchange ideas, highlight new innovations and lobby for the interests of their city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cabinet meetings will be held at least twice a year and will provide a valuable opportunity for cities to discuss key local issues with decision makers in Whitehall and for mayors to strengthen relationships with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes that elected mayors can provide cities with the strong, visible and accountable leadership that will help them prosper nationally and internationally and deliver the homes and jobs this country needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Inspirational city leaders can do great things for their communities which is why I truly believe having a directly elected mayor in every major city in the country will bring about real change for the benefit of local people. And on 3 May 2012 we will be asking 10 cities to vote on having their own Mayor.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;To ensure elected Mayors have a voice right at the heart of Government, I am pleased to announce I will establish a new City Mayors Cabinet so these locally elected leaders can meet regularly with me and raise the views of local people, tackle concerns, share ideas and highlight innovation. I very much look forward to meeting all the new mayors and to our first meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities Minister Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Mayors Cabinet is a real opportunity for an elected mayor to represent their communities at the heart of Government and will ensure their city’s voice is heard right at the top.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Mayors are a very good way of providing the strong, visible leadership that helps attract investment and have enormous potential to drive a city’s future prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;By coming together, sharing innovations and building relationships, city mayors will play an important role in ensuring their city lives up to its full potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to the creation of directly elected mayors in the 12 largest cities outside of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 3 May 2012 ballot boxes will open in Birmingham, Bradford, Bristol, Coventry, Leeds, Manchester, Newcastle-Upon-Tyne, Nottingham, Sheffield and Wakefied for local people to decide whether to have directly elected mayors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leicester has already elected a mayor and Liverpool, following a resolution of the City Council, will hold an election for a mayor on 3 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The announcement was made today at a reception attended by Prime Minister David Cameron and Cities Minister Greg Clark at 10 Downing Street to highlight the forthcoming referendums on City Mayors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9804</id>
    <published>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:30:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-reforms-will-deliver-local-growth-with-community-support--2"/>
    <title>Planning reforms will deliver local growth with community support</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new, simplified planning framework that better supports growth and helps creates the homes and jobs that the country needs, puts unprecedented power into the hands of communities, and helps protect and enhance our natural and historic environment was published by Planning Minister Greg Clark today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new 50 page document, which replaces over 1,300 pages of inherited policy in 44 separate documents delivers on the Coalition Agreement’s commitment to “publish and present to Parliament a simple and consolidated national planning framework covering all forms of development and setting out national economic, environmental and social priorities” by April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Framework has been produced following an extensive consultation with Parliament and the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Framework gives guidance to local councils in drawing up local plans and on making decisions on planning applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government aim is for every area to have a clear local plan which sets out local people’s views of how they wish their community to develop, consistent with the Framework and against which planning applications for planning permission will be judged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local plans have a responsibility to meet the objectively-assessed needs of their area for homes, business premises, schools and other social and cultural facilities, while protecting and enhancing the natural and historic environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final Framework retains all of the key elements of the draft Framework published in July 2011, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enshrining the local plan - produced by local people - as the keystone of the planning system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making planning much simpler and more accessible - reducing over 1,300 pages of often impenetrable jargon in 44 separate documents into a clear, readable guide of 50 pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a powerful presumption in favour of sustainable development that underpins all local plans and decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;guaranteeing robust protections for our natural and historic environment, including the Green Belt, National Parks, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty and Sites of Special Scientific Interest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging the use of brownfield land in a way determined locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the new Framework strengthens the requirement for new development to be of good design; supports local councils who wish to bring into being a new generation of garden cities; allows communities to specify where renewable energy such as wind farms should, and should not, be located; and following the recommendation of the Portas Review allows councils to provide the parking facilities in town centres that will help them compete with out-of-town shopping centres and supermarkets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Framework comes into force with immediate effect for plan-making and decisions. Appropriate implementation arrangements agreed with the Local Government Association have been put in place for local authorities with up-to-date policies in local plans. Immediate advice and support is available to councils through a joint team of the Local Government Association, the Planning Inspectorate and the Department of Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities Secretary Eric Pickles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is another important milestone in the Government’s historic mission to transfer power from the hands of unelected bodies and put it in the hands of people and communities. The Localism Act has allowed us to start scrapping Regional Spatial Strategies which gave development a bad name by imposing top down targets that owed nothing to local needs and threatened the Green Belt.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These reforms go a step further and make it clear that local communities have the responsibility and the power to decide the look and feel of the places they love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new Framework has been strengthened by the responses to the consultation. We have confirmed the core reforms, sharpened the definition of the policies, and emphasised the essential balance that the planning system must achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These reforms will help build the homes the next generation needs, it will let businesses expand and create jobs, and it will conserve what we hold dear in our matchless countryside and the fabric of our history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. A copy of the &lt;em&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/em&gt; can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/nppf"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/nppf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. The Government’s response to the Communities and Local Government Select Committee’s report on draft National Planning Policy Framework can be found at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/issuesandresponses/newsroom/2056346"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/issuesandresponses/newsroom/2056346&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Neighbourhood planning regulations: Consultation - Summary of responses&lt;/em&gt; was published today and can be found here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/neighbourhoodplansresponse"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/neighbourhoodplansresponse&lt;/a&gt;. Neighbourhood planning gives local people a major statutory say in shaping development in their area. It empowers communities to produce a neighbourhood development plan, a neighbourhood development order or a Community Right to Build Order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. The neighbourhood planning regulations set out the requirements for designating neighbourhood areas and forums and preparing key elements of neighbourhood development plans, neighbourhood development orders and Community Right to Build orders. The regulations have been laid before Parliament with the intention that they come into force on 6 April 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. An assessment of how neighbourhood planning and the Community Right to Build will benefit communities and businesses was published today. &lt;em&gt;Localism Act: Neighbourhood Plans and Community Right To Build - Impact Asessment&lt;/em&gt; is available here: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/neighbourhoodplansimpact"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/planningandbuilding/neighbourhoodplansimpact&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9688</id>
    <published>2012-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/manchester-city-deal-brings-6-000-jobs-boost--2"/>
    <title>Manchester City Deal brings 6,000 jobs boost</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greater Manchester will create and protect 6,000 jobs as the city signs an innovative deal with central government giving it new powers to create jobs and train local people with the right skills to fill them, Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg and Cities Minister Greg Clark have announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers, including the ability to ‘earn back’ a portion of the additional tax generated by investing in infrastructure, have been agreed as part of the City Deals initiative, which sees cities bid for powers to free them from Whitehall controls in order to boost growth locally. Manchester is the first ever city in the country to secure such powers and will be able to reinvest the money in local economic development and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city has calculated that the deal will lead to 3,800 new jobs for local people and will protect 2,300 existing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal will permit Greater Manchester to ‘earn back’ up to £30 million a year of tax for growth it creates. Under the scheme, Manchester will invest £1.2 billion in improving infrastructure such as transport. This is the first time that a UK city has had the freedom to reinvest its own national tax revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal will help the city drive growth and create opportunities that will benefit the whole Greater Manchester area. It includes new initiatives on housing, skills, regional growth, business support and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;City Deals are being negotiated with the eight ‘core cities’, the largest and most economically important English cities outside of London. Each city is able to specify the particular powers they need and want to boost local growth. Negotiations are ongoing with the other core cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This deal breaks new ground, giving Manchester the freedom to be truly revolutionary - ‘earning back’ tax for growth it creates.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I congratulate the city on its innovative approach that will see it grow - jobs, skills, transport, and housing - for the benefit of everyone who lives there.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In recognition of this excellence, I am pleased that the government can cut Whitehall ties and devolve power to Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities Minister, Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve said to each City ‘make us an offer’. Tell us how you can drive growth in ways that have not been tried before, or which harness your city’s unique strengths in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For our whole nation to prosper our cities must also unlock the potential of all of the citizens within them. I am especially pleased that this ‘Deal’ includes the truly innovative ‘Earn Back’ model which allows Manchester to reinvest the benefits of its own entrepreneurship. This is just the kind of ground breaking response that we are keen to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key elements of Manchester proposals are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create a ‘revolving Infrastructure Fund’, allowing Greater Manchester to ‘earn back’ a portion of the tax it generates by investing £1.2 billion in infrastructure, on a payment-by-results basis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To establish a Greater Manchester Investment Framework to make the best use of funding from central government, European funding, and private sector funding to drive economic growth. Investment will be prioritised on the basis of Gross Value Added and jobs per pound of public funding.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create a City Apprenticeship and Skills Hub to increase the number of apprenticeships for 16-24 year olds by 10 per cent to 6,000 by channelling funding direct to employers, in particular small and medium sized businesses. To strengthen Greater Manchester’s Business Growth Hub which gives trade, investment and business advice to local companies, with Government contributing £4.4 million of transitional funding, prior to local funding from Enterprise Zone revenues coming on-stream from 2015. The city says this will create 3,800 new jobs and safeguard 2,300 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Develop Manchester’s role as a beacon for high value inward investment. Developing markets in China, India and Graphene technologies especially.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Establish a Low Carbon Hub to integrate multiple carbon reduction measures. The Department for Environment and Climate Change will support Greater Manchester to achieve a 48 per cent carbon reduction target by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Establish Greater Manchester Housing Investment Board to set up an investment fund, to drive the building of 5,000-7,000 new homes by 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commit Government and Greater Manchester to work together to deliver improved transport services by devolving the Northern franchises, bus improvement, including the devolution of central subsidies and smart ticketing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. All figures are based on estimates by Association of Greater Manchester Authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Cities facts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Core Cities are: Birmingham, Bristol, Leeds, Liverpool, Newcastle, Nottingham, Manchester and Sheffield. The eight core cities are the largest and most economically important English cities outside of London.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Cities account for 58 per cent of England’s population and 61 per cent of its jobs. When their wider commuting areas are taken into account, this rises to 74 per cent of population and 78 per cent of jobs. Source: Data for 2008, from the Department for Communities and Local Government (2010) Updating the evidence base on English Cities. Data for cities relates to Primary Urban Areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9112</id>
    <published>2012-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:28:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--2"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation committee</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government today announced the appointment, following open competition, of four non-executives members to the Homes and Communities Agency’s new Regulation Committee:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piers Williamson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jane May&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Richard Moriarty; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jim Coulter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;They will join Chair-designate Julian Ashby in overseeing regulation of the social housing sector from 1 April 2012, when responsibility for this vitally important function transfers to the Homes and Communities Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are committed to robust regulation of the social housing sector, and this is a strong committee which I am confident will ensure that task is delivered. It is right that as the Committee members establish the Regulation function at the Homes and Communities Agency, they should focus on the economic viability, good governance and value for money of Registered Providers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have chosen to appoint a highly skilled Committee while retaining the flexibility to assess and address any emerging challenges as the new Regulatory Framework is implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be joined on the Committee by four such capable people. They bring a range of expertise in their respective fields, including fresh perspectives from other areas of regulation as well as those with substantial experience in social housing. It includes strong financial, commercial and economic expertise which will be essential for the Committee’s core role of economic regulation. Together we will ensure effective independent regulation of social housing that is robust, transparent and commands the confidence of the sector, its lenders and other stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key staff will transfer from the Tenant Services Authority on 1 April 2012, ensuring continuity on ongoing casework. As part of the Homes and Communities Agency, the new Committee will oversee implementation of the new regulatory framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee is a statutory committee of the Homes and Communities Agency, created by virtue of the Localism Act 2011. It will assume full powers and responsibilities from 1 April 2012, following abolition of the Tenant Services Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piers Williamson&lt;/strong&gt; is Chief Executive of the Housing Finance Company, a not-for-profit organisation that raises market finance for registered providers. He brings a wealth of financial services and banking experience along with over nine years experience of the social housing sector. Piers has also held non-executive Board roles at the Co-operative Bank and Insurance Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jane May&lt;/strong&gt; with recent regulatory experience as a Board member of OFWAT and the Office of Rail Regulation, Jane also has commercial experience as Customer Services Director of Thames Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Moriarty&lt;/strong&gt; is currently Director of Economic Regulation at the Civil Aviation Authority, and was previously Director of Regulation at the Tenants Services Authority, and has additional regulatory experience at Postcomm, Ofgem and Ofgas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jim Coulter&lt;/strong&gt; is a current member of the Tenant Services Authority Board. Jim has huge experience in the housing sector as well as significant non-executive experience. A former chief executive of the National Housing Federation, he has also chaired Bridging Newcastle Gateshead and been a Board member of the Audit Commission and the Housing Finance Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chair of the Committee, Julian Ashby, has been appointed for three years, while other members have been appointed for 12 months, with the option to renew, subject to Secretary of State approval. Committee members will receive remuneration of £11,000 per annum for up to two days per month. Existing public servants will forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made after open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government, supported by the Whitehall and Industry Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Committee may consist of between four and six members, in addition to the Chair. Two vacancies will be retained. A further recruitment exercise will be run within the first year and is likely to focus on further boosting the commercial expertise available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9689</id>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mayoral-referendum-election-date-confirmed"/>
    <title>Mayoral referendum election date confirmed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ballot boxes will open on 3 May 2012 for voters to decide on directly elected mayors for England’s largest cities, Ministers confirmed today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government believes that elected mayors can provide cities with the strong, visible leadership that will help them prosper nationally and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement proposed the creation of directly elected mayors in the 12 largest cities outside of London, subject to confirmatory referendum and full scrutiny by elected councillors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leicester has already elected a mayor and Liverpool has decided, following a resolution of the City Council, to move a mayoral form of government and hold an election for a mayor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 10 remaining cities - in Birmingham, Bradford, Bristol, Coventry, Leeds, Manchester, Newcastle Upon -Tyne, Nottingham, Sheffield and Wakefield, referendums will take place on 3 May 2012 for local people to decide whether to have a directly elected mayor. Liverpool’s election will also take place on the same day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Elected mayors can provide the strong, visible leadership to help our cities to prosper, attracting investment and jobs from home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Our greatest cities can benefit from the prestige and international standing a mayor can bring, helping them to achieve their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For Britain to be successful our cities need to be successful. An elected mayor with a strong voice can seize the opportunities for their city to compete on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the approval of Parliament, orders have today come into force giving the go-ahead for mayoral referendums. Where people vote in favour, the city will move to an elected mayor and hold elections on 15 November 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal foundation for the role of directly elected mayors is the Government’s Localism Act, which contains a wide range of decentralising measures. Mayors will have a crucial role to play in shaping the ongoing process of reform - negotiating with Ministers to specify and secure the specific powers that each community needs to prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement set out a commitment to create directly elected mayors in the 12 largest English cities outside London, subject to confirmatory referendums and full scrutiny by elected councillors. The Localism Act empowers local people to decide whether they want an elected mayor for their city. Mayoral referendums are being held on local Election Day on 3 May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a city votes in favour of having a mayor at its referendum, that city will then hold an election for its first mayor on 15 November 2012. Mayors would be elected for four year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leicester elected their mayor in 2011. Liverpool plan to elect their mayor in May 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government recently published the document ‘Unlocking growth in cities’ available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/growthcities"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/publications/regeneration/growthcities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/9666</id>
    <published>2012-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:29:49+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/liverpool-first-to-strike-new-city-deal-with-government"/>
    <title>Liverpool first to strike new City Deal with government</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liverpool has become the first city to agree new powers through the City Deals programme, the Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg and Cities Minister Greg Clark announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of transformative powers will be devolved to Liverpool to give the city what it needs to attract private investment, close skills gaps and create new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This landmark deal will create a new enterprise zone near the city centre, provide powers to help get young unemployed people into work and give greater control over land for redevelopment and help build twelve new secondary schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal will help the city compete in the wider economy, driving growth and creating opportunities that will benefit the wider Merseyside area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;City Deals are being negotiated with a number of England’s cities. Instead of being presented with a set menu of measures decided in Whitehall, each city is now able to specify the particular powers they need to meet local needs and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This first city deal heralds an unprecedented transfer of power from central government to local communities, with new powers and funding for Liverpool to do things its own way. I congratulate Liverpool on blazing a trail we look forward to seeing others follow.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I firmly believe one size doesn’t fit all - whether it’s a Mayor or whether it is a Council Leader, what Cities have to show in return for a City Deal is that there is strong clear leadership. This deal puts Liverpool back in the driving seat to create jobs and boost skills with greater economic and political freedom. It empowers Liverpool to go for growth that will benefit everyone who lives there.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Our cities are Britain’s economic heartbeat and their success is absolutely vital to getting the whole country’s economy growing again. I want to see more cities take us up on our offer and I’m looking forward to announcing more city deals across the country in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities Minister, Greg Clark said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’ve said to each City ‘make us an offer’. Tell us how you can drive growth, and I promise that the Government will respond positively.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Liverpool has risen to the challenge with alacrity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is fantastic to see Liverpool become the first city in Britain to seize the opportunity on offer. This deal will be a major boost to the standing of this great city - both within Britain and on the world stage. Liverpool has seized the chance to attract private investment, create jobs and build a prosperous future.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This is, I hope, the first of many such deals with our cities. For Britain to prosper our cities must prosper. I am determined to devolve power from Whitehall and give local leaders what they need to take their cities forward into a confident and prosperous future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key elements of Liverpool’s proposals are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new Enterprise Zone, that will create a ‘City Fringe Buffer Zone’ to the north of the city centre and Central Business District. This means that for the next 25 years increases in Business Rate income, would be invested in regeneration. The Government will also be prepared to support economic development backed by a strong business case by up to £75 million during the spending review period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creation of a joint Mayoral Investment Board to oversee the city’s economic and housing strategy, pooling local assets including those of the Homes and Communities Agency to drive economic growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launch Welfare Pilots to reduce welfare dependency. The city will work closely with the Government on local schemes including a ‘youth contract’ to increase the number of claimants moving to work and to reduce fraud and error.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Secondary School Investment Plan to build 12 new secondary schools including at least six new academies to help support the local skills agenda and the local economy. The Council will work with the schools, private companies and local universities to develop specialisms to meet local skills shortages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister and Cities Minister launched the City Deals in Leeds on the 08 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/do-it-your-way-deputy-prime-minister-launches-new-city-deals"&gt;www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/do-it-your-way-deputy-prime-minister-launches-new-city-deals&lt;/a&gt; (External link).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/do-it-your-way-deputy-prime-minister-launches-new-city-deals-speech-transcript"&gt;www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/do-it-your-way-deputy-prime-minister-launches-new-city-deals-speech-transcript&lt;/a&gt; (External link).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copy of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/statements/newsroom/2084343"&gt;Written Ministerial Statement: Unlocking Growth in Cities - Liverpool City Deal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="twitter"&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the Department by following us on &lt;a rel="external" href="http://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (external link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="media-enquiries"&gt;Media enquiries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/corporate/about/who/policycontacts/newsroomcontacts"&gt;newsroom contacts page&lt;/a&gt; for media enquiry contact details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
