<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/henry-bellingham</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/henry-bellingham.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Henry Bellingham MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27909</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-appreciation-for-seychelles-role-in-countering-international-piracy"/>
    <title>UK appreciation for Seychelles role in countering international piracy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting focused on sports and the important role Seychelles is playing in tackling international piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the Foreign Office Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was delighted to welcome Minister  Meriton to London and the Paralympics Games. I underlined that a key part of the 2012 legacy is sharing our experience with countries around the world to inspire, promote and develop sporting excellence and participation by young people. So I very much hope to see Seychellois Paralympians competing in Rio in four years time. We also discussed the importance of our partnership in countering international piracy, and I expressed the UK’s appreciation and full support of the active role that the Seychelles has played in tackling this critical problem.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27911</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-meets-un-special-advisor-on-sport-for-development-and-peace"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister meets UN Special Advisor on Sport for Development and Peace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They discussed a range of issues including the work of the UN Office on Sport for Development and Peace, and how the Olympic Truce has been brought to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting, Mr Bellingham said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was delighted to meet Mr Lemke today, during his visit  to London for the Paralympic Games and thanked him for his recognition of the UK’s efforts in promoting the Olympic Truce internationally.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We discussed the importance of ensuring that a firm Olympic Truce legacy remains after the London Olympic and Paralympic Games.  I am pleased that the UK has delivered a range of Olympic Truce activities around the world highlighting the Olympic Truce as a key part of our conflict prevention and peace building work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope the UN Office on Sport for Development and Peace, the International Olympic Committee, the UK and other UN Member States will continue to promote the Olympic Truce as a means of educating people about conflict prevention.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27873</id>
    <published>2012-08-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/africa-continues-to-win-gold"/>
    <title>Africa continues to win Gold</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we cross the finish line of the Olympic Games we should reflect, not just on the success of our Olympians, but also on the ongoing success of London as a global business hub. Africa is rightly a part of this. Too long a continent perceived as holding little but poverty and famine - a different view is coming into focus: one of opportunity and success. I have seen this in London over the past two weeks, not least when meeting members of African Diasporas and African companies keen to make the most of our wonderful Games to do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympics have - more so than ever in this world city - brought Africa to London. And the continent is showcasing what it has to offer. Africa followers are already aware of its latent potential - its growth rate of 4.7 percent in 2011 clearly outstrips the European market. Our competitors have noticed the potential - China, India, Turkey, Brazil have all upped their game. The UK has too, but we need to make sure we are not left behind.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the cynics, I say that African success is more than a blip. By 2050 nearly 1 in 4 of the world’s population will be African. Nearly a quarter of the world’s total land area is in Africa, with some 60 percent of the world’s uncultivated cropland. The continent is already the world’s top producer of many mineral commodities, with more than 10 percent of proven global crude oil reserves, and gas reserves of a similar level. The continent is leapfrogging much of the developed world in technology and is now one of the fastest growing telecoms markets globally. In the last 30 years economic growth has tripled Africa’s middle classes, with all the new consumer power this ignites.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These developments will move some African countries from aid dependency to middle-income status. Ghana has already started those discussions with the World Bank and others. We are right to work with Africa to support capacity building, to create the right institutional framework to encourage investment and new jobs. Africa too has accepted the challenge. In January this year, the African Union signed up to a continental free trade area by 2017.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Africa has grasped the baton of the Olympics to promote itself. Last week I welcomed President Kibaki of Kenya and 11 of his Ministers to London. They took over Mansion House, the official residence of the Lord Mayor. To a packed business audience they showcased bankable projects from their development blueprint “Kenya Vision 2030”. The UK is already the largest investor in Kenya, but we can do even better. And if the Olympics do go to Nairobi in 2024 as Prime Minister Odinga has suggested, British companies have shown what they can do in delivering world class infrastructure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria was also in London in force. On its current trajectory Nigeria is set to become the largest economy on the continent in just a few years. At their High Level Business and Investment Summit I spoke about our joint commitment to double bilateral trade, and called for partnership in realising the immense opportunities. Their new Petroleum Industry Bill is critical. With the right investor-friendly legislation, the Nigerian economy will flourish, to the benefit of all Nigerians.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The President of Cote d’Ivoire was also in town. Before a 10 year conflict the country was the second largest economy in West Africa. They are determined to regain that status. We need to listen. Why? It is a country with a predicted growth rate of 8.3 percent in 2012. With the European and other historical UK export destinations headlining flat growth, it is these less-travelled markets we have to target if the UK economy is to grow. That is why I recently re-opened the British embassy in the capital, Abidjan, and why we are opening up in 5 new embassies in Africa to support more British business. It is why I take UK trade delegations focused on key sectors with me on many of my African trips.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African and UK athletes have won gold in London. But the prize for Africa and the UK is even bigger. It is win-win through partnership and growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27872</id>
    <published>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-13T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/construction-begins-on-anti-piracy-centre-in-the-seychelles"/>
    <title>Construction begins on anti-piracy centre in the Seychelles</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ground-breaking ceremony for the Regional Anti-Piracy Prosecution &amp;amp; Intelligence Coordination Centre (RAPPICC), the Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I welcome the start of construction work on the RAPPICC, which has begun today. This centre will play a vital role in targeting the heart of the piracy operations: the leaders and financiers of piracy who feel as if they are able to act with impunity and hold innocent seafarers and the world’s trade to ransom. By targeting those at the top, the RAPPICC will perform a vital and unique function, and will support regional capacity in tackling serious organised crime in Somalia.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27863</id>
    <published>2012-08-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/inspiring-young-people-in-the-uk-and-anguilla"/>
    <title>Inspiring young people in the UK and Anguilla</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after his meeting with Shara Proctor, Henry Bellingham, Minister for the Overseas Territories, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a great pleasure for me to welcome Shara Proctor to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office today to congratulate her on reaching the Olympic final in the women’s long jump.  Shara Proctor’s achievement is a success for both the UK and for Anguilla, the British Overseas Territory where she was born and brought up.  Because Anguilla does not have its own Olympic Committee, Shara competes for Team GB - and we are very proud to have her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Shara Proctor made her debut representing Great Britain at the European Team Championships in June 2011.  Since then she has gone from strength to strength, winning bronze in the IAAF World Indoor Athletics Championships and setting new British indoor and outdoor long-jump records.  Although Shara is only 23, she has already jumped further than any other long-jumper representing the UK.  I am confident she will jump further yet, and I know that her experiences at the London Olympics will stand her in good stead for future international success including, I hope, at the Rio Olympics in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Britain’s ties with Anguilla go back several centuries and most Anguillians, like Shara, are British nationals.   We enjoy a good relationship with the Government of Anguilla, and I look forward to meeting the Chief Minister again later this year to discuss the implementation of the UK’s White Paper on the Overseas Territories ‘Security, Success and Sustainability’,  which seeks to foster even stronger links with and support for the Territories.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the meantime, I hope the people of both Anguilla and the UK will continue to celebrate the accomplishments already made by Shara, and I’m confident that her achievements will inspire young people in the UK and in Anguilla to take up athletics and other sports.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27853</id>
    <published>2012-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/investment-opportunity-with-the-caribbean"/>
    <title>Investment opportunity with the Caribbean</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the event the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This event was an excellent opportunity to stress the importance of the long-standing trade and investment relationship between the UK and the Caribbean. British firms already operate successful in the Caribbean, as do Caribbean firms here in the UK. But I believe there is much more we can do to raise the level of commercial relations between the Caribbean, the UK and the rest of Europe”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games offer a once-in-a-generation opportunity to enhance Britain’s reputation as an experienced and dynamic business partner and to deliver a lasting economic legacy for the whole country.  We want the Caribbean to share in this, and to maximise the benefits for the region.  I am delighted that events like these and others organised by Caribbean Diplomatic Missions in London have sought to take advantage of the wider international audience to promote tourism and trade.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year the UK’s bilateral trade with the Caribbean exceeded £800 million (£379m in UK imports, £446m in UK exports).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CARIFORUM-EU Business forum was organised by the Caribbean Export Development Agency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27839</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-speaks-at-the-opening-of-jamaica-house"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister speaks at the opening of Jamaica House</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;After his speech at the Opening of Jamaican House, Mr Bellingham said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a great honour to speak at the opening of Jamaica House and to see a corner of London transformed into a small piece of Jamaica. I would encourage as many people as possible to take advantage of this unique opportunity to experience the sights, sounds and tastes of Jamaica in the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would also like to send my congratulations to the Government of Jamaica and to the Jamaican people on 50 years of Independence, which they will be celebrating on Monday.  I’m delighted that the anniversary falls during the Olympic Games, making this a double celebration and a very special moment for the UK-Jamaica relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Jamaica and the UK already enjoy an extremely strong bilateral relationship - the Independence Celebrations at Jamaica House give us the opportunity to further develop our cultural, trade and investment ties.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamaica House will run from 3-12 August at the O2 Arena. It is a home away from home for Jamaican athletes and fans, as well as offering Londoners an insight into Jamaican history, culture, and way of life. It will offer a variety of Jamaican cultural events including food demonstrations, fashion shows and music shows, as well as live screenings of Olympic events. Visitors will also be able to learn about trade and investment opportunities in Jamaica, through various events hosted by JAMPRO (Jamaica’s investment and export promotion agency).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamaica will celebrate 50 years of independence on 6 August, the first country in the Commonwealth Caribbean to reach this momentous landmark.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27838</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/somali-olympic-team-participating-against-all-the-odds"/>
    <title>Somali Olympic team: participating against all the odds</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking from the Olympic Stadium after watching Somali Olympic athlete Zamzam Farah in the women’s 400m, Mr Bellingham said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s has been a real privilege to welcome the Somali Olympic team to London, and to watch their first events with the Somali Minister for Sports.  Against all the odds, and in the face of huge challenges and adversity, these two young athletes have done a great service to their country by competing in the London 2012 Olympics: Zamzam Farah in the women’s 400m and Mohamed Hassan in the men’s 1,500m.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Their story is genuinely inspiring. Unlike most of those who took part, they didn’t have the benefit of professional coaches. They didn’t even have a functioning track to train on, and often they trained in the streets of Mogadishu, even while fighting was going on in the city.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The fact that they made it all is a hugely impressive achievement.  Zamzam and Mohamed are living proof that Somalia may be a failed state, but the Somalis are not a failed people. And they take back with them an invaluable prize: the pride and honour of representing their nation on the world stage.  Baron de Coubertin, considered the founder of the modern Olympics, said that winning medals was not the point of the Olympics, it was participation that counted - it is hard to believe there can have been an occasion in Olympic history when this was more true.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27828</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-welcomes-approval-of-a-new-national-constitution-for-somalia"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa welcomes approval of a new national constitution for Somalia</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased that the National Constituent Assembly (NCA) has approved a new Constitution. The fact that 96% of those present in the NCA voted in favour of the new Constitution reflects the decisive national will to move forward with the political process. This landmark decision bodes well for Somalia’s future. It sets the framework for the next phase in Somalia’s political process, and for further discussion on the Provisional Constitution ahead of an eventual national referendum. It is a particular achievement, for which credit is due to the African Union Mission in Somalia and the Transitional Federal Government forces, that the NCA was able to complete its deliberations in Mogadishu despite the ongoing security challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I now urge Somalia’s leaders to maintain the momentum and press ahead with ending the transition by 20 August. The international community is and will continue to provide the necessary support to the process. I call on the Elders to fulfil their responsibilities by finalising the list of candidates for the next Transitional Federal Parliament as soon as possible, to allow proper scrutiny by the Technical Selection Committee. This process is vital for ensuring that Somalia’s Parliament commands full legitimacy and respect, and is able to carry out its primary duties of enacting legislation and holding the new government to account.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27826</id>
    <published>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-02T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-africa-meets-kenyan-foreign-minister"/>
    <title>Minister for Africa meets Kenyan Foreign Minister</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the meeting, which took place following the successful Kenya Investment Summit at Mansion House on 31 July, the Foreign Office Minister said “the commercial relationship is at the heart of our bilateral relationship. The UK remains the biggest cumulative investor in Kenya. I am determined to build on that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ministers also discussed how the international community could support Somalia to achieve peace and stability as the end of transition approaches on 20 August.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
