<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/hugo-swire</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/hugo-swire.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61175</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T18:49:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-deeply-concerned-by-conflict-in-burma"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister deeply concerned by conflict in Burma</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP expressed dismay today at the ongoing violence in Kachin state in Burma.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am deeply concerned by the ongoing conflict between the Burmese Army and Kachin Independence Army (KIA) in Burma’s Kachin State, including recent reports of air strikes in the state. An escalation in hostilities would put at risk the chance of a lasting peace in Burma. It is imperative that military commanders in Burma heed their President’s calls for an end to hostilities. I raised these concerns with the Burmese government during my visit last month. It is important that all sides, including the KIA, come to the negotiating table and make renewed efforts to work towards lasting peace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During my meetings with the Burmese government I highlighted the importance of normalising the role of the Burmese military. Lasting democratic reform in Burma will not be successful unless they come under the direct authority of the Burmese government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK continues to support the peace process in Burma directly. We are working with experts with experience of inter-communal trust and peace-building in Northern Ireland to encourage Burma’s own reconciliation efforts. The UK is also contributing £3.5 million in humanitarian food aid for civilians displaced by fighting across Kachin State, including in non-government controlled areas. During my visit I stressed the importance of allowing the unhindered supply of humanitarian assistance to the civilian population. We will continue to work closely with humanitarian partners to monitor needs in the event of any further civilian displacement.“&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60963</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T20:15:58+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T20:15:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-offers-condolences-to-ivory-coast-following-deadly-stampede"/>
    <title>UK offers condolences to Ivory Coast following deadly stampede</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has expressed his sadness following the death and injury of people in a stampede in Ivory Coast.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on a stampede following a New Year’s Eve celebration in the city of Abidjan in Ivory Coast, Foreign Office Minister of State Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am shocked and deeply saddened at the tragic loss of life in a stampede in Ivory Coast, which has also injured hundreds of people. During what should have been a happy and joyous celebration of the New Year, many families are now mourning their loved ones. The UK Government sends its sincere condolences to all the Ivorian people at this time.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60744</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:14:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:14:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/this-week-at-the-foreign-office--105"/>
    <title>This week at the Foreign Office</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A look at the work of the Foreign Office and its embassies overseas this week. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h4 id="queen-elizabeth-land"&gt;Queen Elizabeth Land&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visited the Foreign Office on Tuesday for the final event of her Diamond Jubilee year. The Foreign Secretary William Hague &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii-visits-the-foreign-office" title="Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II visits the Foreign Office"&gt;paid tribute to The Queen&lt;/a&gt;, he said: “You have advanced ideals of peace, friendship, freedom and tolerance, and given on each occasion an immeasurable boost to our country’s reputation overseas.” The Foreign Secretary also announced that the southern part of the British Antarctic Territory has been named &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/queen-elizabeth-land" title=" Queen Elizabeth Land"&gt;‘Queen Elizabeth Land’&lt;/a&gt; in honour of The Queen’s sixtieth year on the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="syria"&gt;Syria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UN Commission of Inquiry on Syria report on the human rights situation in Syria concluded that innocent Syrian civilians are bearing the brunt of escalating armed confrontations between regime and opposition forces. Foreign Office Minister Alistair Burt said that &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/un-report-stark-reminder-of-horrific-human-rights-situation-in-syria" title="UN report stark reminder of horrific human rights situation in Syria"&gt;the UK will continue to support the Commission’s work and ensure that those responsible for these appalling crimes are held to account.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="iran"&gt;Iran&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary spoke about the human rights situation in Iran, specifically the case of the Iranian human rights defender Nasrin Sotoudeh, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/iran-must-uphold-the-rights-and-freedoms-of-its-citizens" title="Iran must uphold the rights and freedoms of its citizens"&gt;addressing Ms Sotoudeh directly in a video message&lt;/a&gt; the Foreign Secretary said: “Be assured that we will continue to hold the Iranian government to account for your terrible treatment. We will not forget you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="israeli-settlements"&gt;Israeli settlements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-responds-to-planned-new-settlements" title="Foreign Secretary responds to planned new settlements"&gt;Foreign Secretary condemned Israeli plans to build 1,500 illegal housing units&lt;/a&gt;  in East Jerusalem. He said: “Settlements undermine the foundations of a two state solution and trust between the parties. This decision, which paves the way for the extension of settlements in East Jerusalem, constitutes a serious provocation and an obstacle to peace.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="tibet"&gt;Tibet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a statement about &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet" title="Human rights in Tibet"&gt;self-immolations and human rights in Tibet&lt;/a&gt;. He said that a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="british-diplomacy-today"&gt;British diplomacy today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Speaker’s lecture series on great offices of state the Foreign Secretary gave a speech on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-foreign-office-one-of-the-great-offices-of-state" title="The Foreign Office, one of the great offices of state."&gt;the history of the Foreign Office and the purpose of British diplomacy today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="digital-strategy"&gt;Digital strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published its &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-fco-digital-strategy" title="FCO digital strategy"&gt;digital strategy&lt;/a&gt; this week. This strategy explains how
we will use digital to improve our work, creating a Foreign Office that is more effective, open and better able to deliver in today’s networked world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="seasons-greetings"&gt;Seasons greetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary William Hague remembered those who will be spending the festive season in places of conflict in his &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/the-foreign-secretarys-christmas-message" title="The Foreign Secretary's Christmas message"&gt;Christmas and New Year message.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="also-this-week"&gt;Also this week&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary marked the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-secretary-marks-anniversary-of-un-declaration-on-holocaust" title="Foreign Secretary marks anniversary of UN declaration on Holocaust"&gt;70th anniversary of the UN declaration denouncing the treatment of Jews in Nazi-occupied Europe.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office published &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/christmas-holiday-travel-advice" title="Christmas holiday travel advice"&gt;tips for British travellers this Christmas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners" title="Britain and the Commonwealth"&gt;speech on the importance of the Commonwealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During 2012, the UK celebrated Her Majesty the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee and hosted the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://storify.com/foreignoffice/12-highlights-of-2012" title="Highlights of 2012"&gt;Read about the highlights of 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch the highlights of 2012: a GREAT year for Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a4E3OMacj1g" title="A GREAT year for Britain"&gt;A GREAT year for Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60061</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:08:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/commonwealth-reform-package-endorsed-by-commonwealth-heads-of-government"/>
    <title>Commonwealth reform package endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The agreed reforms include a new Commonwealth Charter and measures to strengthen work on election observation and human rights.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A landmark Commonwealth Charter and a package of reforms to modernise and sharpen the impact of the Commonwealth have been endorsed by Commonwealth Heads of Government today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings to a close discussion on Commonwealth reform which began at the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Perth, Australia, in October 2011, and included consideration of the Eminent Persons Group report A Commonwealth of the People: Time for Urgent Action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agreed proposals include a new Commonwealth Charter setting out the core values and aspirations of the Commonwealth and its members, and commitments to strengthen the Secretariat’s work on election observation and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister for the Commonwealth, the Rt. Hon. Hugo Swire MP, commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Commonwealth Heads of Government have agreed a new Commonwealth Charter and endorsed a package of reforms to strengthen the Commonwealth. This marks an important milestone in Commonwealth modernisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Commonwealth Ministers devoted a great deal of effort to achieve this result. This reflects our belief that the Commonwealth can make a strong, positive contribution on a range of global issues and nurturing democratic standards worldwide.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The reforms, now adopted, show vision and a genuine desire by all members to increase the Commonwealth’s impact and relevance. All parts of the Commonwealth family must now work together to implement these reforms, to ensure that the organisation is as strong and effective as it can be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The ability to protect core democratic values is central to the Commonwealth’s credibility. I hope that the Charter becomes a useful tool to promote these values throughout the Commonwealth. We look forward to events in the coming months to officially launch the Charter, and will play our part in raising its profile in the UK.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.thecommonwealth.org/news/34580/252051/191212epgcharter.htm"&gt;Commonwealth Secretariat press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-take-steps-to-strengthen-the-commonwealth?id=816829782&amp;amp;view=News"&gt;Ministerial statement, Commonwealth Foreign Affairs Ministers meeting in New York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60069</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T17:47:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-commonwealth-historic-friends-future-partners"/>
    <title>Britain and the Commonwealth: Historic Friends, Future Partners</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire gave a speech about the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth at the Royal Commonwealth Society.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Secretary General; High Commissioners; Honourable Members of both Houses; representatives of businesses and NGOs; Welcome to this Commonwealth reception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I must begin by extending my deepest condolences to the people of Samoa who were hit by Cyclone Evan last week. For all those affected – particularly those who lost loved ones – it was a devastating event. Our High Commissioner has conveyed our sympathy to the Samoan Prime Minister. The Cyclone has now also hit Fiji, and our thoughts are with the many Fijians affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an opportune moment for me to commend the work of the Commonwealth, having had the great privilege of meeting its Head, Her Majesty The Queen, this morning, who came to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office on her final Diamond Jubilee year engagement. My short time speaking to her brought to mind the quite extraordinary role she has played for this country and for countries across the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On 21 April 1947, her 21st birthday, Her Majesty was with her parents and younger sister, Princess Margaret, on a tour of South Africa. In a speech broadcast on the radio from Cape Town, she said to the people of the Commonwealth: “I declare before you all that my whole life whether it be long or short shall be devoted to your service and the service of our great imperial family to which we all belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ever since she said those words, her devotion to the Commonwealth has been unwavering. Her Majesty has travelled more than any other monarch in our history. During her reign she has undertaken well over 150 Commonwealth visits, and in 1998 became the first reigning British monarch to undertake State visits to Brunei and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am sure you would all join me this evening, in this historic Diamond Jubilee year, in paying tribute to her work over the past 60 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So it is a real pleasure to be here this evening, in the run-up to Christmas and Parliamentary recess. I would like to thank Danny Sriskandarajah and Peter Kellner for inviting me to speak, and for their tireless work as Director and Chairman of the Royal Commonwealth Society respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Danny has made a disproportionate contribution to the Society and to the Commonwealth more broadly. The vision he demonstrated in designing and delivering the Commonwealth Conversations project, for example – which was the seed that led to our Eminent Persons Group report – was outstanding. We shall miss his energy, vibrancy and innovation, but wish him well in his new life in South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have long been an admirer of the RCS. It is an organisation with deep roots, but one which is constantly evolving. The Society’s role as a promoter of the Commonwealth brand – whether through engaging young people across the world, encouraging public debate on Commonwealth issues, or through spreading awareness of the cultural diversity of its members – is helping to ensure its continued relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And it is on this relevance that I want to focus this evening. Because one can get the sense that for some – British or otherwise – the Commonwealth is an organisation of the past; one which puts on a good sports event every few years, but isn’t in tune with today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to challenge that assertion; to explain why this Government is placing a greater emphasis on the Commonwealth, and what we are trying to do to unlock its true potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-commonwealth-today"&gt;The Commonwealth today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, set out the Government’s vision for Britain’s foreign policy in July 2010, he spoke of our need to respond to an increasingly networked world. Influence today, he said, “increasingly lies with networks of states with fluid and dynamic patterns of allegiance, alliance and connections”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we are to make the most of the opportunities this creates, and respond to the challenges it represents, we need to make full use of our assets and connections. The Commonwealth, one of the world’s greatest – and oldest – networks, remains one of our most valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was therefore delighted when the Prime Minister appointed me as Minister responsible for the Commonwealth – an organisation I have respected for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both the Foreign Secretary and my much-admired predecessor, Lord Howell – who Frank Field described in a debate last week as a “jewel in the crown” of Commonwealth interest – have together put the “C” back into the “FCO”: the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer in the value the Commonwealth adds on the international stage – politically, economically and culturally. So let me first outline what I think are its greatest strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First and foremost is its sheer scale. Its members account for a third of the world’s population, more than a fifth of the Earth’s total land area and have a combined GDP of over £6 trillion. As a whole, it is an organisation with real clout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Secondly, it is a hugely diverse grouping – bringing together different people, united by our shared language, legal systems and values. From the plains of southern Africa to the island nations of the Pacific, the Commonwealth gives all of its members an equal seat at the international table. It can amplify their voices and make sure the views of even the smallest nations are heard by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the Commonwealth provides tangible support very effectively. A few examples spring immediately to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One is election observation. The Commonwealth has observed over 70 elections since 1990, including recent missions to Ghana and Sierra Leone. On each occasion they have provided a trusted, objective judgement on the credibility of the process, the environment in which the elections took place and the final result. But the observation missions don’t just observe: they also submit recommendations, drawing on collective expertise, on how to improve elections in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I would also point to the Commonwealth Scholarships and Fellowships Programme, through which Commonwealth governments offer scholarships and fellowships to citizens from other member countries. Since it was established 53 years ago, 27,000 people have benefitted – including, as a topical example, Mark Carney, the next Governor of the Bank of England. In Britain, we have supported the scheme to the tune of £87 million for the four years from 2011 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another practical example is technical assistance to promote development in member states, which I know is a very important element of Commonwealth membership for some countries. The Secretariat’s assistance on good governance and the rule of law is helping to build the solid democratic foundations required for sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And I would add to all of this a fourth – and significant – strength: that the Commonwealth is not just about government contacts. Looking around this hall, I can see representatives from a huge range of backgrounds – parliamentarians, businesses, NGOs, civil society, young people. It is these groups that make the Commonwealth so effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-the-commonwealth-is-changing"&gt;How the Commonwealth is changing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth of today is a dynamic, diverse grouping – one of the world’s leading soft power networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But it is not standing still. Like any organisation, the Commonwealth isn’t perfect. All of its members, the United Kingdom included, recognise that to maintain its relevance, the Commonwealth needs to respond to shifting global trends and the rising expectations of its citizens – particularly its younger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the driving force behind the agenda to modernise the Commonwealth, which has been in train since last year’s Heads of Government meeting in Perth. We have all been working hard on this and have made good progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just this week the Secretary-General confirmed that, following discussions in September by Commonwealth Foreign Ministers, the majority of the reform measures proposed by the Eminent Persons Group have been agreed by Heads of Government. That is good news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now that we have agreement on the way ahead, we need to make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Key among the reform measures is the agreement to have a Commonwealth Charter to set out, in a single document, the Commonwealth’s core values. It is important that we now work collectively to raise the Charter’s profile, across the Commonwealth, to embed it within the architecture that ensures members uphold these values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government will, with your help, work to raise the profile of the Charter here in Britain, with a focus on Parliament, civil society and youth organisations. I know the RCS has made its own contribution to this by hosting events on the Charter for civil society organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just as important is the strengthening of the Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group, which should enable the organisation to respond more quickly to infringements of Commonwealth values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the swift response of the Action Group to the situation in the Maldives has shown, we are already starting to see the benefits of these changes. Through this and other country engagements the Action Group works on, it must demonstrate that it is living up to its strengthened mandate and can make a real difference on the world stage. This will make a significant contribution to the credibility of the Commonwealth as an international organisation that adds value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-soft-power-network-of-the-future"&gt;The soft power network of the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An increased focus on the Commonwealth has been a key element of this Government’s re-alignment of Britain’s foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In part, this has involved practical steps like the strengthening of our diplomatic network in Commonwealth countries. We opened a new Deputy High Commission in Hyderabad in India in May, with another in Chandigarh to follow soon. We are also strengthening our commercial capacity in Commonwealth countries like Canada, Sierra Leone, Mozambique, Papua New Guinea and Guyana. And here in London we have increased the number of staff working on the Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But our renewed focus has also involved a change in approach; a change in the way we work, by seeking to make the most of our Commonwealth contacts. When William Hague visited Australia last year it was the first visit by a British Foreign Secretary for 17 years. In the past twelve months, Foreign and Commonwealth Office Ministers have visited around 20 Commonwealth countries – including my recent visit to Belize and, just last week, to Brunei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of this has left us in a strong position to build on the progress we have already made on our Commonwealth agenda. This is important, because there is much work to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Trade and investment is a prime example: we should be pushing to increase the volume of trade among Commonwealth members, and – connected to this – working to increase prosperity across the network by creating the conditions that allow trade to flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Intra-Commonwealth trade already amounts to around £250 billion each year.  But we should be much more ambitious, as the potential is vast. The Commonwealth’s middle class has expanded by one billion people in the last 20 years. These new consumers represent a significant and rapidly growing market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can add to this the Commonwealth’s in-built advantages. Research conducted by this Society two years ago found that when two trading partners were Commonwealth members, their trade was likely to be a third to a half more than when one or both trade partners was non-Commonwealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This ‘Commonwealth effect’ – explained in terms of shared history, values, legal systems and language – should enable us to drive trade to even greater heights. Just look at sub-Saharan Africa, for example: the latest World Bank rankings show that all but four of the top 20 countries in which to do business there are Commonwealth members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But this agenda certainly isn’t just about business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also need to ensure that the Commonwealth stands up for its values and beliefs; that it identifies where its values are not being adhered to; and that it speaks up to turn things around when this happens. The strengthened Commonwealth Ministerial Action Group, for which the Secretary-General has committed to provide additional Secretariat resources, has a critical role here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So too does the Commonwealth Games. The 2014 Games in Glasgow – the Commonwealth’s own Olympics – are as much about promoting Commonwealth values, a key element of its brand, as they are about building prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We also need to develop the Commonwealth’s advocacy role to ensure the voices of its members are heard in international negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And we need to increase the Commonwealth’s engagement with Britain’s Overseas Territories, which share many of the challenges facing small Commonwealth states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth Secretariat’s new Strategic Plan for 2013 to 2016 should help us to address these issues. We are working with the Secretariat to ensure its focus is in areas where it has a comparative advantage, to avoid duplicating the work of other international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Next year will offer several opportunities to drive this work forward. This includes the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Colombo. Ahead of the meeting, we will of course look to Sri Lanka – as we would to any Host – to demonstrate its commitment to upholding the Commonwealth values of good governance and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And I look forward to the Commonwealth Week in March which will offer another opportunity to showcase the organisation’s work. Next year’s theme – ‘Opportunity Through Enterprise’ – is particularly relevant at this time of global economic challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth today is as important as it has ever been. Its members represent some of the most fast-growing, dynamic economies in the world. They are political, social and cultural leaders on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With such collective weight, we shouldn’t be surprised that some – including, recently, the British Parliament’s Foreign Affairs Select Committee – think it is an organisation that should do better. They are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Each and every one of us in this room wants a strong Commonwealth; one which makes the most of its considerable assets. I hope I have made clear this afternoon that it already does a lot of things well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we continue to drive forward the reform process, I am confident that we can build an even more successful Commonwealth – one which does less so it can do it better, focusing on those areas in which it adds the most value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These will include strengthening governance and democracy; increasing the resilience of small and vulnerable states; creating more effective frameworks for inclusive economic growth and sustainable development; ensuring members are able to participate in the global trading system; and improving climate financing frameworks for vulnerable states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And for those that still need convincing of the Commonwealth’s relevance in today’s world, I would say this: if it was not important, if it did not play an influential role on the international stage, countries would not be queuing up to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That this is exactly what is happening at the moment is testament to the continued relevance of the Commonwealth today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wish you all a very happy Christmas and a peaceful New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56976</id>
    <published>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-17T17:22:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-has-serious-concerns-about-human-rights-in-tibet"/>
    <title>UK has serious concerns about human rights in Tibet</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has said that the UK has serious concerns about the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a European Union statement on self-immolations in Tibet, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We strongly support the recent statement from Baroness Ashton about the situation in Tibet. We continue to have serious concerns about the human rights situation there, including the self-immolations in Tibetan regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We urge the Chinese authorities to exercise restraint. At the same time, I join Baroness Ashton in calling on Tibetans not to resort to extreme forms of protest such as self-immolation, and urge their community and religious leaders to use their influence to stop this tragic loss of life. We strongly support the resumption of meaningful dialogue to resolve the underlying grievances of Tibetan communities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I also urge the Chinese government to ensure unrestricted access to the Tibetan Autonomous Region and other Tibetan areas of China for diplomats, international media and other concerned parties. We believe a long term solution is best achieved through respect for universal principles of human rights and genuine autonomy for Tibet within the framework of the Chinese constitution.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/en/cfsp/134378.pdf" title="EU statement on Tibetan self-immolations"&gt;European Union statement on Tibetan self-immolations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the Foreign Office on &lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/foreignoffice" title="@foreignoffice"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.facebook.com/foreignoffice" title="FCO facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel="external" href="https://plus.google.com/s/foreign%20office" title="FCO Google+"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56735</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-15T16:36:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/foreign-office-minister-rt-hon-hugo-swire-mp-britain-believes-in-burma-and-the-burmese-people"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP: "Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people".</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Rt Hon Hugo Swire MP led a trade mission to Burma earlier this week.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all I would like to thank the people of this beautiful country for the very warm welcome I have received here. I have been touched by their remarkable kindness and courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few days I have met leading ministers, civil society and business leaders who have been eager to share with me their aspirations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Government I discussed a full range of issues. I welcomed their efforts on ethnic reconciliation, but registered my serious concerns about the ongoing situation in Kachin urging the government to take all necessary measures to stabilise conditions there and insure the safety of civilians. We continue to urge both sides to bring an end to the conflict.
I raised my serious concerns about the situation in Rakhine State, which I visited this morning, and where thousands of people have displaced by violent unrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this afternoon I had the great honour to meet Daw Aung San Suu Kyi and spoke to her about the many challenges facing Burma, not least the ongoing conflict in Rakhine State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share Daw Suu’s concern about the situation having witnessed for myself the seriousness of the humanitarian situation. Conditions remain extremely worrying. I have visited the IDP camps and seen the thousands of people, crowded into tents, with little food or sanitation, and reliant on aid. It left me in no doubt that without urgent action this tragedy will continue to deepen for all concerned. We spoke about the work of her Parliamentary committee and its recent urging for greater security, humanitarian aid, accountability and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can deliver one message on behalf of the people I met at these camps it is that we need to see determination on all sides to bring an end to this conflict and reach a meaningful political solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Government is already playing its part including working with trusted NGOs to deliver emergency water, sanitation and healthcare to over 58,000 people from both communities. While we are presently the single largest aid provider, much more needs to be done and we are working to rally international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of this country’s broader progress, what everyone wants to see here is rapid development and consolidation of democracy. What does that mean? It means that the country operates under the rule of law with strengthened democratic institutions and with respect for human rights; it means greater trade and prosperity so that people are employed; and it means utilities and services from roads to railways, from accessible credit to clean water, and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end I led a trade mission here focusing on the power sector with the aim of helping this country meet its ambition of a tenfold increase in its energy generation over the next decade. This is the sort of responsible investment we need to see here. Modern energy infrastructure, developed we hope with British expertise, will mean that everyone will have access to electricity in their homes and that manufacturers will be able to invest with confidence and produce things people want to buy. I welcomed the government’s commitment to responsible investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to finish on a positive note. This is a beautiful country with lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain believes in Burma and the Burmese people. The best way we can help is not by ignoring its problems but by working together to tackle them. If we can do that then everyone will be able to enjoy the benefits of a free, developed, and prosperous nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50172</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:14:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/britain-and-the-philippines-partners-for-prosperity"/>
    <title>Britain and the Philippines: Partners for Prosperity</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has given a speech about the growing trade partnership between the UK and the Philippines. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here today, and especially pleased that we are in the company of Foreign Secretary del Rosario. I would like to thank the Makati Business Club, the Management Association of the Philippines and the British Chamber of Commerce for inviting me to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a real thrill to be in the Philippines, on my first official visit to this beautiful country. It is almost 30 years since I was last here, in a personal capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a busy two days ahead and have just come from a very productive meeting with President Aquino, during which we discussed how Britain and the Philippines can work together to tackle today’s global challenges and support each other’s prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on the latter that I will focus today. I will talk first about the United Kingdom’s role in today’s changing world, before setting out why I think Britain and the Philippines can be powerful partners for prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom, like the Philippines, is an island nation – a characteristic which, unsurprisingly, has shaped how we view ourselves and the world around us. Britain is a relatively small place. We had enough but not bountiful natural resources. Combine that with a predisposition towards adventure and discovery, and it led us to build truly global networks and trade links. One thinks of names like Drake, Raleigh and Shackleton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No market was too far or too difficult; no peak too high. Indeed, the globalisation that people tend to view today as a very modern phenomenon has roots that go much deeper. The world in which the Victorians lived was far more integrated in some ways, with Britain sitting at the heart of a global economic system, including a de facto single currency – the Gold Standard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this brought us to South-East Asia. Our ties to countries like Malaysia and Singapore are perhaps best known and are still extremely strong. However, Britain’s links to the Philippines stretch back just as far. The first British Consul arrived as early as 1844. And I am reminded of one of your most famous national heroes, José Rizal, who lived in London’s Primrose Hill in the 1880s. Visitors today will find a blue plaque on the house in which he lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, and particularly in the last couple of decades, I have heard some say that Britain lost sight of the importance of South-East Asia; that our attention was diverted elsewhere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that relationships changed. But while it may have felt to some as if Britain had lost focus, we never went away. The commercial figures alone bear this out. UK trade and investment with South-East Asia today is still far higher than it is with China, despite the exceptional levels of growth and development that China has seen over the past 15 years. That said, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office has under the current Government significantly strengthened this focus, placing an even greater emphasis on our engagement with South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have rebalanced our foreign policy and diplomatic network. On a practical level, that means opening new missions, sending more diplomats to places like the Philippines. We are creating around 50 new jobs across the region. And I am sure many of you will have taken note of last month’s visit to Laos by the Foreign Secretary, William Hague, to reopen the British Embassy there. The UK is now represented in all ten ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking this new approach because we see the emergence and re-emergence of economies across the world – not least the growth and development in Asia – as an opportunity. I believe there is much that we can achieve if we work together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in focus is a key element of my Government’s efforts to deliver sustainable economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from an unbalanced growth model, reliant on government spending, to one based on expanding trade, encouraging inward investment, increasing the share of our economy that comes from exports, and manufacturing the goods that today’s consumers want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to meet our ambitious target to double exports to £1 trillion a year by 2020, we need to grow our exports by eight percent a year. Some of these will go to traditional markets like the European Union, but we are looking increasingly to fast-growing economies in places like South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Europe, the UK is leading the efforts to open up the EU market to trade with other nations. Growth may be slow in Europe – the forecasts suggest we can expect only 0.4 per cent next year – but it is still the biggest marketplace in the world, doing £11 trillion of business every year and encompassing 500 million consumers and 21 million companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving our prosperity agenda forward won’t be easy – the global economic environment clearly remains a challenge. But it is a challenge I am confident Britain can respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we are doing within the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to embed commercial thinking should help. We are now training our diplomats in commercial as well as foreign affairs, and deploying new commercial staff across our diplomatic network. Our Ambassadors increasingly undertake secondments to companies before taking up their postings to gain firsthand commercial experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And despite the often bleak commentary from elements of the media, the British economy has real strengths. Just think of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games held earlier this year. The Games followed hot on the heels of Her Majesty The Queen’s Diamond Jubilee, and showcased to the world Britain’s diversity, openness, creativity and dynamism – politically, culturally and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is renowned for its excellence in financial services, the creative industries and, of course, in education. But as anyone who visited the British Business Embassy at Lancaster House in London during the Olympics would have noticed, we also remain one of the world’s most important manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s car industry, currently undergoing a renaissance, is one such example. We are home to seven global car manufacturers.  Ford, General Motors, Jaguar Land Rover and Mini you will know, but we also have big investments from Honda, Toyota and Nissan too, who produced over 480,000 vehicles in Britain last year. In total, more than one million vehicles and two million engines are produced in the UK each year, and over three-quarters of the vehicles we manufacture are exported. And enthusiasts of faster cars will know that eight Formula One teams have their headquarters in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the UK’s expertise across this and many other sectors makes us a highly compatible partner for the Philippines. I would point, for instance, to finance, where our ICT specialists are helping the Philippine Stock Exchange expand their optic fibre network across the ASEAN region; and to healthcare, where our extensive experience in Public-Private Partnerships is helping the Philippines in their plans to develop a centre of excellence in orthopaedic medicine, modelled on the Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our sectoral expertise is certainly not the only reason. What makes Britain a particularly attractive partner is, I think, the openness of our economy, our transparency and adherence to the rule of law and our firm belief in the rules-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of economic uncertainty, some are inevitably tempted to close ranks and protect domestic industries and markets. But protectionism is a short-term measure with long-term consequences, and in Britain we are taking the opposite approach. History has taught us that more trade, more competitiveness and making the UK open for business and open for investment are what will steer us towards sustainable economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines is heading down the same path, and I would highlight four areas that point towards this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is corruption, which remains a scourge on the global economy. It adds as much as 10 percent to the total cost of doing business globally, and up to 25 percent of the cost of procurement contracts in developing countries. Those who are hardest hit are often the poorest and most vulnerable in society. That is why we are proud to have introduced the Bribery Act in the UK to address this all-too-common problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Aquino’s anti-corruption efforts and business-friendly policies such as the Integrity Initiative and the decision to join the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative are exactly the right thing to be doing – particularly now, during this period of global economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second area is building the infrastructure needed to provide the foundations for long-term prosperity. Modern economies need roads, digital and cellular communications, public transport, schools and hospitals. Without them, we cannot deliver the skilled and trained workforce required to compete in the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third area is ensuring peace and stability. This is perhaps the most crucial platform for prosperity. I am proud that the UK played a small but important role in the framework agreement in Mindanao as a member of the international contact group.  And I would like to take this opportunity to repeat our deepest condolences for the terrible devastation caused there by Typhoon Pablo. Successful implementation of the framework agreement will unlock the economic potential of that area. We are also working closely with Secretary del Rosario and his team to bring about a peaceful resolution of the claims in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connected to international peace and stability is the fourth area: shunning protectionism and embracing free trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ future will not be shaped by growth in the archipelago alone. Whether it is through its overseas workers, the foreign investment that can create jobs, or its export markets abroad, it is clear that future prosperity here will be based on partnerships. This agenda is moving in the right direction.  But I think we can go further and faster. Agreeing a free trade agreement between the EU and the Philippines would be a valuable step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this policy prescription is good for your economy. But it is also vital for your broader development. International trade and investment is not just the best route to development; history tells us it is the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am speaking to you here today because I think – in fact I am certain – that the relationship between Britain and the Philippines can play an important part in promoting our mutual prosperity. We have much in common, and economies that rely on a strong and open global economy. We are democracies, with a strong attachment to human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today Secretary del Rosario marked this growth by signing a joint plan of action that will take our relationship to a new level. This is a genuinely exciting proposition. Our partnership will help to shape the business environment – working together on issues like anti-corruption, competitiveness, economic reform, a low-carbon economy and building awareness about the opportunities for trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade between our countries currently stands at around £1.1 billion. That is impressive, but is I think a fraction of what it can be, particularly when you consider just how fast your country is growing. In this year’s third quarter, growth in the Philippines reached 7.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joint action plan should help us to realise this potential. But we as governments can only do so much. Ultimately, it is businesses that will drive growth. We need your help to generate interest, build awareness and deliver projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore pleased that we have with us today some excellent examples of successful companies operating here –like Standard Chartered Bank, Marks and Spencer and Debenhams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On visas – not always an easy subject – I know that we have a fast, fair and efficient service here, and that we are opening new services to facilitate quick and easy travel for business via Saturday openings, a premium service and a new visa application centre in Cebu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sign that we are indeed open to business is the large number of Filipino overseas workers that are employed in the UK, who are making a valuable contribution to our economy but also sending back remittances to family in the Philippines. Their contribution cuts across many sectors, but is particularly evident in health and care work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that our new visa services will lead to many more visitors travelling between our countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help bring this about, I will sign a new air services agreement later today with Secretary Abaya, and meet Ramon Ang and Philippines Airlines, who hope to start direct flights to London soon. And, incidentally, their passengers will probably be arriving on new aircraft made partly in Britain, following the announcement by Philippines Airlines in August of a $7 billion order from Airbus for over 50 new aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want to share our policy experience in infrastructure development, energy and Public-Private Partnerships so you can learn from our experiences, our successes and, occasionally, our mistakes. When President Aquino visited London in the summer, he went to St Pancras Station, a successful example of how well Public-Private Partnerships can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope what you have heard today is a clear indication of the UK’s role in today’s global economy, of what is happening here in the Philippines and, most importantly, a compelling vision for how Britain and the Philippines can be partners for prosperity, looking to the future with confidence and optimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My visit is just one of what I am confident will be many high-level visits in the coming months. I know that my colleague, the Foreign Secretary William Hague, is keen to visit in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the rest of my programme, and – with your agreement – I will not leave it another 30 years before I return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18382</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T15:40:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-mongolia-round-table-discussions-held-in-london"/>
    <title>UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions held in London</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire met the Mongolian Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs for discussions on defence reform and trade links</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 28 November, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire hosted Damba Gankhuyag, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Mongolia for the tenth UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks focused on commercial relations, foreign policy issues and defence cooperation, with the UK and Mongolia ultimately signing a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to increase defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU is aimed at supporting Mongolian defence reform, in light of its peacekeeping activities in UN operations and its recently joining the OSCE. Through modernising equipment, Mongolia hopes to become even more efficient in supporting international operations in less stable regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global partner, Mongolia is becoming ever closer to the UK, with increasing trade and cultural links. The Minister discussed how best to share the UK’s experience of cultivating and managing investment in both directions to improve bilateral trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks saw the UK and Mongolia strengthen their relationship, on the eve of celebrating the fiftieth Anniversary of diplomatic relations next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI hosted a business session in the afternoon, which was attended by a large number of business representatives discussing Mongolia’s extractive industries, mutually beneficial opportunities and Stock Exchange collaboration. The talks were concluded by a session on education cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the tenth UK-Mongolia Round Table. Held every two years, the talks form a key part of the UK – Mongolia relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/35447</id>
    <published>2012-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:23:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/anglo-korean-society-dinner"/>
    <title>Anglo-Korean Society Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire has talked about the UK and the Republic of Korea's close cooperation on international security, climate change and prosperity.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Warwick for that introduction. I would also like to thank Baroness Perry, who is the reason we are able to meet here in Parliament.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to speak to you this evening, so soon after my visit to South Korea. It was a real thrill to set foot in Korea for the first time, and to do so as we prepare to mark 130 years of diplomatic relations.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bonds between our two countries are longstanding-something I was reminded of recently when I heard of the Korean War Veterans Association’s campaign to commission a war memorial here in Britain, which I am sure everyone in this room would support.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few decades the Republic of Korea has transformed itself. You have become the world’s twelfth-largest economy and a member of the G20; the first nation to transition from aid recipient to membership of the OECD Donors Assistance Committee.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are an economic miracle, a thriving democracy and a growing voice for good in the world today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these characteristics that make it so important for Britain to build a strategic partnership with Korea - one in which we work together, across the board, to achieve our common goals.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are, of course, watching the build-up to the Presidential elections with interest. It seems it will be a close contest. But regardless of who wins on 19 December, we look forward to continuing our close relationship with the new Korean government.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few minutes I want to explain what we have done over the past year to consolidate and build our strategic partnership, but also to consider what more we need to do.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new chapter in relations  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last twelve months have seen an unprecedented stepping up of co-operation between the United Kingdom and Korea.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have deployed more diplomatic staff in Seoul, and British Ministers are visiting more frequently.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, visited Korea in March, with Jeremy Browne following two months later. The then-Defence Minister Peter Luff was in Seoul in June; Energy and Climate Change Minister Greg Barker in October; and Lord Howell, the Foreign Secretary’s personal adviser on energy and resource security, just last week.  Korea was the first Asian country that I visited as a Foreign and Commonwealth Office Minister.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have hosted several high-profile Korean visitors here in London, including Trade Minister Bark, Deputy Minister for Political Affairs Kim Kyou-hyun, your Six Party Talks representative Lim Sung Nam, and senior politicians Sohn Hak-kyu and KIM Moon Soo.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These expanded contacts have helped us to drive forward our relationship like never before.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Host-to-Host agreement we signed in March is increasing commercial co-operation ahead of the 2014 Asian Games in Incheon, the 2015 World Student Games in Gwangju, and the Pyeongchang Winter Olympics in 2018. British company Populous designed the main stadium for the Asian Games, and others such as Colt are plugged into the Incheon supply chain.  The success of the London 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games has left us well-placed to share our experience and to win contracts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On defence, we announced in March that Korean Daewoo Ship and Maritime Engineering would build four new tankers for the Royal Navy, a deal worth £460 million. Shortly afterwards Korea announced that Rolls Royce would supply engines for the next generation of Korean frigates, worth $120 million. We hope to continue to expand this relationship.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June we launched our joint Youth Mobility Scheme, an initiative which in 2013 will enable up to 1000 young people from Korea to live and work in the UK for up to two years.  It grants the same rights to British young people, an opportunity I sincerely hope many will take advantage of.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And during my visit, I met some new North Korean settlers benefitting from our ‘English for the Future’ programme, which is helping to develop the English language skills they need to compete in today’s jobs market.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe we can do more.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scope to do more on security  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together to tackle pressing international problems should be a high priority.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month’s inaugural UK-Korea Strategic Dialogue, which I was pleased to attend the opening of, provided an excellent vehicle to begin this. It was also very timely, as Korea prepares to take its seat on the UN Security Council next year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central to our discussions were Security Council priorities such as the Middle East Peace Process, Syria, Iran and, of course, North Korea - on which I believe Britain can offer a valuable insight, given our presence in Pyongyang. Over the next year, I will be taking a personal interest in ensuring that the UK works closely with Korea to progress our common concerns.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to have a truly strategic relationship we need to look beyond these immediate priorities to the issues that will affect us in the longer-term.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is perhaps the most important of these. By spending two percent of GDP on green growth every year for the past four years; by putting in place domestically-binding emissions targets; and by becoming the first Asian country to pass emissions trading legislation, Korea is showing strong regional leadership  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to this your winning bid to host the Green Climate Fund, and the successful launch of Global Green Growth Institute, and it is clear that you are not just regional leaders on climate change - you are global leaders. New Song Do will be an excellent location for the Green Climate Fund, and I am delighted that Britain will take on the role of Vice President of the Global Green Growth Institute Assembly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are other issues to focus on too. I strongly believe that South Korea can be a powerful voice on human rights, for example - in its neighbourhood and beyond.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a shared commitment to international peacekeeping, having both contributed to efforts in Afghanistan, Lebanon, Haiti and the Horn of Africa. The Korean National Assembly’s recent decision to deploy a contingent of military engineers to South Sudan is welcome. I hope that Korea will continue to expand its efforts in this area.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Korea are active international donors, so we have a shared interest in ensuring that aid is used effectively. Korea is uniquely placed, given its own experience of development, to play a key role in the dialogue between developing and donor countries to help us achieve this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should also work more closely on cyber security. It will not be easy to find an international consensus on rules of the road to guide future behaviour in cyberspace, and to combat the worst abuses of it. But the active engagement of countries like yours will help to take us a step closer. We are looking forward to the cyber conference in Korea next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer partners for prosperity  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the prosperity agenda, too, we have much to gain from closer co-operation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned from Korea last month fascinated by the sheer dynamism of its economy. I am keen to make more British companies excited by the opportunities this dynamism creates - especially new exporters and SMEs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I am pleased that next February, UK Trade and Investment will run a week-long series of events across Britain, ‘Opportunity Korea’, aiming to do just that. British companies are already coming on board and I am personally keen to play a part in ensuring its success.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we need your help to spread the message that Korea is a place with opportunities worth exploring. I would encourage businesses here today with experience of Korea to get involved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU-Korea Free Trade Agreement could also provide a significant boost to our commercial relationship. Of course, it needs to be implemented in a way that does not harm business, but if we get it right it could add £49 billion to EU Korea bilateral trade over the next 20 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common understanding  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we work more together, our countries are also developing a greater common understanding. That is important because, like any relationship, you work best together when you know each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of this year, our Embassy in Seoul commissioned a survey of Korean views of the UK. There were some hugely positive messages to come out of this - not least that participants between the ages of 18 and 30 identified Britain as their favourite overseas country. The enthusiasm for the UK - a genuine warmth I felt when I visited - was clear to see.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the survey also brought out traditional themes. People identified Britain as a “nation of gentlemen” - with grand architecture, a Royal Family and dreary weather.  English football’s Premier League also made an appearance, as did Harry Potter.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the stereotype extended into slightly more unhelpful territory. That behind our castle walls, we Brits are technophobes lacking in creativity and ideas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London 2012 started to challenge these perceptions, showing what today’s Britain is really like: diverse, open, connected, creative, dynamic. I know that message was not lost on our Korean friends.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shortly after the international spotlight had been fixed on the UK, it shifted quickly East - to Korea, to Seoul, and, ultimately, to Gangnam.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am talking, of course, about K-pop sensation ‘Psy’, whose “Gangnam Style” has taken the world, and Britain, by storm.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People across the globe - from members of our Royal Family to the UN Secretary General - have been embracing the rapper’s equestrian dance moves. You will be relieved to hear that I will not be inflicting my own rendition upon you this evening.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being serious for a moment, I think that Psy’s music has given the world, and people here in Britain, a glimpse of the dynamism and vibrancy of modern Korea. It has shown a nation of colour, creativity and confidence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I would like to end today by saying that I see Psy’s success as representing just one small fragment of today’s Global Korea.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are already a world leader in the business world, with companies like Hyundai, Kia, LG and Samsung, household names. As “Gangnam Style” has demonstrated, your music is global too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it should not stop there, and I don’t think it will. With your membership of the G20, your forthcoming role on the UN Security Council and your leadership on issues like climate change - you are becoming a truly global nation in the political sphere.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you look to the years ahead, I hope you will view Britain as one of your closest partners. I am sure that the Anglo-Korean Society will help to ensure that you do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
