<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/hugo-swire</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/hugo-swire.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon  Hugo Swire </title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18382</id>
    <published>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-mongolia-round-table-discussions-held-in-london"/>
    <title>UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions held in London</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 28 November, Foreign Office Minister Hugo Swire hosted Damba Gankhuyag, Deputy Minister, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Mongolia for the tenth UK – Mongolia Round Table discussions at Lancaster House in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks focused on commercial relations, foreign policy issues and defence cooperation, with the UK and Mongolia ultimately signing a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to increase defence cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MoU is aimed at supporting Mongolian defence reform, in light of its peacekeeping activities in UN operations and its recently joining the OSCE. Through modernising equipment, Mongolia hopes to become even more efficient in supporting international operations in less stable regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global partner, Mongolia is becoming ever closer to the UK, with increasing trade and cultural links. The Minister discussed how best to share the UK’s experience of cultivating and managing investment in both directions to improve bilateral trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks saw the UK and Mongolia strengthen their relationship, on the eve of celebrating the fiftieth Anniversary of diplomatic relations next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI hosted a business session in the afternoon, which was attended by a large number of business representatives discussing Mongolia’s extractive industries, mutually beneficial opportunities and Stock Exchange collaboration. The talks were concluded by a session on education cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the tenth UK-Mongolia Round Table. Held every two years, the talks form a key part of the UK – Mongolia relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
