<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/jeremy-browne</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/jeremy-browne.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Jeremy Browne MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27432</id>
    <published>2012-09-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-visits-colombia"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister visits Colombia</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Minister for Latin America Jeremy Browne discussed trade, security, prosperity and improved bilateral relations when he met the President of Colombia Juan Manuel Santos in Bogotá.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fco-on-flickr"&gt;FCO on Flickr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=71649" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/foreignoffice"&gt;&amp;gt; See all photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-press-office"&gt;Contact press office&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enquiries from the media start here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00 44 (0)20 7008 3100&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/contact-press-office/"&gt;Full contact details &amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26867</id>
    <published>2012-09-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:18:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/closer-ties-between-uk-and-new-zealand-on-science-and-innovation"/>
    <title>Closer ties between UK and New Zealand on science and innovation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne and Science and Innovation Minister Dr Mapp have given support for a New Zealand-United Kingdom Science and Innovation Working Group to be set up.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fco-on-flickr"&gt;FCO on Flickr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/apps/slideshow/show.swf?v=71649" alt="embed: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/foreignoffice"&gt;&amp;gt; See all photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="contact-press-office"&gt;Contact press office&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enquiries from the media start here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00 44 (0)20 7008 3100&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/contact-press-office/"&gt;Full contact details &amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27917</id>
    <published>2012-09-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:03+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-meets-singaporean-parliamentary-secretary-for-foreign-affairs"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister meets Singaporean Parliamentary Secretary for Foreign Affairs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne today met Sam Tan, Singaporean Parliamentary Secretary for Foreign Affairs, who is leading the Singapore Delegation to the Paralympics.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meetingn the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is a pleasure to welcome Mr Tan to the UK during our second Paralympics Games. I am sure he will enjoy his time in the UK following the progress of Singapore’s eight representatives over the next two weeks. I wish them all the best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today we discussed the wide range of interests that the UK and Singapore share, including on the economy and other international issues. We both expressed our support for the Convention on the Rights of Disabled Persons, which we feel is of particular significance this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope that this year brings further opportunities for the UK and Singapore to work together, and Mr Tan said that both he and the people of Singapore are looking forward to the visit of the Duke and Duchess of Cambridge this September, in honour of the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28856</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:22:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/human-rights-and-the-olympic-and-paralympic-games"/>
    <title>Human rights and the Olympic and Paralympic Games</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne spoke about human rights and the Olympic and Paralympic Games today</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to welcome you all to this event today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should welcome in particular our keynote speaker, Tara Flood, Chief Executive of the Alliance for Inclusive Education, and gold medallist in the 50-metre breaststroke at the 1992 Paralympics in Barcelona.  As well as an outstanding Paralympic athlete, Tara is a tireless campaigner for disability rights, so it is a privilege to have her with us today.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to welcome the Brazilian Ambassador to the United Kingdom, Mr Roberto Jaguaribe; the Vice Minister of Culture from Korea, Mr KIM Yong-hwan; and the Federal Ombudsman (also President of the National Paralympic Committee) from Russia, Mr Vladimir Lukin.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are gathered here in the Durbar Court to announce a Joint Communique agreed by the United Kingdom, Brazil, Russia and South Korea.  The Communique commits each of us to harness the vast potential of sport, through the Olympic and Paralympic Games, to promote respect for human rights internationally.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport can be a hugely effective driver for change.  It promotes inclusivity, bringing people together to interact, co-operate and strive to achieve common goals.  It can reach out to a diverse cross-section of society and connect and integrate people, regardless of background.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just think of how football has changed attitudes towards race in Britain over the last few decades. Talented players from black and other ethnic communities, and work by football authorities, clubs and campaigns like ‘Kick It Out’ and ‘Show Racism the Red Card’, have made a huge contribution to tackling discrimination. Think of how the Paralympic Games have showcased to a global audience the achievements of disabled people - demonstrating that we should all be judged not by what we cannot do, but what we can.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport can transform the lives of girls and women. It can encourage women’s equal participation in society, build strong leadership and decision-making skills and help to change social attitudes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Games have been the first Olympics at which women from all participating countries had the opportunity to take part.  It was truly inspiring to see Sarah Attar being cheered home in the 800 metres, the first woman from Saudi Arabia to compete in Olympic track and field. And we will never forget Nicola Adams of Team GB, who became the first woman to win Olympic gold in boxing - from which women had been excluded previously.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sport can do even more.  It can help to revitalise disadvantaged areas.  It helps foster development and education for young people.  It promotes good health.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, sport encourages the principles of fair play, teamwork and hard work.  It creates role models.  Think of Mo Farah crossing the finish line in the 5,000 metres final, surely one of the most enduring images of London 2012. After completing his double gold victory, the Somali-born athlete said: “Anything is possible - it’s just hard work and grafting”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in all our interests to take advantage of these powerful traits, which the Olympics only intensify. So we are working hard to achieve a global legacy for the London Games.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our International Inspiration programme is enriching the lives of millions of young people across the world by providing access to high-quality physical education, sport and play.  The programme not only engages children in sport itself.  It also targets lasting change by working with governments on school curricula and national policies, and by training tens of thousands of Young Leaders, teachers and coaches in inclusive sport.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of work we have done on the Olympic Truce has been unprecedented, delivering a UN Resolution co-sponsored by all 193 UN Members and an array of projects overseas to promote conflict resolution and peace.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have sought to make London 2012 the most accessible Games ever to disabled people, including through improving transport facilities.&lt;br&gt;
And with almost all 2.5 million tickets sold, we are setting a new global standard for the Paralympics.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this work does not end when the curtain falls on the Paralympics on 9 September. There is more to do.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have joined forces with future host nations - with Brazil, hosts of Rio 2016, and with Russia and South Korea, hosts of the Winter Games in 2014 and 2018 - in a pledge to use the Games to promote and embed respect for human rights across the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Communique we are announcing today commits us to promote awareness and the application of the UN Universal Declaration on Human Rights. It states that we will seek to educate people to respect diversity; to empower girls and women through sport; and to promote the rights and freedoms of disabled people  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is apt that we are making this commitment during a London Games.  Because it was the year the Games were last held here - 1948 - that saw the origins of the Paralympics and the adoption of the Universal Declaration on Human Rights.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s aim, as hosts of the 2012 Olympiad, is to “inspire a generation”.  205 countries took part this year, and around four billion people - more than half the global population - had their eyes on London. So we have an unrivalled opportunity to reach out to the world.  To show them this fantastic celebration of sport, and the principles of non-discrimination, equality and mutual understanding under which it was founded.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just about creating the Jessica Ennises of tomorrow. It is about inspiring people all over the world to experience the joy of participation in sport, and - even more than that - to work hard in pursuit of their ambitions, to work with people of different backgrounds and beliefs, and to respect the diversity of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27905</id>
    <published>2012-08-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:02+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-meets-hong-kong-secretary-for-home-affairs"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister meets Hong Kong Secretary for Home Affairs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne met the Hong Kong Secretary for Home Affairs, Tsang Tak-Sing to discuss the continuing good relations between the UK and the Special Administrative Region.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They explored how the UK and Hong Kong can work together to strengthen our cultural and sporting ties. The Minister also underlined UK support for Hong Kong’s ongoing constitutional reform.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Tsang is in London as head of the Hong Kong delegation for the Paralympic Games and met the Foreign Office Minister on his previous trip to Asia where the Minister also met and played table tennis with the Hong Kong Olympic and Paralympic squads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hong Kong Government is looking to increase the region’s elite sporting facilities through the construction of a 45,000-seater stadium and is currently building an indoor velodrome on the island. They are also planning to develop a Cultural District in West Kowloon, including an art museum, theatres, concert halls and other performance venues, to boost cultural and entertainment establishments in Hong Kong. We are supporting UK business involvement in these developments, building on our expertise in culture and the arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and Hong Kong are currently working together on the development of international Renminbi (RMB) trading. A private-sector led London-Hong Kong International RMB Forum, announced by the Chancellor in January, met in Hong Kong in May and is set to meet again later this year in London. The Forum further deepens collaboration between the UK and Hong Kong in supporting the wider use of the RMB and aims to develop a common platform for international RMB business across the two global financial centres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27857</id>
    <published>2012-08-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/showcasing-the-foreign-offices-work-on-london-2012"/>
    <title>Showcasing the Foreign Office's work on London 2012</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne has met representatives from the governments and organising committees of the next two Olympic Games to showcase the Foreign Office's work with international partners during London 2012</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brazilian and Russian delegations are visiting the UK as part of the Olympic Games Observer Programme. As part of the programme the delegation were briefed on the work of the Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office’s 2012 Co-ordination Centre as well as visiting the GREAT Pavilion at the Foreign Office.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Office Minister Browne said “I am very pleased to welcome Mr Chernyshenko and Mr Fortes as the hosts of the next Winter Olympics in Sochi and Summer Olympics in Rio.  I am glad that we can pass on some of the lessons we have learnt from our experience.  Every Games is different, but international cooperation and harmony is a thread we believe can, and should, run through them all.  I hope that the observer programme continues to deepen the important links between our countries.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chernyshenko, CEO of Sochi 2014, said “The London 2012 and Sochi 2014 Games are once-in-a-generation moments for both our countries. For myself and my team, getting to take part in the Observer Programme has been of enormous benefit as we continue our own preparations. Ever since London won the bid, we’ve been fortunate enough to work closely with the team to ensure we too can also deliver a fantastic Games.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcio Fortes, President of the Brazilian Public Olympic Authority said “I think that with the UK’s support, we will host one of the most important Games in history. It is important to say that there is a very close cooperation between Brazilians and the British through our Government Olympic Observer Programme, there is an unique friendship.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47050</id>
    <published>2012-08-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:24:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-tonga-close-historical-ties"/>
    <title>UK and Tonga: close historical ties</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne met His Royal Highness The Crown Prince of Tonga in London today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK and Tonga have close historical ties and it is my pleasure to welcome The Crown Prince to the UK. I would like to express the UK’s gratitude for Tonga’s continued support in Afghanistan. We are proud to have Tongan troops serving alongside British forces.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Royal Highness has been visiting London for the 2012 Games and has followed the Tongan national team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27847</id>
    <published>2012-08-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/there-and-back-again-a-chinese-olympians-tale"/>
    <title>There and back again: a Chinese Olympian's tale</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Sixty-four years after he first set foot in the UK to play Olympic basketball for his country, Mr Wu Chengzhang has returned: and this time, it’s personal.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The eighty-eight year old former-athlete wrote to the British Ambassador in Beijing to express his desire to see his team play in London once more, and now he is joining forces with Ministers, athletes and well-wishers to promote the Games to the next generation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1948 at the age of twenty-four, Mr Wu travelled to London as part of a thirty-three strong Chinese squad hoping for Gold. He scored thirty two points in one of his games against Iraq, setting a record for the highest personal score for one game.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His team only reached as far as the quarter-finals in 1948 but today, as he travels to London 2012’s basketball arena to see Great Britain play China once more, he will be hoping that history does not repeat itself.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One man who will be hoping it does however will be Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne, who is today hosting Mr Wu at the Foreign Office’s GREAT Pavilion. Taking the visitor on a tour of the area, which currently contains an Olympic exhibition including the 1948 torch, he said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to welcome Mr Wu to London for the 2012 Olympics. As a great competitor from the London Games in 1948, I am pleased he will have the opportunity to watch the UK play China in basketball, 64 years since he played in the same fixture.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit to London Mr Wu was also been reunited with one of the men who played against him all those years ago: British basketball player Lionel Price. Mr Price has been showing Mr Wu the sights and sounds of London, and how it has changed over the past six decades.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following his Olympic career, Mr Price went on to become a furniture manufacturer and property developer in the UK before retiring in 2006. Mr Wu returned to China, where he played and coached basketball in his hometown of Shanghai until he retired. He is much respected in China as one of the country’s last remaining 1948 Olympians.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27840</id>
    <published>2012-08-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-calls-for-abolition-of-the-death-penalty-in-japan"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister calls for abolition of the death penalty in Japan</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne spoke after two executions in Japan on 3 August.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was very disappointed to learn that Japan has carried out two executions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whilst I recognise the seriousness of the crimes for which these two individuals were convicted, it is the longstanding policy of the British Government to oppose the death penalty in all circumstances, in Japan as elsewhere. There is no conclusive evidence that it has any value as a deterrent, its use undermines human dignity and any miscarriage of justice is irreversible and irreparable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope that the Government of Japan will take note of the international trend towards abolition and move to formally establish a moratorium with a view to eventual abolition of the death penalty.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27836</id>
    <published>2012-08-03T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:20:50+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foreign-office-minister-meets-president-of-fiji"/>
    <title>Foreign Office Minister meets President of Fiji</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne met the President of Fiji Ratu Epeli Nailatikau in London on 3 August.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the meeting the Foreign Office Minister said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The President of Fiji and I had a positive meeting at the Foreign Office this afternoon where we discussed the current situation in Fiji. I underlined the importance of a strong civil society and respect for human rights.  We also discussed recent progress towards free and fair elections in 2014. The UK wants this process to succeed and is ready to assist in this important work along with our international partners. I look forward to working more closely with Fiji in the coming months.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
