<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/jo-swinson</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/jo-swinson.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Jo Swinson MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57049</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T11:47:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/press-release-boost-for-business-as-government-sets-out-plans-to-update-employment-legislation"/>
    <title>Press Release: Boost for business as government sets out plans to update employment legislation</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes to collective redundancies rules to help employees and businesses were announced by Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government announced it plans to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the current 90 day minimum period, before very large scale redundancies can take place, to 45 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;legislate to make clear that fixed term contracts which have reached the end of their natural life are excluded from obligations for collective redundancies consultation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introduce new non-statutory Acas guidance to address a number of key issues affecting collective redundancies consultation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment Relations Minister, Jo Swinson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The UK has a labour market that is flexible, efficient and fair but some of our laws need reform to respond to an ever changing employment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to improve the quality of consultations by making sure that there are tools available to help employers manage this process fairly and successfully to deliver the best possible outcomes for all parties.  Acas will be working with stakeholders to produce non-statutory guidance that will be designed to help improve the quality of consultations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have listened to stakeholders and there is a strong argument for shortening the minimum period which is backed up by hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The process is usually completed well within the existing 90-day minimum period, which can cause unnecessary delays for restructuring, and make it difficult for those affected to get new jobs quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our reforms will strike an appropriate balance between making sure employees are engaged in decisions about their future and allowing employers greater certainty and flexibility to take necessary steps to restructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement responds to a consultation launched in June and to calls for improvements to the way collective redundancies rules operate and for the processes involved to be made easier to understand. It also forms part of the Government’s commitment to review employment law to support business and concentrate on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replacement of the current 90 day period to 45 days will still allow full employee engagement and offer employee representatives a statutory right to contribute to the process. The new 45 day period will be a minimum period, and businesses may consult for longer where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will be made through secondary legislation. Draft regulations will be laid in the New Year and the changes are expected to be made by 6 April 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Coalition government started a systematic review of employment law in 2010. This Employment Law Review (ELR) is now half way through its work and aims to provide clarity, certainty and give businesses the confidence to manage their workforce effectively. The Review sits alongside the Employment Law-related Red Tape Challenge to reduce regulatory burdens on business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the government’s response to Collective
Redundancies can be found at
&lt;a href="/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules"&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/collective-redundancies-consultation-on-changes-to-the-rules
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill sets out a comprehensive series of reforms aimed at supporting businesses, developers, and first time buyers by slashing red tape that delays or discourages business investment, development or job creation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government’s economic policy objective is to achieve ‘strong, sustainable and balanced growth that is more evenly shared across the country and between industries’. It set four ambitions in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://cdn.hm-treasury.gov.uk/2011budget_growth.pdf"&gt;‘Plan for Growth’ (PDF 1.7MB)&lt;/a&gt;, published at Budget 2011:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create the most competitive tax system in the G20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To make the UK the best place in Europe to start, finance and grow a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To encourage investment and exports as a route to a more balanced economy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To create a more educated workforce that is the most flexible in Europe
Work is underway across government to achieve these ambitions, including progress on more than 250 measures as part of the Growth Review. Developing an Industrial Strategy gives new impetus to this work by providing businesses, investors and the public with more clarity about the long-term direction in which the government wants the economy to travel.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/39717</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T20:53:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/groceries-adjudicator-to-have-power-to-fine-supermarkets"/>
    <title>Groceries Adjudicator to have power to fine supermarkets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Groceries Code Adjudicator is to be given new powers to fine large supermarkets who deal with suppliers unfairly.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competition minister Jo Swinson has today announced that the Groceries Code Adjudicator will be given greater powers to enforce the Grorceries Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a change likely to be widely welcomed by suppliers and farmers, the government listened to the concerns from stakeholders to give the Adjudicator more teeth to protect suppliers from unfair treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Adjudicator finds that retailers are breaching the Groceries Code and treating their suppliers unlawfully or unfairly, he or she will be able to apply a range of sanctions. In most cases, this would consist of recommendations or ‘naming and shaming’ but, if the breach is serious enough, the Adjudicator will have an immediate power to fine the retailer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Adjudicator is being established after the Competition Commission identified competition issues in their 2008 market study. The Adjudicator will be able to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrate disputes between retailers and suppliers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate confidential complaints from direct and indirect suppliers, whether in the UK or overseas, and from third parties.* &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hold to account retailers who break the rules by ‘naming and shaming’ or, if necessary, imposing a fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jo Swinson said, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The food industry plays an important role in economic growth, and the Groceries Code Adjudicator will help to ensure that the market is operating in a fair and healthy way. Large supermarkets form a big chunk of this industry, and generally provide consumers with low prices and variety whilst providing business for farmers and suppliers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But where supermarkets are breaking the rules with suppliers and treating them unfairly, the Adjudicator will make sure that they are held to account. We have heard the views of the stakeholders who were keen to give the Adjudicator a power to fine, and recognise that this change would give the Adjudicator more teeth to enforce the Groceries Code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We expect fines to be used as a last resort, but the fact that the Adjudicator has the power to impose them will send a strong message to retailers that compliance with the Code is not optional. I am confident that these changes will mean that the Adjudicator is able to ensure fair play in the food supply chain and keep the industry growing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Adjudicator will publish guidance within six months after the Bill comes into effect to propose the maximum amount he or she will be able to fine. Retailers would have a full right of appeal against any fines imposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/Groceries-Adjudicator-to-have-new-power-to-fine-supermarkets-68464.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: Groceries Adjudicator to have new powers to fine supermarkets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/groceries-code-adjudicator-bill"&gt;Groceries Code Adjudicator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/business-law/competition/market-studies/cc-market-investigation-on-the-uk-supply-of-groceries"&gt;Competition Commission Market Investigation on the Supply of Groceries in the UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/groceriescodeadjudicator.html"&gt;Follow the progress of the Groceries Code Adjudicator Bill on the Parliament website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47154</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data"/>
    <title>New power to boost consumers access to data</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Jo Swinson announces new powers for consumers to request their personal customer data from business, under the midata programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;19 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers will be given new powers to request their personal customer data from business, helping them manage their money better and make better lifestyle choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/next-steps-making-midata-a-reality"&gt;consultation this summer&lt;/a&gt;, the Government will announce that it will look to legislate if companies fail to comply with the voluntary release of consumers’ electronic data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;Read the government’s response to the consultation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under new plans, companies would have to release data they hold relating to a consumer’s consumption or transactions in an electronic machine readable format, upon request. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with the power to legislate will be focussed on three ‘core’ sectors: current accounts and credit cards, mobile phones and energy, with further powers to extend the legislation to other sectors if appropriate.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment and Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“‘midata’ is all about putting power into the hands of consumers. Many businesses reap huge commercial benefits from the information they gather from consumers’ daily spending patterns. Why shouldn’t consumers also benefit from this by having access to their own data to enable them to make better choices?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great when your energy provider tells you how much gas or electricity you’re using at any point in the year or when phone companies tell you which one of their tariffs suits you best. But it’s even better when consumers can use that information to get better value for money deals or adjust their lifestyles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is just one of many ways ‘midata’ can help, as businesses increasingly recognise sharing data as a means to deliver a better service for their customers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data/midata-future-10-ways-it-could-shape-your-choices"&gt;A midata future: 10 ways it could shape your choices &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data-68373.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New power to boost consumers’ access to data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;m&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data"&gt;idata - access and control your personal data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;midata review and consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/47154</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:30:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data"/>
    <title>New power to boost consumers access to data</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Jo Swinson announces new powers for consumers to request their personal customer data from business, under the midata programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;19 Nov 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers will be given new powers to request their personal customer data from business, helping them manage their money better and make better lifestyle choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/news/topstories/2012/Aug/next-steps-making-midata-a-reality"&gt;consultation this summer&lt;/a&gt;, the Government will announce that it will look to legislate if companies fail to comply with the voluntary release of consumers’ electronic data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;Read the government’s response to the consultation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under new plans, companies would have to release data they hold relating to a consumer’s consumption or transactions in an electronic machine readable format, upon request. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with the power to legislate will be focussed on three ‘core’ sectors: current accounts and credit cards, mobile phones and energy, with further powers to extend the legislation to other sectors if appropriate.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment and Consumer Affairs Minister Jo Swinson said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“‘midata’ is all about putting power into the hands of consumers. Many businesses reap huge commercial benefits from the information they gather from consumers’ daily spending patterns. Why shouldn’t consumers also benefit from this by having access to their own data to enable them to make better choices?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great when your energy provider tells you how much gas or electricity you’re using at any point in the year or when phone companies tell you which one of their tariffs suits you best. But it’s even better when consumers can use that information to get better value for money deals or adjust their lifestyles.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is just one of many ways ‘midata’ can help, as businesses increasingly recognise sharing data as a means to deliver a better service for their customers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data/midata-future-10-ways-it-could-shape-your-choices"&gt;A midata future: 10 ways it could shape your choices &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/Press-Releases/New-power-to-boost-consumers-access-to-data-68373.aspx"&gt;Press Notice: New power to boost consumers’ access to data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;m&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/consumer-issues/consumer-empowerment/personal-data"&gt;idata - access and control your personal data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/Consultations/midata-review-and-consultation?cat=closedwithresponse"&gt;midata review and consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
