<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/justine-greening</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/justine-greening.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Justine Greening MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-10-14T20:36:02+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14204</id>
    <published>2012-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-14T20:36:02+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/alan-cook-reappointed-non-executive-chairman-of-highways-agency"/>
    <title>Alan Cook reappointed non-executive chairman of Highways Agency</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Alan Cook has been reappointed as non-executive chairman of the Highways Agency Board for another 12 months.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alan Cook has been reappointed by Transport Secretary Justine Greening as non-executive chairman of the Highways Agency Board for a further 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook, who was first appointed in January 2011, will focus on supporting the Transport Secretary’s ambitious programme for reforming the strategic road network while ensuring that the Agency continues to deliver its business against tough efficiency targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Penning, Minister for Roads said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a challenging time for the Highways Agency but I am confident that Alan Cook is the right person to work with Ministers towards achieving the Agency’s transformation into a more efficient, business-like and commercially-focused operator, which crucially does much more to listen and respond to the needs of road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His extensive experience will also help support the Agency in taking forward my roads reform agenda to improve how we operate, maintain and enhance our major roads which are the backbone of Britain, getting people to and from work, powering the economy and keeping families connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, the Transport Secretary published her response to Alan Cook’s independent review of the strategic road network. The Transport Secretary also set out ambitious plans to increase the quality and efficiency of the network, offering a better service to motorists and business users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook’s role will see him providing advice to senior staff and making sure the Agency delivers on changes identified in his independent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He will also offer advice on organisational change and provide views on alternative operating models which are currently being developed as part of a feasibility study announced by the Prime Minister in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the opportunity to continue in the role of chairman for a further 12 months in order to both assist with the crucially important feasibility study and also help the Agency mobilise its own change programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This programme will deliver the changes identified in the government’s response to my independent review with the aim of the Highways Agency becoming a best-in-class executive agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20110110/"&gt;press release announcing Alan Cook’s appointment as the first ever non-executive chairman of the Highways Agency&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Transport Secretary’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120524c"&gt;strategic road network reform announcement in May&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/strategic-roads-network"&gt;Alan Cook’s report ‘A Fresh start for the Strategic Road Network’&lt;/a&gt; is available on both the Department’s and the Agency’s websites. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14207</id>
    <published>2012-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-17T10:59:50+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/4-5-billion-investment-in-new-trains-creates-new-jobs"/>
    <title>£4.5 billion investment in new trains creates new jobs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>596 railway carriages will be built at a brand new train factory in the north east of England.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 900 jobs will be created and thousands more secured after Transport Secretary Justine Greening approved a £4.5bn contract to supply Britain with the next generation of intercity trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a major boost to the UK’s manufacturing industry, 596 railway carriages will be built at a brand new train factory in the north east of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility Trains, a consortium made up of Hitachi and John Laing, has been awarded the contract to build and maintain the trains under the Intercity Express Programme (IEP), the project to replace Britain’s Intercity 125 trains with new higher capacity modern trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitachi will assemble an intercity fleet of 92 complete trains at a new purpose-built factory in Newton Aycliffe, County Durham, in the process creating 730 skilled jobs with a further 200 jobs during construction of the factory itself and securing thousands more in the UK supply chain. The company will also locate its European rail research and development capabilities on the site which will further enhance the factory’s ability to win rail contracts across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as building the new state-of-the-art assembly facility, Hitachi will construct maintenance depots in Bristol, Swansea, west London and Doncaster, and will upgrade existing maintenance depots throughout Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement comes on the eve of the Global Investment Conference in London where the government will kick off the largest series of trade and investment events ever held in the UK involving more than 3,000 business leaders, policy-makers and ministers from around the world, and half the companies in the FTSE 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Justine Greening said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A new train factory is fantastic news for Britain and will be welcomed by everyone who wants to see a thriving UK manufacturing sector. It means 730 new skilled jobs created at the factory, 200 jobs in constructing the plant and thousands of jobs secured in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The decision to build almost 600 new intercity train carriages is great for rail passengers who will experience faster and more comfortable journeys when travelling across Britain on the East Coast and Great Western main lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hitachi is the latest major international company to invest on this scale in Britain and I look forward to this new factory in County Durham following in the footsteps of Nissan’s successful car plant in Sunderland. There can also be fewer stronger signs that the UK is the best place in which to invest, and from which to develop new markets, than Hitachi’s decision to base its European manufacturing base right here in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IEP train fleet will be comprised of electric and bi-mode trains, some five vehicles long and others nine vehicles. These will be faster accelerating than existing stock, and will offer the potential for more frequent services. The higher train capacity will mean more seats and less crowding between Britain’s major cities. The modern vehicles will offer a step-change in passenger comfort through increased carry-on luggage space, electronic seat reservations, and no compromise on leg-room. A performance regime will encourage the trains to run reliably throughout the life of the fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IEP builds on last week’s rail investment announcement of further electrification on the Great Western Main Line between London Paddington and Swansea, and together the new trains and infrastructure will offer the potential for journey time savings of 15 minutes in Swansea to London journeys and 21 minutes in Bristol to London journeys as part of the forthcoming Great Western franchise. Passengers travelling along the East Coast Main Line will also see improvements to their travelling experience, as journeys between London and Newcastle will potentially be reduced by 13 minutes in the forthcoming East Coast franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction at the Newton Aycliffe site is expected to begin in 2013 and will be fully operational by 2015. The first IEP trains will enter revenue-earning service on the Great Western Main Line in 2017 and on the East Coast Main Line by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s Global Investment Conference at the British Business Embassy in Lancaster House, London, will be followed by 17 Global Business Summits to be held throughout the duration of the Games and will be targeted at individual sectors and countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IEP is the programme to replace Britain’s fleet of Intercity 125 High Speed Trains (HSTs) that were originally deployed by British Rail in the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This announcement signifies financial close for the Great Western elements of IEP, and commercial close for the East Coast elements. The East Coast elements will be financed during 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The eventual service pattern will be the responsibility of the future franchisees, although the first phase of the new trains could operate on the following routes:  &lt;br&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great Western: London - Cardiff - Swansea, London - Oxford - Worcester - Hereford, London - Gloucester - Cheltenham, London - Bath - Bristol  &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;East Coast: London - Leeds, London - York - Newcastle - Edinburgh - Aberdeen / Inverness   &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are also options for ordering further trains, which could operate on the following routes: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great Western: London - Exeter - Penzance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;East Coast: Replacement of the newer Intercity 225 electric stock&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;East Coast: London - Cambridge - Kings Lynn&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;West Coast: London - Milton Keynes - Northampton&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The contract structure passes the responsibility for constructing depots and maintaining trains to Agility Trains. The Train Operating Company will pay Agility Trains “Set Availability Payments” for each train that reports for duty each day and remains reliable during the operational period. The Department is providing a “Usage Guarantee” to Agility that a Train Operating Company will be in place to make use of the new trains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the first time in recent history that a bi-mode train has been earmarked for the UK rail network. Bi-mode trains are common on some mainland European national rail systems. Both the electric and bi-mode versions of these trains will include regenerative braking, a system whereby electricity is re-cycled back through the overhead wires when the driver applies the brakes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introducing the bi-mode option for the Intercity Express Programme is estimated to save around £200 million (net present value) as compared to introducing a fleet of all-electric trains to be coupled to a diesel locomotive beyond the electrified sections of the railway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 125 mph (200kph) trains will reduce overcrowding as they will be longer; the new carriages will be 26m in length as opposed to the 23m in Intercity vehicles currently in UK use. 26m vehicles are standard in mainland Europe. The faster journey times will also allow operators to run more frequent services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DeddoFChmm8&amp;amp;feature=context-cha"&gt;Hitachi Intercity Express Train CGI film&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uZ0B2Mv_CiE"&gt;Animation of planned Hitachi Rail Europe manufacturing plant in Newton Aycliffe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/topics/iep"&gt;Intercity Express Programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14826</id>
    <published>2012-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-14T20:18:26+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/innovative-new-proposals-for-a14-corridor"/>
    <title>Innovative new proposals for A14 corridor</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The government today announced proposals for major investment along the A14 corridor in Cambridgeshire.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government today announced proposals for major investment along the A14 corridor in Cambridgeshire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major new road scheme involving tolling will be added to the Department for Transport’s programme of major projects. Subject to agreement with interested local authorities on a funding package and decisions at the next spending review construction work could begin by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plans are designed to address congestion and long term capacity issues on and around the strategically crucial A14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They include a new bypass to replace the existing road around Huntingdon and upgrades along the A14 as far east as Milton. Two new roads would be built in parallel to, with one on each side of, the current A14 immediately north of Cambridge for local use. Meanwhile, the existing A14 carriageway will be upgraded through the removal of accesses and junctions, and improvements to junctions at the northern and southern ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study work has confirmed that funding for these can be generated in part through tolling a length of the enhanced A14, featuring around 20 miles of new or widened road. However, more work will be taken to determine the best tolling solution, including what length the tolled section should be, how users would pay and what the tariff should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schemes will now enter the DfT roads programme and begin detailed design and statutory processes. They are dependent on local government and commercial decision making and will now be considered in more detail by the relevant local authorities and local enterprise partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Justine Greening said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The A14 is a crucial strategic route for the east of England, vital not only for international road traffic using the port of Felixstowe but everyone who relies on it daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is why my department has been working hard to generate innovative and imaginative solutions to tackling long term congestion and I am pleased to be able to unveil what we believe to be the best option for people living locally as well as those who see it as a lifeline to international markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It demonstrates yet again that this coalition government is focused on delivering economic growth and our determination to do everything we can to support delivery of key national infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The A14 road improvement package includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Widening of the Cambridge Northern Bypass between Milton and Girton and enhancement of the Girton Interchange;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provision of high standard roads for local traffic use running in parallel to an enhanced A14 carriageway between Girton and the area near the current Trinity Foot A14 junction;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction of a bypass to the south of Huntingdon between the area near Trinity Foot and the A1, at both ends tying in with the existing A14.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major road scheme between Ellington and Fen Ditton was cancelled in 2010 on affordability grounds. Since then the DfT has been working with local authorities and businesses through the A14 Challenge on alternatives to the previous scheme. Today’s announcement is the outcome of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also identified a package of desirable rail investment that will include major improvements at Ely, Peterborough and Leicester, which will enable more freight to be carried by rail between Felixstowe and Nuneaton. The Secretary of State has allocated £200m to the Strategic Freight Network to fund network enhancements of this kind at the request of the rail freight industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also announced today is government support for a package of local public transport improvements which could include: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commercial express bus services between Peterborough and Cambridge;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A new park &amp;amp; ride site at Alconbury;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Park &amp;amp; ride bus services to Cambridge via the Busway;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A new ‘Number 5’ local bus service from Bar Hill to Cambridge via Science Park and Cambridge Science Park station.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13796</id>
    <published>2012-07-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T11:08:47+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/high-speed-rail-phase-1-consultation-update"/>
    <title>High Speed Rail: phase 1 consultation update</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Justine Greening MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 10 January this year, I made a statement to the House announcing my decision to take forward proposals for a national high speed rail network following the completion of a major public consultation exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 29 May, the consultation responses were made available online. Subsequently, when it became clear that a small number of responses had not been published, my department and HS2 Ltd reviewed how the consultation responses had been processed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This review identified that 413 responses, amounting to less than one per cent of the 55,322 responses received in total, had not been included in the part of the consultation response assessment carried out by the government’s independent response analysis consultants, Dialogue by Design. The results of this analysis were summarised in their report published alongside my announcement of 10 January (High Speed Rail: Investing in Britain’s Future - consultation summary report). This report formed just one of the elements supporting my decisions, alongside other evidence including analysis of issues raised in consultation responses carried out by my department and HS2 Ltd, as well as engagement with the public, MPs and other stakeholders through roadshow events, seminars, visits and meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 413 responses identified, six had been incorrectly marked as duplicates by Dialogue by Design. The remaining 407 were amongst those sent in by email to my department rather than via the direct channels set out in the consultation document and were unintentionally not forwarded to Dialogue by Design for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My department commissioned a supplementary analysis from Dialogue by Design which concluded that these responses “do not provide any information that was not already included in the previous consultation summary report or would have made a difference to the substantive content or balance of that report”. Inclusion in the original analysis would not have changed the substance of Dialogue by Design’s findings, nor affected the considerations which informed me in taking my decisions following the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All affected respondents will be contacted with these details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120822180117/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/high-speed-rail-addendum/"&gt;High speed rail: investing in Britain’s future consultation summary report addendum, 20 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120817045408/http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hs2-maps-20120110/"&gt;HS2 revised line of route maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13792</id>
    <published>2012-07-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-24T10:43:52+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/implementation-of-the-penfold-review"/>
    <title>Implementation of the Penfold Review</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Justine Greening MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing a consultation document detailing proposals to simplify the process of applying for the stopping up or diversion of a highway, where this is required for the purpose of property development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Penfold Review examined various development consents, additional to planning permission, which developers must apply for. It identified measures the government could take to minimise the burden of complying with and administering these consents, while maintaining the essential benefits that they protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose to permit applications for a stopping-up or diversion order to be submitted at the same time as applying for planning permission, whereas under existing legislation the developer can only apply after securing planning permission, and are consulting on options for devolving decision-making to the local authority level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These measures were committed to in the 2011 Autumn Statement and will help to deliver the government’s growth agenda, by removing unnecessary burdens faced by businesses, speeding up the application process and removing unnecessary bureaucracy. They will play a useful role in encouraging investment and therefore growth in local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the policy options in the consultation will require primary legislation to amend the Town and Country Planning Act 1990, as it applies to England. Subject to the outcome of the consultation, we intend to deliver this through the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document, including impact assessment, will be available in the libraries of both Houses and on the department’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120820123759/http://dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-36/"&gt;Stopping up and diversion orders: reform of the application process for local highways, 16 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14830</id>
    <published>2012-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T18:58:39+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/investing-in-rail-investing-in-jobs-and-growth"/>
    <title>Investing in rail, investing in jobs and growth</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>More than £9 billion of growth-boosting railway upgrades across England and Wales.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than £9 billion of growth-boosting railway upgrades across England and Wales - representing faster journey times, more reliable services and capacity for 140,000 extra daily commutes by train - have been announced by Transport Secretary Justine Greening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full £9.4bn programme of improvements to the rail network published today will meet the needs of intercity passengers, commuters and freight up to the end of this decade while the government continues to work on High Speed 2 to deliver rail capacity for the British economy in the decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/"&gt;‘High Level Output Specification’ programme&lt;/a&gt; for 2014-2019 will be discussed at today’s meeting of the Cabinet which the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister will hold outside London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crossrail, Thameslink, and electrification between London and Cardiff, Manchester to Liverpool and Preston, and across the Pennines, are among £5.2bn of projects already committed to during 2014-2019. New schemes totalling £4.2bn unveiled today include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Upgrades to stations and tracks creating enough capacity around cities for an additional 140,000 daily rail commutes at peak times. In addition to Crossrail and Thameslink, announced previously, today’s enhancements - such as the £350m lengthening of platforms at London Waterloo station - will provide capacity for 120,000 more daily commutes in and out of London and 20,100 extra daily commutes across Birmingham, Leeds, Manchester and other cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Faster journeys and more train capacity from £240m of improvements along the East Coast Main Line from the North East down through Yorkshire, Lincolnshire and Cambridgeshire to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The creation of a high-capacity “electric spine” running from Yorkshire and the West Midlands to South Coast ports allowing more reliable electric trains to cut journey times and boost capacity for passengers and freight. This comprises: an £800m electrification and upgrade from Sheffield - through Nottingham, Derby and Leicester - to Bedford, completing the full electrification of the Midland Main Line out of London St Pancras; and electrification of the lines from Nuneaton and Bedford to Oxford, Reading, Basingstoke and Southampton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The landmark decision to take electric rail beyond Cardiff to Swansea, completing the full electrification of the Great Western Main Line out of London Paddington at a total cost of more than £600m, and electrifying the Welsh Valley lines, including Ebbw Vale, Maesteg and the Vale of Glamorgan. These will give two-thirds of the Welsh population access to new fleets of electric trains helping to generate Welsh jobs and growth by slashing journey times and boosting passenger and freight capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Completion in full of the “Northern Hub” cluster of rail enhancements with the approval of £322m of outstanding track and capacity upgrades across Manchester city centre, Manchester Airport and across to Liverpool. These are in addition to £477m of Northern Hub schemes already approved across the North of England such as electrification of the North Trans Pennine route between York and Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A new £500m rail link between the Great Western Main Line and Heathrow allowing direct services to the airport for passengers from the West Country, the Thames Valley and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HLOS package will be funded in part from fare rises already announced in 2010 and also from the substantial efficiency savings which projects like electrification will have on the long term operating costs of the railways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Justine Greening said:
&amp;gt; Investment on this scale, in every region of the country, shows how this coalition government is focused on delivering an affordable, reliable and faster railway network that drives jobs and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These plans to increase capacity and shorten journey times on intercity, commuter and freight services are, alongside our plans for high speed rail, absolutely key to securing our country’s prosperity in the decades ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment was also hailed by the Prime Minister, Deputy Prime Minister and Chancellor of the Exchequer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From Crossrail, high speed rail and now the billions of pounds of investment we are announcing today, this government is committed to taking the long term decisions to deliver growth and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In what is the biggest modernisation of our railways since the Victorian era this investment will mean faster journeys, more seats, better access to stations, greater freight links and a truly world class rail network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the biggest expansion in railways in over 150 years, with more than £9bn of investment across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst we inherited a deficit greater than any in our nation’s peacetime history, we knew that we had to give the country the boost it needs, to build great railways and make journeys better for the millions of hard working people who use the train every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Electric Spine’ will make a significant difference for passengers linking London, the Midlands and Yorkshire in a much more efficient rail line, connecting the South and North more effectively than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As someone who cares deeply about the environment, the opportunity to dramatically expand rail, a greener form of transport than aviation or road is very exciting indeed. This investment will help people to choose trains over cars, reduce carbon emissions and provide a rail system that is faster, more reliable and greener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased that the Northern Hub will be funded in full as part of the government’s plans, which is a significant boost for the major towns and cities of the North, helping to rebalance the UK economy and enabling growth and regeneration throughout the regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This government is making more funds available to invest in rail projects than at any time since the Victorian era, and shows that the government is committed to delivering on its promises to support investment in public infrastructure that will support economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/"&gt;High Level Output Specification (HLOS) statement&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#illustrative-options"&gt;Maps of how HLOS is benefitting each region&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/greening-20120716a"&gt;Rail Investment, statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 16 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#railways-act"&gt;Railways Act 2005 statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#sos-guidance"&gt;Secretary of State for Transport’s Guidance to the Office of Rail Regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#illustrative-options"&gt;DfT Illustrative Option schemes in CP5 HLOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 4671 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15544</id>
    <published>2012-07-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-29T10:33:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-investment--7"/>
    <title>Rail investment: High Level Output Specification announcement 15 July 2012</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Justine Greening MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I am announcing my High Level Output Specification (&lt;abbr title="High Level Output Specification"&gt;HLOS&lt;/abbr&gt;) for the railway, as required by the Railways Act 2005. Covering the period from 2014 to 2019, it describes my vision for a railway which is more financially and environmentally sustainable, which supports economic growth and which delivers for its passengers and freight customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confirming £16 billion of public support for rail in this period, which will support £9.4 billion of infrastructure enhancement. £5.2 billion of this has previously been committed, including Thameslink, Crossrail and electrification of the Great Western Main Line and in the north west and Yorkshire. The additional £4.2 billion includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new electric spine - a passenger and freight corridor linking the core centres of population and economic activity in the East and West Midlands and Yorkshire with the south of England, which includes electrifying the Midland Main Line&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;further targeted electrification alongside this, including the Great Western Main Line from Cardiff to Swansea and the Welsh Valleys; between Micklefield and Selby in Yorkshire and between Walsall and Rugeley in the West Midlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased rail capacity for commuters, with over £700 million to be invested on the most congested routes in London and the south east and over £400 million for other cities, including completing the Northern Hub that will link key Northern cities bringing clear benefits to Newcastle, Liverpool, Manchester Leeds and Sheffield; taken with Crossrail, this will provide for 120,000 additional commuting trips per day into London in the morning peak and 20,000 into our other major cities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;further investment on Great Western Main Line, including at Bristol and Oxford stations as well as additional track capacity on the approaches to Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over £900 million investment in funding for smaller schemes to improve:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stations, including accessibility so that everyone can use the railways&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the current strategic rail freight network&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;passenger journey times and reliability&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement represents another historic landmark in the regeneration and modernisation of Britain’s railway. This government’s vision for the railways is clear - a railway system that is faster, more reliable, less crowded, and more green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we are dealing with the budget deficit, so we are also determined to deal with the massive infrastructure deficit we inherited. Rail is just one part of an unprecedented programme of transport investment this government has put in place to drive growth and job creation in the UK economy. We are building &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt;, investing £1 billion in strategic road schemes and supporting 56 local road schemes, as well as supporting light rail and bus projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous governments have underinvested in rail. We will not repeat those mistakes. This is a government with a long term vision for a modern and efficient rail system that supports growth and improves competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120716a/"&gt;Press release: Investing in rail, investing in jobs and growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#railways-act"&gt;Railways Act 2005 statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#sos-guidance"&gt;Secretary of State for Transport’s guidance to the Office of Rail Regulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/#illustrative-options"&gt;DfT Illustrative option schemes in CP5 &lt;abbr title="High Level Output Specification"&gt;HLOS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12807</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T10:42:24+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/hs2-london-to-west-midlands-property-compensation"/>
    <title>HS2 London to West Midlands Property Compensation</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Justine Greening MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In January I announced the government would proceed with plans to build a high speed rail network linking London with Birmingham, Leeds and Manchester. This is a vital project that will create jobs, drive economic growth and provide a solution to the capacity crunch facing our existing rail network. Work on the project continues apace and I will be publishing my preferred routes for the second phase of the project in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside January’s decision I confirmed my intention to deliver a generous compensation package for those affected by the route which goes over and above the minimum required by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am acutely aware of the impact that the proposals for HS2 are having on the property markets along the line of route from London to the West Midlands. The impacts on property are some of the most direct and personal effects of HS2. This is why we have committed to going above and beyond the statutory requirements for property compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing the right property compensation package is complex as it needs to be fair to those living and working along the HS2 London to West Midlands route while recognising our broader responsibility to the taxpayer. It was clear from the responses to the consultation that we held last year that property compensation was an issue that generated a considerable amount of understandable concern from those affected. In addition, from personally dealing with the casework from the operation of the existing Exceptional Hardship Scheme, I recognise the range and complexity of issues that the property and compensation package for HS2 will need to deal with. This all means that it is imperative that we put in place the right package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keen to consult as soon as possible to provide people with certainty but, given the nature of the issue and its implications for Phase 2 and work to assess stations and route options, it is clear to me that the detailed work to fully assess options means that we will consult on the property and compensation package for HS2 after Parliament returns from its summer recess in September. I understand that this delay will not be welcomed by individuals and businesses who had hoped to see an earlier resolution to the uncertainty surrounding HS2 property and compensation policies. However, this will enable the government to put forward a comprehensive, practical and affordable package of property and compensation measures. I will be writing to those likely to be most directly affected by the project to explain this change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14210</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-25T10:54:44+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/aviation-policy-framework"/>
    <title>Aviation Policy Framework</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Written statement by the Rt Hon Justine Greening MP, Secretary of State for Transport.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, the government launched a scoping exercise towards developing a new sustainable policy framework for UK aviation. I am grateful to the more than 600 organisations and individuals who responded. We have given careful consideration to their responses in preparing the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-35"&gt;draft Aviation Policy Framework consultation document&lt;/a&gt;, which I am publishing today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responses to the scoping exercise reflected a wide degree of consensus on aviation’s significant economic contribution and its other benefits, that its global and local environmental impacts are real and need to be tackled effectively and that maintaining the UK’s excellent international connectivity is critical. The consultation document sets out the government’s high level policy in each of these areas and seeks views on some of the measures we propose in support of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We clearly recognise the value of aviation as an important economic sector in its own right and as a key driver of UK economic growth. It contributes around £17 billion of economic output and employs over 220,000 workers directly and many more indirectly. And we recognise the strength of the UK’s aviation connections which give us the third largest aviation network after the US and China and make London one of the best connected cities in the world with direct links to over 360 destinations worldwide, more than either Paris or Frankfurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has a package of measures underway to improve the passenger experience at our airports and make the best use of existing capacity, as well as taking forward a process to address the UK’s international connectivity needs in the medium and longer term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we are improving efficiency at our borders. My Rt Hon Friend, the Home Secretary is reviewing the UK’s visa regime, to improve the passenger experience and to ensure that our border policy supports our prosperity agenda whilst maintaining effective security. Any changes to the UK’s visa regime will be implemented during the course of 2013. The Home Office has also brought forward the recruitment of 70 additional staff at Heathrow to provide additional flexibility to secure the border while dealing with increased passenger numbers. And it is looking at how we can improve the role of automation in the expedited clearance of passengers, linked to the development of a registered traveler scheme to replace the current IRIS scheme which has been extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are improving reliability and reducing delay at Heathrow through the trial of measures introducing greater operational flexibility. If operational freedoms show clear benefits in terms of resilience, reducing delays and allowing planes to land more effectively, thereby reducing the impact of noise for residents under the flight path, then we will consult on making these benefits permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking forward other recommendations of the South East Airports Taskforce, such as airport performance charters which will set out the level of service that airlines and their passengers should expect, as well as new guidelines developed in a Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) chaired industry group which will make the best use of existing capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are transforming the economic regulation of airports through our Civil Aviation Bill to promote passengers’ interests. We propose to replace the current uniform approach to regulation - where designated airports are subject to mandatory five-year price caps - with a modern licensing regime where licence conditions can be tailored to the specific circumstances facing individual airports. By allowing for more proportionate regulation, the new regime also enables the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) to take steps to reduce the degree or scope of economic regulation imposed on individual airports if they decide this would benefit passengers. The Bill will also ensure that airports can respond more flexibly to real-time events such as severe weather or volcanic ash and put in place a long-term framework for improving quality of service and investing in better infrastructure and facilities. The Bill is on track to receive Royal Assent by spring 2013 and we expect the new licensing regime to be implemented from April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are improving surface access to airports with significant new investment. In total over this spending review period the government is supporting investment of  £1.4 billion on rail and road schemes which will directly or indirectly benefit airports across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes a fleet of thirty new electric trains on the Stansted Express to London which entered service last year and a £53 million upgrade of Gatwick Airport station with improved passenger facilities, an extra platform and more track and signalling by 2013 and a Regional Growth Fund contribution of £19.5 million for junction enhancements to be completed by 2014 which will improve access from the M1 to Luton Airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Metrolink extension to Manchester Airport is due to open in 2016 which will provide a tram every 12 minutes between Manchester Airport and Manchester city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, Luton and Gatwick will receive improved rail services through the Thameslink programme and we expect Heathrow passengers to benefit from Crossrail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we recognise that we need to go further now in enhancing the capability of UK airports, particularly in the South East. So today we are also announcing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The commitment of up to £500m towards a western rail link to Heathrow, subject to a business case and conclusion of agreements with the aviation industry. This recognises the continued importance of Heathrow as our major international hub. Businesses west of the airport have been calling for this vital investment for many years. It will cut typically 30 minutes off the journey to Heathrow from the west of England and south Wales, with significant benefits for growing cities like Swindon, Bristol and Cardiff. The service could come into operation as early as 2021. I will shortly publish a rail investment strategy, which will recognise the importance of transport investment to the economy, including improving connectivity between cities and airports.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposals to further liberalise the UK aviation market to encourage foreign airlines to develop new routes by extending to Gatwick and Stansted the ability for foreign airlines to pick up passengers when flying to other destinations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our proposal to remove bilateral restrictions on air services on a case-by-case basis. This will mean open access to airports outside the South East for new air services, in order to facilitate inward investment in new routes and extra choice for business and passengers without necessarily having to secure reciprocal access for UK airlines to the airports of the other country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our commitment, building on the Olympics and the GREAT brand, to develop a new marketing package, working with &lt;abbr title="UK Department for Business Innovation and Skills"&gt;BIS&lt;/abbr&gt;, &lt;abbr title="UK trade and Industry"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;, and others to market the benefits of flying to a range of UK airports and to target new carriers, particularly carriers in emerging markets such as Latin America, India and South East Asia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That we will work with airports to explore, with the US authorities and others, the feasibility of US pre-clearance facilities being made available in the UK, which could improve the competitive offer airports operating such a scheme would be able to make.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That we will invite train companies to explore the potential of ‘code-sharing’ between flights and long-distance train services, to enhance competition between trains and domestic flights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our intention to identify options, within the EU legislative framework, aimed at ensuring that slots at our congested airports are used in the most economically beneficial way for the UK. The focus of this work is on seeking to optimise the functioning of the secondary trading market for airport slots. We expect to engage with key stakeholders later in the summer and publish a progress report in the autumn. We are also working with the EU, in the context of the commission’s proposals on reform of the rules on landing slots to secure measures to support UK regional connectivity, such as protecting the provision of air services between Northern Ireland and Heathrow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our support for the introduction of new rules by airport operators aimed at maximising the use of existing capacity at our busiest airports - for example, by limiting access to smaller planes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In doing so, we recognise the very substantial efforts the aviation industry is making in continuing to invest and respond to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Heathrow and Gatwick are investing £5 billion and £1 billion respectively over the next few years in better infrastructure and Birmingham Airport will shortly begin constructing a £65 million runway extension which will increase the airport’s scope to open new routes to long haul destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airlines are launching new routes to key emerging markets, such as British Airways who recently announced a new service to Seoul. China Southern Airlines is now flying from Heathrow to Guangzhou and Gatwick is showing its potential, for example with Air China’s new service to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are positive developments and will help to maintain the UK’s excellent international aviation connectivity in the short term. The government recognises, however, that it must not only take steps for the short term but also address the issue of future airport capacity and we are committed to doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following our scoping exercise last year, our draft Aviation Policy Framework is the next step towards that and we welcome responses to this consultation. We will follow this, later this year, by issuing an open call for evidence inviting stakeholders to submit specific, evidence-based proposals for consideration in identifying the medium and long term steps needed to meet the government’s economic and environmental objectives for aviation. This is a structured process towards delivering a solution that is sustainable, not only economically and environmentally but also politically. The failure of successive governments to tackle this issue shows that we need to get it right this time. Success depends upon agreeing a solution that can be delivered regardless of the political cycle and that requires an objective evidence-based process which draws on the views of the full range of interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14450</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T12:42:12+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/foundations-laid-for-future-growth-of-aviation-as-government-unveils-long-term-strategy"/>
    <title>Foundations laid for future growth of aviation as government unveils long-term strategy</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Transport Secretary Justine Greening has published the draft aviation policy framework.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More frequent flights to emerging markets, improved access to airports - including £500m towards a new rail link to Heathrow - and a reduction in the impact of airports on local communities is to be put at the heart of UK aviation strategy Transport Secretary Justine Greening has said, as she published the government’s long-term vision for the sector today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-35"&gt;draft policy framework&lt;/a&gt;, which will form the basis of future sustainable aviation growth in the UK, has been developed following discussions with the industry. The framework also includes a package of measures which will quickly deliver operational improvements and boost economic growth within existing airport capacity constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measures include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further liberalisation of the UK aviation market to encourage foreign airlines to develop routes from airports other than Heathrow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving reliability and reducing delays at Heathrow - if operational freedoms show clear benefits in terms of resilience, reducing delays and allowing planes to land more effectively, thereby reducing the impact of noise for residents under the flight path, then the government will consult on making these benefits permanent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addressing the environmental and local impacts of aviation through: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pushing for international action on aviation emissions while continuing to support EU Emissions Trading Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;incentivising noise reduction though higher landing fees for noisier aircraft at unsociable hours and higher penalties for breaching noise limits at any time&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£500m towards a western rail link to Heathrow, which is in addition to £1.4bn already being invested to improve surface access to airports, including £44m towards upgrading Gatwick Airport station and a new fleet of thirty electric trains already improving services on the Stansted Express - in addition the government is pressing ahead with HS2 which will significantly improve access to airports such as Birmingham and Manchester&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving efficiency at the border, including a review of the UK’s visa regime, bringing forward the recruitment of 70 additional border staff at Heathrow and working with the US authorities to look at the options for speeding up entry into the US&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting the introduction of new rules by airport operators to maximise their existing capacity, for example through limiting access to smaller aircraft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introducing airport performance charters which will set out the level of service that airlines and their passengers should expect from airport operators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the overall passenger experience through the Civil Aviation Bill which is expected to gain Royal Assent in 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A separate call for evidence on how to maintain the UK’s international connectivity and hub status will follow later in the year once the industry has had time to consider the measures put forward for consultation today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Justine Greening said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This framework aims to strike a balance between allowing the aviation industry to make the most of our current capacity, while also recognising the need for a tough regime to tackle levels of noise experienced by residents on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;London is already one of the best connected cities in the world, but there is still an important but challenging debate to be had on how we accommodate the long-term growth of aviation. This framework provides the building blocks for this debate and I look forward to working with the industry, residents and other interested parties on this once they have had the chance to consider these measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s draft Aviation Policy Framework document has been published on the Department for Transport’s website and is subject to full public consultation, lasting until 31 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-35"&gt;Aviation Policy Framework consultation document&lt;/a&gt; is available on the Department for Transport website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today’s publication follows an exercise last year to seek industry and other stakeholder views on the future shape of aviation policy through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2011-09"&gt;scoping document: Developing a Sustainable Framework for Aviation&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Western Rail Access to Heathrow project will be included in the government’s forthcoming High Level Output Specification for the railways (HLOS) announcement - the project is subject to a satisfactory business case and the agreement of acceptable terms with the Heathrow aviation industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
