<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/liam-fox</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/liam-fox.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Liam Fox MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-12T14:06:47+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56080</id>
    <published>2011-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:06:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-lead-non-executive-for-defence-appointed"/>
    <title>New Lead Non-Executive for Defence appointed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Secretary of State for Defence Dr Liam Fox has today announced the appointment of Mr Gerry Grimstone, the Chairman of Standard Life plc, as the new Lead Non-Executive for Defence.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Grimstone has had a distinguished career in both the public and private sectors for nearly 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has already worked closely with the MOD over a number of years, most notably as a non-executive director at Air Command, during his 2010 independent review of the way civilians are employed in Defence, and most recently as a member of the Defence Reform Steering Group which reported to the Defence Secretary in June this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the lead non-executive board member Mr Grimstone will become a key member of the new Defence Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as providing an independent and objective perspective on Board business in the way that Non-Executives always have, he will work closely with the Defence Secretary, the Permanent Secretary and the other members of the Board to ensure that it provides clear and effective leadership for the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lead Non-Executive will also take an active role in assessing and improving the Board’s performance. He will lead the Non-Executive team and he will have a direct line of access to the Government’s Lead Non-Executive (Lord Browne). All of this is aimed at ensuring good practice and strengthening corporate leadership across government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to welcome Gerry to this appointment. His extensive knowledge of how the MOD operates combined with his renowned business acumen will, I am sure, enable him to make a valuable contribution to the Department’s business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Grimstone said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be appointed as the lead non-executive member of the Defence Board. This is a genuinely exciting challenge in a period of great change. I know the Department well and recognise the important contribution its people make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a privilege to be asked to apply the skills and knowledge and experience I have developed in both the private and public sectors to contribute to the MOD’s future success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18730</id>
    <published>2011-09-15T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:06:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-09-15-transforming-the-management-of-defence"/>
    <title>2011/09/15 - Transforming the Management of Defence</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Extracts of a speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the Financial Times Annual Defence Dinner, London on Thursday 15 September 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2005 David Cameron invited me to be the Shadow Secretary of State for Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the only good thing about opposition, and even that is stretching the point, was that we had time to think about how we would change the way business was done or indeed what parts of the business needed changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk to you this evening about how we are taking that forward and importantly about the intellectual underpinning of the transformation in the way business in Defence is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="inheritance"&gt;INHERITANCE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me reflect first on what we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing that everyone in the Defence Community could agree on was that change had to come - how painful you thought it was going to be depended on your optimism or indeed your pessimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the depth of the black hole in the Defence programme was difficult from the outside to pin down, the symptoms of the disease were on show for everyone to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects were regularly and almost routinely delayed or cancelled, fleets were consistently salami-sliced, in-service dates were delayed by months or even years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently costs continued to grow ever more out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Bernard Gray said in his 2009 report “(the MoD has) too many types of equipment being ordered for too large a range of tasks at too high a specification. This programme is unaffordable on any likely projection of future budgets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their final year in office alone the previous Government presided over an increase of reported cost by a staggering £3.3 billion in just two programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the state of the public finances, simply from a management point of view, this would have to be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the state of the public finances we inherited, there was no question of just pouring money into the hole that was left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I told the audience at DSEI this week, for a politician, it is painful to be a hawk on the deficit as well as a hawk on Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that the moment of transformation had to come at a time when the public finances were under so much pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what the crisis has forced us to do in Defence - and indeed more widely across government - is face some harsh but necessary truths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me draw out for you two that are relevant here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-weakness-is-a-national-security-liability"&gt;ECONOMIC WEAKNESS IS A NATIONAL SECURITY LIABILITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, tackling the crisis in the public finances is not just an issue of economics but an issue of national security too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debt is a strategic issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or to be brutal - you cannot be secure if you’re broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just look at the figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the Coalition’s aggressive action, the Office for Budget Responsibility forecasts public sector net debt to peak at over 70% of GDP in 2014/15. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current national debt is roughly equivalent to almost a quarter of a century of spending on Defence at the level of this year’s budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest, just the interest, paid out last year alone was £43bn - greater than the annual budgets of the MoD, plus the Foreign Office, plus DfID put together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year the interest payments will be in the order of £50bn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the lessons of history are clear - from the Roman Empire to the Soviet Union - even Britain’s own 20th century history bears this out - relative economic power is the wellspring of strategic strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural economic weakness, if not dealt with, will bring an unavoidable reduction in our ability to shape the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Defence terms, without sound finances and a sustainable Defence programme the inevitable result in the long-term is a collapse in capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition has acted to address both the structural economic weakness of the country and the unsustainable defence programme in order to avoid these outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not alone in doing this although we may have been the first or at least amongst the earliest to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same process is also now taking place in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is why our approach to Strategic Defence and Security Review had to be logical and unsentimental and include realigning our Defence priorities with the economic realities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the vision of Future Force 2020 - supported by the fourth largest Defence budget in the world and by real terms rises in the equipment programme in the next spending period - is a vision that maintains formidable capability - from nuclear weapons to aircraft carriers, from state of the art jets to precisions weapons, from multi-role brigades to cyber defence - an adaptable defence posture for a volatile dangerous and unpredictable world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transforming-the-way-things-are-done"&gt;TRANSFORMING THE WAY THINGS ARE DONE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second harsh truth from the state of the public finances is this - just as throwing money at problems doesn’t automatically produce improvements, simply cutting things does not bring your budget into balance in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you change the way you do things, you risk history repeating itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the drivers of financial instability and the lack of accountability in the management of Defence had to be tackled too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is what I want turn to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose an approach of simultaneous reform rather than sequential reform because the vision of the SDSR will be unachievable if not accompanied by a management system robust enough to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I set up the Defence Reform Unit under Peter Levene before the SDSR had been completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was very clear in his critique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A department with overly bureaucratic management structures, dominated by committees leading to indecisiveness and a lack of responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bloated top level defence board without Ministerial membership allowing strategic decision to drift and unable to reconcile ambition with resources. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budget holders without the levers needed to deliver and Ministers kept in the dark. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to his report we have initiated a transformation in Defence in not seen for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, three key changes have to be made in contrast to what went before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - We have to have confidence that what is being ordered can be afforded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - we have to live with our means - there has to be a mechanism for the real time control of budgets so that if things start going wrong they can be identified and dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - authority has to be aligned with responsibility - so budget holders have the levers to deliver and the incentive to do so but can also be held to account for failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take each of these in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commitment-control-regime"&gt;COMMITMENT CONTROL REGIME&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the commitment control regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that ministers in the previous government knew the Defence program was unsustainable they continued to add new elements to it knowing that there were no secure funding in the budget to finance them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often, in order to get projects included in the programme, fantasy numbers produced by the MOD and Industry were accepted at the outset knowing that cost overruns would have to be recovered later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By looking at and approving programmes in isolation from the totality of departmental spend any programme can be made to look affordable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when they are considered together, the cumulative risk and cost become unmanageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These practices in the MoD would not be tolerated in the private sector and they will no longer be tolerated in the MoD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A risk-aware and cost-conscious mentality must permeate every level at the Ministry of Defence, civilian and military alike. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commitment control regime means that guarantees of realistic budgets for development, procurement and deployment must be presented to Ministers before spending can begin on new programmes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of this in action is the recent order placed for 14 Chinook Helicopters - 12 to expand the fleet and two to replace losses in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Financial Times wrote at the time “The broader significance of the order may now be less to do with the extent the new aircraft will boost airlift capacity, and more to do with what it conveys about the MOD’s procurement system.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not willing to sign the order unless I had a budget that I could guarantee. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also sought guarantees that the projected costs had been thoroughly vetted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all part of the commitment control regime run by my Permanent Secretary Ursula Brennan and Chief of Defence Materiel Bernard Gray. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we went through the SDSR I was never convinced that the Department was in full control of the facts about real costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having brought Bernard Gray in and having asked him to thoroughly scrub the equipment programme, I think we now have a much better and more rigorous idea of what things really cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the most positive results of the recent three month exercise we undertook to prepare for the next annual planning round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that exercise I said to the Department you need to give us all the information that we need because if you come back afterwards and say ‘by the way this is actually costing a bit more’ you will have to find it from somewhere else inside your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my second key change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="major-projects-review-board"&gt;MAJOR PROJECTS REVIEW BOARD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a realistic projection of costs and a budget to meet them is only the first part of the jigsaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping to budget, as anyone in the private sector knows, requires real-time control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was a complete lack of process within the MOD to achieve that and no system to hold to account project leaders in the MOD and indeed in Industry for failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first we had to initiate a process of regular review - that is what the Major Projects Review Board (MPRB) is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 20 biggest procurement projects which make up 80% of the equipment budget are now reviewed on a quarterly basis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a particular programme is showing signs of incipient failure, then those responsible are brought in front of the Board to explain the problem and to outline the proposed way ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course problems can lie with the MOD or with Industry or both - but I believe, when public money is involved, that the public has a right to know where things are going wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is perfectly reasonable when Government and Industry are working in constructive co-operation that shareholders and indeed the stock market are kept informed of progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined that the discipline of the market should apply as much to Defence as it does other areas where Government is investing in infrastructure over long-timescales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This external discipline is now regularly and routinely being applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is exactly this discipline that is required if we are to ensure that the Department lives within its means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="authority-and-control"&gt;AUTHORITY AND CONTROL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last fundamental change I want to address is on authority and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the MOD was in the private sector it would be the third biggest company in Britain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we inherited a management system where the Secretary of State didn’t even chair the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is part of my basic Conservative philosophy that politicians shouldn’t try to tell people how to do the jobs they are trained to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should set out what we want the outcome and the output to be and then we should leave professional people to make those judgements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no intention of micro-managing the Armed Forces which is why we have reconfigured the management structure of the Department - including the Defence Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to this is empowering the Service chiefs to run their own individual services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single service chiefs are the custodians of their services, the fundamental building blocks of defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new model, the Service chiefs get a clear strategic direction within set budgets that enables them to carry out the detailed military capability planning needed across equipment, manpower and training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once that is agreed, they will be given greater freedom to veer and haul between priorities within their own service to deliver what is needed in Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will enjoy long-denied freedoms, and they will be held robustly to account for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I have said this evening are procedural changes which to the average tabloid reader would seem to be meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course as you are all FT readers I’m sure you agree that this will bring an essential discipline to how the Ministry of Defence operates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that the difficulties have ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am confident that we are on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A path that leads not only to a balanced Defence budget, but also to Armed Forces able to keep our citizens safe, and to project the military power required to do so at a distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain will remain one of the few countries in the world able to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this last 16 months we have achieved much in the Ministry of the Defence - the SDSR, the Armed Forces Covenant, the Defence Reform Unit, the Reserves Review, the Basing Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve set up the Defence Infrastructure Organisation and the Defence Business Services Organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve reconfigured the management system, set up the Major Projects Review Board, set up the Defence Exports Support Group and set up the Defence Suppliers Forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve begun the transformation in the management of Defence from a cumbersome Cold War bureaucracy to an adaptable 21st century organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while we have done so, our Armed Forces have been proving themselves again and again on operations - in Afghanistan - in the skies over Libya - on their standing tasks around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often say to me that I must have one of the worst jobs in Whitehall, but I think exactly the polar opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I have one of the best jobs in Whitehall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am working with some of the best minds in Britain in the Military and in the Civil Service and in Industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have the absolute honour of seeing day in and day out the professionalism, courage and commitment of the men and women of our Armed Forces who do some of the most difficult jobs in the most dangerous of circumstances all around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enormously proud of what they are achieving - I’m humbled to be nominally in charge of them and I’m proud of what is being achieved at the Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18729</id>
    <published>2011-09-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:02:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-09-13-building-security-celebrating-success"/>
    <title>2011/09/13 - Building Security, Celebrating Success</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the Defence and Security Equipment International (DSEi) 2011, ExCel London, on Tuesday 13 September 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to be here at DSEi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is not my first visit, it is as Secretary of State for Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in that role let me add my words of welcome to representatives of our many allies and partners from around the world here this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSEi brings together over 1,300 suppliers from the global defence and the security sectors - everything from traditional defence platforms to cyber security and counter-terrorism to commercial security, fire protection and safety. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the United Kingdom’s own industrial presence here is exceptionally strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m pleased to see a record number of small and medium sized businesses represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This represents a track record of manufacturing prowess, engineering skill and innovation that exist in businesses and people from across the whole country - a track record of which Britain can be rightly proud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to celebrate that success but I also want to talk about some of the difficult challenges ahead - not just for the United Kingdom - but for all those who seek to build a stable and secure environment in which our societies can prosper and flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-value-of-defence"&gt;THE VALUE OF DEFENCE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we take pride in the job that our Armed Forces do - it is right that we take pride in those in industry who support them and provide the tools that keep us safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From those who research and design solutions that may well save lives, to those who engineer, produce and support equipment and capabilities too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only that this maintains over 300,000 jobs across the country - in all parts of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only that this pays around £2bn a year in taxes to the exchequer and a £35bn contribution to the wider economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this helps to ensure that our Armed Forces and those of our allies and partners are equipped, armed and supported in operations that protect our national interest and give many people in many parts of the world new hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeing this in Afghanistan and the recent NATO action in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our forces in Afghanistan who are doing a fantastic job in challenging circumstances have never been so well equipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will continue to support them properly until the mission is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Libya, state of the art precision weapons, such as Brimstone, have allowed NATO forces to prosecute a dynamic campaign within the terms of the UN resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the performance of Typhoon in its first multi-role contribution to operations has been fantastic - exceeding our own high expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time Britain has relied on Typhoon to defend our homeland and our dependent territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Typhoon is tried and tested in a ground attack role too -  and has proved its versatility, endurance and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to thank all those who have worked so hard to deliver the support our forces needed on recent operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A healthy and thriving defence and security sector supports more than our Armed Forces, it supports our foreign policy aims too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence and Security exports play a key role in promoting our foreign policy objectives - building relationships and trust, sharing information and spreading values - these things cannot be measured in monetary terms on a balance sheet alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me it is irrefutable - helping one of Britain’s most dynamic, successful industries to export responsibly is in British national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud that the UK is the second biggest defence exporter in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I and my fellow Ministers at the MOD and across government are proud to play our part in supporting that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is fundamental part of the Coalition Government’s agenda for economic growth but it is also part of our strategy of enlightened international engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Margin, profit, market share - these are not dirty words - but the language of multi-national business can sometimes appear values free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nations that set the framework in which manufacture and exports take place are most definitely not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To represent Britain, in war, in peace and, yes, in business, is to represent our inherent democratic values, the rule of law, and respect for life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the United Kingdom’s export licensing regime is amongst the most rigorous in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms are mandatory considerations for all export licence applications which we consider on a case-by-case basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When conditions change we act swiftly to revoke licences that do not meet our strict criteria - just as we did earlier this year as the events in the Middle East and North Africa unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This important area of policy is subject to rigorous scrutiny and regular review, and the Foreign Secretary will update Parliament in due course. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not compromise our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me be equally clear, we will continue to support our allies and partners, we will help with their security needs, and we will support businesses seeking to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-adaptable-approach-in-a-volatile-world"&gt;THE ADAPTABLE APPROACH IN A VOLATILE WORLD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our export controls, just like our promotion of responsible exports, are not tactical - they are strategic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this volatile world, it is in Britain’s interests to help create security where there is none, promote stability where it is threatened, and reinforce responsible governance wherever it exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our strategic response has to be relevant in the conditions that exist and designed to help positive transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arab Spring shows just how quickly circumstances can propel countries and, indeed whole regions, from one condition to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a dynamic process whose ultimate conclusion is as yet unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such swift change requires our export regimes as well as our international security structures to be flexible, responsive and multi-layered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they require our Armed Forces to be adaptable too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is now implementing the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR) announced last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR lays out a roadmap for sustainable, well-managed and formidable Armed Forces - structured for the rigours of the future character of conflict - able to swiftly adapt to circumstances - able to operate with our allies or independently if necessary -  and fully able to provide for Britain’s Defence in an age of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is exactly because of the unpredictability of this volatile world - exactly because of the continuing need to use military force to protect Britain’s interests at distance - that the SDSR places such a premium on the flexibility and adaptability of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are testing times - not just in security terms but in economic terms too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many of our allies and partners, the United Kingdom is seeking to bring order to our public finances and to its Defence programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been among the first to recognise just how dangerous the economic crisis could be in terms of long-term security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic growth and economic success are issues of national security too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is painful for a politician to be both a hawk on the deficit and a hawk on Defence but you cannot be secure when you’re broke &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influence depends on both economic power and military power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why our approach to Defence transformation has had to be logical and unsentimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each step we have considered the implications of cost and capability, we have considered the impact on current operations, and we have considered capacities for capability regeneration against real world risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This methodology has allowed us to seek budgetary balance while investing in the future platforms and systems our Armed Forces will need to remain formidable and adaptable - from aircraft carriers to cyber capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you know, this has meant taking difficult decisions on particular programmes that have implications for industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in doing so we have achieved a level of stability and predictability that was previously absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s commitment to a 1% real terms increase in the Defence equipment and support budget from 2015 underlines our determination to realise the transformation of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are moving towards a period of growth with greater opportunities for industry as we build the capabilities upon which our Future Force 2020 will rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to the relationship between Government and industry we need if we are going to produce both economic growth and national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-on-success"&gt;BUILDING ON SUCCESS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, these are testing economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite this the UK defence and security industry is a real success story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year the UK maintained its position as the second largest exporter of new Defence products and services winning almost £6Bn of new Defence orders and increasing its share of the global Defence market to 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, security exports grew too by 8% to £2bn fuelled by the 9,000 companies and 140,000 people in the UK who work hard to bring new, relevant and innovative security products to market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British success story is not just about global prime contractors - it is about the small businesses who are world leaders in cutting-edge technologies - they are the lifeblood of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about family-owned companies like Tinsley Bridge Group in Sheffield who worked with BAE Systems to produce suspension on Warrior vehicles that provides mobility and protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about companies like Cambridge Design Partnership who have designed a lightweight integrated oxygen concentrator that helps medics administer life-saving treatment - this is technology not just for the front-line, but for search and rescue operations, disaster relief and civilian ambulances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology transfer works both ways - the new Foxhound light patrol vehicle incorporates technology developed in Formula 1 racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British engineering solutions found in some of the most advanced racing cars in the world - found in some of the most advanced military vehicles in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This innovation means that Foxhound has the potential to be a world leader in protected mobility and will be deployed to Afghanistan next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have collected many of the innovative ideas and capabilities that UK has to offer into a UK Capability Showcase at the eastern end of the North Hall, and I urge you all to pay it a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="constructive-co-operation"&gt;CONSTRUCTIVE CO-OPERATION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the new environment, businesses, both big and small, will have to continue to adapt to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government is going to be a tougher, more intelligent customer - it needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure on the public purse means that now more than ever, value for money for the taxpayer must be demonstrable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value for money is not about compromising your Defence aim or compromising business viability - it is about realising those aims in a way that is sustainable for both customer and supplier. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That balance has not always existed in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a measure of our determination to redress this and as part of Defence Transformation, the Ministry of Defence has been we are conducting a programme of contract review and re-negotiation affecting up to 500 contracts with a value of £8bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the new Major Projects Review Board brings much needed market pressure into the process of ensuring projects are proceeding on time and on budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said - profit is not a dirty word - but neither is competition or value for money or ‘off the shelf’ - or as I prefer to call it ‘barcode procurement’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know that our contractors have demonstrated great flexibility to meet the requirements of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has demonstrated to me the terrific capability that can be generated from within the UK’s industrial base and by our overseas suppliers in a time of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the behaviour and the outcomes we need to have in all our dealings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry does not need handouts - nor will it get them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry looks to Government to be clear in defining its needs, consistent in its application of policy and transparent in how business is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what we are delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have consulted widely and intend to publish our policy approach in a White Paper before the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="export-led-growth"&gt;EXPORT-LED GROWTH&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also crucial to success is what DSEi is all about - the quality of product and the export potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Defence Survey published yesterday by ADS suggests that export sales last year amounted to over 40% of total turnover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long export potential has been ignored when initiating projects for the UK’s own use - that needs to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exportability needs to become engrained in the requirement setting, commissioning and production processes - because only through exportability can risks and costs be shared in a viable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to sustain UK Defence and security jobs in the long term is to widen the customer base through enhanced Defence exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence and Industry working together can be at the forefront of an export led growth strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also must recognise and understand the needs and priorities of our allies and partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful exports is not just about selling equipment and capability; increasingly success is based the ability to create joint ventures with the excellent industries that exist amongst the countries represented here at DSEi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite rightly sovereign nations wish to have indigenous defence industries, perhaps not all embracing, but which play to individual strengths and areas of expertise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be looking at these as opportunities for our industry to grow and for Government’s deepen and strengthen partnerships.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces of the United Kingdom are among the best equipped in the world, funded by the world’s fourth largest Defence Budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cutting edge technology they are able to call on gives them a true advantage on the frontline - it protects them, it informs them, and ultimately it provides them with precision offensive capability to deliver battle winning effect - it has been tried and tested on operations some of the most demanding environments in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this exhibition you will see much of that equipment and you will see the world class British engineering that is delivering battle-winning capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to see so many of our allies and partners here this week - the responsible stewardship of international stability and security is not a task just for a few but a task for all those who wish to see their societies prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are reminded this week - in the long shadow of the terrible events of 9/11 - that security does not exist unless it is created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the world changes around us, the adaptability of our defence and security forces will be key to keeping our citizens safe - and the strength of our economy and the innovation of our industry will be key to national success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18727</id>
    <published>2011-09-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T12:53:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-09-08-statement-on-the-report-into-the-death-of-mr-baha-mousa-in-iraq-in-2003"/>
    <title>2011/09/08 - Statement on the Report into the death of Mr Baha Mousa in Iraq in 2003</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Statement delivered by Secretary of State for Defence to Parliament on Thursday 8 September 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Madam Deputy Speaker, with permission I would like to make a statement on the Report into the death of Mr Baha Mousa in Iraq in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any conflict, no matter what the reason for our country’s involvement and no matter how difficult the circumstances, what separates us from our adversaries are the values with which we prosecute it and the ethics that guide our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To represent Britain, in war as well as in peace, is to represent our inherent democratic values, the rule of law and respect for life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When those values are transgressed, it is vital that we get to the bottom of what has happened, are open about the issues and their causes, make sure what reparations we can make are made, and do all we can to prevent it happening again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only in that way can we ensure that those values hold firm - in how we think of ourselves and in how others perceive us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, I am today laying before the House the independent report published this morning by Sir William Gage as Chairman of the Public Inquiry into the circumstances surrounding the death of Mr Baha Mousa in Iraq in 2003. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Sir William and his team who have produced a report that is sober, focussed and detailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all I believe it to be both fair and balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, however, a painful and difficult read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the report sets out, “Baha Mousa was subject to violent and cowardly abuse and assaults by British Servicemen whose job it was to guard him and treat him humanely”, and this was the primary cause of his death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Inquiry was rightly set up in 2008 by the previous Government with the intent to shine a spotlight on the events surrounding the death of Baha Mousa and to provide the most definitive account possible in the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does that comprehensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened to Baha Mousa and his fellow detainees in September 2003 was deplorable, shocking and shameful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD and the Army have previously made a full apology to the family of Baha Mousa and to his fellow detainees and has paid compensation to them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can take some limited comfort that incidents like this are extremely rare - but we cannot be satisfied by that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the seriousness of this case, there is a series of questions that I have myself asked and that others in this House will ask too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who was responsible and what happened as a consequence? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What action has been taken to prevent a recurrence? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we have the right protection in place today in Afghanistan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, how will the Government respond to the recommendations made in the report?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, on responsibility the report makes clear the extent of the failings of individuals, the Ministry of Defence and the Armed Forces at the time and in earlier years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the shocking displays of brutality for which individuals are responsible, it is also clear that there were serious failings in command and discipline in the 1st Battalion the Queen’s Lancashire Regiment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lack of clarity in the allocation of responsibility for the prisoner handling process and sadly too there was a lack of moral courage to report abuse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it must be acknowledged that a small number behaved with both integrity and courage in reporting what they had witnessed and they are examples of how others should have behaved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wider than the Battalion, there were also deficiencies in policies, orders and training relating to detention at that time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chairman notes that there was inadequate doctrine on prisoner handling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a ‘systemic failure’ that allowed knowledge of the prohibition on abusive techniques made by the Heath Government to be lost over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Report confirms that the Army was underprepared for the task of handling civilian detainees, having expected after the end of war-fighting to provide humanitarian aid rather than becoming involved in counter-insurgency activities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madam Deputy Speaker, since this incident in 2003, six different Defence Secretaries have stood at this Despatch Box and I am sure all will regret that it has taken so long to get to the bottom of what happened, and that even now the refusal of some involved to tell the whole truth means it has not been possible to establish the full extent of the culpability of individuals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their behaviour is a matter for their own consciences but others must take responsibility for the wider failures and deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report does not mean that our investigations of mistreatment of detainees are over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence from the Inquiry will now be reviewed to see whether more can be done to bring those responsible to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would therefore not be appropriate to comment here in the House of Commons on specific individuals and the role they played in this appalling episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have asked the Chief of the General Staff where individuals are still serving, to consider what action is necessary to ensure that the Army’s ethical standards are upheld - that action is underway through the chain of command as we speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investigations of the Iraq Historic Allegations Team (or IHAT), which started work in November last year, are now well under way and are revealing evidence of some concern. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is too early to comment on what the conclusions of the IHAT investigations might be, but cases will be referred to the Director of Service Prosecutions if and when there is sufficient evidence to justify this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, since 2003 action by the MOD and the Army to address failings as they were identified has touched every aspect of the prisoner handling system from policy and doctrine to ground level directives, as well as training and oversight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes wrought have been fundamental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army Inspector’s report in 2010, validated by an independent, expert adviser, is one example of the detailed scrutiny applied to the training and doctrine for handling detainees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I can assure the House that there is a commitment to continuous improvement at all levels inside and outside the Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Report acknowledges, further positive changes have been made as a result of matters that emerged from evidence heard during this Inquiry’s final module - Module 4 - which was a thorough scrutiny of our current detention policies, practices and training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister for the Armed Forces and I take a close personal interest in detention matters in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that our approach to detention there is now markedly improved from the period rightly criticised in this report. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are in no way complacent about the issues identified by Sir William.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can inform this House that I am accepting in principle all of his recommendations with one reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that we retain the techniques necessary to secure swiftly in appropriate circumstances the intelligence that can save lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recommendation that we institute a blanket ban during tactical questioning on the use of certain verbal and non-physical techniques I am afraid I cannot accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I share some of Sir William’s concerns and I have asked the Chief of Defence Staff to ensure that this approach is only be used by defined people in defined circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madam Deputy Speaker, let me conclude by saying this: In Iraq, between 2003-2008, 179 British personnel were killed serving their country and many more returned injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In autumn 2003, the 1st Battalion Queen’s Lancashire Regiment faced an immensely difficult challenge as they attempted to bring law and order to a large area that had been subject to a brutally oppressive regime for many years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Sir William acknowledges, the issues addressed in his Report - and I quote - “need to be understood in the operational context in which they occurred: the tempo of operations; the poor state of the local civilian infrastructure; a daily threat to life from both civilian unrest and an increasing insurgency; the deaths of fellow service personnel and incessant oppressive heat. In combination these factors made huge demands on soldiers serving in Iraq in 2003.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few of us sitting in the comfort of the House of Commons who can claim to understand what this must have been like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the vast majority of Armed Forces personnel faced these same challenges and did not behave in the way outlined in this report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They represent the fine ethical values found day in and day out in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not allow the unspeakable actions of a very few to damage the reputation of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be clear, Baha Mousa was not a casualty of war. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His death occurred as a detainee in British Custody - it was avoidable and preventable and there can be no excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no place in our Armed Forces for the mistreatment of detainees and there is no place for a perverted sense of loyalty that turns a blind eye to wrongdoing or erects a wall of silence to cover it up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any Serviceman or woman, no matter the colour of uniform they wear, is found to have betrayed the values this country stands for and the standards we hold dear, they will be held to account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, whatever the circumstances, the rules or regulations people know the difference between right or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not allow the behaviour of individuals who cross that line to taint the reputation of the Armed Forces of which the British people are rightly proud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this statement to the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ENDS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18725</id>
    <published>2011-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:27:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-08-30-partnership-with-purpose-multi-layered-security-in-the-21st-century"/>
    <title>2011/08/30 - Partnership with Purpose: Multi-Layered Security in the 21st Century</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the Baltic Defence College, Tartu, Estonia, on Tuesday 30 August 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20 years ago this month the international community recognised the restoration of independence and liberty in Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia as the shackles of the Soviet Union were cast off once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was, of course, not a single event but the culmination of a struggle - a struggle spanning half a century - with many heroes - and sadly many victims of many different nationalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain we continue to mark the 8th May 1945 as Victory in Europe Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we remember that liberation for some was not liberation for all and the throwing off of oppression that the 8th May represents for much of Europe was not secured by many in North and Eastern Europe for another 45 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never forget that the Cold War did not simply end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cold War was won - won by those who believed in the triumph of liberty and human spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not by guns and tanks and missiles, although deterrence played its part, but won by the dynamism of the free market and the courage of people desperate for freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty is not the natural state of affairs - it must be fought for and defended repeatedly in place and time, in every nation and by every generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current struggle in Libya is part of that same long continuum that people here in the Baltic are familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will not be the last conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forces of freedom and the forces of tyranny are in a constant battle for supremecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the ‘Baltic Way’ of 1989, when millions linked the capitals of Tallinn, Riga and Vilnius in a human chain, read Bouazizi Square, Tahrir Square and Martyr Square in Tunis, Cairo and Tripoli today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here and now, in the 21st century, the people of Lithuania, Estonia, and Latvia are enjoying the fruits of 20 years of successful democratic governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now members of NATO and the European Union. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of a family of nations united by values - united in defence of those values and in defence of one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Baltic Defence College here in Tartu is part of how that unity is fostered - those with a responsibility for national and collective Defence coming together to learn together - and to learn from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am particularly pleased that, after a few years absence, the United Kingdom is once again represented among the student body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This college teaches not only the craft of defence but the values of NATO - values which have been on display in the campaign in Libya - not only the justification for NATO’s initial involvement, but also the way in which the campaign has been prosecuted - with precision, to protect civilians and to minimise casualties showing that we have greater regard for life than the regime being overthrown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk about how we defend our values and maintain our collective defence in this globalised, unpredictable, fast moving world - a world in which threats are not single but diverse - a world in which our security response necessarily cannot be monolithic but needs to be flexible and multi-layered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="afghanistan"&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first I want to dwell for a moment on another, much less auspicious anniversary that is nearly upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 11th September will mark ten years since the Al-Qaeda terrorist attacks in New York and Washington, which killed nearly 3,000 innocent people and changed the way many political leaders saw the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years later Osama Bin Laden is dead, but the followers of his deadly, nihilistic, extremist creed - though weakened - have not gone away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t shoot an idea. Just as Soviet communism had to be beaten in the mind, the heart and the pocket - so must violent Islamic extremism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the Arab Spring and what NATO has been helping to achieve in Libya is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows that violent extremism is not the only route to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It demonstrates that representative government and freedom are not simply ‘western’ values but represent a universal aspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It disproves the myth peddled by extremists that freedom is somehow incompatible with Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The desire for control over your own destiny is not constrained by religion but by those who seek to use religion to oppress legitimate aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the presence of NATO in Afghanistan is a direct consequence of 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first and only time in its history, NATO invoked Article V of the Washington Treaty - an attack against one being an attack against all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mission in Afghanistan is to build up the capacity of the Afghan Government so that it is able to prevent the return of those who pose a threat to us and our allies around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We protect our own national security and the security of the NATO alliance by helping the Afghans take control of theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has been slow at times and difficult, but it is real and meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now entering a new phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size and capability of the Afghan National Security Forces (ANSF) has grown significantly, first meeting and exceeding targets, and is now at the stage where transition of lead responsibility for security can take place area by area as conditions allow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is happening now in Helmand where US, British, Estonian and Danish troops are co-operating together alongside the ANSF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghan forces are doing more fighting and patrolling - our forces are doing more training and mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security for the provincial capital Lashkar Gah is now the responsibility of the ANSF, but the security situation in other parts of the province remains challenging and there is no room for complacency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan remains a dangerous place and progress is by no means irreversible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the Baltic nations are contributing to ISAF and on behalf of the British Government I want to thank Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia for their efforts in pursuit of our collective security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With your contributions you are putting to shame some of NATO’s larger nations and this will not be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you will forgive me for dwelling a moment on the contribution of Estonia, whose troops train side by side, and fight side by side with those from Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are particularly grateful that Estonian troops serve without caveats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a valuable part of Task Force Helmand - valued in particular at that soldier to soldier level where personal trust is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operating now with 42 Commando Royal Marines as part of Combined Forces Nad ‘Ali (North), the Estonian troops from the 1st Infantry Brigade have played a significant role in the latest Operation OMID HAFT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that the Estonian BRIMSTONE team of bomb disposal experts were outstanding in finding and disposing of the deadly IEDs that laced the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations like this are inherently dangerous and I pay tribute to those Estonians who have lost their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their sacrifice is not forgotten - nor do we forget those who have been injured - just as we fight side by side, so do our medical teams work side by side - and those who are seriously injured are able to use the medical facilities in the UK designed for treatment and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I was at the military ward at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital, in Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met there a young Estonian soldier who is recovering from his wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told him I was soon to be visiting Estonia and speaking here at Tartu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said I was lucky and that he was looking forward to coming home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He and his colleagues are truly ‘Lions of Estonia’ - highly capable, good in a fight, and feared by the insurgency for their tenacity and professionalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share with the Government of Afghanistan the objective that the Afghans assume lead security responsibility across the country as a whole by the end of 2014 so British troops will not be in a combat role by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as Minister Laar, Minister Bech from Denmark and I set out when we met in Kabul in June, “though the nature of our forces might evolve during the transition process, the mission will remain resourced and the right balance maintained between combat troops and others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="preparing-for-the-future"&gt;Preparing for the Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan represents a significant test for the NATO alliance and it may well point the way to a character of warfare that NATO could face in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must be careful not to use Afghanistan - or indeed Libya - dogmatically as exemplars of other current challenges or those that we may face in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can never assume that the conflicts of the future will be the same as the conflicts of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom we have just been through a rigorous process of reassessment, completing our first Strategic Defence and Security Review for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of our Defence capability is now underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Armed Forces that will emerge from this process will remain formidable, advanced and structured for swift deployment overseas, but they will be more flexible and more able to withstand the rigours of modern warfare on land, sea, air and notably in cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will of course remain a nuclear power, supported by the fourth largest defence budget in the world, continuing to meet the NATO criteria of 2% of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our review was thorough, based on a fresh assessment of Britain’s wider national security requirements, and based on realistic judgements about the nature of the threats we face and the risks we need to prepare for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-strength"&gt;Economic Strength&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share with you with just a few strategic conclusions I have drawn from the process we have been through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - structural economic weakness is a national security liability and has to be dealt with as a priority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t be secure if you are broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without sound finances and a sustainable defence programme the inevitable result in the long-term is a collapse in capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Soviet Union’s implosion was in part caused by an economic system that could not sustain the myth of communism’s superiority - nor sustain the military forces required to hold the myth together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons of history are clear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative economic power is the wellspring of strategic strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The determination of the UK Government to reduce the structural deficit in our public finances comes in part from recognition of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reality is being recognised in the United States and in some parts of Europe, but I fear that the message still needs to get through in some quarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural economic weakness, if not dealt with, will bring an unavoidable reduction in our ability to shape the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not only economic weakness that could stand in our way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my second point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="adaptability-deployability-and-political-will"&gt;Adaptability, Deployability and Political Will&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this volatile world we cannot predict with certainty exactly when and where threats may emerge so the requirement is for Armed Forces that are agile, adaptable and of high quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And equally important is that they must be deployable - and supported by a political class willing to use them and to explain to their public the requirement for intervention in the collective interest - even if the public mood is otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the means without the will to use it is not what NATO needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new world is not only volatile, but connected like never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like contagion in financial markets, it is not long before threats emerging from instability even in regions thousands of miles away, are felt in our own backyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That can be through disruption to trade, access to natural resources, through migration flow, or even more directly through security threats like trans-national terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has never been, nor can there ever be, such a thing as Fortress Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be prepared to confront those who would threaten international stability or our collective security - outside our region and outside our comfort zone if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the philosopher John Stuart Mill said: “war is an ugly thing, but not the ugliest of things: the decayed and degraded state of moral and patriotic feeling which thinks nothing worth a war is worse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not advocating a strategy of unfettered liberal interventionism, but I am advocating a hard headed strategy of enlightened national interest where threats are tackled at source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An integrated approach which includes financial action, trade, conflict prevention, poverty reduction and development assistance is of course part of such a strategy, but ultimately we have to have the will and capability to respond militarily if required - swiftly, decisively and at distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I have a great deal of sympathy with the forensic dissection of the challenges facing NATO delivered by my very good friend and former US Defence Secretary Gates in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The imbalances in NATO that Bob Gates set out are not only financial - they are about the kind of capability that exists and the political will to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear, I do not believe we need to choose between the capabilities required for both Article 5 and non-Article 5 activities - deployability is central to the effectiveness of NATO in both areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to my third point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="partnership-with-purpose"&gt;Partnership with Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country acting alone can hope to protect every aspect of its national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnership is not discretionary - partnership between like-minded countries - partnership with clear purpose - based on clear values - is the only way to meet the threats of this new age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom belongs to a wide range of organisations and institutions allowing us to generate influence - the Security Council of the United Nations as a permanent member, NATO, the Commonwealth, the European Union, the G8, G20 and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s membership of NATO remains the bedrock of our collective security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is through NATO that the UK is committed to ensuring the continuing active participation of the United States in Europe’s security into the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our SDSR confirmed, the United States remains Britain’s most important security relationship, not least because of our conviction that NATO should remain a guarantor of European security well into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why NATO will not be well served by a dismissive response by some European members of NATO to issues raised by Bob Gates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union is also a key part of the means through which we could promote security and prosperity in our neighbourhood - but it should be complimentary, and in addition, to NATO. Not a substitute which dilutes or diverts our efforts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that what is required is multilayered security so that nations can respond using the right means for the right occasion - through multi-lateral organisations such as NATO wherever possible - but also through small group and bilateral relationships - when the task requires it - or when wide consensus is harder to achieve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the United Kingdom is embarking on a drive to maintain, improve and forge where necessary bilateral and small group relationships between like-minded states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we might describe as a ‘building block’ approach to defence and security in the Euro-Atlantic area and further afield. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows natural bi-lateral partnerships to flourish, allows regional groupings to flourish - and crucially it has the capacity to add value to the capabilities available to larger multi-national institutions such as NATO, the UN or the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combination of strong bilateral ties and multilateral arrangements brings added strength to the whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK-France Defence Co-operation Treaty is part of this process for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So too is the Northern Group of nations, which includes the Baltic and Nordic countries, Germany, Poland and the Netherlands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recognises our shared history as Northern European states - a history which I have to admit for too long Britain seemed to have forgotten but which the new Coalition Government greatly values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the Northern European neighbourhood it makes sense to work together to secure our own region, to keep our trade routes open, to exploit together new opportunities and to face together threats as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK does not believe that relationships in Europe always have to be about political Europe or the EU - we can and should work with geographical Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We view Europe differently, not just in terms of its institutional structures, but as a geographically united group of sovereign nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northern Group includes nations who are members of NATO but not the EU and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this model of multi-layered security is inclusive - it is a perfect example of why multilateralism outside traditional institutions is sometimes a better way and certainly a complimentary way to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude with this thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the end of the Cold War, the Baltic region has experienced a reawakening and renewal - a renaissance that Britain is proud to have supported and been involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course our shared history is much wider and deeper covering over a thousand years of migration, trade and yes, conflict at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was struck by Mart Laar’s pamphlet on the Estonian War of Independence. He set out how the intervention of the British Fleet in Baltic waters was instrumental in the struggle leading up to the signing of the Treaty of Tartu in 1920.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Admiral Cowan is remembered here in the Baltic Defence College and of course in the name of the first Sandown Class mine countermeasures vessel commissioned in the Estonian Navy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British were among those who gave their lives in the fight for freedom in the Baltic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today in the 21st century, that passion and committment is absolutely undiminished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18721</id>
    <published>2011-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:13:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-07-13-air-power-in-an-age-of-uncertainty"/>
    <title>2011/07/13 - Air Power in an Age of Uncertainty</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the Royal United Services Institute Air Power Conference, London on Wednesday 13 July 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how much resource you commit, no matter how many great minds you employ, no matter how clear the analysis, it is impossible to predict with absolute precision when, where, and in what way Britain will find itself drawn into conflict in the future to protect the national interest and national security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We prepare but we cannot know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would have predicted at the time of the publication of the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR) that barely two months later the desperate act of a street vendor in Tunisia would set off a wave of protest across the Arab world, demanding reform, toppling Governments, blinking in the light of freedom? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would have predicted that by the summer of this year the Royal Air Force would have flown over 1,500 sorties in support of OPERATION UNIFIED PROTECTOR, as part of a NATO-led, UN-mandated coalition, stopping the forces of the Gaddafi regime from using the skies to brutalise his own people and degrading his ability to do so from land and sea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t - and I doubt anyone in this room did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="prepared-for-the-unpredictable"&gt;PREPARED FOR THE UNPREDICTABLE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point is this: despite this lack of prophetic talent, the RAF has flown over 1,500 sorties and continues to contribute significantly to coalition operations in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with our allies, the war machine Gaddafi had been using indiscriminately against his own people has been significantly degraded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF alone has damaged or destroyed over 500 military targets, including command and control sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the performance of Typhoon in its first multi-role contribution to operations has been fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time now we have relied on Typhoon to defend the UK and our dependent territories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Typhoon has truly come of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few months, Typhoon has flown over 1700 hours with the average hours flown per aircraft increasing fourfold - proving its versatility, endurance and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outstanding performance of Typhoon is increasingly impressing those countries who are considering upgrading their fleets, as was clear when I visited India at the weekend. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course operations in Libya are not an RAF only affair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy is off the Libyan coast penning in the regime’s maritime forces, policing the arms embargo, and contributing to strike missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army is flying Apache Helicopters off HMS Ocean providing tactical flexibility to NATO commanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this has been achieved with crucial support from ISTAR and Command and Control platforms and from the air transport and refuelling fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our Armed Forces are doing all this while continuing to focus energies on the main effort in Afghanistan where 9,500 men and women from all three Services face tough and dangerous challenges as I have seen for myself in recent weeks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying that this is easy, without cost, or without consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that we recognise and reward those who are engaged in the very highest areas of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I can announce today that Service personnel on operations in Libyan airspace and territorial waters will receive the Operational Allowance reflecting the rigours and risks that they are facing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our forces currently on Operations in Libya are performing brilliantly and at considerable risk to themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We regularly review the payment of the Operational Allowance that recognises the risk and hardships faced by our forces on operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recently completed such a review, and have decided it is only appropriate to extend the Operational Allowance to all those serving this country on operations in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will result in the payment of Operational Allowance to anyone operating within the landmass, airspace and territorial waters of Libya, including all aircrew operating over the Libyan landmass and to ships and submarines within 12 nm of the coast. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Payment is based on the number of days within the specified areas, and I am pleased to announce will be backdated until 18 March with funding coming from the Reserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the agreed policy, those engaged in Operations for which they are in receipt of Operational Allowance on the day that individuals are notified will be excluded from the redundancy programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, those on a dedicated operational work up package (of up to 6 months) or post operational tour leave on the day of notifications will also be excluded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will never have a crystal ball for international events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is precisely because we can’t always predict, that we have to prepare, plan and put in place contingencies for a range of capabilities against a range of scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is precisely what the National Security Strategy and the SDSR have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may not have mentioned Libya by name, but the National Security Strategy placed an international crisis drawing in the UK and its allies in the top tier of risks over the next five years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planning assumptions in the Strategic Security and Defence Review allow for our Armed Forces to respond to a number of different scenarios, concurrent or otherwise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where planning meets reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can, and have, planned for operations such as those we are undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no-one can predict how long a complex intervention will take - every scenario will be different - militarily, politically and diplomatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustaining the tempo does increase the pressure on both personnel and equipment as planning assumptions are tested, and it tests the ability of defence companies to support front-line operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all accept that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the costs of the Libya campaign are being met from the Treasury reserve, not the MOD budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the MOD, we must use our skills to match resources with commitments in the right way for the circumstances - that is our core business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no-one wants the operations in Libya to take a day longer than necessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the bottom line is this - we can, and will, sustain operations in Libya for as long as it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what our national interest requires, and that is what our commitment under a United Nations mandate to the people of Libya requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not doing this alone, nor would we choose to, and as NATO operations continue, and as members of the alliance participating adjust to the pressures being placed on their Armed Forces, we will look to the breadth of capability that the alliance possesses as a whole to sustain the tempo of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="testing-times"&gt;TESTING TIMES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, these are testing times - for the country as a whole and for Defence in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing times force us to make unpalatable decisions, but they provide opportunities too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take the difficulties first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is committed to eliminating the deficit in the public finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequence of not taking tough action is there for all to see in the events playing out in the Eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic power is the well-spring of strategic strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without it we will not be able to afford in the long-term the public services our country needs and the military forces required to meet the needs of Britain’s security and protect our interests around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this means tough decisions across public spending, including in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such action is not confined to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama has talked of cuts in the US security budgets of $400bn over 12 years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new US Defense Secretary Leon Panetta is undertaking a comprehensive review to contribute to that aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he is clear - as I am - that “we do not have to choose between strong fiscal discipline and strong defence.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in the longer-term one provides for the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Ministry of Defence we face the added pressure of tackling the long ignored black hole in the defence budget bequeathed to us by a decade of over-programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do not do so now, the inevitable consequence will be a severe recalibration in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know of no mainstream voice arguing for that kind of retrenchment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also embarked on reforming the way we go about managing Defence, because if we do not the systemic problems that have allowed this situation to build up will simply repeat themselves overtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the opportunity in adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the SDSR and the reform of Defence management proposed by Lord Levene provide the blueprint for sustainable, well-managed and formidable Armed Forces - structured for the rigours of the future character of conflict - able to swiftly adapt to circumstances and operate with allies - fully able to provide for the Defence of the United Kingdom in an age of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is exactly because of the unpredictability of this volatile world, exactly because of the continuing need to use military force to protect Britain’s interests at distance, that the SDSR places such a premium on the flexibility and adaptability of our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Power and the Royal Air Force are a central component of this vision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I became Secretary of State for Defence there were voices - strong voices - urging me to merge air operations fully into the other services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am clear that the RAF makes a definable and unique contribution to Britain’s Defence - a contribution that it would be wrong to dispense with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some say the distinct heritage and tradition of the RAF is immaterial as it does not have a demonstrable monetary value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the cost of something does not always demonstrate its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot afford to lose the doctrinal understanding of air power and its effects which is burned deep into the collective fibre of the force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of the RAF is not confined to history - far from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="integration-and-internationalism"&gt;INTEGRATION AND INTERNATIONALISM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the RAF is operating across all four enduring air power roles on current operations in Afghanistan and Libya, in addition to the standing operational commitments of defending Britain and our overseas territories: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, securing control of the air, guaranteeing freedom of manoeuvre and action to coalition forces while severely curtailing the options of our adversaries;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, delivering intelligence and real-time information to support commanders and decision makers at every level;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, providing global reach through strategic lift and theatre support through tactical lift;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And fourth, delivering firepower rapidly and with precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Power remains critical to the 21st century battle space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this conference I have no doubt that we will hear many perspectives on the utility of Air Power, not least from the Chief of the Air Staff later today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about two particular areas - joint operations and international operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will also know that today Lords Philip is publishing his report on the Mull of Kintyre accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making a statement on this later in Parliament today , so you will understand why I cannot make further comment on that at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From its very establishment as an independent service in 1918, the RAF has recognised that despite standing alone as a profession, the utility of air power rests in achieving effect not only in the air, but integrating into other domains and contributing decisive effect to campaigns on the land and the sea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of joint operations is in the very DNA of the RAF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So too is the concept of international action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF came of age in World War Two at a time when operating alongside allies was imperative for the survival of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when we famously ‘stood alone’, in the ranks of the RAF who faced the Luftwaffe at the Battle of Britain were pilots from over a dozen other nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the end of the Cold War in the skies over Iraq, Bosnia, Kosovo, Afghanistan and now Libya the RAF has built up an unrivalled experience in working as part of wider international coalitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future character of warfare will demand both joint operations and the international integration of effort and increasingly so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level and sophistication of the integration between air and surface that has been forged in campaigns such as Afghanistan needs to be maintained and then taken forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So too does our understanding of, and interoperability with, our main allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air power in all its forms is a key part of the advantage that Britain continues to hold over opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF’s long focus on flexibility and adaptability is suited to the unpredictability of future conflict and operations in Libya are proving yet again how air power provides decision makers with vastly increased options in supporting the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I can envisage no future conflict in which air power will not be required - none whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air power is, quite simply, mission critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn to a couple of issues that our future RAF must grapple with to ensure that they remain at the forefront of aviation and of military evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="capability"&gt;CAPABILITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the fleet itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role call of iconic aircraft that the RAF has flown over its history is long and distinguished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spitfire, Lancaster, Vulcan and Lightning among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aircraft are now joined in retirement by the Harrier and the Nimrod which have served the people of the United Kingdom magnificently over the last 4 decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These decisions were not taken lightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the decision to reduce manpower, these were some of the most difficult, and alongside the decision to decommission Ark Royal, they were the most finely balanced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to achieve the real savings required to put the Defence programme towards balance, reductions in the number of platforms was essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period later this decade in which the Tornado GR4 force is drawn down and the Joint Strike Fighter comes up to speed will be particularly challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course numbers matter, but as the late Air Vice Marshal ‘Jonnie’ Johnson said, “good aeroplanes are more important.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am particularly pleased with the performance of Typhoon as a multi-role aircraft in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the introduction of the world’s first and only 2nd generation E-SCAN radar, Typhoon will remain at the forefront of aviation technology for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also why I am looking forward to the capabilities of the powerful [and more cost-effective] carrier variant of the Joint Strike Fighter, or ‘Lightning II’ as it will be known - to be jointly operated, of course, with the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overhaul in the consolidated transport fleet will see greater capacity and capability, with the new Voyager tanker and the A400M operating alongside the C17. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the additional capabilities provided by ISTAR programmes, the RAF of Future Force 2020 will have one of the most formidable and high-tech fleets in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let me be clear, the RAF will continue to rely as much on its people as on its platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human underpinning of the RAF - the commitment, talent and technical understanding of the men and women who serve - will be the difference between success and failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I find any polarised position between manned and unmanned aircraft as an utterly false choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with Admiral Mullen, the US Chair of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, that we are at a time of transition in future aviation in terms of remote technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But two things strike me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - a UAV is a sophisticated flying machine with sensors and weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But unless it has a skilled set of human beings operating it, interpreting the data it provides and making real-time decisions it has absolutely no impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - we are some way away from remotely piloted systems being able to deliver all that manned aircraft can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does not mean that we do not need to research, develop and invest in remotely piloted technology for all three services - and we will do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the foreseeable future it will be a combination of the speed, payload and survivability that only piloted systems can currently supply - complemented by the persistence and flexibility of remotely piloted air systems - that deliver the overall air power effect that is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude on this theme of the utility of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen for myself on many occasions what the RAF do - from my time as a GP at Beaconsfield to Tango ramp at Kandahar airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it’s not all about fast jets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the work of those at the less glamorous but equally critical end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the air bridge up and running, keeping our forces supplied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The force protection provided by the RAF Regiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The medics, the mechanics, the armourers, the analysts, the air traffic controllers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the support staff that keep the organisation delivering at the sharp end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Air Chief Marshal Sir Stephen Dalton, the RAF has a Chief of Staff who not only directs his own service with insight, commitment and tenacity and but just as importantly who understands the application of military power across the three services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is supported in his efforts by some of the most capable and dedicated men and women in the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been times in our history when the light blue line was the only thing that stood between us and defeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, if so called upon today, this generation will take the fight to the enemy, no matter what the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of this United Kingdom know that the Royal Air Force will never let them down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56484</id>
    <published>2011-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:06:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/operational-allowance-extended-to-libya-operations"/>
    <title>Operational Allowance extended to Libya operations</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Service personnel operating within the landmass, airspace and territorial waters of Libya are now eligible to receive the Operational Allowance (OA), Defence Secretary Dr Liam Fox announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence conducts a review of the locations eligible for OA on a six-monthly basis - the most recent of which led to today’s extension and means that personnel working as part of the ongoing campaign to protect civilians under United Nations Security Council Resolution 1973 will now receive the Operational Allowance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Operational Allowance is already paid to all Service personnel serving in Afghanistan on Operation HERRICK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move means that all servicemen and women deployed within the geographical confines of Libya on Operation ELLAMY will now receive the allowance, which is based on an assessment of the risk and rigour of the operating environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pilots and aircrew operating over the Libyan landmass and the crew of ships and submarines operating within 12 nautical miles (22km) of the coast will receive the allowance for each day that they are serving in these specific areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The payments will be backdated to 18 March this year, when the United Nations resolution justifying military action was signed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been doubled by the Government last year, the tax-free Operational Allowance now stands at £29.02 per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Fox said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is important that we recognise and reward those Service personnel who are engaged in the very highest areas of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Eligibility for the Operational Allowance reflects the rigour and risk of the operation in question and I am delighted that we can now extend these payments and recognise more of our brave servicemen and women in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18717</id>
    <published>2011-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T13:41:39+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-06-27-reforming-defence"/>
    <title>2011/06/27 - Reforming Defence</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the Reform Think Tank, 1 Whitehall Place, London on Monday 27 June 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I became Defence Secretary just over a year ago with great expectations about what we could achieve in Defence but with eyes wide open about what we would face and with growing realisation of the scale of the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I will set out what we have accomplished and what remains still to be done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the problems inherited from the Blair-Brown government, Defence was always going to provide one of the greatest headaches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As George Osborne has said “of all the budgets I have seen, the defence budget was the one that was the most chaotic, the most disorganised, the most overcommitted”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years successive Defence Secretaries failed to get a grip on the equipment programme and failed to hold the department and industry to account for delays and poor cost-estimation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often in the past, in order to get projects included in the programme, fantasy numbers have been accepted at the outset knowing that cost overruns could be recovered later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Bernard Gray said in his 2009 report “(the MoD has) too many types of equipment being ordered for too large a range of tasks at too high a specification. This programme is unaffordable on any likely projection of future budgets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their final year in office alone Labour presided over an increase of reported cost by a staggering £3.3 billion in just 2 programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it has been no easy task to match our aspirations with our resources, especially in the appalling economic mess left behind by Labour. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has also been essential to deal with the very structures which allowed the Ministry of Defence and its budget to become so dysfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course we knew the financial position we were inheriting was grim. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We assessed that there was an unfunded liability of at least £38 billion up to 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we could not know was that the highly committed nature of the budget, especially in the early years, meant that there was little room to deal with the problem without taking some very difficult decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, with the budget in the first year already 90% contractually committed they were unavoidable constraints on the speed at which we could act to reduce the deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that Labour ministers knew the defence program was unsustainable they continued to add new elements to it knowing that there were no funds in the budget to finance them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future defence program was worse than a delusion- it was a deliberate lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the scale of the problem we were never likely to be able to eliminate Labour’s black hole quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the reductions in the future programme already made, we need reform of the MoD and cost reduction, changes to the procurement practices and, as the Prime Minister has said, a year-on-year real terms increase in defence spending in the second half of the decade to meet Future Force 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have said repeatedly that tackling the crisis in the public finances is not just an issue of economics but an issue of national security too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons of history are clear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative economic power is the wellspring of strategic strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And conversely, economic weakness debilitates every arm of government including security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government inherited from Labour a record peacetime annual deficit equal to over 11% of GDP. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural economic weakness, if not dealt with, will bring an unavoidable reduction in our ability to shape the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So realigning our Defence priorities with the economic realities was essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within days of entering office the Coalition Government launched the Strategic Defence and Security Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first fundamental review of defence in 12 years, and the first of its kind to span the whole of government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new National Security Strategy set out the policy framework that was the force driver of the SDSR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It recognised that we are both more secure and yet more vulnerable than in most of our history and that only by mobilising the whole of Government would our country’s security interests be safeguarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant defence, diplomacy and development, delivered through the National Security Council, all pulling in the same direction with UK’s interest in mind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all-of-government approach is at the heart of the coalition approach to government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR was a coherent outcome that ensured that we have an overarching ‘adaptive posture’ to deal with the threats of today and begin the transformation of our Armed Forces to meet the challenges of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering each defence programme we developed a generic template to compare the respective costs, capability, operational risk, opportunities for regeneration and real-world risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way we could make objective decisions based on the facts and a clear understanding of the risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adaptive posture demands that our Armed Forces become a more flexible and agile force with global reach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;capable of providing nuclear and conventional deterrence, containment, coercion and intervention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;investing in new technology and capabilities more suited to the likely character of future conflict, such as cyber security &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;divesting ourselves of capabilities that have less utility in the post-Cold War world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and with the ability to regenerate capabilities that are not needed now if threats change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Achieving all of this in the circumstances meant smaller armed forces, painful decisions, and sacrifice from our people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it has ensured we will remain in the premier league of military powers able to project influence and protect our interests wherever they may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya has proved to be the acid test of the SDSR and the adaptable posture we advocated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were amongst the first countries to evacuate our own nationals, and helped many other countries to do the same; it was the UK that coordinated much of the humanitarian effort; and it was the UK who led the way in establishing the no fly zone and preventing a massacre in Benghazi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR may not have named Libya, but it imagined exactly the type of conflict we would be in and prepared us accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be very clear, we are able to continue operations in Libya for however long is necessary and have the political resolve and will to do so..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have advocated a reopening of the SDSR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the same strategic outlook, the same financial constraints and the same black hole the outcome would remain the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they are really asking for is not a reopening of the SDSR, but a reopening of the cross-Government Comprehensive Spending Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who advocate this course need to tell us which taxes they will raise, what services they will cut more, or indeed if they intend to take the insane course of yet more borrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR required tough choices, but these were taken on the basis of clear military advice and within a financial environment that constituted a national economic crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me take head on the persistent claim that the nature of our operations in Libya, and the cost of them, would be different had we an aircraft carrier and the Harrier in service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that we still would have based RAF Tornados and Typhoon to Italy for the air to air role and to carry the precision weaponry such as Stormshadow or Brimstone that Harrier cannot carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would not have been cheaper - in fact it would have been much more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could simply not afford to retain a third fast jet type and deal with Labours legacy on Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labour had already reduced the Harrier fleet in 2009, leaving them unable to sustain operations in Afghanistan let alone undertake contingencies such as Libya - only Tornado has the capacity to do both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harrier served us well, but we have to move on and embrace new technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However great the contribution in the past we cannot allow sentiment to drive our policy for the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much to look forward to in Defence for all three services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will continue to have the fourth largest defence budget in the world-a fact that seems to have been overlooked by many commentators and critics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2020 the Royal Navy will have new aircraft carriers, a high readiness amphibious capability and a new fleet of Type 45 destroyers and Astute class submarines, and soon after, the Type 26 Global Combat Ship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RAF will be built around state of the art multi-role fleets of Joint Strike Fighter and Typhoon jets, as well as a new fleet of strategic and tactical transport aircraft with the introduction of the A400M and Voyager. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army, based on Multi-Role Brigades, will be powerful, flexible, fully equipped for the land environment and able to operate across the spectrum of conflict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD spends around a third of its budget every year, or around £13bn, on equipment acquisition or equipment support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fundamental activity at the heart of defence and if and if it fails, it is the men and women on the frontline who suffer the consequences and the tax payer who pays the price. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February of this year I announced a programme of work aimed at dealing with the fundamental causes of delays and poor cost estimation in the equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the so-called conspiracy of optimism, through which the risks and costs in new or existing projects are under-estimated both by industry and government, only to find mushrooming costs and time delays later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the inclusion of programmes without clear budget lines for development, procurement and deployment that merely compounded an already unaffordable defence programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, a lack of real time cost control and tight budgetary discipline that masked project failure and neutered effective project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, a relationship with industry that was out of balance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All too often the master had become the servant, with value for money and the needs of our armed forces being undermined by inefficient practices and unreconstructed cost-bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost over runs and time delays as well as poor cost and risk estimation have long plagued successive Defence Secretaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is no question that the performance at DE&amp;amp;S is improving, much more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end I established the Major Projects Review Board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board, which I Chair, receives a quarterly update on the Ministry’s major programs to ensure that they are on time and within budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are not, those responsible are rigorously held to account as those who attended the first session last week will attest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these programmes continue to suffer time delays or cost increases, relevant details of programmes and the reasons for failure will be made public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way market forces can hold industry and the department dramatic to account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has begun with the 20 biggest projects by value and will rapidly expand to the 50 biggest projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board has already reviewed several programs and demanded improvements of the management teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also set up the Defence Exports Support Board, abolished the National Defence Industries Council and will shortly publish our white paper on equipment support and technology for UK defence following the successful consultation launched by Peter Luff and Bernard Gray. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will cover how we will identify the critical areas where the UK has or needs an operational advantage and freedom of action for a particular capability; how we intend to strengthen bilateral international co-operation and collaboration; how we will enable SMEs, which are a vital source of innovation and flexibility, to fulfil their potential; and how we will give support to exports within a framework of responsible licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know how but I anticipate it will emphasise open competition in the global market, buying off-the-shelf where we can, and only using single-source suppliers were we must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also set out the vital importance of science and technology to our future security and the viability of UK industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together this work will ensure that critical skills are retained in some of our most technologically advanced areas, that SMEs can compete as equals and British industry remains at the cutting edge on the world market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An essential part of reducing the cost of the defence programme was renegotiating our contractual liabilities with industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme has begun, and we are already looking at 300 contracts in light of the SDSR decisions to ensure they are both necessary and give greater value for money for the taxpayer where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also embarked on a pilot programme to renegotiate three of our PFIs, with a number of further projects being considered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June Chief of Defence Materiel - Bernard Gray - launched ‘The Materiel Strategy’ that will encompass a fundamental review of the delivery of equipment and support to the front line and will deliver the necessary step change in performance and reduction in running cost needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernard Gray is talking to a number of stakeholders both within the Department and outside to understand the true nature of the problems we face, their root causes and potential solutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernard’s previous experience in the commercial world and his far reaching review of defence acquisition in 2009 give me confidence that the potential solutions will challenge the accepted norm and provide fundamentally different ways of doing business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect to see recommendations for the way forward towards the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of our positive vision for the future can be achieved if we don’t tackle the drivers of structural financial instability and the institutional lack of accountability throughout the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department needed radical reform, so in August of last year I asked Lord Levene to establish a hard hitting group of external experts to lead a root and branch review of the way the department was structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report will be published later today, setting out a vision of transformation on a scale not seen in Defence for a generation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will understand why I am unable to detail the recommendations here before I have put them to the House, but I can say that there are a number of key strategic themes that have influenced this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene is clear in his critique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A department with overly bureaucratic management structures, dominated by committees leading to indecisiveness and a lack of responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bloated top level defence board without Ministerial membership allowing strategic decision to drift and unable to reconcile ambition with resources. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budget holders without the levers needed to deliver and Ministers kept in the dark. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene has proposed a new, simpler and more cost-effective model for departmental management, with clear allocation of responsibility, authority and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will mark an end to the micromanagement of the individual services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report addresses the lack of key skills and fragmented career paths within defence and considers radical ways in which the Department can encourage a more joint approach across defence and promote the advocacy of joint capabilities, particularly those that deal with emerging threats such as cyber and cross-cutting issues such as intelligence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so many different and at times conflicting channels of military advice, greater clarification at the top of the services is also given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also advocates tighter financial management and a more risk-aware and cost-conscious mentality at every level at the Ministry of Defence, civilian and military alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is not a criticism of our people, but a constructive critique of a department in need of reform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Lord Levene’s work has exposed that the people who are at the heart of defence are the greatest advocates of the need for change at the MoD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the various reforms of acquisition and departmental structure, our Armed Forces themselves are undergoing similar change to deliver the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rationalisation of RAF bases, the move to a new concept of deployable Multi-role brigades and the withdrawal of our forces from Germany all mean we need to reconsider the basing of our forces across the whole of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing Basing Review was the necessary follow-on work from the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It offers a significant opportunity to balance the Defence footprint across the UK, and provide greater stability to our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will bring better value for money for the tax payer, as well as helping to realise the challenging estate sales targets we are committed to achieving. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the delivery of defence capability is paramount, careful consideration has been given to a range of other factors including the welfare of service families and consistency with the New Employment Model as well as the impacts on the local economy and environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is making good progress, and we hope to be able to announce the key outcomes shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the three services the way in which we generate forces vary greatly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also operate differently from international comparators. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason in December of last year I launched a review of the way we generate and sustain forces within defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work has considered the efficiency and effectiveness of the processes by which individuals and units are prepared for operations and the overall balance between the Front Line and Non Front Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has also reviewed the optimum tour length, tour interval and harmony for the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect the review to propose moving toward increased standardisation in tour lengths across the services, whilst maintaining a scalable approach where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maximising key and niche skills that rest in our Reserves also demand serious consideration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find the best balance of Regular, Reserves, Civil Servants and Contractors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Future Reserves 2020 study (FR2020) was commissioned by the Prime Minister to ensure the most cost-effective use of Reservists to meet the UK’s operational requirements for future conflict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FR2020 Commission is committed to ensuring that the Reservist experience remains valuable for both the individual and his/her employer, as well as providing an important output for Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to reviewing the recommendations of the commission shortly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there needs to be cultural changes too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There must be a rebalancing between political control of the armed forces from the centre and the ability of service chiefs to manage their own services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will set out plans by which I mean to do this in the House of Commons this afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to see more open, meritocratic Armed Forces better shaped to adapt to the challenges of the future, able to absorb the widest range of talents possible and to prepare for the future as well as understanding the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these ideas – budgetary control, reform of procurement, reform of MoD structure, export promotion, SME development or change to the Armed Forces will be solutions by themselves to the problems we inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But taken together they provide a radical programme for change which will provide stability for future planning and improved security of United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18713</id>
    <published>2011-06-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T14:11:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-06-07-cyber-the-war-of-the-invisible-enemy"/>
    <title>2011/06/07 - Cyber: The War of the Invisible Enemy</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at the London Chamber of Commerce and Industry Annual Defence Dinner, on Tuesday 7 June 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, while we dine, Britain’s interests are under attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a continuous battle being waged against us, day in, day out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 2009 and 2010, security incidents more than doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this in Afghanistan? No - this was in cyber space and the target was the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I and my senior colleagues are routinely alerted to incidents that could have had severe consequences if they’d not been stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our systems are targeted by criminals, foreign intelligence services and other malicious actors seeking to exploit our people, corrupt our systems and steal information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea of the challenge, last year we in the MOD blocked and investigated over 1,000 potentially serious attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The risks to Defence are real, and I take them very seriously. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These risks are not restricted by the geographic constraints of conventional conflict - we are not protected by distance or by natural barriers - in cyberspace our adversaries are on our doorstep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the war of the invisible enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success cannot be achieved by government alone because, in cyber space, there are few boundaries between government, business and every individual internet user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now see weekly reports of cyber attacks against businesses, institutions and networks used by people going about their daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost to the UK economy of cyber crime is estimated to be in the region of £27bn a year and rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are attacks against the whole fabric of our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to cyber security - we must fight this battle together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of our response must be to act internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foreign Secretary has set out 7 broad principles which the UK sees as important including the need for governments to act proportionally in accordance with international law, the need to provide proper protect for intellectual property and the need to act collectively to tackle the threat of cyber criminality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take international dialogue forward the UK will host in London in November an International Cyber Conference that aims to provide some focus to the currently fragmented international response to the challenges of cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must also continue to act here at home.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why, last autumn as part of the Strategic Defence and Security Review (SDSR), we allocated an extra £650m to create a National Cyber Security Programme funding work across government, including the MOD, to strengthen our understanding, our resilience and our defences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk today about how we can work together to meet this threat, but first I want to talk about other challenges facing Defence over the next few years and how those relate to industry in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-weakness-is-a-national-security-liability"&gt;ECONOMIC WEAKNESS IS A NATIONAL SECURITY LIABILITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government inherited a level of debt and economic mismanagement that represents a national economic emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the aggressive action we are taking to eliminate the structural deficit, the Office for Budget Responsibility forecasts public sector net debt to peak at over 70% of GDP in 2014/15 - well over 1.3 trillion pounds - equivalent to almost 40 years spending on Defence at the level of this years budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put aside for a moment the economic arguments about how Britain’s deficit reduction programme brings confidence to the financial markets, just consider the opportunity costs of running a national debt of this size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest, just the interest, paid out last year was £43bn -  around the same as the annual budgets of the MoD, FCO and DfID combined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not just opportunity costs - this is an issue of national security too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons of history are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative economic power is the wellspring of strategic strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural economic weakness, if not dealt with, brings an unavoidable reduction in any country’s ability to shape the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the National Security Strategy clearly sets out, Britain’s national interest requires our continued full and active engagement in world affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trade and economic relationships are world-wide - we are connected to, and reliant on, the global economic system as never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A threat that appears in one part of the world, such as in Afghanistan, can swiftly be felt on our streets and those of our allies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect our interests at home, we must project our influence abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain can ill-afford another ‘East of Suez’ moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But without a strong, sustainable economy we will not be able to afford the Armed Forces and other levers of influence required to keep us safe in a volatile and unpredictable age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deficit reduction has to be the Government’s number one priority in the short-term, and it is something I am fully signed up to, both as a Cabinet Member and as Defence Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Prime Minister said yesterday, “In the end, this isn’t just about economics - it is also about the morality of it all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-defence-deficit"&gt;THE DEFENCE DEFICIT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence budget was perhaps the worst inheritance of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the SDSR the forward defence programme was overcommitted to the tune of £38bn over the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons why, in relation to the vast majority of government departments, the MOD is contributing less to deficit reduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the mess we inherited, putting Defence on a sure footing with a predictable budget is going to take time and cannot be pain-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the only way in the long-term that we can we can sustain the Armed Forces we require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Defence and Security Review has set the right direction, ensuring that we will remain in the premier league of military powers - supported by the fourth largest defence budget in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adaptable posture we have embraced gives us the best capability to respond with agility to changing threats in an uncertain world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But staying the course will require sustaining the strict cost-control regime I have put in place at the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the consequences of the mismanagement of Defence over the last decade - including what Chief of Defence Materiel, Bernard Gray described as ‘the conspiracy of optimism’ in the department’s planning - is that we have to prove that Defence can be managed sustainably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is as if we have taken over a troubled business, with the Treasury as our main investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to show that we can live within our means and have a business plan for recovery to ensure the further investment we need to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR is part of that plan, but so too is tackling the drivers of systemic financial instability and the institutional lack of accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the work of Lord Levene and his Defence Reform Unit to reform the operating model of Defence is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is the work of Bernard Gray on ‘The Materiel Strategy’ to achieve best value in procurement and set the forward equipment programme on a sustainable basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably - the relationship between Defence and the industries that support our Armed Forces will have to change too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry"&gt;INDUSTRY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have published our Green paper on Equipment, Support and Technology with the White paper expected later this year and obviously I can’t pre-empt its conclusions tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the principles are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are determined to create a climate in which Defence and Security companies are resilient, and can flourish, without using the Defence Budget to subsidise them - maximising the benefits of international collaboration and exportability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be crystal clear, the primary purpose of defence procurement is to provide our Armed Forces with the equipment and support they require to do the job we ask of them and at a cost acceptable to the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This need not be inconsistent with a decent rate of return for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Budget is there to be used for Defence purposes and where there’s a real need to protect national security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our approach is not laissez-faire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an interest in our wider security relationships, British influence, and the economic benefits of a flourishing industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and other factors will be weighed when spending the £20bn we do each year on Defence with UK-based industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am clear that our default position is open competition and buying off-the-shelf where we can, albeit that many of the goods on the shelf are wholly or partly British. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science and Technology is a key element of our overall capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R&amp;amp;D is extremely important in delivering a technological edge to the Forces of the future and continuing to support them on operations today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government has allocated £200 million for the establishment of a network of elite Technology and Innovation Centres which will help the UK to take advantage of new and emerging technologies in areas where there are large global market opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas and technology can come from across the S&amp;amp;T community - big and small industry and the UK’s excellent universities and research organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true in the work required to maintain and develop our defences in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cyber"&gt;CYBER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Security Strategy recognises the threat of attacks from cyber space as being in the top tier of our national security concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This threat is growing in scale and sophistication - my Department is a prime target. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the core Defence networks there were an average of over a million security alerts every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of this can be attributed to deliberate activity by adversaries - many are the result of the back ground noise of the Internet and the unintended consequences of the interconnected environment in which we have to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I said earlier many are potentially serious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the cynic might say that we have coped for hundreds of years with the threat of espionage from our competitors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have always adapted and designed strategies to thwart our adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this modern cyber age, where we have increased our own ability to work efficiently, exploit paperless environments and share information - we have made the task for our adversaries easier - and they have not been shy in taking advantage of our open and free society. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the opening of the new Global Operations and Security Control Centre, we have already made significant strides in ensuring that we can defend our departmental systems, but there is more to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with our ICT suppliers, we will continue to develop the defensive capability of our systems and we will continually re-evaluate our budgetary plans as the threat evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I try to come to terms with the challenges that my Department faces in cyber space, I am constantly reminded that the issue is not just one for our departmental systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no Maginot Line in cyber space as recent high profile attacks on defence contractors have shown. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our national intellectual property in defence and security industries is at risk from a systematic marauding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only could it severely affect the future success of British industry, our economic advantage, and the country’s financial recovery - but also directly impacts upon our national security today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pride ourselves in maintaining a technological edge over our adversaries and collectively, Aerospace and Defence companies in this room spend over £1.7 Billion on R&amp;amp;D every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that technological edge is at risk of being eroded as your hard won nuggets of intellectual property are targeted on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without proper protection, what took years of diligent work and millions of pounds of funding to develop could fall victim to an expert adversary with the right know-how working on a simple networked laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is taking this seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister led a senior level meeting with key Industry CEOs in February to look at the problem and how we might tackle it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for the Cabinet Office, Francis Maude now has responsibility for co-ordinating efforts on cyber security across government and with business and academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new type of partnership will be required if we are to survive this new battle in cyber space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partnerships often fail when there is no shared interest in the outcome - I believe the protection of our intellectual property and the national advantage it affords offers just such a shared interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest we forget, much of the infrastructure we are worried about is not government property, but it is no less critical to our society and its security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, we must recognise that cyber space is now where most business is done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Sony incident and the phishing attacks on the Google accounts of US officials have proven that a passive approach to cyber security is not enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detica’s recent study of the costs of cyber crime suggest that the Aerospace and defence sector is particularly exposed -  losing £1.6bn per year as a result of espionage and the theft of intellectual property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I look across the defence and security industries, I see a complex supply chain with many companies, all of whom use the internet to do business, and all of whom are vulnerable to cyber intrusions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that increasingly we will worry about how seriously our suppliers take account of the cyber security threat when we are placing our business, so I am encouraged by the recent joint initiative by ADS and Intellect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will establish a new partnership with you - I will make sure that my department plays its part by being more open about the scale and nature of the threat and by tackling barriers to international co-operation on cyber security matters with our key Allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I look to you to recognise the seriousness of this issue -  and to work with me to improve our national security and our competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and Gentlemen, we face a challenging few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must tackle the deficit, grow our economy, and put defence on a sustainable footing while ensuring that we are successful in the wars of today - in Afghanistan, in Libya and in cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this a new partnership between government and business is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to provide our Armed Forces with the equipment and support they require at a cost that the taxpayer is willing to bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has to provide industry with a competitive edge in the global market, but it has to be based on reality not wishful thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to deal with the world as it is, not as we hope it would be, and that includes the opportunities and challenges of cyber space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that a strong economy is a national security requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An affordable Defence programme is the only responsible way to support our Armed Forces in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18710</id>
    <published>2011-05-19T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-08T14:03:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2011-05-19-strong-economy-strong-defence-strategic-reach-protecting-national-security-in-the-21st-century"/>
    <title>2011/05/19 - Strong Economy, Strong Defence, Strategic Reach: Protecting National Security in the 21st Century</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Secretary of State for Defence at Chatham House, London on Thursday 19 May 2011.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true test of Government is to act not for party political advantage, but to act in the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government inherited a level of debt and economic mismanagement that represents a national economic emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deal with it we have had to take difficult and potentially unpopular measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they are essential if we are to put Britain back on track in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as important for national security as it is for national prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This requires not only dealing with the here and now, but charting a course 10, 15, 20 years ahead - acting to position the country for the safety and prosperity of future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="acting-in-the-national-interest"&gt;ACTING IN THE NATIONAL INTEREST&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in no area is this more important than in Defence and Security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Armed Forces remain at a high and sustained operational tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirement to fight, and win, the wars of today is not optional but necessary to protect national security and meet the national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when our Armed Forces are committed, they deserve and the country expects that they get the support they need to do the job we ask of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why current operations in Afghanistan and in Libya remain the priority for the Ministry of Defence and the men and women of our Armed Forces fighting on the front-line get first call on MOD resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the requirement for strategic thinking, for strategic planning and preparation - the requirement to play the long-game - is equally necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - because conflict and threats to national security do not fit neatly into electoral cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hunt for Osama bin Laden and the campaign against al-Qaeda’s brand of violent extremism has been taken forward under three American Presidents and three British Prime Ministers of different political persuasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the long watch of the Cold War - it took 10 different US Presidents and 9 different British Prime Ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - the character of conflict evolves and new threats arise, but the complex military equipment required to meet these challenges can take a decade or more to design and build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we must constantly scan the horizon and prepare for the world as it will be, not as we hope it will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Defence, contingency planning is central to ensuring that we are prepared for what may come - even if we can’t predict exactly when and where threats may emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drives a continuing requirement for Armed Forces that are agile, adaptable and of the highest quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - building and sustaining the power, influence and prosperity of a country in the long flow of history - particularly in our age of rapid change and unpredictability - requires action now to ensure the country can succeed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy security is one example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change would be another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I want to set out what we have achieved in Defence over the last year to set in place a long-term strategy for the safety, security and prosperity of our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Defence and Security Review has ensured that we will remain in the premier league of military powers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not an agenda for retrenchment; it’s an ambitious agenda for transformation over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not an agenda for the next general election; it’s an agenda for the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This long-term vision for Britain’s Defence depends upon a sound economic base that enables sustainable military power to be built - together economic power and military power are the foundation of global influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper strategy for the long-term health of our country must balance ends and ways with the means available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why tackling the crisis in the public finances is not just an issue of economics but an issue of national security too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is central to sustaining in the long-term Britain’s reach, military power and influence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-lessons-of-history"&gt;THE LESSONS OF HISTORY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us not forget our own history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contraction of European influence in the 20th century was driven as much by the economic exhaustion of European nations over two World Wars as it was by political enlightenment in support of decolonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the First World War in the 1920s and 30s, Britain’s national debt was regularly over 150% of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After World War Two, it peaked at around 250% of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As examples of the effect, economic considerations underpinned both the British withdrawal from Palestine in 1948, and the abandonment of the Suez campaign in 1956.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t until the 1970s that the debt position recovered to under 50% of GDP - a quarter of a century after the end of the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain’s so-called ‘East of Suez’ moment in 1967 when the Wilson Government announced a major withdrawal of UK forces from South East Asia, was a response to the decline in the country’s relative economic strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, the Cold War was won because the Soviet Union collapsed under the weight of an economic system that could not sustain the myth of communism’s superiority - nor sustain the military forces required to hold it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the early 1980s for instance, the Soviet Union was spending around 20% of GDP on Defence - roughly four times the level of the US and wholly unsustainable in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons of history are clear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative economic power is the wellspring of strategic strength. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And conversely, economic weakness debilitates every arm of government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural economic weakness, if not dealt with, will bring an unavoidable reduction in our ability to shape the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-weakness-is-a-national-security-liability"&gt;ECONOMIC WEAKNESS IS A NATIONAL SECURITY LIABILITY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s relate these lessons to our situation today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking at Chatham House last week, Niall Ferguson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“fiscal and monetary stimulus, no matter how much it may take and how many times you read aloud the collected works of John Maynard Keynes, sooner or later brings a hangover.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has fallen to this Coalition Government to nurse Britain through the hangover of the decade of financial mismanagement that put us where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When, as Chancellor, Gordon Brown abandoned sticking to the previous Conservative Government’s strict spending policies, Britain’s national debt began an inexorable rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the benign economic environment of most of the last decade, from 2002-2007 under Labour, UK national debt as a percentage of GDP increased not decreased - from around 31% to around 37%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the back of the financial crisis it has ballooned to around 60% of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government inherited from Labour a record peacetime annual deficit equal of over 11% of GDP - in 2009/10 alone that meant a spend of over £150bn more than the Government brought in in income. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the structural deficit is eliminated, Britain’s national debt will only continue to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the Coalition’s aggressive action, the Office for Budget Responsibility forecasts public sector net debt to peak at over 70% of GDP in 2014/15. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It currently stands at over £900bn - equivalent to almost a quarter of a century of spending on Defence at the level of this year’s budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015 it is likely to reach well over 1.3 trillion pounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest, just the interest, paid out last year alone was £43bn - greater than the annual budgets of the MoD, FCO and DfID combined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£43bn pounds a year of taxpayers’ money that could pay for a tax cut to each taxpayer of almost £1,500 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could pay for a million teachers or over a million nurses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Defence - a dozen Queen Elizabeth Aircraft Carriers or 33 Astute Class submarines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the bad news is, next year the interest payments will be £50bn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all while we are tackling the deficit and before we even begin reducing the national debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me boil down this barrage of statistics to my central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chancellor doesn’t just sit on the National Security Council to tell us how much everything costs, he does so because this Government recognises what the last did not - that our national security is linked to the health of our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating military power on the back of borrowing at times of extreme or existential threat, such as during the World War Two, is understandable and reasonable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you continue to do so as a matter of routine, as Labour did over the last decade, you set off a ticking fiscal time bomb that if not defused will inevitably result in strategic shrinkage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t come into politics to cut the defence budget, but neither did I come into politics to be fiscally irresponsible - because the consequences of that are written deep in the historical record. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a hawk on defence, you need to be a hawk on the deficit and the national debt too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-defence-deficit"&gt;THE DEFENCE DEFICIT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence spending represents the fourth largest chunk of public expenditure, so the MoD must play its part in addressing the current economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the MOD we face a particularly tough job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence budget was perhaps the worst inheritance of all -  before the SDSR the forward defence programme was overextended to the tune of £38bn over the next decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was spending on all the equipment, programmes and all other variables previously planned over and above a budget rising at the rate of inflation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knew the Defence Budget was running hot and that addressing this would have been required regardless of fiscal tightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons why, in relation to the vast majority of government departments, the MOD is contributing less to deficit reduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is also why the transformation of Defence will have to take place over a longer-term period too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cannot be done overnight - with sunk costs, kit in build, contractual liabilities and other inherited committed spend, room for manoeuvre in the short-term is limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s a process charting a course for the recovery of Defence capability and the sustainability of its funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strategic Defence and Security Review has set the right direction - and I will return to this and Future Force 2020 in a moment - but staying the course will require sustaining the strict cost-control regime I have put in place at the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will inevitably require that tough decisions are taken on a regular basis to keep the budget on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the SDSR we made it clear that there would be a series of complicated second order consequences including the basing and reserves reviews, as well as the emerging work from the Defence Reform Unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having completed the current planning round, we have started the next Planning Round to take forward the work needed to balance defence priorities and the budget over the long-term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department has recently initiated a three month exercise as part of that work to ensure we match our assumptions with our spending settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to draw all this work together to inform the next planning round and to avoid the mistakes of the previous government in building up to an unsustainable Defence programme &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made it clear that while the SDSR had made substantial inroads into the £38bn funding deficit, there is still more to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the mess we inherited putting Defence on a sure footing, with a predictable budget, was always going to take time, but we believe it is better to be thorough than quick&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister has set out his personal view, with which I strongly agree, that achieving our vision for the future structure of our Armed Forces will require year-on-year real growth in the Defence Budget after 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we approach the next General Election, and as we prepare for the next Defence Review in 2015, a commitment to meet Future Force 2020 will be a key signifier for those political parties dedicated to the vision of a Britain active on the world stage and protected at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="building-for-the-future"&gt;BUILDING FOR THE FUTURE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the National Security Strategy clearly sets out - our national interest requires our continued full and active engagement in world affairs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trade and economic relationships are global.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A threat that appears in one part of the world can swiftly be felt at home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect our interests at home, we must project our influence abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming together as they did, the National Security Strategy, the Strategic Defence and Security Review and the Comprehensive Spending Review, set us on a course to maintain our strategic reach, renew military capability on a sustainable basis, and address the structural weakness of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the MOD it was not only a budgetary deficit that we inherited. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a capability deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had failed properly to adapt to meet future challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had scores of tanks on the German plains, but insufficient cyber capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were committed to an expeditionary policy, but increasingly dependent on ageing strategic airlift. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have embarked on a long-term programme of renewal and revitalisation in Defence that maintains our strategic reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so we have rejected alternative postures quite strongly advocated by some. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was that we should invest in what you might call ‘Fortress Britain’, withdrawing back closer to home and investing in the appropriate assets in that direction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under such a posture there would be no requirement for expeditionary capabilities on our current scale, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were others who said to go exactly the other way, and that we should have a highly committed posture and just assume that the conflicts of the future would be like the one we currently face in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under such a posture there would be no requirement for widespread maritime capabilities, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that is difficult is to quantify but undoubtedly real is Britain’s invisible export of security and stability carried out by our Armed Forces, including the Royal Navy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearing mines in the Arabian Gulf, anti-piracy actions in the Gulf of Aden, protecting our own sea lanes - all contribute to international stability and the free movement of goods upon which our prosperity relies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So neither a fortress nor a committed posture would have met the requirement in the National Security Strategy for continued engagement in a world where threats are evolving and unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adaptable posture we have embraced gives us the best capability to respond with agility to changing threats in an uncertain world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means keeping our forces ready to react swiftly to those things we cannot easily predict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means upgrading strategic lift capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means investment in Special Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means being efficient, cutting down on duplication and numbers of equipment types to shorten the tail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it means investing in areas of capability that suit the future character of warfare - such as cyber, intelligence and unmanned technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means investing in activities, such as conflict prevention and aid, that prevent the development of threats ‘upstream’, before they require a more demanding military response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in doing so we are not ignoring conventional military power required for flexible, multi-rolled, deployable forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2020, The RAF will be built around hi-tech multi-role combat aircraft Typhoon and the Joint Strike Fighter, surveillance and intelligence platforms such as Airseeker, and a new fleet of strategic and tactical transport aircraft including A400M and Voyager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Navy will have new aircraft carriers with the JSF carrier-variant, a high readiness amphibious capability, a new fleet of Type 45 destroyers and Astute class submarines - and ready at that point to accept the new Global Combat Ship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army, based on Multi-Role Brigades, will be powerful, flexible, fully equipped for the land environment and able to operate across the spectrum of conflict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will remain one of the few countries who can deploy and sustain a brigade sized force plus its air and maritime enablers, capable of both intervention and stabilisation operations almost anywhere in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will remain a nuclear power, maintaining a minimum credible nuclear deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely clear, as I said in the House of Commons yesterday, that a minimum nuclear deterrent based on the Trident missile delivery system and continuous at sea deterrence is right for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have the fourth largest defence budget in the world and will continue to meet the NATO target of spending 2% of GDP on Defence over the spending review period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, pursuing the necessary long-term strategy set out in the SDSR is not the only mark of renewal in Defence over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years successive Defence Secretaries have failed, often through no fault of their own, to get a grip on the equipment programme and failed to hold the department and industry to account for delays and poor cost-estimation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drivers of structural financial instability and the institutional lack of accountability, from ministers down, must be tackled if we are to avoid history repeating itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the work of Lord Levene and his Defence Reform Unit to reform the operating model of Defence is so important along side the work of the Chief of Defence Materiel, Bernard Gray, to set the forward equipment programme on a sustainable basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also acting to redraw and rejuvenate the relationship with industry to ensure the tax payer gets the best deal from the investment in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all measures in support of the long-term transformation of Defence and the vision set out in the SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labour’s Defence Green Paper published just months before the election admitted with what I have to say is spectacular understatement that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“the forward defence programme faces challenging financial pressures”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It said in particular that the MOD:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“cannot proceed with all the activities and programmes we currently aspire to, while simultaneously supporting our current operations and investing in the new capabilities we need. We will need to make tough decisions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we have made those tough decisions, and I stand by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in setting your strategic direction and sticking to your plan unless the facts change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we completed the SDSR, the financial position of the country has not changed nor substantially have the nature of the threats we face. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us be honest about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who are arguing for a fundamental reassessment of the SDSR are really arguing for increased defence spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they fail to spell out the inevitable result - more borrowing, more tax rises, or more cuts elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that a strong economy is a national security requirement and an affordable Defence programme is the only responsible way to support our Armed Forces in the long term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no easy answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no silver bullets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only tough decisions, hard work and perseverance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To pretend otherwise is to fail in our duty to our country and its people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
