<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/lord-green-of-hurstpierpoint</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/lord-green-of-hurstpierpoint.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Lord Green of Hurstpierpoint</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18370</id>
    <published>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-04-24T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mid-sized-business-boost-in-turkey"/>
    <title>Mid-sized business boost in Turkey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mission will take around 30 UK mid-sized businesses on a two-day intensive visit to Turkey to boost trade and investment between the two countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK companies, including Amino Technologies, Black Country Metals and Brompton Bicycles, will meet key figures from the Turkish Government and business community. They will get the opportunity to build and strengthen new and existing links in a growing market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment Minister, Lord Green, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is an exciting mission, the first of its kind, that brings together the opportunity offered by Turkey, one of the fastest growing economies in the world, and the export potential of the UK’s mid-sized firms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government has set a clear target to get another 100,000 UK firms exporting as a key part of driving economic recovery. Direct engagement with key figures from the government and business community will help break down barriers and foster understanding that will lay strong foundations for future trade and investment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Cridland, CBI Director-General, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This trade mission breaks new ground, as the first one designed specifically for ambitious mid-sized businesses. If we are to achieve the Government’s ambition of doubling our annual exports by 2020 to £1 trillion, we must look beyond the BRIC countries to other successful, high-growth markets such as Turkey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Turkey has a dynamic, growing economy, with an increasingly aspirant middle class keen to buy the sorts of goods and services we excel at, such as construction, education, and high-value manufacturing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="growing-business"&gt;Growing business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission brings together the Department for Business, UK Trade and Investment and the CBI and their joint focus on helping to improve the performance of mid-sized businesses, announced as part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/as2011_index.htm"&gt;2011 autumn statement&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business and Enterprise Minister Mark Prisk outlined the three key areas where mid-sized firms could improve their performance: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harnessing leadership capability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting access to finance for investment and growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging export as a strategy for growth. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mission is a key part of the work to unlock growth among the UK’s 10,000 mid-sized businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been described by the CBI as a “forgotten army” of businesses, representing 0.2 per cent of all UK firms but accounting for one fifth of private sector output and employment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CBI &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cbi.org.uk/media/1125696/future_champions__finalb_.pdf"&gt;Future champions&lt;/a&gt; report set out how, with the right conditions, mid-sized businesses could unlock up to £20 billion annual GDP in the next ten years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcomes and experiences of this mission will help pave the way for future mid-sized business focused visits concentrating on key emerging markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey is already an important partner for British businesses with trade currently worth more than £9 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major British companies like BP, Tesco, Vodafone, and HSBC already have a strong presence in Turkey, but there is scope to strengthen this relationship further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/midsizereview/"&gt;BIS mid-sized businesses review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/export/countries/europe/southerneurope/turkey.html"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment - exporting to Turkey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinturkey.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;British Embassy in Turkey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18295</id>
    <published>2011-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/business-is-great-britain"/>
    <title>Business is Great Britain</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the Royal Wedding this year and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/london2012/index.aspx"&gt;London 2012&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/what_we_do/honours/diamondjubilee.aspx"&gt;Diamond Jubilee&lt;/a&gt; next year, the eyes of the world are on the UK. The Government is determined to seize this unprecedented opportunity to ensure that the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games are not only a spectacular celebration of sport, but also deliver a lasting economic legacy for the whole country, boosting investment, jobs and growth.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/8442.aspx"&gt;The new GREAT campaign,&lt;/a&gt; announced by the Prime Minister in New York, will focus on everything the UK has to offer as one of the very best places to visit, study, work, invest and do business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will allow Britain to speak with one voice about the opportunities to invest in the UK and help to attract millions of visitors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron&lt;/strong&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In 2012 there is only one place to be. With the Olympic and Paralympic Games coming to London next summer, the greatest show on earth is about to arrive in one of the world’s greatest cities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are determined to make the most of this unprecedented opportunity to ensure we deliver a lasting economic legacy that will benefit the whole country.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This campaign is simple. There are so many great things about Britain and we want to send out the message loud and proud that this is a great place to do business, to invest, to study and to visit. “&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="billion-olympic-business-boost"&gt;£1 billion Olympic business boost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister also announced plans for a ‘Global Investment Conference ‘ for investors and business leaders to be held in London on the eve of the Games and an innovative programme of business summits including the ‘British Business Embassy’ highlighting key sectors for global growth and an on-line ‘British Business Club’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme of business events will be delivered by &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/home.html?guid=none"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment&lt;/a&gt; and is expected to generate, over time, at least a £1 billion boost for British business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable&lt;/strong&gt; said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Olympics is a tremendous opportunity to showcase the best of British. We want to demonstrate the great products we already offer the world, from Formula One racing cars to innovative aerospace technology and cutting edge fashion brands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we want to highlight the opportunities for world-leading businesses with global ambition to invest and grow in Britain.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minister for Trade and Investment, Lord Green&lt;/strong&gt; added:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am determined that we make the most of 2012 to promote brand Britain and deliver long-term economic benefits for the whole country. The GREAT campaign will be an important part in achieving that goal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment’s innovative programme of business engagement will, over time, deliver more than a billion pounds of additional revenue for British business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="an-extra-4-million-visitors"&gt;An extra 4 million visitors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tourism will be a key part of the GREAT campaign. The sector already contributes £115 billion each year to the UK economy and we believe it has the potential to be one of the fastest growing sectors in the years ahead. Our aim is to attract an extra 4 million visitors to the country over the next 4 years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Hunt, Secretary of State for Culture, Olympics, Media and Sport, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the eyes of the world on Britain in 2012, we have a fantastic opportunity to showcase everything that the country has to offer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The GREAT campaign will ensure that we make the most of London 2012 to boost tourism and business, leaving a lasting economic legacy from London’s Games.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-some-of-greats-supporters-have-said"&gt;What some of GREAT’s supporters have said:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marc Bolland; Chief Executive, Marks &amp;amp; Spencer:&lt;/strong&gt; “As a true British brand, Marks &amp;amp; Spencer is proud to represent all that is great about Britain to our customers internationally.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colin Grassie; Chief Executive Officer UK, Deutsche Bank:&lt;/strong&gt; “We are delighted to be associated with this exciting campaign and look forward to engaging with the Government on it”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Goodwin; Co-founder of the Founders Forum &amp;amp; PROfounders:&lt;/strong&gt; “We are proud to be linked with this exciting campaign and will work with the Government to drive it forward.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steve Holliday; Chief Executive, National Grid:&lt;/strong&gt; “We strongly support the aims of this campaign and will assist the Government where we can.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justin King; Chief Executive Officer, Sainsbury’s Supermarkets Ltd:&lt;/strong&gt; “We are delighted to support this exciting campaign. We want to play our part in putting the Great back into Britain.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Julian Roberts; Chief Executive, Old Mutual plc:”&lt;/strong&gt;This is an exciting campaign which we are delighted to be involved with; we will work closely with the Government to help achieve its aim.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angela Ahrendts at Burberry:&lt;/strong&gt; “We applaud the vision of the new GREAT campaign. As a global brand with a proud British heritage, we fully support its aim of raising international awareness of the country’s unique assets and tremendous opportunities for inward investment.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tom Albanese at Rio Tinto:&lt;/strong&gt; “We are delighted to be associated with this exciting campaign and look forward to engaging with the Government on it going forward.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dominic Murphy at KKR:&lt;/strong&gt; “We think Great Britain is a GREAT place to invest” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-great-campaign"&gt;The GREAT campaign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GREAT campaign will focus on everything the UK has to offer, as one of the very best places to visit, study, work, invest and do business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will centre on areas of British excellence covering reasons to invest in the UK and reasons to visit the UK. These areas are Technology and Innovation, Entrepreneurship, Creativity, Knowledge, Green, Heritage, Sport, Shopping, Music, Countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reasons-to-invest"&gt;Reasons to invest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Innovation: Innovation lies at the heart of our culture. British ideas and inventions have helped shape our world: from the telephone to the World Wide Web. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurship: You can now set up a company in Britain in less than two weeks. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creativity: The UK has the largest creative sector per head in the world. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge: We have four of the top ten universities in the world. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Green: Britain is a world leader in offshore wind energy and is home to the biggest wind farm in the world off Thanet in Kent   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.number10.gov.uk/"&gt;Number 10 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.london2012.com/"&gt;London 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/home.html?guid=none"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.culture.gov.uk/"&gt;Department for Culture, Media &amp;amp; Sport &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.visitbritain.com/en/GB/"&gt;Visit Britain &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/britishbusinessclub/home.html"&gt;The British Business Club&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26557</id>
    <published>2011-06-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-06-16T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-minister-for-trade-and-investment-to-attend-st-petersburg-international-economic-forum"/>
    <title>UK Minister for Trade and Investment to attend St Petersburg International Economic Forum</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of days, Lord Green will join Russian President Dmitri Medvedev, Chinese President Hu Jintao and other political and business leaders at the St Petersburg International Economic Forum to talk about how to improve the investment climate in Russia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of his visit, Lord Green will open the new assembly facility of the British company Spirax Sarco, which exports and installs energy efficient equipment in Russian factories. Given the scale of the industries which need modernisation in Russia, and their high level of energy intensity, this is a sector with high growth potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Green will speak to an audience of UK and Russian business about the strengths of UK products and skills across a range of sectors, and meet UK companies who are overcoming the challenges and growing their businesses.  In 2010, UK exports to Russia were up by 51%, recovering ground lost in the economic crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lord Green visit to St Petersburg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.flickr.com/slideShow/index.gne?group_id=_groupid_&amp;amp;user_id=ukinrussia&amp;amp;set_id=72157626980491908" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The St Petersburg International Economic Forum is an annual economic summit, bringing together governments, businesses, international organisations and experts. It has been described as the ‘Russian Davos,’ the equivalent of the annual World Economic Forum meeting in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26392</id>
    <published>2011-05-12T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-12T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lord-green-welcomes-greater-trade-relations-with-the-west-coast-of-america"/>
    <title>Lord Green welcomes greater trade relations with the West Coast of America</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The visit includes meetings led by Lord Green to ensure enhanced co-operation with California on issues including High-Speed Rail and investment in the UK’s Tech City.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and US enjoy a very close commercial relationship. British companies investing in the US, for example, support nearly one million American jobs with an average salary of more than $70,000.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) launched its five-year strategy. As part of this, our aim is create up to 750 inward investment projects each year. Last year, 484 US companies invested in the UK. We hope that many more US companies will follow in their footsteps and take advantage of the extensive support we offer to help them expand profitably into the UK market. More than a quarter of all US investment to the EU goes to the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment Minister Lord Green said:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK’s trade relations with the US remain strong and both countries are committed to driving forward balanced economic growth.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My visit to California will be an opportunity to strengthen this relationship and meet many of the UK and US companies investing in our two countries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“California and the UK are focussed on nurturing a dynamic, low-carbon economy. I want to share our knowledge and commitment to growing the talent that will deliver strong innovative companies in high-growth industries such as those taking root in the UK’s Tech City.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government last year announced its blueprint for technology - this includes plans to develop Tech City in East London. Tech City is already a beacon for many technologies, digital and creative companies such as Lastfm, Dopplr, and Tweetdeck.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London’s Tech City has grown from some 15 high-tech companies in 2008 to around 200 today in Europe’s fastest-growing technology hub.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s combined IT and creative industries sector is one of the most vibrant in the world and employs more than three million people and contributes more than £83bn to the UK economy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fact File:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UK has the biggest industries in Europe for creative industries, financial services and life sciences  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UK and US enjoy the world’s largest Foreign Direct Investment relationship  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK has the strongest research base in Europe and the best IT infrastructure of all major European economies  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One pound in every six from exports being earned from our trade relations with the US  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US remains the UK’s top export destination and after the European Union, our second-largest trading partner  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 the UK attracted 1,619 FDI projects with the most projects - 484 - coming from the US.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18244</id>
    <published>2011-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/britain-open-for-business"/>
    <title>Britain open for business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable, Foreign Secretary William Hague and Trade and Investment Minister Lord Green today launched a new cross-government focus on trade and investment, launching UKTI’s new five year Strategy, and the FCO’s Charter for Business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also announced the appointment of Nick Baird as new Chief Executive of UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accepting the appointment, Nick Baird said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The launch of the new strategy for UK Trade and Investments makes this an exciting time for me to be taking up this role.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy will place the nation’s commercial interests at the heart of its foreign policy and I hope to lead this organisation in successfully delivering this aim.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Baird will join UKTI later this year. The appointment is for three years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="five-year-strategy"&gt;Five year strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktihome/aboutukti/aimsobjectives/corporatestrategy.html"&gt;The UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) Strategy&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/economy/commercial-diplomacy/"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) seven-point Charter&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate the Government’s dedication to supporting international business, championing UK business overseas and attracting investors to the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UKTI Strategy is a five year plan that will see it adopt a more entrepreneurial approach to deliver growth. It lays out four pathways to balanced growth: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Targeting services at innovative and high growth SMEs to encourage more companies to export, and help existing exporters reach more high growth and emerging markets. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winning high value opportunities in overseas markets for UK businesses of all sizes. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delivering high quality inward investment, with a drive to market large British infrastructure and regeneration projects to foreign investors. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building strategic relationships at the highest levels with the most significant inward investors and with the UK’s top exporters and major overseas buyers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//assets/biscore/economics-and-statistics/docs/i/11-805-international-trade-investment-rationale-for-support.pdf"&gt;Read BIS’s International Trade and Investment - the Economic Rationale for Government Support. (PDF, 1.5 Mb) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy and the FCO’s Charter form a central part of the Government’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/ukecon_growth_index.htm"&gt;Plan for Growth&lt;/a&gt;, and recognise the fact that a new focus on business is needed if the UK is to remain economically competitive in the years to come.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Feb/trade-and-investment-to-drive-growth"&gt;Trade and Investment for Growth,&lt;/a&gt; a White Paper published in February, set out the Government’s plans to rebalance the economy through trade and investment. UKTI’s Strategy and FCO’s Charter are the next step in this process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is now looking in more detail at how it works with businesses, especially small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs), and what action can be taken to make this more effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nick-baird-appointed-as-new-chief-executive-for-uk-trade--investment"&gt;Nick Baird appointed as new Chief Executive for UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently Director-General Europe and Globalisation at the Foreign Office, Nick Baird has also worked as the Ambassador to Turkey and has extensive experience of working with both the European Union and emerging markets.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcoming Nick Baird into his new role, Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This Government is committed to ensuring that trade and investment plays a key role in delivering our plan for growth. We want to ensure UK businesses of all sizes bring their expertise to the world and take advantage of key overseas markets, particularly the emerging economies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted that Nick Baird has joined UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment, his knowledge of the emerging markets will be fundamental to driving forward this trade mission. “&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=419395&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;press release - Further support announced to help British companies compete on the global stage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/home.html?guid=none"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/economy/commercial-diplomacy/"&gt;Commercial Diplomacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/economy/commercial-diplomacy/around-the-world/"&gt;Commercial diplomacy in action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/"&gt;Foreign &amp;amp; Commonwealth Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26384</id>
    <published>2011-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-05-10T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/helping-uk-companies-compete-on-the-global-stage"/>
    <title>Helping UK companies compete on the global stage</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable, Foreign Secretary William Hague and Trade and Investment Minister Lord Green today launched a new cross-government focus on trade and investment to help the British economy grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.ukti.gov.uk/uktistrategy"&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (UKTI) Strategy&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/global-issues/economy/commercial-diplomacy/"&gt;Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) seven-point Charter&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate the Government’s dedication to supporting international business, championing UK business overseas and attracting investors to the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They form a core plank of the Government’s Plan for Growth, and recognise the fact that a new focus on business is needed if the UK is to remain economically competitive in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy will see UKTI adopt a more entrepreneurial approach to deliver growth. As part of this UKTI will actively seek out overseas investors, help UK companies expand into overseas markets and work more closely with key British companies. Examples of this approach include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establishing a new private sector delivery partner with the incentive to attract and retain high value investments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expanding the Global Entrepreneur Programme (GEP) to win more investment to the UK.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re rightly proud of British firms and making sure they can increase their exports to a worldwide audience is vital if we are to rebuild our economy. We also know the UK already has a great reputation as a place to do business and we want to do all we can to make sure foreign investors come here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, we’re announcing practical help for UK companies to ensure they win business overseas. And we’re setting out how we will actively attract inward investment to the UK with ambitious plans to target sovereign wealth funds and expand the global entrepreneur programme.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign Secretary William Hague said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Charter for Business is part of our commitment to inject a new commercialism into the Foreign Office, using our international influence to help British businesses secure new trade opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will work tirelessly to champion UK business abroad and to help attract investment to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Businesses will be able to capitalise on the FCO’s in-depth local expertise to identify and exploit opportunities. Ministers will continue to build the strong bilateral political relationships needed to help business thrive, as well as working to influence trade policy internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Together with the Trade and Investment Strategy, the Charter marks an important step in delivering commercial diplomacy and sets out a clear vision for how the government will deliver growth and prosperity for the UK.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents launched today reinforce the Government’s desire to place the nation’s commercial interests at the heart of its foreign policy. Both were developed in consultation with industry leaders and signal that Britain is, and remains, ‘open for business’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment for Growth, a White Paper published in February, set out the Government’s plans to rebalance the economy through an ambitious framework for trade and investment.  UKTI’s Strategy and FCO’s Charter are the next step in this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is now looking in more detail at how it works with businesses, especially small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs), and what action can be taken to make this more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment Minister Lord Green said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Strategy we have developed builds on our successes to date but this is not business as usual by any means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As UKTI seeks to become more entrepreneurial, it will bring more private sector expertise into its relationship with exporters and inward investors and develop new partnerships with key businesses which support SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our plans will ensure that UKTI is well equipped to face the demands of the future, listening to the concerns of businesses so that we have an economic climate that benefits us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UKTI Strategy signals how the Department intends to become more entrepreneurial in focus by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bringing more private sector expertise into its relationship with exporters and inward investors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developing new partnerships with key businesses which support SMEs, and using their networks to raise awareness of the benefits of exporting.   &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a new online self-help community for UK SME exporters, so that they can support each other and share experience as they seek to internationalise their businesses.  This new development will also provide a continuous feedback loop so that customers can tell us what they think of UKTI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establishing a new Strategy Task Force, with members drawn from the most innovative UK-based companies, to inform the future direction of both UKTI and ECGD  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These actions will help to develop new ways of relating to businesses, with a renewed focus on partnerships with the private sector to boost productivity and improve performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FCO Charter will focus on using FCO resources to meet the needs of British business. It is part of the FCO’s work to drive lasting prosperity for the UK, setting out the specific contribution that the FCO will make to support business across the world. Embassies and High Commissions overseas will continue to champion the UK as an excellent place to invest and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FCO Charter, together with UKTI’s Strategy, will be available to UK businesses from today to demonstrate the support available to them and where they can access this to boost their work internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="trade-and-investment-fact-file"&gt;Trade and Investment fact file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Companies tell UKTI that its support to exporters has helped them generate £6 billion of profit for the UK economy. This additional profit has helped generate more than 126,000 jobs in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last year, UKTI played a role in securing 759 investment projects, nearly half of the national total. These projects helped generate more than 40,000 jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For every £1 spent, UKTI generates £22 for the UK economy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In October 2010, UKTI was named as the best Trade Promotion Organisation in the Developed World.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ninety per cent of UKTI’s customers are small and medium-sized businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UKTI has a network that extends to almost 100 overseas markets, which generate 98% of world GDP. It also has a presence in the UK regions and online at www.ukti.gov.uk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26342</id>
    <published>2011-04-27T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-04-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/minister-for-trade-and-investment-visits-turkey"/>
    <title>Minister for Trade and Investment visits Turkey</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While in Turkey, he will be meeting Turkish business leaders and politicians, to discuss economic growth and trade cooperation between the UK and Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://ukinturkey.fco.gov.uk/resources/en/word/21520888/lord-green-article"&gt;Lord Green’s article published in Dunya Newspaper on 27 April 2011 [Word 36 KB]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xifo56?theme=none&amp;amp;wmode=transparent" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28858</id>
    <published>2011-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/building-growth-in-the-low-carbon-economy--2"/>
    <title>Building growth in the low-carbon economy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you and good afternoon everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the background documents to the conference today rightly calls Britain the cradle of the industrial revolution. The consequences of the revolution that Britain set in motion in the nineteenth century brings us all together today in pursuit of another sort of revolutionary change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Directly or indirectly, industrialisation did of course bring initial hardships of a considerable order, and eventual wealth to much of the world. It brought health services and much longer life expectancies. It brought universal public education for both boys and girls. It brought of course, underlying all of that, urbanisation. And the process continues. As you are probably all aware, it was the year 2008 when we passed the threshold of fifty percent of the world living in big cities. That is expected to rise to at least seventy per cent over the next forty years. These are truly radical, revolutionary changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we all know that they have been purchased at a high long-term cost in terms of impact on climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Britain began the process of industrialisation, the world’s industries have spewed around 500 billion tonnes of carbon into the earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences are there for all to see and to anyone who is prepared to judge the evidence on its merits, we can’t go on this high carbon development path - or else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1900, the earth’s average temperature has increased by about three-quarters of a degree Celsius and the world is continuing to warm. The ten warmest years on record have all occurred since 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urgency of acting to reduce carbon emissions is drastically clear. The difficulty, or one of the sensitivities in this - to use an image given to me by Nick Stern - it is as if there was a banquet in which the participants have sat through the meal and invited the poorer countries for desert, or even just for the coffee, and then expect them to split the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way out of the paradox, or the dilemma, or the embarrassment if you will, that it is countries like Britain, the G7 countries of the world who have already achieved development, that have contributed so much of the carbon emissions stock in the climate today. What we are now facing is the challenge implied by growth of so many other countries achieving their legitimate aspirations to an equally attractive standard of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shift to a low-carbon economy will require profound transformations in people’s lives and the way we all do business, but also to the way different nations interact with each other on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report by the Economist Intelligence Unit examined how global businesses are adapting to climate change. This survey of over 700 international companies found that 90 per cent of them had been experiencing climate impacts. In the past three years, more than half were noting that these impacts were increasing.  So this really is out there in the public domain as far as business strategy is concerned and business challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, two-thirds of those same businesses believed that adapting to climate change would provide new business opportunities. Therein lies, in my view, the basis for optimism about the challenge. The glass is half full and not half empty because transition to a low carbon growth path has been more and more widely recognised as essential, and more and more widely seen as a transition that will increase opportunities and not just difficulties and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly as far as Britain is concerned, I think this a matter of opportunity, and not just challenge.  We know that we have got plenty to do. We know that we have a transition a low carbon growth path. And we know that as we do that, we can set an important example both by delivering at home and by sharing the expertise, that I believe lies within the British economy, broadly through the world. This is a challenge that we all share.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows from all this that our ambition should be to drive economic recovery by building a green economy that will deliver future prosperity and energy security, as well as meeting our ambitious climate-change targets that are in the public domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also want to play our part in driving this transformation forward globally. Those parts of government that I am directly responsible for, UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment and ECGD, are moving to the forefront of the UK’s business-facing activity helping UK-based companies to succeed in the global economy, on the basis that we are showcasing a real expertise on the low carbon growth path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement and the Trade &amp;amp; Investment for growth White Paper specifically both direct UKTI and the Export Credits Guarantee Department “to become champions for British companies that develop and export innovative green technologies around the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three months that I have been doing this job, I have seen that the UK hosts companies across a wide range of low-carbon sectors, including energy efficiency; water treatment; financial services; ICT; new materials; electric vehicles and advanced manufacturing. Wherever you look, you find UK businesses across the range of sectors are facing up to the challenge of climate change and seeing the opportunities that lie in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are already working with partners across the globe to develop innovative solutions. I was, a couple of weeks ago, on my first significant long distance business trip in my new job, inevitably in India and China - two countries that I have visited often with my previous hat on. This was the first time I have visited both countries back-to-back. I was once again struck by the dynamism, the momentum, the sheer scale in both countries of visible transformation, the rapid rate of urbanisation. For all of the differences between them, these are two of the most exciting economies on the planet. But what you also both see and hear as you talk to people there, in both places, for all their obvious differences, is a very real concern to address the low carbon growth challenge. They know that urbanisation brings with it such significant physical and social changes that is has to go along with a proactive climate change strategy if we are to do this in a way that really does deliver for the citizens of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent figures show that the UK’s low-carbon and environmental goods and services market is already the sixth-largest in the world, worth £112 billion a year and employing over 900,000 people. This is becoming a significant part of economic activity in the UK - and of course in other countries around the world too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is scope for it all to grow much further in the next decade or two. So far as the Government is concerned, it is our job to facilitate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why you will have seen in the Budget, just a couple of weeks ago, we announced an extra £2 billion for the Green Investment Bank, giving it £3 billion of capital in total and allowing it to start borrowing from 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will start operating earlier than expected in order to enable it to leverage in an extra £15 billion of private investment over the lifetime of this Parliament, and increasingly significant in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bank will help secure the finance needed to make our economy more environmentally sustainable, unlocking significant new private investment into sustainable infrastructure projects.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Green Investment Bank is far from the only environmentally focused measure that is important if we are to succeed in meeting this challenge. For example, the Budget also signalled plans for sweeping changes to the planning regime, including a clear presumption in favour of sustainable development.  And further measures to reduce corporate taxes and to incentivise investment in research and development - which will have a very direct bearing on businesses engaged in green technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear what the overall challenge is, and what we all need to be doing. It is clear that there is momentum underway, both in G7 economies and in the emerging markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very clearly something in which businesses have an important role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the thinking going on in the British government, this will lead up to a Roadmap to a Green Economy, which we expect to publish by the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will provide businesses with more clarity and more certainty, and we certainly recognise that is necessary when you are investing in technology at the leading edge, you need as much certainty about the regulatory framework as possible in order to make a decision on a sensible basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Roadmap will support the continued growth of low carbon in both the UK’s domestic and export markets alike.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that the Government play its full part in supporting businesses as they rise to the challenge of technological development and investment, in a sector which is going to grow as part of the manufacturing sector in this country and globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also supporting this process at the research end. We are supporting the National Renewable Energy Centre in Northumberland. This is a state of the art testing facility where companies can test and develop experimental technologies until they are commercially viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of what we are talking about is already considerable.&lt;br&gt;
The Carbon Trust estimates that the offshore wind sector alone could create up to 70,000 new jobs in this country by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very important challenge facing us all. There is a very good story to tell so far. There is a long way to go on this, both here and globally. But if there is one thing that is for sure, I believe that this is sound both economically and necessary for human long-term well being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a long-term view of investment, it is very clear that there are all sorts of investors both domestic and foreign who have an interest in looking at investments in reasonably predictable operating environments with stable long-term returns. If you think about the objectives of Sovereign Wealth Funds around the world, which are there to provide income for future generations, it is the kind of investment that they should be interested in.  If you think about pension funds which have long-term liabilities matched with long-term income streams, it is the kind of investment they should be interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the opportunities are there on the technology side in terms of business development, and the opportunities, I believe, are there on the investment side for anyone looking for long-term predictable returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we ever needed any incentive, we only need to be reminded that this an important imperative for the human race - if that doesn’t sound too grandiose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am in position of having five grandchildren, and they, on current demographic trends, have a fifty-fifty chance of living to see the next century, then you realise that actually the benefit we talk about for future generations is rather focussed on some individuals who you already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28857</id>
    <published>2011-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-world-in-flux-politics-in-crisis-mode-markets-under-scrutiny-lessons-to-learn"/>
    <title>"The world in flux, politics in crisis mode, markets under scrutiny: Lessons to learn"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you and good evening ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that it is a rather strange experience for me, to come here not as a banker but as a trade minister in government.  A year ago I had been expecting to retire sometime this year: it never occurred to me that I would instead be embarking on an entirely new career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of my twenty-eight years at HSBC, I was involved in a global banking system that seemed so large and powerful that it would endure for ages to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, during my four years as Chairman of HSBC, I watched that system brought to its knees through a combination of too much bad debt and too little capital, through poor risk management and through sheer greed.  Everyone from economists to factory workers wants to know how the crisis happened and who was at fault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seems to me that a more urgent question for us should be not “who was to blame?” but “What lessons are there to learn?”.  And the lessons are plainly not just of academic interest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full extent to which old certainties have been swept away is still becoming clear and, indeed, will ultimately become the business of historians rather than of governments.  But I think that we are already beginning to make out the broad outlines of what will follow it and how that will affect the work we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And tonight, I am highly aware of being in the midst of people who are helping to shape the financial and economic world of tomorrow.  Which is in many ways a new world, with different rules and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is that world that I would like to talk to you about tonight.  And especially about how the world is changing and about what we must do together - governments, financiers and business people - to make sure that change works for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the economic downturn has shown that the global economy has real and serious weaknesses.  As a result, some of the rules of the global economic system, and indeed its values, will have to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How we respond to that fact is up to us.  One option is to behave like the citizens of some latter-day Mahagonny, who resigned themselves to their fate and said:&lt;br&gt;
“Konnen uns und euch und niemand helfen”?  &lt;br&gt;
Indeed during the Great Depression, that is exactly what some nations tried to do.  Alternatively, we can say, with Goethe:&lt;br&gt;
“Das Leben gehort den Lebenden an, und wer lebt, muss auf Wechsel gefasst sein.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the changes we must confront are indeed both profound and very complex - changes in market philosophy, changes in global macro-economics, changes in international political relationships - changes which will radically affect us all over the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the crisis, the market was the determinant of all, and “price” was always the best measure of values.  Efficient market theory ruled supreme.  Markets were trusted to allocate resources correctly and economic policies dictated that they should be left to do so.  This was a failure, too, to look beyond the short-term in pursuit of quick profits.  Leaders in the banking sector need to recognise the moral dimension of what happened in the years preceding the crisis. This was a failure of governance - an abdication of responsibility - which had led to destruction of value on a huge scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now know how misguided that ideology was.  As bankers - or in my case, a former banker - we all know that strong financial markets lie at the heart of every successful economy, lubricating the engine of growth and prosperity.  But while that remains fundamentally true, we have to learn new things about economics and re-learn some old ones about human weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not intend to ruin your dinner by listing the technical reforms which have been so extensively debated in the last three years.  Suffice to say that the current agenda for banking reform is indeed critical to the future of the global economy and is one we must get right.  We are now seeing global convergence on the key aspects of the model of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is plenty yet to discuss, and this year in particular will be decisive, with its ambitious international regulatory agenda.  But I believe the broad direction of technical regulatory reform is clear and correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But regulatory reform, while necessary, is plainly not sufficient.  We also have to recognise that the severity of the crisis, and the obvious failure of the efficient market theory - which almost became the god of a new form of fundamentalism - has called into question the very purpose of capitalism.  Capitalism has of course survived the crisis.  It remains critical to economic development and I would defend it on the same basis that Churchill famously defended democracy: that it is the worst system of government we know - except for all the others that have been tried from time to time.  But the fact is that virtually everywhere in the developed world, public trust in the capitalist market system - not just in banks - has declined sharply.  (Interestingly, this is not true in the new, dynamic world of the Asian economies, though.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, there is public discussion of the whole purpose of business - of its corporate social responsibilities - for the first time in a generation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is fair and reasonable to argue that the responsibility of the board of a company to which shareholders entrust their capital is to build sustainable returns for those shareholders.  And sustainability means focussing on some older principles which are as relevant today as they ever were - long-term relationships with customers; high levels of commitment to those who work in the business; and it also means positive engagement in the social issues and the economic conditions in the communities where business is done, an essential ingredient to the long term viability of the business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, boards need to ask all these questions about the purpose and sustainability of their business, in the context of profound changes taking place on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For it is also now being clear that the crisis has accelerated the shift of balance in the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the crisis, the scales were tipping slowly but surely towards a new equilibrium.  This previously gradual swing is now faster and more visible than in the pre-crisis world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At HSBC I saw first-hand the rise and rise of Asia; the economic miracle which allowed places like Hong Kong, Korea, Singapore and Taiwan to evolve from dire poverty in the 1950s to become prosperous economies with high standards of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are now joined by China and India as formidable global economic powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only last week, I returned from a visit to these two countries.  I was reminded once again of the extraordinary dynamism of both these huge countries, and of the profound implications of what is happening there before our very eyes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people forget that for much of history China was the world’s largest economy and India the second.  The fact that countries as large and with civilisations as ancient as theirs are now returning to their former economic prominence should surprise no-one with an understanding of history.  It will change political relationships on the world stage forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair account for eighteen percent of global GDP and they are host to an army of young and innovative firms which are increasingly sophisticated, creative, and international in outlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of Asia has profound implications for every country, business and individual on the planet.  It is the most important fact of the twenty-first century: it is a fact which presents us with huge opportunities, as well as significant challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of a huge Asian middle class presents untold opportunities.  Where twenty years ago BMW and Mercedes sold cars primarily to wealthy consumers in Europe and America, today it’s the streets of Guangzhou that are full of luxury vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within five years the Chinese middle class will be larger than the entire population of the USA. And it’s a similar story in India, Brazil and other emerging economies which are producing rapidly growing middle classes too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dozens of cities with names that few recognise today - like the cities along the Delhi - Mumbai corridor - some with populations larger than entire countries such as Denmark or Finland - will be the engine-rooms of the global economy tomorrow.  And these cities have a pressing need for the legal, financial, infrastructure and environmental expertise in which European companies are world leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our best companies - large and small alike - now rightly look eastward for their growth markets: Tesco, the UK’s biggest food retailer is looking to more than double its Chinese stores, making Asia the focus of a major international growth strategy.  The German automotive industry, the Italian fashion industry - across sectors, across countries in Europe, the signposts point in the same direction.  &lt;br&gt;
But if the opportunities are obvious, so are the challenges.  It would be naive to suppose that the course of economic development is ever smooth: or that trading with major emerging markets is plain sailing.  Notoriously, there are often risks to intellectual property in China, for example: and in many countries there is widespread corruption and lack of transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the inevitability of urbanization - with its implications for infrastructure, for social change, and for the environment - is perhaps the biggest single challenge for countries such as China, India and Indonesia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many of these problems inevitably become all of our problems in a globalized world.  Meeting them inevitably means global coordination.  And global coordination means recognition that we now live in a multipolar world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the G20 is the best symbol of this new multi-polar world order.  It is perhaps too soon to say that the G7 has been marginalized (witness its recent role in the currency markets at a time of exceptional Yen volatility).  But clearly the G20 has become established as the principal global forum of macro-economic policy making for the new era.  It is a genuinely positive sign of the world’s recognition that it needs to work in a much more coordinated fashion if we are to address the issues that we will face, and in particular the task of ensuring that markets continue to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the challenge of global imbalance is still with us.  Global imbalances were at the core of the crisis that we have lived through.  Some nations were accumulating enormous reserves, whilst concurrently, others ran huge and growing deficits.  The arrangement is inherently unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is thus whether it is the deficit countries that are to shoulder the entire burden of rebalancing, or whether - one way or another - we can do this more collectively. For without this readjustment, the risk of future crises will remain, and political pressure for disastrous protectionism will grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, there are few places where it is more appropriate to look to the future and to speak of change than right here in Berlin.  Through its times of glory and its times of darkness, the tumultuous history of Berlin, especially in the twentieth century, reminds us not only that change is inevitable, but also and more importantly of the resilience that is required to survive and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what Berlin is becoming now, in the 21st century, is a world-class city, with an openness and vivacity, and a cultural richness and variety, which reminds me of my home city of London.  It is that sort of openness that we in Europe are going to need.  Because the economic crisis has done more than reveal flaws in the system that must be corrected to prevent something similar happening again.  It has changed the environment in which the world does business and created opportunities that were not there before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtually all of us here grew up in a world dominated by two military superpowers.  It was, however, a world with only one real economic superpower, the United States of America.  Despite the Wirtschaftswunder and the growing economic strength of Japan, that supremacy remained unchallenged for at least half a century.  It was said with justification that when the USA sneezed, the rest of the world caught cold.  And the world crisis showed that this remained true at least for the countries, including Germany and Britain, for whom the USA has long been the main trading partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is also true that, today, the geopolitical influence of the USA, represented mainly by its ability to project power on a global scale, remains unrivalled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But financially, industrially and economically, the dependency of the global markets on the health of the US system that we knew in the second half of the last century is no longer absolute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding that the US economy remains the world’s largest, the shift in the world’s centre of commercial gravity from West to East is going to prove, as I have already implied, the biggest macroeconomic fact of the first half of the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the recession, the USA is going through a period of de-leveraging and economic uncertainty.  The Obama administration has provided a massive fiscal and monetary stimulus to pull the country out of the recession, yet there are still clouds on the horizon.  One is the scale of America’s debt burden.  Another is uncertainty about what quantitative easing may do to the inflation outlook.  And a third is that the stimulus-fuelled economic recovery has still not produced enough new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that the critical foreign policy challenge for the USA is how to adapt in order to profit from the rise of the Asian giants.  And, as President Obama’s most recent State of the Union address showed, there are signs that America is stepping up to the challenge, as he announced his target to double exports over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Europe, the economic crisis wiped out four years of economic growth and the average unemployment rate is similar to the USA’s but has risen to worrying levels in some places.  Germany, of course, has performed astonishingly well; but overall, Europe’s position is far from robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe’s share of world output is projected to fall by just under a third in the next two decades.  Average government debt in the EU is around eighty per cent of GDP.  And Eurozone leaders have had to contend with governance issues around the single currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our businesses are prepared to grasp the new opportunities that global economic rebalancing will bring, the effects on European countries, whether with trade deficits, like the UK, or with trade surpluses like Germany, as well as the medium-term effects on jobs and growth, could be enormous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hovering over all of these problems is the lingering perception that Europe lacks economic dynamism.  When reflecting on the failure of the Lisbon Strategy, former Spanish PM Felipe Gonzalez blamed the lack of “mobility” in Europe.  That in America a company like Google can emerge and grow quickly into one of the biggest in the world whereas the European business hierarchy rarely changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is truth in this.  And if we are going to expect European business to adapt successfully to changing global markets, then we must first make sure that we have put our own house in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That must begin with making the internal European market work better because there are still swathes of the economy that are not properly served by single market rules that have remained substantially unchanged since nineteen ninety-two.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They include, notably, new sectors, like the digital industries, where so much of our potential for growth lies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade in goods across European borders is still four times lower than what it should be if the EU was as economically integrated as the USA, even when allowing for language and geographical factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are still loading far too many bureaucratic burdens, and the cost that they entail, onto business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also get more serious about innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take just one example of the sort of thing I mean; words about making Europe the “most competitive knowledge-based economy” will remain cheap as long as it costs seven times as much to acquire a patent in many member states as it does in Japan and South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most importantly, we must uphold the principle of free trade and encourage others to do the same.  Benjamin Franklin said that&lt;br&gt;
“No nation was ever ruined by trade”&lt;br&gt;
But plenty have been ruined by lack of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OECD estimates that a ten percentage point increase in trade exposure is associated with a four per cent rise in per capita income.  That is why all of us in Europe should actively, aggressively push for free trade.  Starting with Doha, for which, as the British Prime Minister, David Cameron, has said&lt;br&gt;
“Two thousand and eleven is the make or break year”.&lt;br&gt;
We cannot afford to miss this opportunity of a hugely expanding, consuming middle class in Asia.  We have the goods and services the world wants to buy - now let us have the confidence to strike those deals and sell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not just about open trade and international finance, important though commerce is for development and wealth creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about the human spirit.  For Europeans, it is about recognizing our need to change with the times, to be open to the cultural currents of a globalized world, to be flexible, to be creative, to be engaged in the wider world - because that is way we will flourish, be enriched, and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one thought with which this retired banker would like to leave you this evening, if only his grasp of the German language were good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, your greatest poet expressed it very beautifully in his greatest work, Faust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with your permission, I will borrow his words for one last time this evening.&lt;br&gt;
“Was heute nicht geschieht, ist morgen nicht getan.&lt;br&gt;
Und keinen Tag soll man verpassen,&lt;br&gt;
Das Mogliche soll der Entschluss&lt;br&gt;
Beherzt sogleich beim Schopfe fassen,&lt;br&gt;
Er will es dann nicht fahren lassen&lt;br&gt;
Und wirket weiter, weil er muss.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for listening.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28086</id>
    <published>2011-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-china-partners-for-growth"/>
    <title>UK &amp; China - Partners for Growth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trade and Investment Minister Lord Green&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be here in China, the UK’s ‘Partner for Growth’, so early in my time as Minister of State for Trade and Investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an honour to be asked by the Prime Minister, David Cameron, to take on this crucial yet challenging role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK needs to grow its economy, and trade performance is undoubtedly at the heart of that. That is why our Government published a White Paper last month pushing for growth through trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, as a strong and emerging market, featured heavily in this White Paper. It has seen spectacular unbroken growth over the last thirty years and is a market that is very important to the UK’s economic development. It is our key partner for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Prime Minister could not have been clearer about the role China has to play in our future trade and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did he visit Beijing last November, where it was agreed that the UK and China would aim for $100 billion annual trade by 2015, but our Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg hosted Vice Premier Li Keqiang in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is engagement from the highest level down, and we intend to continue with more visits to China in the months and years to come. As we do so, we will want to focus not just on the traditional markets of the east but the centre and the west as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many people know, I have been fortunate enough to live and work in China as part of my past role for HSBC, a role that I held for 28 years. This has given me the opportunity to see first-hand the wealth of business developments that are taking place across the country, and the impressive range of skills that exist in every sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inland China is becoming increasingly important commercially, and whilst I am here I am visiting the Two Rivers New Zone in Chongqing, part of the Western Development Strategy. We see big opportunities here to work together. It is a core part of China’s low-carbon agenda, which we also have a strong interest in, and which we have already seen significant collaboration. Only last year Fudan University in Shanghai joined with a number of UK universities to work on solutions to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get British businesses involved in China’s large regional projects, and I am particularly keen to see small and medium enterprises (SMEs) doing this. China’s economic development depends on that as much as our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs are the bedrock of a successful economy and we know that exporting can make them stronger and more innovative. They are often the companies with the most inventive new ideas and the biggest potential for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I am here in China, I want to showcase what we in the UK have to offer you. I want to demonstrate the UK’s technical competence and its business excellence in areas from education to security, IT to engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You put priority on financial services, advanced engineering and new energy, and we do as well. In fact we have real expertise in these areas - expertise that we can share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a country, the UK is a great place for business. We are the most open economy in Europe, and the World Bank ranked us first in Europe for ease of doing business. Crucially, we are also the gateway to the 27 European Member States and can provide Chinese companies with valuable contacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Government has made clear its intention to support business. We are reducing the main rate of corporation tax from 28 to 24 per cent and are tackling excessive regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ours is a country that welcomes investment and the benefits it can bring, not only nationally but to regional communities as well. The more areas opened to foreign investment, the bigger impact that investment can have on the wider economy. This message ties in with China’s twelfth Five Year Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have said, this is about being partners for growth and while I am supporting the UK in China I also want to support China in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would welcome more Chinese investment in the UK, including in infrastructure investment and from Sovereign Wealth Funds. Your companies already contribute greatly to our economy, with firms such as ChangAn Automotive, Fosun Pharma, NewSummit Biopharma, Xiangxue Pharmaceutical Company, Yuchai Engineering Machinery Company and Zhuzhou CSR Times Electric establishing links over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These offer so much more than the sum of their parts. Of course they are good for the companies involved, but they also offer employment to people in the UK and help to develop different industries throughout the country. This sharing of expertise can have wide ranging benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I continue with my visit to China and see for myself how new industries are developing and new regions are emerging I hope to be able to share a message of unity: that the UK and China can support one another in their economic development. This is the crucial point that I want to make with politicians and business people alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
