<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/mark-prisk</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/mark-prisk.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Mark Prisk MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65403</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T12:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/million-pound-boost-to-extend-homelessness-help-to-thousands"/>
    <title>Million pound boost to extend homelessness help to thousands</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A cash injection of £1.2 million will help thousands of vulnerable people into the rented homes they need, Mark Prisk said today. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting the London Crisis Skylight Centre, the minister said the cash will extend the charity’s work through the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.privaterentedsector.org.uk/prs-funding.asp"&gt;Crisis Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme&lt;/a&gt; to provide housing help for single people at risk of homelessness, who are unable to find private accommodation on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk at the Crisis Skylight centre" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/6010/mark_prisk_crisis.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk speaks to Steve Grant at Crisis Skylight to hear the problems faced by single homeless people&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id="helping-vulnerable-people-into-rental-homes"&gt;Helping vulnerable people into rental homes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Private Rented Sector Access Scheme, run by Crisis with government support, has helped nearly 4,000 people find the rented homes they need in the last 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already established in 120 areas across England, the scheme offers single people the advice and support they need to find and sustain a private rented tenancy, helping them overcome hurdles like budgeting and paying a deposit and working with local landlords to ensure the homes provided are suitable, safe and secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s £1.2 million cash injection will extend the programme, creating a further 23 local schemes. By focussing on helping those most at risk of homelessness, including young people, it aims to help a further 1,300 people in the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government has a strong safety net in place to prevent homelessness and Crisis’s programme has been a vital part of this, helping nearly 4,000 vulnerable people in just two years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why today I’m providing 1.2 million to extend that support even further. With another 23 areas on board, the scheme is set to help many more single people at risk of homelessness to find and keep the long-term home they need, providing the safety and security to get their lives back on track.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leslie Morphy, chief executive of Crisis, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To have already helped 4,000 homeless people into decent homes is an incredible achievement for the Private Rented Sector Access Development Programme and the local organisations working hard to support tenants and landlords. Challenging conditions in the private rented sector make this work difficult but all the more important as people struggle to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement of funding is for a further 23 schemes that will focus on helping particularly vulnerable people with no home of their own including young people and those leaving prison - groups that too often struggle to find a home and have often not been a priority for assistance through other schemes and programmes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The department has provided £10.8 million to Crisis to run the private rented sector scheme. The £1.2 million funding announced today is part of that investment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organisations that will help deliver the extended programme include:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homeless Action Resource Project (HARP), Southend on Sea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Giles Trust,	London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadway, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hope Worldwide (HWW), London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAYSH, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;St Mungo Community Housing Association Ltd, London&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DePaul UK, North Tyneside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stockton &amp;amp; District Advice &amp;amp; Information Service, Stockton on Tees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquila Way, Gateshead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hyndburn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crewe YMCA, Crewe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real Lettings South, Portsmouth and Southampton &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Society of St James, Hampshire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Southdown Housing Association, West Sussex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leatherhead Start, Mole Valley and Epsom and Ewell &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next Steps, Tandridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelter The National Campaign for Homeless People Limited, Cornwall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Threshold Housing Link, Swindon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1625 Independent People, Bristol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encompass, Torridge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SIFA Fireside, Sandwell&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundation, Hambleton&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fusion Housing, Kirklees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos of the visit to the London Crisis Skylight Centre are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632484931391/with/8368181276/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64090</id>
    <published>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T11:24:12+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/support-for-social-tenants-to-have-their-say-on-local-services"/>
    <title>Support for social tenants to have their say on local services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Housing Minister Mark Prisk today launched a new training programme designed to put power firmly in the hands of social tenants.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He launched the £1.2 million Tenant Training and Support Programme to give residents the skills they need to hold their landlord to account, whether on their own, by setting up a tenant panel, or by taking over the management and maintenance of their homes and neighbourhoods themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boost in funding will offer a way for residents to ensure they get the service they deserve and that landlords offer the best possible value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said this new training programme would empower residents to take the first crucial step to having the necessary know-how to use their powers and take control in their neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="empowering-tenants"&gt;Empowering tenants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/"&gt;Tenant Participation Advisory Service&lt;/a&gt;, the programme offers advice, training and support to tenants by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing tenants together from different neighbourhoods to discuss their experiences and inspire new tenant panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping individual tenants to engage with their landlords on a range of issues and services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offering face-to-face training with expert advisors for around 5,000 tenants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing a tenant training programme to help them make the most of the powers they have, from accredited courses to local training systems and e-learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By doing this, new and existing social tenants will be equipped with the skills they need to engage and negotiate confidently with their landlords. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be able to sign up to Community Cashback, which enables tenants to take over the management of their neighbourhood, from overseeing maintenance and minor repairs to signing up new contractors to run cleaning services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country want to use the powers they have to ensure their needs are reflected in the services they receive. But many simply lack the confidence to challenge the people in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is why we’ve put this new tenant training scheme in place, helping make their voices heard and giving people the skills they need to ensure the changes that matter to them are made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by playing this enhanced role tenants can help landlords improve the efficiency of local services and their work will help inspire even more communities to take control.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Meakin, Tenant Participation Advisory Service chair said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is exactly the programme we’ve all been waiting for. I urge any tenant who wants to be involved and make a difference in their community to get in touch and take advantage of the free support and training on offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples-of-effective-tenant-involvement"&gt;Examples of effective tenant involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helena Partnerships&lt;/em&gt; has set up the tenant-led customer excellence panel to challenge their landlord on performance and service delivery. It sets its own review programme, commissions mystery shoppers and has unfettered access to Helena’s performance and complaints information, customer surveys, activity-based costing and customer insight data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel carries out tenant-led peer reviews and hosts a series of webinars to engage with other organisations involved in scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works closely with Helena’s young inspectors - a group of under 25’s who play an active role in testing and challenging services while gaining transferable skills for employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel’s work has been responsible for a number of practical changes to Helena services to reflect the needs of tenants and delivered value for money savings, including tailored rent statements, extended repairs appointment times and changes to the complaints service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tower Hamlets, &lt;em&gt;Poplar HARCA&lt;/em&gt; (8,500 homes) is committed to helping social tenants to play a key role in their local housing. Recognising the benefits of tenant empowerment, the association enables democratically elected residents to monitor services on each of the association’s 12 estates, where they have delegated budgets enabling them to make community improvements. Additionally, tenant board members scrutinise the association’s policies and initiatives, challenging senior managers and making recommendations for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents can also use their local knowledge to try to resolve complaints about the association’s services. A youth empowerment board has been set up, comprising 30 young people drawn from across the estates, to ensure that the views of young people are heard. In total, over 300 residents are directly involved in decision making, performance monitoring and complaints handling at the association. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenant empowerment programme is designed to inspire tenants to lead change in their communities by having the skills and confidence to scrutinise, influence and control local services through tenant panels and other scrutiny mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant funding of almost £1.2 million will be made to the Tenant Participation Advisory Service to deliver a training and support programme. For further information on the programme visit their &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.tpas.org.uk/tenantcentral"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow DCLG’s Tenant Empowerment Team on Twitter (&lt;a rel="external" href="https://twitter.com/TenantPower"&gt;@TenantPower&lt;/a&gt;) for all the latest news and updates on this programme and other activities to empower the lives of social tenants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61041</id>
    <published>2012-12-31T10:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-31T10:01:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/make-it-your-new-year-s-resolution-to-help-get-rough-sleepers-off-the-streets"/>
    <title>Make it your New Year’s resolution to help get rough sleepers off the streets</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>People setting their New Year’s resolutions can now pledge to offer practical help to rough sleepers in 2013.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk urged anyone wanting to get help for someone sleeping rough to use the new StreetLink hotline and website to ensure they are put in touch with the local agencies offering it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that while people want to offer help to those facing homelessness, they often don’t know where to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But StreetLink, run by charities Homeless Link and Broadway with support from the government, offers a “valuable alternative” to a cash handout for people sleeping rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those looking to offer help can call 0300 500 0914 or go to &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk" title="StreetLink"&gt;www.streetlink.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; to put those facing sleeping rough in touch with local charities and councils who can them get them long-term support and safe accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued this new and innovative service helps support the No Second Night Out initiative as it is extended across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London, where No Second Night Out has been adopted, 70% of rough sleepers have not spent more than one night on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The New Year offers many of us an opportunity to make a new start - StreetLink offers that opportunity to those facing the prospect of living on our streets and a valuable alternative to simply a cash handout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge anyone looking to set themselves a New Year’s resolution to use this service to ensure people sleeping rough in their area get the support they need to get off the streets and into a stable home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;Mark Prisk on rough sleeping and Streetlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60137</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-200-million-build-to-rent-fund-will-boost-housebuilding"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk: £200 million Build to Rent fund will boost housebuilding</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new £200 million fund will boost the construction of new homes specifically for private rent, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Build to Rent fund aims to cut the risk for developers more traditionally used to building homes for sale who are looking to branch out into building homes for private rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By financing the construction of rental homes until they are built, let out and managed, the fund will give developers the freedom to build homes specifically for that market with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management companies will have the chance to invest in these new rental developments, and developers will then repay the investment from government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching the new fund, the Housing Minister described it as yet another step to support housebuilding which will help boost the economy, create jobs and strengthen the housing market by providing people with a broader housing choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="reviving-the-rental-market"&gt;Reviving the rental market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that Build to Rent follows recommendations contained in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/private-rented-homes-review-of-the-barriers-to-institutional-investment" title="Private rented homes: review of the barriers to institutional investment"&gt;Montague report&lt;/a&gt; into rented homes earlier this year and will help address the varying level of quality across the nation’s private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of private rental landlords are small-scale, individual investors. This fund will redress the balance, by stimulating the market in private rented homes for large-scale housing organisations that will in turn help set a new benchmark for landlords across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kickstart this new, larger scale market for privately rented homes, the minister said that Build to Rent will fund ‘demonstration’ projects to show how it might work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expert taskforce will also work to boost investor awareness of the fund and offer practical support to those interested in this new market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A healthy rental housing market must have a broad range of choice across the board. But for it to grow and develop, we must first attract new investors. The Build to Rent fund will support this, helping to build homes specifically for private rent and breathing new life into the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And by driving this market in housebuilding, the fund will also help create new jobs, build the homes that families need and local people want, and support economic growth across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor of London Boris Johnson said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The private rented sector now houses a quarter of Londoners and has the potential to support the delivery of a huge number of new homes in the future. I welcome this funding and I will continue to make the case that investment in London’s housing infrastructure is one of the best ways to deliver much needed construction jobs and economic growth now, while at the same time laying the foundations for our economic growth for years to come.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greater London Authority will lead on assessing the expressions of interest for sites in London. Shortlisting decisions will be made by DCLG, the Homes and Communities Agency and the Greater London Authority. The Homes and Communities Agency will undertake due diligence, contracting and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The £200 million Build to Rent Fund is now open for bids, and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/private-rented-sector" title="Build to Rent Fund prospectus"&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt; has been published on the HCA website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fund has been developed to support purpose built, private rented demonstration schemes across England which have the potential to attract investors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57535</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T16:22:45+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T16:22:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/eric-pickles-opens-pop-up-shop-to-showcase-high-street-entrepeneurs"/>
    <title>Eric Pickles opens pop-up shop to showcase high street entrepreneurs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>DCLG is giving a big boost to small retailers today as it opens a brand new pop-up shop in its own headquarters.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the government’s efforts to regenerate high streets and encourage entrepreneurs, the shop is being opened in time for final Christmas present buying this week by Communities Secretary Eric Pickles and Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk, with the support of national enterprise campaign StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To directly support enterprise and showcase Britain’s best new retailers, ministers have set up the pop-up store inside their Victoria-based office building to act as a blueprint for high streets across the country to emulate through schemes such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cutting the ribbon on the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5697/ribbon-cutting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Eric Pickles cutting the ribbon with Mark Prisk and Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Pickles unveiled the first ever Whitehall pop-up shop with ‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell. Every fortnight six new British start-up businesses will move into the shop, sharing costs and trialling their exciting ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shop will be open to the public for at least a year and will offer affordable retail space to over 150 small start-up businesses. The department is not seeking any financial return from the shop, which is being supported by sponsors Intuit, John Lewis, SNR Denton and StartUp Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside the pop-up shop" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5698/shop-floor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The first 6 pop-up tenants are NANUKK, Milla &amp;amp; Arti, Arthur &amp;amp; Henry, London Mummy, Morrow’s Outfitters and The English Tee Shop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers believe pop-ups are a great way to get empty spaces used and could be easily replicated in other town centres across the country. Mr Prisk has written to the British Property Federation to urge landlords to get on board. He said that, starting in January, all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Town Team partners will receive support to facilitate new pop-ups in their empty high street premises, which could support thousands of new businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is committed to rejuvenating the high street. A multi-million pound strategy is backing local partnerships such as Portas Pilots and Town Teams to breathe new life into their town centres. This includes a doubling of small business rate relief; mentoring from retail experts; and workshops to address town centre challenges. A guide to opening a pop-up will be published soon and StartUp Britain has published a tool kit today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is providing over £80 million of start-up loans for young entrepreneurs, which could create over 30,000 new businesses. Ministers are also changing planning restrictions so that landlords can alter how an empty shop is used for up to two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these steps will make it easier for start-ups to find other low-cost stores to set up in. Last year 450,000 people set up new businesses and almost two thirds of new start-ups say they would benefit from trading on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are absolutely determined to support the high street and we know pop-ups are a great way to bring empty shops back to life and get new businesses going, so we thought ‘why not open one right here in the department?’. It will also showcase how we can unleash more of our best and brightest young entrepreneurs onto the country’s high streets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Jones, co-founder of StartUp Britain, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The PopUp Britain model gives retail entrepreneurs an affordable opportunity to scale up their businesses and become a part of their own high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing record numbers of people setting up businesses and they are starting out small and online. They are the driving force of the economy. This initiative offers them a chance to physically test out new markets as well as get their products in front of consumers and big buyers in a way that has never been available to them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By actively encouraging local authorities to give start-ups access to empty shops across Britain, we hope it will help accelerate British enterprise as well as providing a vibrant addition to the local British shopping experience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real appetite in our town centres to get them revitalised so they remain attractive places to visit. And it’s not just talk: there are many extremely capable and serious people with some superb ideas; but they need a bit of help to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up shops are a superb way for all sorts of entrepreneurs to test their ideas. So I’m delighted that this department is opening the first pop-up shop in Whitehall and I look forward to inviting all 27 Portas Pilots and 330 Towns Teams here to see how they could replicate this model across the country in the new year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Apprentice’ winning entrepreneur Tim Campbell added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a brilliant idea and it is great to see the government actively supporting business in this way. For many aspiring and growing enterprises, having access to a retail unit where new propositions and ideas can be tested directly with customers can be the catalyst to increase sales. I hope other landlords follow this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the Bright Ideas Trust, where we invest in businesses started by young unemployed people, we see many business struggle to secure retail space as they grow out of their bedrooms and away from their kitchen tables.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=neKNqnTu6qY"&gt;Pop-up shop event video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="startup-britain"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.startupbritain.co/"&gt;StartUp Britain&lt;/a&gt; is a national campaign by entrepreneurs for entrepreneurs, harnessing the expertise and passion of Britain’s leading businesspeople to celebrate, inspire and accelerate enterprise in the UK. The campaign was founded by eight entrepreneurs and was launched in March 2011 by the Prime Minister. It has successfully run pop-up stores in Richmond, Surrey, which opened in July and which have already helped 42 businesses get access to the high street. Four in five of the tenants said the experience had been good for their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="first-six-pop-up-britain-victoria-tenants"&gt;First six pop-up Britain Victoria tenants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established 6 months ago by 27-year-old Shrewsbury-based designer Sarah McLeod, silk scarf company &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nanukk.com/"&gt;NANUKK&lt;/a&gt; features beautiful pieces of Art printed onto silk fabrics. All the scarves are made in England. Sarah has been labelled as one to watch, after she was awarded the River Island Graduate Fashion Week Award in 2008. 
Sarah said: “It will be great to have a physical presence in the marketplace at last! So far I’ve only been online. People will love the feel of my silk scarves and I hope it will make them buy. I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.millaandarti.co.uk/"&gt;Milla &amp;amp; Arti&lt;/a&gt; was set up by product design consultant Deborah Reyner 18 months ago. Her British-made homeware collection includes bespoke lavender hearts for weddings, patchwork kits, gift ties and ribbons, collars and bows. 
Deborah said: “This is a wonderful opportunity for Milla &amp;amp; Arti and to talk about my products which are made by the British seaside and get people interested in making and doing themselves. I haven’t been able to sleep for a week before this, I’m so excited!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brother and sister Mark and Clare Lissaman named their ethical organic cotton men’s shirt company after their grafting grandfathers. &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.arthurandhenry.com/"&gt;Arthur &amp;amp; Henry&lt;/a&gt; was developed after ethical consultant Clare noticed there were no ethical formal shirts on the market. “I was at the World Congress on Organic Cotton a few years back and realised that although all the men attending were passionate about organic cotton - none were actually wearing any as they were all suited up and couldn’t find proper smart shirts in organic cotton,” Clare, from Islington, said. “So we thought we’d make some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re thrilled and delighted to have this opportunity. For a newly established, ethical menswear brand, this is an amazing opportunity to meet customers face-to-face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single mum and former interior designer Esther Gibbs, from Chiswick, created &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.londonmummy.com/"&gt;London Mummy&lt;/a&gt; after people kept asking her where she bought the cushions and accessories she had made herself. All her products are now either made in England – some by Esther herself - or by women’s collectives in China. Her handpicked selection includes retro bed linen, colourful crochet animals, quirky kids’ stationery, classic toys and games, funky lunchboxes, wall art and more. Esther also makes beautiful children’s fabrics, which she sells in store too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther said: “I sell online but I’ll sell much more in the shop. Once people understand what the shop is about and what it’s doing for small British businesses, it will be a great asset for the high street and small businesses. I’m delighted to be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sock entrepreneur Philip Morrow, 25, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.morrowsoutfitters.com/"&gt;Morrow’s Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; last year as a way to re-establish his great-grandfather’s former gentlemen’s outfitters shop that operated in Liverpool between 1912 and 1987. His range of Loughborough-made cotton socks come in over 40 designs and colours. 
Phillip said: “Pop-up shops make a great deal of sense for small online businesses such as mine. I’m over the moon about getting the opportunity to come into PopUp Britain in Victoria.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-time English teacher and designer Alia Qadir, 30, from Ealing, started &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.theenglishteeshop.com/"&gt;The English Tee Shop&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to combine her passion for fashion and love of grammar! All her cotton is English-made and printed. She sells online and runs her business part-time from home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia said: “Until now I have relied on my online presence to sell my brand. But my T-shirts are made from a really good quality, soft jersey, and that doesn’t come across online. I’m really delighted about this new pop-up adventure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="new-town-team-tool-kit"&gt;New Town team tool kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the prototype shopping concept comes a newly-developed pop-up-specific tool kit for Town Teams to implement, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a national pop-up lease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a central website with information about the initiative for town teams and new businesses interested in applying for a slot at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.popupbritain.com"&gt;www.popupbritain.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;access to free pop-up payment equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a step-by-step guide for setting up a PopUp Britain shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PopUp Britain branding to make the shop recognisable to the consumer as a place where they can support British enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="portas-pilots"&gt;Portas Pilots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking forward the first recommendation from Mary Portas’s high street review, the department is running a number of high street Town Team Portas Pilots in England. We’re encouraging local partnerships and consortiums to come up with innovative ideas about how to transform their local high street into a social place, bustling with people, services and jobs. Twelve town centres from across England were selected as the first Portas Pilots Town Teams in May, and 15 more in July, with three from London, bringing the total to 27. They each receive up to £100,000 of funding plus support from Government and retail expert Mary Portas. More detail can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-high-streets-and-town-centres"&gt;Improving high streets and town centres pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="town-teams"&gt;Town Teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 330 Town Team Partners support includes: an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management; special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and support from industry experts and trade bodies including an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice; regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas; and ‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work. All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20120919132719/www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;List of Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="statistics"&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key statistics and evidence on start-ups in the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011 saw a record high for start-ups: over 450,000 people set up a company
 and became their own boss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a StartUp Britain poll revealed 82% of start-ups found the pop-up experience was valuable for their business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the UK, there are 4.8 million private sector companies employing an estimated 23.9 million people with a turnover of £3,100 billion. Small and medium-sized enterprises also account for almost half of the net growth in jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to the latest figures from the British Retail Consortium, 11.3% of shop premises in UK town centres are now vacant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;according to research from StartUp Britain, 63% of businesses not already on the high street think their business would benefit from a high street presence and, of these, 88% believe funding is the biggest barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id="additional-quotes"&gt;Additional quotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Johnson, Chairman of StartUp Britain, former Pizza Express boss and Chairman and part-owner of Patisserie Valerie and Giraffe, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A new high street name that will become synonymous with buying British and supporting small British enterprise is a fantastic idea. I’m sure PopUp Britain will be embraced by town planners and local government as a way to offer tangible support to their own high streets and start-up communities.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Russell, Chief Executive of WeArePopUp, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-ups are ideal incubators for the next generation of entrepreneurs. It’s very encouraging to see the Government opening a national showcase in a high-profile location such as Cardinal Place in Victoria. Pop-ups can change the fortunes of local communities and we look forward to this support encouraging more landlords to open up their empty shops and become part of the solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosie Cann, Director at Popupspace, a property consultancy that specialises in pop ups, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find space for lots of established retailers, but the challenges for new businesses wanting to open shops are much wider. What we have here is a unique offering to smaller start-ups looking for affordable space to sell, but also for business support and a high profile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Little, UK Managing Director of Intuit, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pop-up tenants need to be able to accept card payments but it can take weeks to get set up, the equipment and transactions can be expensive and require long-term contracts. Intuit is proud to support PopUp Britain with Intuit Pay, giving start-up retailers a way to get set up in minutes to securely take card payments on their smart phone or tablet – with no commitment and no contracts. With Intuit Pay anyone can now accept card payments.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the shop are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269606220/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56906</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T14:39:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:39:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-funding-to-unlock-delivery-of-12-000-new-homes"/>
    <title>Government funding to unlock delivery of 12,000 new homes</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New government support for large housing sites will unlock the delivery of new homes and create thousands of jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intervention will accelerate building on 2 large sites in East Devon and near Milton Keynes; unlocking development and bringing forward construction to 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A £20 million injection of funding for the new town of &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/cranbrook"&gt;Cranbrook&lt;/a&gt;, near Exeter, will enable local partners to bring forward the delivery of new homes included in the local plan, and create 1,500 jobs in the town that will include 6,300 homes and a new rail station with links to London and Exeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money will also unlock construction of a new high street and transport infrastructure needed to develop the town centre, as well as 2 new schools in the next phase of development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a visit to Cranbrook, the minister met local construction apprentices who would work on the scheme. He said the government’s investment would create jobs for young people and bring a powerful economic boost to the area, while giving the consortium behind the new town the confidence and resources to drive forward its completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark Prisk with construction apprentices" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5640/Mark-Prisk-meets-apprentice.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mark Prisk meets apprentices who will work on the new town at Cranbrook&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also revealed that the construction of 6,000 new homes on the Fairfield development in Milton Keynes will also be brought forward without the need for direct funding, following discussions with the developer behind the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intervention builds on the deal made earlier this year for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/case-studies/ebbsfleet"&gt;Eastern Quarry&lt;/a&gt; development near Ebbsfleet in Kent, a site for over 22,000 homes, bringing total number of potential homes unlocked through these schemes to over 34,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the minister also pledged support for housing programmes near Wokingham, where £2.5 million will enable local partners to solve key transport issues in the town in order to unlock the potential for over 10,000 new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the government is making strong progress to boost house building despite the difficult economic circumstances, and he was in discussions with other schemes across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is serious about building more homes. That’s why we have been looking carefully at how we can accelerate large, planned housing schemes that already have the support of local people, but need help to move forward in the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So I’m delighted that today I can announce our intervention will unlock the delivery of 12,000 new homes, and create thousands of jobs for local people. In the months ahead I will be announcing support for similar schemes. That means more investment, more jobs for our young people and more affordable homes for families across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have set aside considerable funding to assist large housing programmes like Cranbrook, and I would urge anyone with similar proposals to come forward and contact my department.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East Devon District Council Leader Councillor Paul Diviani said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a unique opportunity here to create Cranbrook’s town centre as a shining exemplar of how all town centres can function!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Currently the town centre is a blank canvas; we are not restricted by existing buildings or street formations. With support from central government our vision of a town centre that is vibrant, attractive, welcoming, the beating heart of the new community, can become a reality much sooner than previously expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement is the first allocation of £225 million, earmarked by the Chancellor in last week’s Autumn Statement, for the delivery of 50,000 new homes in large, locally-supported housing programmes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding programme for planned, large-scale sites, administered by the Homes and Communities Agency, will be targeted at schemes that could deliver real benefits to their communities, but are struggling to move forward because the current economic climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside funding to unlock new construction, the schemes will receive a package of support, including help to facilitate close co-operation with the local council and community during planning and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress-on-public-land"&gt;Progress on public land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said an expert review published today also demonstrates the government is taking the right steps to quickly release its previously-used, surplus land for building new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the recommendations in the report, led by the chairman of Berkley Group, Tony Pidgley, are already shaping measures being taken forward by the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date enough land has been sold to build up to 33,000 new homes, and last week’s Autumn Statement included a £290 million fund for the Home and Communities Agency to introduce measures that will quickly bring forward new sites for development, such as installing the right infrastructure so the land can be used for building new homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Pidgley, chair of the Expert Advisory Panel said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a golden opportunity to deliver growth and great places. It’s surplus public land. It doesn’t need new legislation. All that’s required is a simple system to dispose of the land, alongside investment in infrastructure, and then the private sector can get on with building these much needed homes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further reaction to the funding support for Cranbrook: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the consortium partners - Hallam Land, Persimmon Homes and Taylor Wimpey - Mike Owen, project manager for Cranbrook, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were privileged to give Mark Prisk a tour of the development which gave him an insight into the brand new community being created. From the very start the development of Cranbrook has been about partnership and this announcement of funding support for phase 2 continues that process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without this phase 2 Cranbrook would have been delayed at the end of phase 1. Instead, we have certainty in the delivery of phase 2, we can move ahead now and commit with confidence to the next key stages of the project and delivering further community infrastructure and bringing forward much needed private and affordable homes. The success of Cranbrook to-date has been underwritten by the amenities and infrastructure that we have been able to provide. In turn this has enabled the creation a real community from day one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Will Mumford, Chair of Exeter and Heart of Devon Growth Board and cabinet member for Economy, Enterprise and Employment, Devon Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that Cranbrook has been recognised for its successful delivery and for the additional funding to enable us to bring phase 2 forward. This keeps the project momentum going, will secure additional jobs and investment and is a resounding vote of confidence in the partnership approach.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Molton, Homes and Communities Agency Executive Director for the South and South West, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The government has shown its commitment to housing and development as a major route to driving economic growth and we welcome the confidence ministers have shown in our ability to deliver its key initiatives, supported by new investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s welcome news also that Cranbrook is rightly identified as a vanguard project which will help drive economic growth in the south west, by providing the essential investment needed to deliver the second phase of the project. This is a huge opportunity, and I know that our partners will grasp it to maximise delivery of new homes and growth in Exeter and East Devon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public land review published today can be found on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/news&amp;amp;newsArticleID=6604&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;Berkley Group website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the visit are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632269488244/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56673</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T10:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T10:29:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-backs-new-rough-sleeping-helpline"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk backs new rough sleeping helpline</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A new national hotline and website will connect rough sleepers with local help.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone looking to help rough sleepers this winter should contact a new service to get them long-term support, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister spoke at the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt;, a new national hotline and website service that connects rough sleepers with the local help and advice they need to get off the streets and get their lives back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="StreetLink poster" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/2025/streetlink_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said that while many want to help the people they see sleeping rough, they don’t know what to do. So the government has supported homelessness charities Homeless Link and Broadway to develop this new service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that StreetLink offers concerned members of the public a better option than handing out money or food, by directing rough sleepers to the help they need, and providing them with a “hand up, not a hand out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this service, the public can now turn their concern into practical action and take a direct step to help rough sleepers change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister urged people across the country to get behind StreetLink and call if they see someone in need this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the nights getting colder, many people will be wondering how they can help when they see someone facing a night on the streets. StreetLink will give them the chance to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This new service will help rough sleepers across the country to connect with their local services, offering the help and advice they need to get back on track. So save the StreetLink number, 0300 500 0914, onto your phone, download the app or bookmark the webpage today. Your action could help a rough sleeper get out of the cold and into long-term support.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZBIXCl1UwE"&gt;StreetLink video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/54937</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:00:23+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/national-summit-to-end-rough-sleeping"/>
    <title>National summit to end rough sleeping</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Housing Minister Mark Prisk on the launch of StreetLink and successful local steps to end rough sleeping.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of year, when the cold weather bites, it’s natural that people are concerned when they see people sleeping on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as you know better than most, this is not just an issue at Christmas; it’s a year-round problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it is not enough to offer a helping hand just during the season of good will. To really make a difference, we need to tackle the causes of rough sleeping, all the year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-action"&gt;Government action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the problems we face today, is a lack of affordable homes in the housing market. A market in which, for 15, maybe 20 years, we have seen just half the homes we actually need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, when this government came to power, we committed to building more homes, and more affordable homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means unlocking substantial investment of £19.5 billion so we’re able to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes over this Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means a significant expansion of the private rented sector, to give tenants much greater choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it’s a sector that has often been overlooked, which is why we asked Sir Adrian Montague to carry out an independent review of the sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’ve now adopted his excellent report with a clear commitment, to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, so that we can deliver more new homes for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s often a debate about whether to focus on owner occupied homes, or the private rented sector, or affordable housing. But we need to deliver in all 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want there to be a bigger, better housing market, capable of providing people with more quality and more choice at affordable prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are building more homes, but we’re also determined to address all the issues that drive people towards homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we protected £400 million of funding, for tackling and preventing homelessness, over 4 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because homelessness is caused by the convergence of different problems, my predecessor Grant Shapps established the Ministerial Working Group that, for the first time, regularly brings ministers together from across Whitehall - from Health and Welfare, to Justice and even Defence - because we need to look at all the links between homelessness and for example, mental health, as well as some of the unique challenges which people face if veterans or former prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="homelessness-prevention"&gt;Homelessness prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve put the right building blocks in place, and today I want to discuss how else we’re moving forward, not least by focussing on prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular the new approach, through StreetLink to stop people slipping through the net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means tackling the underlying problems. And, (if people do turn to sleeping rough), early intervention to ensure they are swiftly helped off the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why, (on top of the £400 million funding for tackling homelessness), we announced an additional £70 million last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extra cash is ensuring vulnerable single people, (a high risk group), get early access to good housing advice, to prevent them becoming homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="no-second-night-out"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also looking to boost hostel provision, and supporting the national roll out of ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now after a really encouraging pilot in London (which we were able to support), this initiative is proving essential in ensuring people do not become caught up in a pattern of sleeping rough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s proved effective at providing a rapid response to new rough sleepers, by ensuring that no one has to sleep out for a second night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, tackling problems early is fundamental to the scheme’s success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m pleased that the momentum for ‘No Second Night Out’ is growing, with several more authorities adopting the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merseyside was quick off the mark, being the first area outside London to introduce their own initiative last February. 6 local authorities are now working in partnership, to really put an end to persistent rough sleeping they’ve had to endure right across the Liverpool city region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a commendable achievement and an example to other authorities - and you will hear more about how they delivered this when Councillor Anne O’Byrne speaks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="streetlink"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are many people beyond government (and the professionals) who also want to help. Often they see people sleeping rough, but they are not quite sure what they can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re concerned that giving money isn’t the best solution, but don’t know where else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why, as a government, we decided to support your sector to develop a new approach, with the launch of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.streetlink.org.uk/"&gt;StreetLink&lt;/a&gt; today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how will it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for the general public StreetLink provides a central point of contact, that people who want to help rough sleepers can call. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minute anyone sees someone on their local street or town centre sleeping rough in their neighbourhood, they will be able to contact StreetLink and provide details on a confidential and secure basis, so vulnerable people can be found and connected to local services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the new approach is that it’s easy to use. StreetLink will be contactable by phone on 0300 500 0914, by using the website, the mobile website accessible by smartphone, or by using the StreetLink ‘app’, available for iphones and android devices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You maybe concerned that it’s difficult to do, but if I can get it on my mobile (and my wife will confirm), anyone can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it won’t just be about reporting problems: members of the public will also be able to see what action has been taken. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll be able to ask for email feedback from local services about the outcome of the information they’ve provided, and see the outcomes of their referrals on the StreetLink website, on a Google map that they can search by location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the first time, the public will be able to judge for themselves whether rough sleeping is being taken seriously and tackled effectively in their locality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does it mean for service providers - local authorities and your sector? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By involving the public, it will mean your outreach teams can help more people, because you will have better intelligence about what’s happening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homeless Link tell me that every local authority has agreed to accept referrals, with some already receiving and acting on the details provided by the public through the website, which has been live for over two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also supports your approach to helping rough sleepers. You, more than anyone, know that they need a hand-up, not just a handout. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the public will now be able to turn their concern into practical, effective action, and take a direct step to help vulnerable adults change their lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - it will help link up the different services helping rough sleepers. Callers in an area with a ‘No Second Night Out’ initiative or other rough sleeping helpline will be transferred directly to that scheme. In other areas StreetLink will refer the details to the local authority or local outreach team for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a smart, joined-up way of tackling the problem, and will have truly national coverage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to pay tribute to Homeless Link and Broadway for its development, using the support from government. It’s real partnership in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, most of us will struggle to understand what it is like to sleep on the streets. That’s why, when people see rough sleepers, they want to reach out and help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to engage with this issue, and ensure the right intervention is made, as early as possible. We need to break the habit to help people to turn their lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this must be a collaborative effort - including local authorities and the voluntary and charity sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me say a big thank you to all of you for the vital work you do. It’s tempting for the media to think it’s just a Christmas issue, but it’s 365 days a year. You are part of the reason we have one of the best safety nets in the world, to prevent and tackle homelessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted that, from today, StreetLink will strengthen this safety net. Everyone will now have an easy and effective way of helping change the lives of those who have been on the fringe, for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more to do, but I’m confident that, together, we can make a real difference to thousands of people, who are real in need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/49040</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:36:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-regulation-committee--3"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Regulation Committee</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government has appointed two non-executive members following open competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two non-executive members are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonathan Adlington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingeborg Kettner-Wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am pleased to announce the decision to appoint Jonathan Adlington and Ingeborg Kettner-Wood as members of the Homes and Communities Agency (&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt;) Regulation Committee. Their legal and financial expertise will strengthen the Committee’s capacity to deliver effective regulation in the social housing sector, with a particular focus on driving high standards of governance, financial viability and value for money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Ashby, Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The social housing sector is becoming increasingly complex. It is therefore imperative that members of the Regulation Committee - which is responsible for regulation of social housing providers in England - have the right mix of regulatory, financial, legal and commercial business expertise. The strong individuals appointed today will significantly strengthen the skills and experience available to the Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am also pleased that existing Committee members have had their initial appointments extended; a testament to the progress we have made as a Committee over the past 9 months. This brings stability and continuity to the Committee.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-details"&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is the government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth. &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; is also the regulator of social housing in England, exercising its regulatory functions through its statutory &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/regulation-committee"&gt;Regulation Committee&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hca-regulation-committee"&gt;
&lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Adlington is the Senior Partner of Trowers &amp;amp; Hamlins. He also works as a partner in the firm’s Housing Projects department. He is due to retire from the firm in March 2013 at which point he will take up his position on the Regulation Committee. Jonathan’s appointment will be for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inge Kettner-Wood was the Chair of Charnwood Neighbourhood Housing (an Arms Length Management Organisation in Loughborough) until 31 October when it transferred back into the council. She has over 14 years of senior experience in the social housing sector, with extensive involvement in governance, regulation and finance issues, and more than 12 years experience as an auditor. Inge has been appointed for 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has decided to reappoint Jane May (for 3 years), Richard Moriarty (for 3 years) and Piers Williamson (for 2 years) to the Regulation Committee upon the expiry of their current terms on 31 March 2013. Jim Coulter has chosen to step down and the process to recruit his successor will begin in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remuneration for &lt;abbr title="Homes and Communities Agency"&gt;HCA&lt;/abbr&gt; Regulation Committee members is £11,000 for 2 days per month. Existing public servants forfeit any right to remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Regulation Committee have been appointed to varying term lengths in order to create a smoother appointments cycle in future years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61125</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T12:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T12:04:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-boost-to-councils-and-communities-through-the-new-homes-bonus"/>
    <title>Boost to councils and communities through the New Homes Bonus</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The New Homes Bonus scheme pays over £1 billion to councils backing growth.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Council efforts to get Britain building are to be rewarded with a multi-million pound &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus" title="New Homes Bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, Housing Minister Mark Prisk announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next year, England’s 353 councils are set to share a cash payout of £661 million, after delivering 142,000 new homes, including 58,000 affordable properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding also rewards councils for bringing 13,000 long-term empty properties back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s provisional allocation, to be paid in the 2013 to 2014 financial year, means councils will have received £1.3 billion through the New Homes Bonus scheme since its launch in April 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This total recognises over 400,000 new builds and conversions, and over 50,000 empty properties being brought back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister argued that the New Homes Bonus had proved critical in ensuring communities see the benefit of housing growth in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For years, developers found themselves at loggerheads with communities unconvinced that their plans for growth would benefit them. But the New Homes Bonus is turning this around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The £1.3 billion paid out to councils to date has meant that now local people are able to see the rewards of new developments in their area - paving the way for thousands of much-needed, locally-supported homes to be delivered across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="getting-britain-building"&gt;Getting Britain building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils across the country have made the most of this additional funding to directly benefit their local communities. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Tyneside Council, which has allocated some of its New Homes Bonus funding towards a £3.1 million revamp of a library which overlooks a Georgian square in the heart of North Shields. The library scheme forms part of the regeneration of the square, which also includes the refurbishment of properties, bringing it back into residential use for the first time in decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warwick Council, which has entered in a 10-year partnership with the Waterloo Housing Group to deliver new affordable homes in the area, with all New Homes Bonus payments generated by additional new homes built recycled back into the scheme to deliver additional housing and bring empty homes back into use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uttlesford District Council is allocating some of its New Homes Bonus to fund a hi-tech shelter for teenagers in a new play park at Carver Barracks. Those using the shelter can generate their own power through crank handles located around the room, with the energy generated able to support the use of Bluetooth and MP3 players. The idea for the project came from a committee - The Rowney Community Park Fund - made up of soldiers’ wives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A full list of provisional allocations of New Homes Bonus for the 2013 to 2014 financial year can be found &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/36865/121212_Provisionals_-_version_for_gov_uk_site.xls" title="New Homes Bonus provisional allocations 2013 - 2014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
