<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/mark-prisk</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/mark-prisk.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Mark Prisk MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18653</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-04T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/rough-sleeping-help-offers-winter-lifeline"/>
    <title>Rough sleeping help offers winter lifeline</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night the minister visited Westminster’s Cathedral Piazza, a rough sleeping hotspot, where he saw the outreach work of homelessness charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.passage.org.uk/"&gt;The Passage&lt;/a&gt; and the help provided by local hostels to get those at their lowest ebb back on the road to a stable, healthy lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister said that the services, from an offer of immediate help to long-term support, were a last line of defence in helping vulnerable people, especially as the temperature continues to drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit was part of joint work between government, local authorities, homelessness charities and other agencies who work with the homeless to prevent rough sleeping and support those who fall through the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is investing £400 million over 4 years to help local authorities prevent and tackle homelessness, including rough sleeping, with an additional £70 million investment last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, on top of a pledge to roll out London’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nosecondnightout.org.uk/"&gt;No Second Night Out&lt;/a&gt; service across the country, means that anyone facing losing their home and sleeping rough this winter will get the support they need and deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nobody should have to face the frightening prospect of a night on the streets, and we have some of the strongest homelessness protections in the world to help prevent it. But sometimes people fall through the cracks, which is why we have the emergency support in place to protect them, especially as the winter weather continues to bite. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The work I saw last night showed me the real issues faced by rough sleepers, and the important role local services play in helping them get their lives back on track. For many, they are a vital lifeline at the most difficult time, and the last line of defence, not only against the cold, but against a long-term life on the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17099</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T13:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-sets-out-government-support-for-lifeline-shops"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk sets out government support for "lifeline shops"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the Association of Convenience Stores, Mr Prisk described them as a vital service for the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He warned against overlooking the crucial role the army of small shopkeepers across the country plays not only economically but also socially - offering a friendly face and social hub to local communities, and especially older people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister pointed to research suggesting that around a quarter of elderly people use their local shop, often a convenience store, every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convenience stores represent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;almost 40% of all rural shops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over a third of shops in urban areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a quarter of all shops in the suburbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the age of supermarkets and online retail it’s easy to forget that convenience stores make up more than quarter of all shops. Yet they are not just an important part of the economy. For many people their local shop is also a lifeline. Whether they’re used for daily supplies or the occasional pint of milk, they are an essential part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s why this government is introducing measures specifically designed to support convenience stores. That means reforming the planning system, easing the financial pressures with business rate support, and offering practical ways to attract new custom, all in order to keep this vital local resource intact.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="government-support-to-convenience-stores"&gt;Government support to convenience stores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk acknowledged the new economic challenges traditional shops now face, especially the changing way that people shop - whether online or in out-of-town retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he also highlighted some of the key actions the government is taking to help them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the government’s work to cut the deficit by a quarter in 2 years, which has kept interest rates lower for longer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new changes to the planning system to ensure that existing town centres should be the first preference for new retail facilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expert support and a multi-million pound fund for Portas Pilots and Town Team Partners will encourage strong and bold local leadership to create competitive high streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doubled small business rates relief and a 20% reduction of corporation tax are helping smaller firms manage their bills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a delayed business rate revaluation, providing a more stable business environment and preventing an increase in rates for around 800,000 premises &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans to help town centres adapt to changing demands, making it easier to convert empty offices into homes and bringing people back into the town centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"&gt;speech to the Association of Convenience Stores&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17100</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/heart-of-the-community-conference-2012"/>
    <title> Heart of the Community conference 2012</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be able to join you at this, my third Association of Convenience Stores conference, though I don’t think that earns me a Crackerjack pen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I would like to pay tribute to James Lowman and the work of the Association. Whilst we have not always agreed, I have always found James to be both persistent and effective, in putting your case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it was following talks with James that I pressed for, and secured, a 3 year moratorium for small shops from the tobacco display ban, (much to the chagrin of the supermarket groups!). This was partly because of the points James made on how a convenience store is run, so his knowledge is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tough-times"&gt;Tough times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I recognise as someone who has been involved with business, and the government recognises, that these are tough times for retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer incomes are under continuing pressure. The uncertainty in the Eurozone has prolonged the credit crunch. And of course there is increasing competition, which only squeezes your already tight margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, alongside the established competition from the supermarkets and out of town centres, we are also seeing a long term shift in consumer habits, as the online market grows. In fact, I was looking at the numbers and online sales have doubled in the last decade, to make up 10% of UK retail sales. That trend is only going to continue, and begs real challenges for all of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift in consumer habits is not wholly bad for smaller bricks and mortar retailers. Indeed it has been shown to actively help specialists or those with a particular offer to reach much wider markets. But it means that the question for all retailers is no longer whether you should adapt your business, but how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a very important shift which we in government must respond to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="value-of-convenience-sector"&gt;Value of convenience sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In government, we recognise the economic worth of the retail sector, both by turnover and measured by the number and type of jobs. Retailing is, for example, one of the most important ‘first’ employers, with a third of all retail employees, aged under 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a social value in small shops, (and particularly in the convenience sector) which we should not ignore, as indeed your research has shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A local convenience store is often one of the few places, where people meet and talk today. In villages and on many estates, it’s you and it’s your staff who know the local community, (and make time to talk to the elderly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representing 40% of all rural shops (and a third of shops in our towns), it’s the convenience sector which is usually there for a whole range of customers - perhaps those who don’t have a car, for young families, and for the elderly. It’s not to say that you aren’t economically important, but I also recognise the social benefit of a diverse, convenience sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, both as a constituency MP and as a member of Parliament, as well as a user of my local convenience store, and on behalf of the many customers who rely on the service and care you and your staff provide, let me say thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-can-be-done-to-help"&gt;What can be done to help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a former businessman, I understand that of course empathy doesn’t pay your bills, or help you compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I would like to do if I can, is explain what we’re doing in government to help business generally, and retailing in particular, to weather the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think it’s important that we have been able to keep interest rates lower for substantially longer, by cutting the financial deficit by a quarter. The fact that we’ve been able to do this over the last 2 and a half years is vital. Clearly, there’s a difference between what we the government and you as retailers can borrow, but if we had continued to borrow, interest rates would have soared, crippling businesses and families alike. We can all see what that means, when we look abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So low interest rates have helped. But the government has also acted to cut your costs. We have cut corporation tax rates to 24 pence for larger firms, and to 20 pence for smaller businesses. And we have reversed plans to increase National Insurance contributions, which would have hit jobs hard. The Association of Convenience Stores were amongst those who helped to make that point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we came into office, we also acted to help cut business rate bills. It’s why we extended and doubled the small business rates relief that’s helped thousands of small shops pay their bills, and it’s why we have now given councils new powers to discount rates, (funded locally), to help those firms which are struggling. It’s a new power, only a few months old, and only a few councils have taken it up. I am sure the association will want to change that. In fact, your own submission to the Treasury says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s there, now all they need to do is use it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, our financial room for manoeuvre is very limited but we are listening carefully to your concerns and will try and help where we can. However, as I’d like to remain a minister, I won’t pre-empt the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently we have delayed the planned revaluation from 2015 to 2017. This is an important issue. Let me explain our thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we know that the last thing businesses needed right now, is the uncertainty which a revaluation would create. You get your valuation, there’s the counter valuation, appeals which leads to 18 months of uncertainty. It isn’t the right time to be doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we looked carefully at the independent evidence produced by the Valuation Office Agency as to who the likely winners and losers would be. We were and you might be surprised by the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Valuation Office Agency’s analysis shows that some 800,000 premises would have seen a real term increase in their rates bill, with roughly 300,000 benefitting. Indeed many of the businesses represented here would have seen big hikes, in some cases up to 28%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems counter-intuitive, but the reason for this, is that because the revaluation must be revenue neutral, to compensate for lower rateable values, the tax rate would have to increase by approximately 20%. As a result, many businesses whose rents have fallen by less than the national average, which is how it is balanced, would have seen business rate bill goes up from 2015. We have asked business to come in so that we can explain how this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we felt, on balance, that now is not the time to be making this revaluation and in doing so we believe we can help many businesses in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that for many people, they think, ‘my rents have gone up’ but because there are 2 elements to business rates it doesn’t quite work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="town-centres-need-to-compete"&gt;Town centres need to compete&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s not just individual shops that need help. It’s also the traditional high street and many of our town centres. And our role should not be not to protect, but to enable. To ensure that our high streets are able to adapt to changing markets and consumer habits, so you can compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why last year the Prime Minister asked Mary Portas to review what needs to be done, by government, by local authorities and by business itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has produced an excellent report and brought her typical real energy and a keen consumer eye to the towns wanting to pilot this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s actually happening on the ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, our Town Centres First policy is an important and explicit part of our new National Planning Policy Framework. What it means in practice is that town centres should be the first preference for new retail outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we want to reform, planning to help town centres adapt. This means making it easier for the conversion of redundant first floors into homes, and secondly to enable empty offices that can often blight some high streets to also be converted into homes. Both these measures will bring people back into the town centre, increase footfall and so help existing retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we believe that strong local leadership is vital if towns are to be renewed. That is the clear lesson from both the Portas pilots and what we see regularly from successful shopping centres, who manage the whole customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If struggling high streets and town centres are to compete, they need the right people to deal with the promotion, management and coordination of their ‘centre’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we announced last month the creation of over 320 town team partners, who will get the expert advice, mentoring and support they need, to get an effective business plan in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went to Deptford, where I met the leaders of their town team, who are using one-stop shops and community cafés to make the most of what they feel is their unique selling point - its significant cluster of local artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UuacApa2aUE"&gt;Deptford visit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They plan to bring benefits to the entire high street, install art in the high street and set up shops as galleries under the ‘Made in Deptford’ banner to bring more people in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a really encouraging visit and just shows what together local civic and business leaders working as a partnership can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="physical-change"&gt;Physical change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course if towns are to compete, they need to address other issues than those I mentioned: from actively promoting local markets; through to being innovative, when managing and charging for local parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, lets be honest many need to change their appearance. And getting empty shops occupied is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why my predecessor Grant Shapps provided a £10 million High Street Innovation Fund, specifically to help those areas with the worst levels of empty shops. We’re already starting to see this helping to bring run down shops back into use, with other businesses kicking off as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think we can do more. The pop up shop movement, which helps new businesses set up and sell, is a great idea. Its something I want to impress on both landlords and tenants, and see expand right across the country, not least as it helps new firms start and will generate additional footfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I am in talks with the Pop Up Britain team, led by Emma Jones, to see how we in government can help promote pop up shops across the country, and I hope to have something positive to say about it very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-next-step"&gt;The next step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope you can see, as a government we believe that much can be done to help retailers and our town centres compete. But it has to be a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government, councils, businesses and local people (especially) need to be engaged and feel that they can make a difference. This involves a long term shift and short term squeeze. This won’t be easy and many towns will struggle, especially where that sense of collaboration is missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it can be done. As the people in Deptford have shown, if there’s the right imagination, will and support our high streets can have a great future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be different to what went before, but it’s vital that once again our town centres regain their role, at the heart of our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14296</id>
    <published>2012-11-10T09:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-10T09:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mark-prisk-urges-shoppers-love-your-local-market"/>
    <title>Mark Prisk urges shoppers: "love your local market"</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk called on communities and budding entrepreneurs to back their local markets well into the New Year, as part of a wider effort to breathe new life into the nation’s high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister confirmed that the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.loveyourlocalmarket.org.uk/" title="Love Your Local Market"&gt;Love Your Local Market&lt;/a&gt; campaign in 2013 will take place from 15 May, and will give aspiring retailers the chance to test out their ideas at their local markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Love Your Local Market campaign, new stallholders will be able to take advantage of a ‘Table for a Tenner’ deal - with some offering free pitches - at markets across the country, with many offering mentoring to those setting up shop for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make sure as many high streets as possible can take part, the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nabma.com/your-local-market/" title="National Association of British Market Authorities"&gt;National Association of British Market Authorities&lt;/a&gt; will hold a series of roadshows sharing ideas that councils and other market operators can take to make their events a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 400 local markets across the country were involved this summer, with a locally-defined programme of events designed to attract visitors into town centres and help new start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Markets can play an integral role in reviving our high streets, offering something new and exciting for shoppers in a way the Internet and out-of-town retail centres can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would urge traders and councils across the country to back this effective and important campaign, offer support to budding entrepreneurs looking to trade and Love Your Local Market.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Wilson, OBE, Chief Executive of the National Association of British Market Authorities, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Love Your Local Market and National Market Day provided a great impetus to the campaign to revitalise the high street and created an opportunity for almost 2000 people to sample market trading for the first time. We now want to build on this success and make LYLM 2013 bigger and better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Harrison, Chief Executive of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nmtf.co.uk/" title="National Market Traders Association"&gt;National Market Traders’ Federation&lt;/a&gt;, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We, at the National Market Traders’ Federation, are happy to see this campaign running again for a second year, and are delighted to support it. We do hope it has an even bigger impact than the first event with regard to the encouragement of new start-up businesses within the industry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="following-up-on-a-successful-fortnight"&gt;Following up on a successful fortnight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows the success of the Love Your Local Markets event in June this year, which saw over 400 markets run over the dedicated 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this scheme:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;around 400 markets took part under the Love Your Local Markets banner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just under 2,000 new traders joined local markets during last year’s campaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;over 3,000 ‘Tables for a Tenner’ and free pitches were offered - over half of which were taken up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Rogers, whose chocolate stall is now a regular fixture at Ludlow Market, with visitors now looking to buy her products online and making bookings for her to cater weddings and other events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obi Nwosu, who started selling during Love Your Local Market at Portobello in London, and now has stalls in six locations across the Capital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keith Smith, who started his Natural Ingredients stall at Fleetwood Market earlier this year, but is now trading on every market day of the week, and sell into retail outlets including food halls and other local specialist markets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16022</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-frees-councils-to-tackle-homelessness"/>
    <title>Government frees councils to tackle homelessness</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;New laws coming into effect from today will give councils the freedom to help those facing the frightening prospect of homelessness by finding them suitable homes in the private rented sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous rules meant that many homeless households spent long periods in expensive temporary accommodation, turning down offers of good quality private rented accommodation while waiting for social housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said that the new changes would make waiting lists fairer, helping councils fulfil their legal duty to those in need of homelessness help without the extra expense of long-term temporary accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he said the new protections in place today would also ensure that every rented home offered by councils would be good quality suitable accommodation, offered for sufficient time to allow households the space to resolve a homelessness crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homes on offer must meet a set of key standards, and councils will be required to minimise any disruption a move would cause to employment, education or caring responsibilities. This would include considerations such as transport, amenities and medical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguards include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a current Gas Safety record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any appliances, furnishings and wiring conforming to standards on fire and electrical safety&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the need for a valid Energy Performance Certificate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a written tenancy agreement that the local authority considers adequate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the council must also be satisfied that the landlord is a ‘fit and proper person’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For too long, councils have been restricted in the way they provided homeless assistance when good quality rented accommodation was available right on their doorstep. Today’s changes will lead to a fairer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The safeguards we’ve put in place today will give vulnerable families the reassurance they need whether they’re housed in the private or social rented sector, and with new freedoms and flexibilities, councils can now fulfil their duty and provide a safe and secure roof for the people who need it most.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/12966</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least fifteen years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need. Indeed, under the last government we saw that the rate of housebuilding dropped to the lowest level in peacetime, since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their 20s and 30s still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive ‘Housing strategy’ designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the private rented sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the planning system and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified ‘National planning policy framework’ and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last two years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the FirstBuy scheme, to help first time buyers, buy new build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the NewBuy scheme, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, Right to Buy is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using community land trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots – whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new Community Right to Build scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self build mortgage products up, from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14936</id>
    <published>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/council-of-mortgage-lenders-conference"/>
    <title>Council of Mortgage Lenders conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a chartered surveyor, I feel I have some understanding of the housing and the property markets. But I come to this role recognising that, frankly, I still have much to learn, especially about the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me start by saying that I want to listen. The considerable expertise gathered here is something I will not ignore. Indeed, it’s experience that I value. There will be times when we won’t always agree, but if we work together, we can make a real difference in quite challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="a-dysfunctional-market"&gt;A dysfunctional market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a government we inherited a dysfunctional housing market, whether it’s freehold or leasehold. A market in which (for at least 15 years) we have been building roughly half the homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social consequences are considerable. Housing waiting lists have soared in many cities; hundreds of thousands of people been unable to buy or move, and that has seen private sector rents climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see some 1.6 million young people in their twenties and thirties still living with mum and dad, because they cannot afford their own place. That cannot be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="governments-role"&gt;Government’s role&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why I make no apologies for saying that we need more homes, and we need better homes, for more families. More homes for tenants, more homes for owner occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why last November, we set out a comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/laying-the-foundations-a-housing-strategy-for-england--2" title="Laying the foundations: a housing strategy for England"&gt;housing strategy&lt;/a&gt; designed to tackle our dysfunctional housing markets in the short and long term, rented or owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, £19.5 billion is being invested in much-needed affordable housing. We’re doing this slightly differently by working with the private sector. Government has invested £4.5 billion, and a further £15 billion has come through private funding. It means we’re on track to deliver 170,000 new affordable homes, by the end of this Parliament (with some 55,000 supplied last year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we are taking radical steps to inject substantial investment into building homes for the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/improving-the-rented-housing-sector--2/supporting-pages/private-rented-sector" title="Private rented sector"&gt;private rented sector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between social homes, the rental sector and private ownership are often overlooked, and we’re trying to bring them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the excellent report from Sir Adrian Montague and his team, we have committed to provide a £10 billion debt guarantee and a £200 million equity finance fund, to help lever in substantial new providers, including some established players from overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, we want it to be a bigger, better market, capable of providing tenants with more quality, and more choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we are reforming the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively" title="Making the planning system work more efficiently and effectively "&gt;planning system&lt;/a&gt; and the maze of non-planning building consents. Don’t get me onto the subject of the greater crested newt. We’ve introduced the new, simplified National Planning Policy Framework and we are now looking to strip away much of the bureaucracy around those other consent systems, to enable and speed up sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, we are determined to enable the re-use of previously developed land and of homes lying empty. So we’ve identified surplus government land, capable of providing 100,000 homes, and we’ve already sold land capable for some 33,000 homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to do in that area, and alongside our multi-million programme to bring empty-homes back into use, the work is starting to provide real dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think from this can see we are actively pursuing a range of supply side policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="helping-home-buyers"&gt;Helping home buyers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this audience will know more than many, tackling supply alone, is not enough. We fully recognise that there are serious problems with demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of context, tackling the fiscal deficit we inherited has, of course, been fundamental to our economic strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By cutting the deficit by a quarter over the last 2 years, it’s allowed us to retain the confidence of the global market to lend to the UK, and to do so at lower rates, than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means that interest rates here in the UK have remained lower for longer. But we recognise that consumer confidence remains weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence is, frustratingly, both crucial to the housing and mortgage markets and one of the most difficult things for government to be able to affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolonged credit crunch and the continuing uncertainty in the Eurozone has cast a long, dark cloud over all of us, both businesses wanting to invest and families looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But practical action can and is being taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funding for Lending Scheme is now providing a steady flow of credit into the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I gather from some of the major lenders that this is already helping them launch new products, some at a lower price. We’ve seen early signs of increased mortgage approval rates and I hope that continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have now extended the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers" title="Help for first-time buyers"&gt;FirstBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt; to help first-time buyers buy new-build homes. In its first year we have seen over 8,500 reservations, with 3,000 sales already completed. It’s why we’ve decided to treble the scheme, to assist up to some 27,000 people. And, of course, by helping first time buyers, we are able to unlock many more housing chains and help many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we have backed the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme" title="NewBuy Guarantee scheme"&gt;NewBuy scheme&lt;/a&gt;, run by yourselves and the Home Builders Federation. Acting as a mortgage indemnity scheme, NewBuy started in March and we have already seen over 2,000 reservations. Indeed, the Home Builders Federation estimate the NewBuy scheme will assist some 25,000 families, and as a Government we have made provision for many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all the signs are that, after a cautious start, NewBuy is progressing well, after a cautious start. Savills’ recent research shows that NewBuy mirrors takeup of FirstBuy in its first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what more can be done? What can government and industry, lenders included, do next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I value the work of the CML and the work of the lenders represented here today, particularly in regard to repossessions. I want to pay tribute to the work of many lenders and advisers here, who have worked hard to help borrowers who are struggling to pay their mortgage by offering forbearance options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been one of the most encouraging aspects of the recent recession has been that, so far, the level of repossessions has been far lower than in previous downturns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we’re not complacent. That’s why I’ve extended the Mortgage Rescue Scheme by a further 12 months to March 2014, so that we can help more homeowners (who may be at risk of repossession) to stay in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognise that the FSA and lending industry have worked constructively together to ensure there are now clear rules arising from the Mortgage Market Review. This is vital if we are to have a stable and healthy housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think there’s still more that the government, and this sector, can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these challenging times we all need to think differently. We need to be challenged in our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, how as an industry can you bust the myth, that mortgages just aren’t available? You’ve told us that 80% of mortgage applications are accepted, so there’s clearly a gap between the actual mortgage market and what people think is the case. What can you do, together, to change these perceptions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I see many consumer surveys (such as the well-known analysis on Generation Rent by Halifax) suggest that your potential customers are confused, by what’s on offer. How could this sector improve transparency, to make it easier for potential customers to buy your products?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/right-to-buy" title="Right to Buy"&gt;Right to Buy&lt;/a&gt; is back on the agenda, and should be considered afresh. It’s true, the scheme dwindled under the last government, but we have now completely revamped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential discounts for tenants have radically increased, almost quadrupling in some areas to £75,000. And we have a concerted marketing campaign, which, over the coming months will continue to target hundreds of thousands of households to explain the changes, and how they can buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My question here is, are you aware of this change? There’s a real opportunity here, right across the country. Are you ready to be part of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps even more importantly, there’s a new market opportunity I want you to bring to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-build market in this country has historically been tiny to be honest, both numerically, and as a proportion of the overall market. Industry figures suggest that it’s only 1 in 10 new homes that are self-built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in many other markets the picture is very different. In the USA 45% of all homes are self or custom built, in France and Germany it’s over 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand in the UK is now changing. The number of people now looking to build their own home, is at a record level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, in a recent survey by the Building Societies Association 53% said they wanted to build their own home, and interestingly two thirds of the people who want to build their own home want to within the next 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this isn’t a pie in the sky dream, it’s a real ambition for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principle restraints to self build has always been finding a plot of land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities have responded to this challenge by using Community Land Trusts. Groups of people across the country are getting together to build on local plots - whether that’s in, Shropshire, Devon, Cumbria or right here in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/community-right-to-build" title="Community Right to Build"&gt;Community Right to Build&lt;/a&gt; scheme, which has just begun, will also make it even easier for larger custom-built projects. And planning authorities are now identifying land where self and custom-built home will be encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government, we are determined to make self and custom build housing a realistic option for many more people. Hence the change to the planning rules, and the creation of new vehicles to enable custom-built homes to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to realise our ambition (to double the size of the sector over the next decade) we’re going to need fresh thinking from builders and designers, planners and yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some members have already responded - with self-build mortgage products up from 14 to 24 in the last year. Indeed some independent predictions are anticipating lending will rise by 140% in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not pretending self build is the entire answer, but it’s a element I want to encourage you to incorporate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to encourage you to go even further, and fully consider the opportunities of this market for your business. Whether that’s by tailoring your lending products for builders and contractors (who are building custom homes) or extending products like build-out insurance, which can help reduce lending risks for your sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ladies and gentlemen, I strongly endorse the principle of this conference - that all of us need, to think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we’ve had a dysfunctional housing market, with too few homes for a growing population. And, let’s be clear, finance has been part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with reforms now in place to help both the supply of homes, and to ensure that appropriate finance is available to those who are credit worthy, we need to work together, to help us return the market to a sustainable, healthy state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a government we are committed to these reforms and to working closely with builders and with lenders, so that we can ensure that many, many more people can finally get the home that they and their family need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14745</id>
    <published>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/appointments-to-the-homes-and-communities-agency-board"/>
    <title>Appointments to the Homes and Communities Agency Board</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Communities and Local Government today appointed three non-executive members to the Board of the Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) following open competition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Richard Hyde&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anthony Preiskel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruth Thompson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the appointment, Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce the appointment of Richard Hyde, Anthony Preiskel and Ruth Thompson to the HCA Board. They will bring valuable commercial experieince to the Board, helping the Agency to deliver housing and regeneration to meet the needs of local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chairman of the HCA Board, Robert Napier said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I very much welcome these appointments. The HCA has a strong Board and it will be further strengthened by the wealth of commercial and public sector expertise that Anthony, Richard and Ruth will bring; helping to ensure that the Agency continues to meet local priorities while providing good value for money for the taxpayer.
&amp;gt; “And I must also record my thanks to those who are stepping down from the HCA Board; together they have been instrumental in driving the Agency in successful delivery, meeting or exceeding all of the key targets set by Government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Homes and Communities Agency (HCA) is the Government agency tasked with supporting and enabling places to deliver their housing and regeneration needs and helping to drive local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The appointments were made on open competition, conducted by the Department for Communities and Local Government in accordance with the Commissioner for Public Appointments’ Code of Practice for Ministerial Appointments to Public Bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Richard Hyde is currently chief executive of Brian Hyde Ltd (a sales, distribution and marketing business), a non-executive at Midland Heart housing association and Centro, the West Midlands passenger transport authority. He is deputy chairman of the Shakespeare Birthplace Trust. He was previously deputy chairman of Advantage West Midlands. Richard was also previously a Conservative County (Warwickshire) (2001-2009) and District (Stratford-on-Avon) (1996-2002) councillor, and spent time as deputy leader of the district council and deputy group leader of the West Midlands Local Government Association.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anthony Preiskel recently retired from a career of more than 20 years at P&amp;amp;O, chiefly as Deputy Chairman and Managing Director of P&amp;amp;O Properties. He is currently an independent director of the Kensington &amp;amp; Chelsea Tenant Management Organisation (TMO), the company which manages all the social housing owned by the Royal Borough.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ruth Thompson’s career has been in the utilities sector, including senior roles at National Grid, Transco and British Gas. Her responsibilities have included delivering major business change involving significant asset portfolios and engagement with regulators. Ruth moved into a non-executive career in 2006, including as deputy chair of the One North East Regional Development Agency up until its abolition and as a member of the National Renewable Energy Centre.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Richard Hyde, Anthony Preiskel and Ruth Thompson have each been appointed to the Board for a term of three years commencing on 1 November 2012. Their remuneration will be £12,000 for two days per month.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State has reappointed Ian Robertson and Bob Lane to the HCA Board for terms of three years and two years respectively with effect from 1 October 2012. Shaukat Moledina, Peter Roberts, Dru Vesty and Don Wood had all left the Board by the end of October 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Government has also undertaken a separate process to appoint new members to the HCA Regulation Committee. These appointments will be announced shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14737</id>
    <published>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-23T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-support-to-help-town-team-partners-transform-their-high-streets"/>
    <title>New support to help 'Town Team Partners' transform their high streets</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of towns across the country are being offered support that will help them revitalise their high streets, Local Growth Minister Mark Prisk announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following applications by local MPs, over 300 Town Teams have signed up to become &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/townteampartners/"&gt;Town Team Partners&lt;/a&gt;, and will benefit from a package of support, which includes help from the Government as well as advice and support from leading retail experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Town Teams Partners will receive an immediate boost, with national event to be held in Birmingham tomorrow by the Association of Town Centre Managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk said the extra support would help the teams to strengthen their leadership on the ground, and enable them to try new ideas on their high streets to make them more attractive and competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="designs-for-deptford"&gt;Designs for Deptford&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mark the announcement the Minister visited Deptford, a successful applicant to become a Town Team Partner. The team have plans to use the creative buzz generated by local artists by installing their art works in the high street and in local shops - from boutiques to the local fishmongers -  all under the ‘Made in Deptford’ banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Prisk also saw the Deptford Project, a railway carriage that has been transformed into a cafe - a great example of how the Town Team Partner plans to transform the look of the high street and showcase local talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/UuacApa2aUE?rel=0;showinfo=0" alt="iframe: "&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/word/2242676.doc"&gt;Town Team Partners - Transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;MS Word, 27 kb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local Growth Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s a real hunger in town centres across the country for them to be revitalised and remain attractive places to visit. So I’m delighted that from today over 300 Town Team Partners will begin to receive a package of support that helps them breathe new life into their high streets.
&amp;gt; “No one’s pretending that there’s a silver bullet for improving the performance of our town centres. Yet as I saw in Deptford: with this new support, and the opportunity to learn from each other, Town Teams can channel their energy and enthusiasm into promoting a more exciting and competitive offer on our high-streets, and help them thrive for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="package-of-support"&gt;Package of support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity to become a Town Team Partner received an overwhelming response from towns across the country, with hundreds of MPs submitting applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Town Team Partner will have access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;help to get started and become established in their town&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an advice line and a network of advisers managed by the Association of Town Centre Management&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;special national events to learn from other Town Teams, and secure support from industry experts and trade bodies&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an online ‘Knowledge Bank’ with expert advice and support&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;regular meetings with other Town Teams to share tips and ideas, and&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘Crowdfunding’ - a potential way to attract local investors and raise small amounts of finance to support their work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All Town Team Partners will also benefit from a Government-sponsored fund designed to help towards getting their plans off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list of Town Team Partners is available at: &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls"&gt;www.communities.gov.uk/documents/newsroom/1786823/2241696.xls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="high-street-x-factor"&gt;High Street x-factor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Town centres also have the opportunity to win the £1million &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/regeneration/economicgrowth/highstreetsportas/"&gt;Future High Street X-Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prize will be shared among the high streets that show the greatest improvements. Towns will be judged by an independent expert panel, for the inventiveness of their schemes and evidence of their impact, such as increased footfall or turnover, or improved skills and employment levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towns will also need to explain how they plan to use their prize money to further support their high streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14727</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-10-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/welcome-support-for-park-home-residents"/>
    <title>Welcome support for park home residents</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government today welcomed a Parliamentary Bill that will seek to offer additional protections for residents of park homes against unscrupulous or dishonest operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Aldous’ &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/mobilehomes.html"&gt;Private Members’ Bill&lt;/a&gt; (external link) is fully supported by the Government, led by the Housing Minister Mark Prisk, and has its second reading debate in the House of Commons on Friday 19 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many park home residents live in poor conditions and are unable to exercise their existing legal rights. The worst practices of dishonest site owners include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blocking the open market sales of park homes on their sites - without justifiable reason;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neglecting their sites and failing to make adequate repairs; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;charging excessive pitch fees and breaching site rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These abuses have manifested in real-life examples where operators have lied to prospective purchasers about the conditions of homes and even dug holes around homes to make them unsaleable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms are designed to ensure site owners who behave responsibly can continue to operate as they do already while rogue operators are properly tackled - as well as being made to meet the cost of their negligence rather than the taxpayer picking up the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms to the licensing system that applies to park home sites;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures to prevent operators from blocking residents’ sales in the open market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the existing law to protect occupiers from harassment and make it an offence to lie to prevent a home being sold;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a possible future ‘fit and proper’ registration to restrict the ability of unscrupulous operators from management of sites; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a scheme to make pitch fee reviews more transparent and new rules on reviews so they are fairer and reflect the condition of the site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Housing Minister Mark Prisk said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many people choose a park home expecting a peaceful retirement and a good quality of life. This bill will help to make that a reality by ensuring that sites are safe and properly managed and that residents are better able to exercise their rights.
&amp;gt; “This industry has been blighted by rogue operators - these reforms aim to drive them out of the industry securing a fairer deal both for home owners and for the good operators, running decent businesses.
&amp;gt; “This is why the Government is fully backing Peter Aldous’ Mobile Homes Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="images"&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard" alt="http://www.communities.gov.uk/images/newsroom/1639509?view=Standard"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
