<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/mark-francois</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/mark-francois.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Mark Francois MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17217</id>
    <published>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-30T19:36:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/military-urge-generous-public-not-to-swamp-postal-system-at-christmas"/>
    <title>Military urge generous public not to swamp postal system at Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Service personnel are urging members of the public to avoid sending unsolicited Christmas gifts and packages to operational theatres.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Christmas post deadline of 3 December approaches for Armed Forces personnel serving overseas, servicemen and women are urging members of the public not to send unsolicited gifts and packages to operational theatres such as Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these kind sentiments are appreciated, such generosity has often resulted in delaying important mail from family and friends reaching their destination at this special time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceFor/ServiceCommunity/BFPO/BritishForcesPostOffice.htm" title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;British Forces Post Office&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;) is overwhelmed by the generosity of the public who send individuals, and groups, in operational theatres boxes of treats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although well-intentioned, the message is very clear: if people wish to show their support for those serving in Afghanistan, there are far more effective ways of doing so such as donations to Service charities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking from &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbrizenorton/" title="RAF Brize Norton"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt; spokesperson Lieutenant Colonel Brett Duxbury said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with every year, the Christmas post period is by far our busiest. Just this week we dispatched more than 10,500 bags of mail to operational theatres, which will arrive in time for Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unsolicited mail can seriously impact on our ability to deliver post from loved ones to personnel serving on operations at Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We do not underestimate the impact that mail from friends and family can have on morale and it is for that reason we make it our priority each year to ensure it arrives on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parcels are coming in thick and fast to the military’s premier transport hub of &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, via the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, and have been loaded onto aircraft ready for dispatch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Service personnel are working hard to ensure that this mail is delivered alongside other vital supplies such as helicopters, armoured vehicles and lifesaving equipment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporal Danny Smith, from No 1 Air Mobility Wing at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last two days over 23 tonnes of mail has arrived at Brize Norton from the &lt;abbr title="British Forces Post Office"&gt;BFPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, which has been loaded onto aircraft and is now en route to various operational theatres including Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s a challenging but important task ensuring it is all dispatched quickly. Having served in Afghanistan at Christmas last year, I understand how much value our boys and girls place on receiving post from people closest to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1242/Mail1g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas mail for the troops, sorted, bagged and packaged, awaits final transportation to Afghanistan in the air cargo hangar at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The volume of mail arriving at Camp Bastion for onward distribution to other locations in Afghanistan can cause other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The onward delivery of goodwill parcels to forward operating bases necessitates additional resupply flights and convoys, which places Service personnel at additional risk in what is already a difficult and dangerous operating environment. Every time an additional convoy is laid on, more troops are put at risk of enemy attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of items included in many welfare parcels are either already readily available in theatre or are simply not appropriate for the Afghan environment. Not only does this mean that the items go to waste, but time and resources have to be diverted from crucial operations to organise their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans, Mark Francois, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Government is dedicated to the care and welfare of the men and women of our Armed Forces, particularly those deployed on operations. This is reflected in the Deployed Welfare Package, a key part of which is the safe and timely delivery of free personal mail from family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the past this mechanism has been used by the general public to show their support and resulted in huge volumes of unsolicited goodwill parcels being sent, which have overwhelmed the in-theatre postal and logistics capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whilst unsolicited mail is well-intentioned, mail sent by families and friends is the most important to deployed personnel and is our absolute priority. Moreover, unsolicited mail strains the logistics supply and prevents mail from families getting through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason the MOD will be repeating its unsolicited mail campaign. Rather than sending their own letter or parcel, I would encourage people to make a donation to one of Britain’s excellent Service charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They might also consider &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;‘uk4u Thanks!’&lt;/a&gt; - a charity that provides Christmas gifts to deployed Service personnel. Once again I would like to say thank you to the British public, on behalf of the MOD and Armed Forces, for their incredible support of our serving personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas mail for the troops" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1243/Mail2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mail for troops in places such as Afghanistan awaiting loading onto aircraft at &lt;abbr title="Royal Air Force"&gt;RAF&lt;/abbr&gt; Brize Norton [Picture: Steve Lympany, Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the charity uk4u Thanks! will, for the ninth year, deliver a Christmas Box of practical gifts and treats to every soldier, sailor and airman deployed overseas - in Afghanistan and elsewhere - and to those in hospital and recovery centres in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its parcels are delivered via the supply chain, meaning there is no impact on the mail network. Although the charity benefits from corporate sponsorship, it also needs donations from the public to continue its work bringing Christmas cheer to thousands of personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD provides a comprehensive Deployed Welfare Package which includes a free mail service for families and friends, 30 minutes of telephone calls a week and internet access, there are still areas where life in an operational theatre can be improved over and above that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and in order to enable members of the public to make a contribution to the welfare of personnel in an appropriate way, the MOD Operations Welfare Fund was established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priority for spending from the fund is set by commanders in theatre for those items which have the most impact on enhancing the morale of their personnel, and any money donated to this fund enables commanding officers on the ground to bid for items which their men and women have asked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of items purchased through the fund are Wii handsets, portable DVD players, games and table tennis tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make a donation can send a cheque to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations Welfare Fund, J1 Operation HERRICK, PJHQ, Sandy Lane, Northwood, Middlesex HA6 3HP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recommended Christmas posting date for personnel on Her Majesty’s ships is Friday 30 November 2012, and for Operation HERRICK and Operation KIPION is Monday 3 December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60064</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:55:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/recognition-for-veterans-of-arctic-convoys-and-bomber-command"/>
    <title>Recognition for veterans of Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Prime Minister has welcomed Sir John Holmes' review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Parliament today, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, welcomed the conclusion of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review into the rules and principles governing the award of military campaign medals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his review, which was requested by Mr Cameron, Sir John Holmes has recommended recognition for veterans of the Arctic Convoys and Bomber Command Second World War campaigns. The Prime Minister has agreed to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veterans of the Arctic Convoy campaigns will get recognition with an Arctic Convoy Star medal. Meanwhile, the aircrew of Bomber Command who played such a vital role in the war will be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5776/arcticconvoy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from the cruiser HMS Sheffield during an Arctic Convoy escort patrol, December 1941 [Picture: Lieutenant R G G Coote, Royal Navy. © IWM (A 6892)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased that some of the brave men of the Arctic Convoys will get the recognition they so richly deserve for the very dangerous work they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On Bomber Command, Sir John concluded they have been treated inconsistently with those who served Fighter Command. He’s therefore recommended – and I also agree - that the heroic aircrews of Bomber Command should be awarded a Bomber Command clasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An underwater detonation during a convoy to Russia in September 1942" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/5777/arcticconvoy2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An underwater detonation erupts next to HMS Ashanti during a convoy to Russia in September 1942. The destroyer HMS Eskimo is seen in the foreground. Merchant ships are in the background [Picture:  British Newsreel Pictures. © IWM (A 12022)]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My own father served in World War Two and I believe those that have served our country in Bomber Command and on the Arctic Convoy deserve nothing but the utmost respect and admiration from us all. I am delighted that I can confirm that both of these special groups of men who served will be able to receive a new form of recognition next year, as announced by the Prime Minister today. We are looking at the implementation of this and hope to make a further announcement by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Agreement included a commitment to review the rules surrounding the award of military campaign medals, as part of work to strengthen the military covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the second part of Sir John Holmes’ review will report back in the New Year, when the Ministry of Defence will also set out eligibility criteria for the medals and clasps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28536</id>
    <published>2012-12-07T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T17:09:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/armed-forces-discount-card-launched-in-time-for-christmas"/>
    <title>Armed Forces discount card launched in time for Christmas</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>A brand new discount card, exclusively for members of the Armed Forces, their families and veterans, will be rolled out next week.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 50 high street companies and businesses have pledged generous discounts to show their support for the Armed Forces Community through the Defence Discount Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Defence Privilege Card, which will be available to sign up for online next week, will ensure our Armed Forces Community get exclusive discounts from participating stores across the country. This new card will provide money off items ranging from children’s toys and winter knitwear to mobile phones and even food shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 24,000 members of the Armed Forces Community have joined the scheme to date. Examples of the discounts they will now be able to access include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="An example of the Defence Privilege Card" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1361/DefenceDiscount-5Dec2012_2519.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of the Defence Privilege Card [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10% off all groceries at Iceland&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20% off phone contracts at Vodafone&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20% off tickets at Vue Cinemas&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an introductory 20% followed by 15% off everything in store at Austin Reed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10% off everything at KFC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 to 10% off gift cards ordered from the Defence Discount Service website for most major supermarkets, Boots, Toys R Us, Topman, Currys, Debenhams, House of Fraser, B&amp;amp;Q, Homebase and H Samuel.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The roll-out of the new Defence Privilege Card coincides with the publication of the first annual report on the Armed Forces Covenant. This sets out key disadvantages the Government has tackled over the last year to improve life for our Armed Forces Community and ensures personnel and their families are not unfairly affected by their service to their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="David Cameron welcomes Service personnel to No 10" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1362/DefenceDiscount-5Dec2012_2503.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Prime Minister David Cameron welcomes Service personnel to No 10 Downing Street [Picture: Crown Copyright/MOD 2012]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Handing out the first Defence Privilege Cards at No 10 Downing Street yesterday, the Prime Minister, David Cameron, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted that we have managed to get so many companies to sign up to this - and just in time for Christmas. As well as allowing people to save money, these discounts are a token of the immense appreciation that we all have for our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is fitting that the cards are launched in the year that the military have done so much for our country, not just abroad but here in the UK, showing the very best of British during the Olympics and the Jubilee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The men and women of our Armed Forces, their families and our veterans reflect what is best in our society. That is why we are committed to rebuilding the Armed Forces Covenant and it is with great pride that I am publishing the first ever Armed Forces Covenant report today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17806</id>
    <published>2012-12-04T09:55:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-05T09:55:01+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/lorraine-kelly-launches-christmas-box-appeal"/>
    <title>Lorraine Kelly launches Christmas Box appeal</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>TV presenter and journalist Lorraine Kelly joined members of the Royal Marines on a zip wire from Wellington Arch in London today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event launched the annual Christmas Box campaign for the Armed Forces, run by the charity &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.uk4u.org/" title="uk4u Thanks!"&gt;uk4u Thanks!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign sees 22,500 boxes - affectionately known as ‘square stockings’ - sent to servicemen and women across the world who are working away from their families and members of the Armed Forces recuperating in hospital this Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorraine Kelly joined members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/The-Fleet/The-Royal-Marines" title="Royal Marines"&gt;Royal Marines&lt;/a&gt; Commando Recruiting Troop on the zip wire descending 80 feet (24 metres) from the top of Wellington Arch in Hyde Park down to the ground below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were greeted at the bottom by Father Christmas who gave everyone a 2012 Christmas Box painted in the colours of the Diamond Jubilee Medal ribbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Christmas Boxes being handed to soldiers in Afghanistan" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1326/boxes2g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Christmas Boxes being handed to the men of 35 Engineer Regiment in Afghanistan in 2011 (library image) [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the launch, Lorraine Kelly said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be showing my support once again for such a worthwhile cause as the Christmas Box appeal, and I had a great time with the Royal Marines on the zip wire today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can join me in wishing a Happy Christmas to all our servicemen and women away from their families at this time of year by donating to the charity uk4u Thanks! who’ll send each of them a fantastic box full of goodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also present were other members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/" title="Royal Navy"&gt;Royal Navy&lt;/a&gt; and members of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.army.mod.uk/" title="British Army"&gt;Army&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.raf.mod.uk/" title="Royal Air Force"&gt;Royal Air Force&lt;/a&gt; who have received a Christmas Box while serving on operations on Christmas Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt="Soldiers with Christmas Boxes" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1327/boxes3g.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Soldiers at Forward Operating Base Shawqat in Helmand province in 2011 with their Christmas Boxes (library image) [Picture: Corporal Jamie Peters RLC, Crown Copyright/MOD 2011]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;uk4u Thanks! works with the Armed Forces to send the boxes, containing some 20 items, out to locations such as Afghanistan, the Falklands, and ships and submarines across the world in time for 25 December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do not use the British Forces Post Office system so as not to delay parcels from families and friends getting through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence Minister Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Christmas can be difficult for many of our servicemen and women who are deployed on operations away from their families when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can all therefore show that we are thinking of them by donating to charities such as uk4u Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45358</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T17:45:41+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-11-06-address-to-the-armed-forces-community-covenant-conference"/>
    <title>2012/11/06 - Address to the Armed Forces Community Covenant Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans at the Armed Forces Community Covenant Conference, MOD Main Building, London on Tuesday 6 November 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Cromwell’s troops once declared that, “on becoming soldiers, we have not ceased to be citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would go further and say that the men and women of today’s Armed Forces - through their dedicated, demanding and often dangerous service to their country - are, to quote Winston Churchill, “twice the citizen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is not fair that, because of the nature of their service, they should have unequal access to the services on which we all depend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept of creating a fair deal for our Armed Forces - past and present - is at the core of the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have already heard from General Rollo and others about what this means from the military perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from this Government’s perspective it is about encouraging the whole of society to recognise its moral obligation to our Service men and women, and to the families that support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cannot be achieved by central government alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can address some of the issues by getting all departments to understand the unique requirements of the military, better coordinating the allocation of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also work closely with charities such as The Royal British Legion, which has recently published its Best Practice Guide to Community Covenants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to see Chris Simpkins here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Armed Forces Covenant needs to be implemented by all sections of society: including by local communities, local charities and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is at the local level that many issues are best resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community-covenant"&gt;Community Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why Community Covenant Partnerships are central to the delivery of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tremendous progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much actual delivery is down to local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have well and truly picked up the ball and started running with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant is close to my heart on a number of levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of you will know I began my political career in local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I served as a councillor on Basildon Borough Council.  It was a robust council. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was once described as the only council in the UK where councillors actively heckled the public gallery during meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know what it’s like to be a councillor dealing with competing priorities, with limited resources and financial pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that not everyone you assist remembers to say thank you after you’ve helped them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me, while I’m here, say “thank you” - all of you - for what you’ve done to support our Armed Forces through the Armed Forces Community Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As councillors, supported by your officers, you have been a credit to the people who elected you to public office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also want to say that nobody can say that local government has not stepped up to the plate on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And anyone who does will have to get by me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that as representatives of your communities you are often best placed to pick up on the needs of the Service personnel who reside in your jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is vital, because the requirements of a soldier posted to Wellington barracks, just the other side of St James’s park, might be very different from the requirements of a sailor based in rural Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can’t dictate what you should do from the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s up to you to decide how you should do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps I can suggest three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, that you all appoint an Armed Forces champion - a councillor who is nominated to make sure that the principles of the Covenant are carried through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, that in your housing allocation policies you ensure serving personnel and veterans get the best possible treatment.  And ideally, where possible, you appoint a Senior Housing Officer to be responsible for this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And please bear in mind that around 1 in 10 adults is a veteran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thousands live in your areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, on education, that you do everything you can to help Service children get the education they deserve, particularly working to mitigate any disruption to schooling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, by following Oxfordshire Council in accepting school applications from Service families before they are posted and have basing addresses in the area to which they are going to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has long been an issue for service families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sense of urgency to get all of this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our troops are going to be coming home from Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they have given so much for us, it is only fair that we try to give something back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a window of opportunity to get things right for our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my aspiration is that in this time before they have all come home we achieve national coverage for the Community Covenant, so that wherever our Armed Forces and veterans live they know their local authority will be looking out for them and critically their families as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to your hard work I know we are making real progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a position where Community Covenant Partnerships have been signed by over 200 local authorities, up and down the UK, with more on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of the first annual report on the Armed Forces Covenant, which is not far away now, will lay out this progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the principle of no disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second that special consideration is appropriate in some cases, especially for those who have given most such as the injured and the bereaved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now the law of the land that the Secretary of State must provide a report to Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would be arrogant in the extreme to believe that we could solve all the problems in a single year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we have now initiated a process that will allow us to address problems systematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase Churchill again: With regard to the matter of the Armed Forces Covenant Report, this is not the end.  It is not even the beginning of the end.  It is not even the end of the beginning.  This is in fact the beginning of the beginning.  But nevertheless this process has now well and truly begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I saw that this morning when I was in my own patch in Essex, co-signing a Community Covenant, which was signed by Essex County Council and all 14 other local authorities in Essex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may know, I once applied to be a candidate in a by-election in Kensington and Chelsea.  I lost out to some chap called Michael Portillo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that time I was asked by a lady from Chelsea with a cut glass accent, “Mr Francois, would you say that you are proud to call yourself an Essex Man?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No Madame, but I am very proud to be a man from Essex.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have never been prouder than when I saw all of the local authorities of Essex sign their Community Covenant, one after another this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also very proud of all the other local authorities across the country that have signed their Covenant agreements as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These partnerships have helped local authorities to understand the needs of Service families, introducing practical measures to improve their access to GPs, dentists, local schools and housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everywhere I go, I get feedback that part of the value of the Community Covenant comes from establishing a framework for dialogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dialogue between local authorities: unitary, county, district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dialogue between sectors: private, public, voluntary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a dialogue between communities: military and civilian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But fundamentally this is a dialogue between individuals: person-to-person contact that works out problems and gets things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this network of conversation people are discovering low cost or no cost measures that add up to have a genuine impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple things, like the staff who provide some of Gateshead Council’s frontline services asking, the question, whenever people approach the council: are you part of the Armed Forces community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not all just about communication and coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant is backed by a separate £30m Grant Scheme to support local projects that benefit veterans, serving personnel and the communities they live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will hear from the leaders of three successful projects later today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the scheme, in June 2011, we have received 240 bids - 120 of which have been successful - amounting to £5 million of already allocated funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will have instantly realised, this is a far higher success rate than most bids to the National Lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to the Community Covenant Grant - it really could be you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next panel considering grant applications will sit on 13 December this year with a deadline for submissions to the MOD for bids of 28 November. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following panel will sit on 14 March 2013 with a deadline of 28 February 2013 - that is two bidding rounds you can apply to so get your pens out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two days time I will be back in Essex to see the Royal Anglian Regiment, my old regiment, march through the Borough of Basildon - with trumpets sounding, drums beating, fifes playing and colours flying - as they exercise the freedom of the borough which they were give two years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you how much these parades mean to those returning from operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are really important to them and to their families who miss them while they are away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And particularly also to those who have lost loved ones in the service of their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I thank all of you who have granted freedom to your local Armed Forces and encourage others who can to consider doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe wholeheartedly in the value of the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why all local authorities in England and Wales have recently been sent a letter that I have co-written with Sir Merrick Cockell laying out the merits of the Community Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be writing in the same terms to local authorities in Scotland very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who have yet to sign a Community Covenant, I hope that you leave here today with a whole host of reasons to do so, and a clearer idea of how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who have already signed a Community Covenant, I would encourage you to share your ideas and experiences - which are helping to turn the Covenant into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud of the progress we have already made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think together, working in partnership, we can do more - particularly in the context of our returning troops, which gives immediacy to the whole project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must all play our part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, particularly at this time of remembrance we must never forget the fact that we live in a free country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that we can only do this thanks to some very special people - our Service men and women - who are prepared to lay down their lives to protect that freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something which we should not take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recognised this in the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Community Covenant gives this real form at local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us - all of us - owe these people a debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must honour the Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s roll up our sleeves and get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45352</id>
    <published>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T18:38:42+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-31-the-confederation-of-service-charities-cobseo-agm"/>
    <title>2012/10/31 - The Confederation of Service Charities (COBSEO) AGM</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans at the Victory Services Club, London on Wednesday 31 October 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been the Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans for little over two months now and it is an honour to be able to fulfil this role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My portfolio covers issues like: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure that we do what we can to strengthen the backbone of our Armed Forces - the forces families who support them; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure our wounded get the best care we can provide;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure that the hidden wounds of war are treated too with the new emphasis on mental health;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping Service personnel succeed in civilian life when they leave;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making sure that we continue to honour the service of our community of veterans, who make up around 1 in 10 of our adult population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you seeing a pattern here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concerns are basically your concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody knows better than you, the life changing work that your organisations do on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not need any convincing of the value of COBSEO members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering services; sharing the burden; helping to meet our collective obligations under the Armed Forces Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to take this opportunity to thank you for everything you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You complement the work of the MOD in a huge number of areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly view the relationship as symbiotic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are partners, very definitely not rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-cobseo"&gt;Importance of COBSEO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO is central to making this partnership work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are lucky in Britain to have such a wide range of dedicated Service charities helping those who have given so much to their country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some who question the very existence of service charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shouldn’t this all be done by Government?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else do we pay our taxes for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the MOD does directly fund a lot of the work that COBSEO organisations help with, but for me, it just isn’t an either or.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity is a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should never allow the cynics, or those who seem to believe that making a contribution to society should be exclusively for the public sector, we should never allow them to devalue what is achieved by organisations like COBSEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Chairman, the State claims no monopoly on good will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the Big Lottery Fund which is providing £35m for veterans projects like the Forces in Mind Trust run in partnership with COBSEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society is stronger and healthier for the contribution that charities make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of you has your own niche - representing special groups and possessing your own expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That diversity is a massive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also makes it difficult for the MOD to be in constant touch with all the work that is going on out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to establishing a proper dialogue, COBSEO provides an effective and powerful, unified voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD is approached by hundreds of charities a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to know that all of those charities are legitimate, well run and sustainable before we engage with them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COBSEO membership is useful because it gives us an additional degree of confidence in a charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But COBSEO is not the only way charities can represent themselves to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the embedded charity staff in personnel recovery centres, to the close working relationships between military Welfare Officers and a wide range of charities - there are thousands of interactions between the MOD and COBSEO members at grass roots level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the strategic level COBSEO is an important channel of communication and advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charities are often well placed to pick up on the concerns of the groups that they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that in his earlier address the Chairman raised concerns about the future status of the Independent Medical Expert Group (IMEG) which has been subject to review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce today, that following discussions with the Cabinet Office, Ministers there have agreed that the IMEG will now be established permanently as an Advisory Non-Departmental Public Body in order that it can continue to provide independent expert medical advice on matters relating to the Armed Forces Compensation Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are keen to hear what you have to say. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why COBSEO is an influential member of the Armed Forces Covenant Reference Group - the CRG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This body helps to steer the direction of the Armed Forces Covenant, which recognises society’s moral obligation to our Service men and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have always understood this moral obligation and been at the forefront of meeting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense, then, that you help us to identify where disadvantage exists and where special provision is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when the Chancellor announced that money from fines levied on banks involved in Libor rate fixing would be spent on the Armed Forces Covenant, it was only right that this £35 million would be allocated in partnership with the CRG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This money will go towards supporting the Armed Forces community, including through Service charities, funding work that will address some of the disadvantages that the Armed Forces community face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-armed-forces-covenant"&gt;The Armed Forces Covenant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Armed Forces Covenant is being implemented by many sections of society: by national and local government, by local communities and, of course, by charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of these efforts can be wasted, if we apply our resources to the wrong areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is another area where your advice is so effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to your help the Covenant is starting to make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over a year ago we launched the Community Covenant Scheme, encouraging local authorities to meet the unique requirements of the Service personnel and their families living in their jurisdictions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a position where Community Covenant Partnerships have been signed by over 200 local authorities, up and down the UK, with more on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance in my own patch in Essex, the County Council will sign the Community Covenant next week in the run up to Remembrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These partnerships have enabled local authorities to understand the needs of Service families and introduce practical measures to improve their access to GPs, dentists, local schools and housing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant Scheme is backed by a separate £30m Grant Scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around £5m has already been released to support local projects that benefit veterans, serving personnel and the communities they live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also re-launched the Defence Discount Service, helping to recognise the contribution of our Armed Forces by providing them and their families with financial savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are many other initiatives at national and local level which help make the Covenant a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the Covenant is getting society to understand how much it owes the Armed Forces - past and present - and the families that have supported them - and to encourage society to find ways of repaying that debt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need you to continue helping deliver the Covenant, but we also need you to help judge the progress of that delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The charities’ commentary on the Secretary of State’s Annual Report on the Covenant is one of its most important sections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It holds us to account and it gives us guidance on how we might improve in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of this first annual report, which is not far away now, will show progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is only a beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this job I am absolutely determined to put flesh on the bones of the Covenant to give it real form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to use it to improve the lives of service personnel and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still much to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hope that when you see the report you will feel that we have made a good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that you too have been discussing your future today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been told that this AGM represents something of a crossroads for COBSEO and its members as you decide your long term direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right that these are decisions for you to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me just say though that I have been impressed with how much impact COBSEO has made with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value the coherence it gives to Service charities and the validating role it has with regards to its members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these are functions that you might like to consider taking forward and developing in partnership with the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We certainly don’t want you to lose your individual identities as charities.  They define you and they focus you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the confederation of charities that COBSEO represents, works very well from our perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever decisions you make, I look forward to continuing the extremely productive relationship that we have forged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you and Good Luck.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34759</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:01:55+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/138-2012-new-armed-forces-pension-agreed"/>
    <title>138/2012 - New Armed Forces pension agreed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Armed Forces personnel will continue to receive one of the best and most valuable public service pensions, under a new scheme announced today by the Ministry of Defence.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In July, the Ministry of Defence published an outline design of the new Armed Forces Pension Scheme and invited further comments. The consultation has resulted in a key change - Service personnel will now have more flexibility for the money they receive if they qualify for an early payment at 40. This is another benefit exclusive to Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new scheme means unlike other public service pension schemes, Service personnel will still not have to make personal contributions and the Normal Pension Age will be 60, whereas for most other public service pensions the Normal Pension Age will be linked to the State Pension Age, which is considerably higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will also deliver on the approach set out in Lord Hutton’s Independent Public Service Pensions Commission to reform pensions and ensure that they are more affordable and sustainable for the long-term. Changes will not affect accrued rights of those currently serving or the age at which their accrued pension benefits can be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government had to make some tough decisions to ensure sustainable public service pensions, but recognises the unique commitment made by the Armed Forces and therefore protected them as much as possible, making these changes in the fairest way possible. Armed Forces personnel will continue to receive one of the best and most valuable pensions in the public and private sectors, maintaining the non-contributory element, an early pension point at 40 and a lower Normal Pension Age than other public sector employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits of the proposed new scheme include:
* It creates one scheme for all – including Reservists. There are currently several different Armed Forces pension schemes; 
* Service personnel won’t have to make any personal contributions to their pension;
* Service personnel will receive a monthly income and a tax-free lump sum if they leave the Armed Forces aged at least 40 and have given at least 20 years of service. No other public service makes any pension payment that early. In addition, Service personnel will now have the flexibility to convert their total Early Departure Payment lump sum into additional monthly income payments; 
* As recommended by Lord Hutton, the Normal Pension Age will be 60 – considerably lower than most other public service pensions;
* Accrued pension rights have been protected so there is no change to the age at which those currently serving can draw the benefits that they have accrued in the current schemes, which are based on final rank and salary; 
* It is in line with Lord Hutton’s recommendations and other public service schemes, moving to a pension based on career average earnings, rather than final salary; and
* All members of the Armed Forces Pension Scheme who were within ten years of their Normal Pension Age on 1 April 2012 will receive transitional protection and will not be transferred to the new scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme was designed after extensive consultation with over 25,000 personnel both in the UK and overseas including Afghanistan, Germany, Gibraltar and the Falkland Islands which included presentations, focus groups and questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 the Government announced it would be reforming all public service pensions and later accepted the Independent Public Service Pensions Commission’s recommendations to make them fair and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Defence ran an Armed Forces Pension Scheme consultation exercise from March to May 2012 to set out the reasons for change and invite views from Service personnel and external stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 31 July, the Ministry of Defence published the Outline Scheme Design, which set out the key features of the new scheme. The document was primarily aimed at Service personnel and external stakeholders, including the Forces’ Families Federations, the Forces Pension Society and the Royal British Legion. There was a further period of consultation for personnel to make comments which ended on 7 September.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new Armed Forces Pension Scheme will be introduced from April 2015. All those serving when the new scheme is introduced will be automatically enrolled unless they qualify for transitional protection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The total cost of the new Armed Forces Pension Scheme will be 31.5 per cent of pensionable pay, which is all borne by the Exchequer, as there are no employee contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the final agreement can be found at &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/WhatWeDo/Personnel/Pensions/FinalAgreement.htm"&gt;http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/WhatWeDo/Personnel/Pensions/FinalAgreement.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For further media enquiries please call Robert Mead at the Ministry of Defence press office on 020 7218 7924.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55478</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:02:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-armed-forces-pension-agreed"/>
    <title>New Armed Forces pension agreed</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Armed Forces personnel will continue to receive one of the best and most valuable public service pensions under a new scheme announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In July, the Ministry of Defence published an outline design of the new Armed Forces Pension Scheme and invited further comments. The consultation has resulted in a key change - Service personnel will now have more flexibility over the money they receive if they qualify for an early payment at age 40. This is another benefit exclusive to Service personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new scheme means that, unlike other public service pension schemes, Service personnel will still not have to make personal contributions and the Normal Pension Age will be 60, whereas for most other public service pensions the Normal Pension Age will be linked to the State Pension Age, which is considerably higher. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will also deliver on the approach set out in Lord Hutton’s Independent Public Service Pensions Commission to reform pensions and ensure that they are more affordable and sustainable in the long-term. Changes will not affect accrued rights of those currently serving or the age at which their accrued pension benefits can be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister of State for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Government had to make some tough decisions to ensure sustainable public service pensions, but recognises the unique commitment made by the Armed Forces and therefore protected them as much as possible, making these changes in the fairest way possible.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Armed Forces personnel will continue to receive one of the best and most valuable pensions in the public and private sectors, maintaining the non-contributory element, an early pension point at 40 and a lower Normal Pension Age than other public sector employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits of the proposed new scheme include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• it creates one scheme for all - including reservists. There are currently several different Armed Forces pension schemes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Service personnel won’t have to make any personal contributions to their pension&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Service personnel will receive a monthly income and a tax-free lump sum if they leave the Armed Forces aged at least 40 and have given at least 20 years of service. No other public service makes any pension payment that early. In addition, Service personnel will now have the flexibility to convert their total Early Departure Payment lump sum into additional monthly income payments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• as recommended by Lord Hutton, the Normal Pension Age will be 60 - considerably lower than for most other public service pensions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• accrued pension rights have been protected so there is no change to the age at which those currently serving can draw the benefits that they have accrued in the current schemes, which are based on final rank and salary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• it is in line with Lord Hutton’s recommendations and other public service schemes, moving to a pension based on career average earnings, rather than final salary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• all members of the Armed Forces Pension Scheme who were within ten years of their Normal Pension Age on 1 April 2012 will receive transitional protection and will not be transferred to the new scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme was designed after extensive consultation with over 25,000 personnel both in the UK and overseas, including in Afghanistan, Germany, Gibraltar and the Falkland Islands, in the form of presentations, focus groups and questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45363</id>
    <published>2012-10-02T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T18:10:57+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-10-02-address-to-the-surgeon-general-s-triple-serpent-conference"/>
    <title>2012/10/02 - Address to the Surgeon General’s Triple Serpent Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech delivered by Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans at the Medical Services Training Group, Ash Vale, Aldershot on Tuesday 2 October 2012.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Philip [Surgeon Vice Admiral Philip Raffaelli, the Surgeon General] for that introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pleasure to join you at the end of the first day of the Surgeon General conference - and so soon after taking up my post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this has been a long day and the bar beckons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to join you later for a drink - medicinal purpose only of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I discussed with my team was getting me some early opportunities to see you on your own turf - and the work you do for our Armed Forces Personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to visit our troops in Helmand in the coming months, and I will make sure that includes the Hospital in Camp Bastion - and, of course, its new maternity ward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am planning to see some of you at the Royal Centre for Defence Medicine at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of my first public duties was to be present when HRH The Prince of Wales opened the Jubilee Complex at Headley Court last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, for me, was both a humbling and an inspirational experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the bravery the men and women of our Armed Forces possess is not just expressed on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was incredibly impressed by the spirit of our wounded personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was equally impressed by the care and commitment shown by the people who look after them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am advised that even our US and Israeli colleagues would admit that we are now world leaders in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to start today by saying thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You work at the cutting edge of medical science and the first beneficiaries are those to whom the people of this country owe a great debt - those who risk life and limb to protect our national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of them are alive now because of you - and, compared with previous conflict, many of the seriously injured can expect to lead much more fulfilling lives because of the efforts you make. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that this is our first meeting I thought I would use this occasion to let you know where I’m coming from, and to talk just a little bit about the challenges we face together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="working-together"&gt;Working Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just a little about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Father served in the Royal Navy in World War Two, he fought at D-Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own service was as a TA Officer with the Royal Anglian Regiment during the 1980s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a different army then, trained for a very different war - a war that thankfully never came to pass.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I never saw active service and I have no medals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have worn the uniform, and, as a Reservist, I also remember what it was like to juggle Service with life outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that counts for something with you - because it certainly counts for something with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked to come to the MOD, and I am doing a job I want to do, working to improve the lives of the best and most dedicated people our country has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know that this is something you have been doing probably your whole professional lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you are recognised internationally as experts in your chosen field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not coming here to second guess you as professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am here primarily to listen and learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as a Minister, I also intend to be pro-active in getting things done, not sitting back and waiting for problems to cross my desk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a young platoon commander I was taught to seize the initiative and that is what I plan to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that my fresh eyes and ears will be of help in trying to get to the heart of some of the issues so that together we can make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are those issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="operations"&gt;Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first priority, of course, is operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan remains the number one priority for the Ministry of Defence and the Armed Forces and the work of the doctors, nurses and medics on the front-line is quite simply awe-inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at the National Arboretum last week and read the memorial for Army Medical Officer Capt Noel Chavasse, the only man to win the Victoria Cross twice during World War One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Chavasse died from his wounds at Passchendaele but not before saving the lives of countless others, which is what earned him the Bar on the Victoria Cross he originally won at the Somme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example of Captain Chavasse lives on in today’s medics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week we honoured Corporal Julie May, who twice put her own life at risk to save colleagues in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She received a Mention in Dispatches for attending to an IED casualty despite the significant danger posed by secondary devices in the area, and for stabilising an Afghan soldier whilst her position was under fire.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear stories like this I am truly impressed by the courage and skill displayed by members of your profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As UK Forces draw down from a combat role between now and 2014, one of the greatest challenges will be to make sure that we maintain the right medical support in theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be difficult to strike the right balance between reductions in scale and maintaining the capability and the capacity to deal with the unexpected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But strike the right balance, we must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the withdrawal from Afghanistan, we will to identify what lessons learned and new skills might be embedded in the Defence Medical Services for the future and, indeed, transferable into current NHS practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="where-we-are-now"&gt;Where We are Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back here at home Defence Transformation will be the vehicle that will shape the future of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now part of Joint Forces Command, which is one of the first tangible signs of transformation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know Air Chief Marshal Sir Stuart Peach will be addressing you this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the history of Defence Medical Services has been one of transformation - not always positive and certainly not straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over the last few decades - just as the Armed Forces themselves have changed from the massed forces that trained to face the Warsaw Pact across the North German Plain - Defence Medical Services has changed too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the virtually autonomous Single Services that ran their own hospitals when I served in the 1980s, to consolidated joint Defence Medical Service today - where the patient is the focus, which is part of the wider medical community, and which collaborates far and wide to ensure that evidence based, cutting edge medicine and treatment are embraced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially evident in the work being done in partnership with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The establishment last year of the National Institute of Health Research Centre for Surgical Reconstruction and Microbiology in Birmingham enables military personnel to share advances and surgical innovation with the NHS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples of the partnership approach are the work being done with the Royal British Legion and Imperial College London on blast injury, and the King’s Centre for Military Health Research on mental health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will be meeting Professor Simon Wessely to talk about his pioneering work at King’s, which is doing so much to further develop our understanding of the psychological effects of warfare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I did my Masters in War Studies at King’s College, under Sir Laurence Friedman, so I am looking forward to visiting my alma mater in the not too distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know this transformation hasn’t been easy, or without controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have come a long way since the outcome of Defence Cost Studies 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I think we should be proud of the quality of the care that is now being provided to our Service people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Clinical and Academic Units at Queen Elizabeth Hospital, our Service personnel have access to some of the best medical care available in dealing with the most serious injuries with all the key specialities, such as plastics and neurosurgery, under one roof. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see for myself next week how having a military ward in a cutting edge NHS hospital provides a reassuring environment for our service personnel while at the same time providing a level of care that would be difficult to recreate in a purely Service environment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as I have seen for myself, at Headley Court, the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre provides world class care and we are constantly investing in staff, facilities, patient welfare and treatments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly, and personally, pleased that this Government is helping you to focus attention on mental health - which had, perhaps, for many years not been given the priority it really deserved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to continue to champion a through life approach to mental health, drawing on the work of my new Ministerial colleague Doctor Andrew Murrison, as well as the considerable amount of research undertaken at King’s College. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is where we are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Care Quality Commission report praised the facilities available to casualties in theatre, as well as those for patients at Headley Court. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t happen by accident. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens because of people like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no successful organisation can be complacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me turn briefly to the future&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must continually strive for greater excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in today’s economic climate we must also strive for greater efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to go into detail on the pressures on the Government purse or on the Defence Budget - and I don’t want to get partisan about the reasons for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say we are where we are, and we face a delicate balancing act: reducing the fiscal deficit while making sure front-line services are protected as much as possible; making sure that our service personnel get the best care available, because the best is what they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is no pot of gold to fix things with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward we are going to have to be innovative and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the work underway on Defence Medical Services 2020 cannot happen in isolation from the wider changes taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true when it comes to Reserves, who will play an increasingly important role in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the autumn, we will be looking closely at the deal for Reservists and employers to make sure the offer to both supports our plans for a larger, more integrated Reserve. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is also true when it comes to the changes taking place in the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already had a very productive meeting with Dr Dan Poulter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan is a GP and the new Minister within the Department of Health with responsibility for the provision of secondary healthcare to Service personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have agreed to work together on a number of Service personnel and Veterans’ issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the planning application to build the Defence and National Rehabilitation Centre at Stanford Hall in Nottinghamshire is soon to be submitted to the Local Authority - and I am hoping to go and see the site for myself next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have committed to work with the Department of Health, the NHS and the project team to ensure that the National element of the project is given a high priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this close working together is framed by the Armed Forces Covenant, in which healthcare is a key and enduring obligation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress has already been made in delivering against our commitments, such as a greater focus on mental health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we go forward, the challenge will be to continue working successfully with the NHS as both organisations - them and us - go through transformation and reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will soon be a major change in the management of primary healthcare in Defence itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is designed to provide opportunities for better use of resources, improved quality through sharing best practice and expanded career options for medical staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Surgeon General has set out his clinical priorities that range from Combat Casualty Care, to Mental Health and Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, throughout this transformation we need to advance these clinical priorities, see through the cutting edge research, become even more efficient and even more patient focussed, while improving the standard of care provided to our Armed Forces personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be what my officials refer to as - “challenging”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are only going to succeed if we work together to achieve all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;‘#Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in no doubt, that when the Government sends the young men and women of our Armed Forces into harms way, we have a moral obligation to make sure they are properly equipped for the task they have been set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That they are given the best medical care available on the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that they and their families are properly looked after when they are away and when they get home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined to strive as hard as I can as a Minister to ensure that this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that together, with your help, that is what we will achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together, let us do our best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/34766</id>
    <published>2012-09-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T14:01:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/127-2012-1-3-million-for-communities-getting-behind-the-armed-forces-covenant"/>
    <title>127/2012 - £1.3 Million for communities getting behind the Armed Forces Covenant</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>More communities across the country are coming up with innovative ideas and initiatives to improve the lives of Service personnel and their families, the Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois has announced today.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the Army Families Federation annual conference and launching the next set of Community Covenant Grant projects, Mark Francois confirmed the Ministry of Defence would give £1.3 million to communities across the country – funding 36 new projects. This now brings the total Ministry of Defence spend on the Community Covenant Grant Scheme to £5 million in just over a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Community Covenant Grant projects announced today include:
* funding for a new support centre for veterans and their families in Nottinghamshire;
* an innovative peer-mentoring scheme to help young people from the Armed Forces integrate into communities in Cornwall;
* helping veterans find work in Glasgow; and 
* three projects to bring together the Armed Forces and local communities in Bradford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Minister for Defence Personnel, Welfare and Veterans Mark Francois said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These latest projects demonstrate the high regard the public has for the Armed Forces and I am delighted that people up and down the country continue to show their support and gratitude through each new idea and initiative. As a former Territorial Army officer I welcome any project which will help forge closer links between the Armed Forces and their local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Covenant scheme was launched in June 2011 and since then nearly 150 local authorities across the UK have pledged their support to the Armed Forces and signed up to a Community Covenant, including cities such as London, Edinburgh and Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government also made £30 million available for communities to establish their own projects and kick start initiatives that will make real change for Armed Forces and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to Editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Armed Forces Covenant is a statement of the moral obligation which exists between the nation, the Government and the Armed Forces. The Government has already taken swift action to improve the lives of service personnel, veterans and their families. This includes:
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a £15 million investment in prosthetics provision; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;improvements to mental healthcare; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a scholarship scheme for bereaved service children; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;priority on the Government’s First Buy scheme for members of the Armed Forces in England; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Doubling Council Tax Relief twice, which now stands at nearly £600 per service person for a six-month deployment; &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;tax free operational allowance has doubled so those serving on eligible operations now receive a lump sum of just over £5,000 for a six-month tour; and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;new online postcodes to ensure service personnel stationed overseas have improved access to online and financial services.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For further information on the Armed Forces Covenant and the Community Covenant Grant Scheme visit &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mod.uk/covenant"&gt;www.mod.uk/covenant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For all media enquiries or to find out if there is a Community Covenant Grant project in your area call the Ministry of Defence press office on 020 7218 7924.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
