<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/michael-moore</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/michael-moore.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Michael Moore MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-07T14:43:33+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56803</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T14:43:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/scotland-in-the-world"/>
    <title>Scotland in the world</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore, Secretary of State for Scotland, talks about Scotland in the world.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much to [Jeff Anderson] for inviting me to speak to you about Scotland in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a privilege to be here today in the Riggs Library here at Georgetown University and I am grateful to you, to Phoebe Wood and to the BMW Centre for the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my years as an opposition MP at Westminster I served a spokesman for my party on foreign, defence and international development issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore very aware of the range and extraordinary quality of both the teaching at the research undertaken at this university’s School of Foreign Service and Department of Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no coincidence that this institution counts President Clinton among its graduates and Secretary Albright as its Mortara Distinguished Professor of Diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month I had the honour of meeting Dr Albright and introducing her as the guest speaker at an annual business dinner in Glasgow, back home in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her insights were as prescient as ever and her comments on the value of keeping countries together were both welcome and positive - at least for those of us who wish to keep our United Kingdom together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is on that topic that I want to speak with you this afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scots’ impending choice in 2014 on whether they want to remain within the UK family or leave it forever with all the implications that has for Scotland itself, the rest of the United Kingdom and our respective relations with the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, for the past two and a half years I have served in the UK government as Secretary of State for Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of 5 Liberal Democrat cabinet ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting at the cabinet table, my job is to represent the specific needs and interests of Scotland in the government’s decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those issue are diverse, from agriculture to aviation and energy to defence, where Scotland’s requirements vary in profile from other parts of the United Kingdom, it is in the interests of all of the UK that this is understood and reflected in government policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government of which I am a member is the first coalition government that the UK has experienced since Winston Churchill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that time the coalition government faced a world-war and came together to work in the national interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government that I am part of faces a very different form of global challenge, but still serious, as we respond to the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the coalition took office in 2010, the UK was running a deficit equal in size to that of Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been our task to reduce spending while taking the decisions that will set our economy back on the right track, while in the midst of a Europe-wide crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a complex economy to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Scotland, that has required an understanding of the needs of the oil and gas industries in the north east, the banks and insurance companies centred primarily around Edinburgh and the extensive engineering, manufacturing and export sectors that feature in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all their considerations into account been a key priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And has had a clear demonstration of the UK government’s commitment to its success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is timely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the economy is not the only fundamental issue that the government must address with regard to Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important debate of my life-time - indeed of most people’s life-time - is currently going on in Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two years time those of us who live in Scotland will have the opportunity to cast our vote on the future of our country in a referendum on Scottish independence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will make a fundamental choice between remaining a key part of the United Kingdom, or leaving it and going alone into the world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the most important collective decision people in Scotland have ever been asked to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many questions to ask and answers to give on the impact of such a permanent and irreversible step. 
This isn’t a decision that will just affect our day-to-day lives within Scotland and the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a decision that will affect our relationships with people and countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You won’t be surprised to hear that I’m very clear on my view: Scotland is better off within our United Kingdom, and the United Kingdom is very much better off with Scotland part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am going to set out why that is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show how Scotland has flourished and achieved within and because of the United Kingdom - not in spite of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How Scotland can continue to contribute to and benefit from our United Kingdom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why that contribution is important to us all: not just in Scotland and the rest of the UK, but overseas too - here in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that by standing together we can continue to achieve, as Scots within the United Kingdom and with our friends and partners across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let’s think about how we got here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the long story - and the short story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the short story: 2011 was a big year in Scottish politics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish National Party’s outright win in the May 2011 election to the devolved Scottish Parliament in Edinburgh means that Scotland has its first single-party majority government since the devolved Parliament was established in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is significant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; entered that election campaign with a manifesto pledge to hold an independence referendum and succeeded in electing more than enough Members of the Scottish Parliament to set the legislative agenda in Holyrood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what it didn’t have was the legal power to hold that referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the settlement which established the Parliament in 1999, the responsibility and power over all aspects of the constitution was retained at Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why nearly 12 months ago now - the UK government took the first step to ensuring that rather than just talking about a referendum, there could actually be one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Scottish Parliament to have acted alone - would have been to act outside the law.  And as any government knows: the rule of law is a fundamental first principle of government; abandon that at your peril.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the UK government worked with the Scottish government to agree a framework to ensure that we can have a legal, fair and decisive referendum in Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A framework that allows the decision on Scotland’s future to be taken by people in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many hours of discussions and deliberations on 15 October the Prime Minister, David Cameron and I signed an agreement with Alex Salmond, the First Minister for Scotland and the Deputy First Minister Nicola Sturgeon to take the necessary legislative steps in both the UK Parliament and the Scottish Parliament to pave the way for the referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That agreement is about the referendum process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about making sure that the referendum is above legal challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That it is held in a way that is fair - and seen to be fair by both sides of this passionate debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that by sticking with the procedures set out in our agreement the referendum produces a decisive result that allows everyone in Scotland to feel a conclusion has been reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliamentary process is underway to ensure that the Scottish Parliament has the legal power to introduce a Referendum Bill, and we expect that legislation to be introduced early in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching an agreement on the process was a big moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now we are entering a new phase of this debate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One where we move from process to substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should Scots do? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaffirm their commitment to the most successful family of nations the world has known or leave it forever?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is where the long-story comes in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For while the 2011 elections to the Scottish Parliament brought the independence question to the fore, the debate about Scotland’s place in the UK  has been going for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Liberal Democrats like me, the debate is about greater ‘home rule’, as we style it - essentially the notion that decisions about how we lead our lives should be taken as close to the peopled affected as possible - a position that the Liberal Party first adopted back in Gladstone’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the modern Labour party, there have been supporters of devolution for most of the past century, and a firm commitment to it in the past quarter century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for Conservatives the support for devolution has been more recent still, but the latest tax-raising powers passed to the Scottish Parliament were part of a shared coalition commitment delivered by me and my colleagues earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These parties disagree on a lot but, today, we are united in our support for a devolved and effective Scottish Parliament embedded in a strong secure United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the outlook of the Scottish Nationalists is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their very raison d’etre for the past 70 odd years of the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s existence has been to create an independent Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sets them apart and constitutes the fundamental fault line in the constitutional debate as it stands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s been a lively debate for some time.  Or as we might say in Scotland, a good rammy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The referendum is making all of us consider things from first principles, as we should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Salmond has said that for him, the key driver of his support for independence is not the economy, but Scotland’s sense of itself as a nation.  That nations always do better when they are independent countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not share this view - and I don’t think that the majority of Scots share this view either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom does not oppress Scots: on the contrary, it is a partnership of nations in which each has to contributed to the whole and benefited from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom does not stop us celebrating our sense of Scottish identity, be that about place, people or traditions: it embraces it, alongside traditions from other parts of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that emotion plays no part in this debate.  Of course it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own story is a case in point - I am a proud Scot, but like many of my fellow countryman, mine is a family with a very British story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents are from Northern Ireland and that is where I was born.
But I moved to Scotland early in life and my younger sisters were born and raised there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife was born in England, but we now live happily in Scotland with our daughter who is being raised to be proud of her Scottish and British heritage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want my daughter to have to choose.  I don’t need a legal frontier to establish my identify, and nor does my daughter: we are Scottish and British and we are proud of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made - and will continue to make - the emotional case for my country¿s place within the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must consider evidence and reason alongside emotions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Scots are already saying loudly and clearly that they want the decision they take to be fully informed, as it should be.      &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a debate about what is best for Scotland, now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is something with which I am wholly comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the facts are many and clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the case for the United Kingdom is real and robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why Scotland should remain in UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 300 years Scots have achieved so much from within the UK family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this there is an embarrassment of riches spanning global commerce, scientific invention and military endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let us illustrate Scots’ achievements here today by looking at one specific area of particular relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a brief tour of the historical links between Scotland and the United States demonstrates the contribution that Scots have made to American life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a visit 15 years ago to New York’s Ellis Island, my eyes were first opened to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the excellent museum there was a large map of the United States.  Push a button and you could see where you could find descendants from your home country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I pushed the Irish button - hundreds of lights lit up across the map: with large concentrations in New York, Boston and Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pushed the Scottish button, and the Irish were put in the shade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly 30 million American citizens - according to the 2010 US Community Census - can claim roots in Scotland, the vast majority making that journey since the creation of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From New York to Virginia to Tennessee, Scots came to America, shaped America, built America, so often with the Presbyterian ethic of self-reliance and hard work that still forms a core part of the American story today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if America is the land of rugged individualism, look at what individuals of Scots ancestry have achieved collectively over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly half of the signatories of the Declaration of Independence could claim Scottish ancestry: the role call of surnames bares testimony to that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, some of the greatest presidents, with the most impressive legacies have been from Scottish stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jefferson and the Declaration of Independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilson and liberal internationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johnson and the Great Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, a leader of a different sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late Neil Armstrong had his family origins in Langholm, a town in the Borders of Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just three years after his moon mission, Armstrong visited Scotland to receive the freedom of the Burgh of Langholm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This link between Scots and the United States is one that has continued. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of Scots past, present and future in the United States is recognised on 6th April every year in parades and events held right across the States to celebrate the Annual Tartan Day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These international events help us to celebrate our national identity - and as a Scot that is something I am fiercely proud of. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud because when I come here to talk to you today, I know I can do so not just on the basis of what Scots have achieved in the past, but also what they are achieving in the here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as part of the UK, Scots are still doing great things in and with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst I’m here in the States I will be visiting Scottish companies who have established a presence here, including Optos, originally based in Dunfermline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optos is a leading provider of devices and solutions to eye care professionals and demonstrates the strength of high-tec Scottish companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their devices can produce high resolution digital images of approximately 82% of the retina, something no other device is capable of doing in any one image allowing significant steps forward in the diagnosis and management of eye disease.   The majority of the 4,400 devices that Optos has worldwide have been installed in North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already visited this morning one of the many US companies with a base in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honeywell is a US owned technology and manufacturing company that has a strong footprint in Scotland. Honeywell’s Newhouse Campus in Scotland was established in the 1950s and employs up to  800 of the 7000 staff that Honeywell employs in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course other, better known, trade links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first half of 2012 Scotland exported £1.5 billion worth of goods to the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these, our top export remains Scotch Whisky which accounted for about a third of all Scottish exports to the US in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality textiles too are a major and growing export market with Scottish cashmere top of the list and - if I may point out - heavily centred on my own Borders constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these very Scottish success stories are amplified by a very British support system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s not just Scotland that has forged close trade links; it is all of the UK’s constituent parts that, together, are reaching new heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK and the US are one another’s single largest foreign investors: we have almost one trillion dollars invested in each other’s economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over one million people in the United States go to work each day for British companies based here in the States and likewise over a million people in the UK go to work for US companies based in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we provide each other with vital export markets: the US is the largest single destination for UK exports and the UK attracts over 25% of all US investment in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what sustains this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Optos rely on the strong embassy networks that the United Kingdom has, with over 14,000 people in nearly 270 diplomatic offices, enabling real reach and influence around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They benefit from the 150 offices that UK Trade and Investments have around the world, covering 98% of global GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of support system - this access to expertise - is open to Scotland because, in partnership, the UK family has had the size, strength and skill to build it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with these UK networks Scottish companies like Optos, defence companies and those in the oil and gas industry are able to engage in markets around the world.  In turn US companies have confidence investing in Scotland as part of the United Kingdom and as a member of the EU. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would be lost if Scotland left UK?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this debate it is not just about setting out and reflecting on the things we have achieved as Scots within the UK ¿ important though that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also think about the ‘what if’s?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be no doubt that leaving the United Kingdom would reduce Scotland’s horizons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is a partnership, it is not a single entity: it is made up of four parts all of which bring their diversity, traditions and skills together to create something bigger than the sum total of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set out some of strengths of Scotland’s international exports, but what we must also acknowledge is that around two-thirds of Scottish exports are to the rest of the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland’s 5 million citizens are currently part of an economy of 60 million people with no boundaries, borders or rules dividing them, but with a common currency and set of regulations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provides enormous opportunities for both business and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a powerful argument for all including American businesses based there, with access to all of the UK, be it the defence budget or the rest of the UK’s 60 million consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot we gain and so there is a lot at stake for us - it would take some impressive arguments to persuade Scottish businesses to let go of the network of support that the UK provides around the world, including here.  And vice versa I believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the United Kingdom would turn Scotland into a separate state from the rest of the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the impact on our domestic trade would be real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act of Union removed the border between Scotland and England more than three hundred years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, it made possible a single domestic market in which the United Kingdom’s family of nations have traded fully and freely with one another, and shared influence and success across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today that domestic market is as integrated and seamless as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has one set of domestic financial regulations, a single regulator, and a pensions and insurance sector that covers all of our nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within our borders there are no discriminatory economic policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And together the United Kingdom remains, despite all the challenges and obstacles, the seventh largest economy in the world ¿ and the third largest in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s membership of the European Union has broken down trade barriers, lifted trade tariffs, and opened up new markets for my country and for every country that has joined it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a large and influential member, the UK’s priorities - Scotland’s priorities - help shape the EU position when it comes to WTO negotiations and bilateral trade deals around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, Scotland’s economic prospects, within the UK family, benefit from a triple guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An integrated domestic market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expanding European market, despite its own economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a liberalising global market where the pace will only quicken and key players will determine the direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matters to people in Scotland, in precisely the same way as it matters to people in England, Wales and Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want our businesses to prosper, our jobs market to strengthen, our family finances to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our integrated economies require the same conditions to make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, by shared endeavour, our triple guarantee is the way to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that guarantee is not a single transferable good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an inherent benefit to being part of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And leaving the United Kingdom would put all of it at risk - for Scotland certainly, but for the rest of the UK too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a separate state - no matter how well it gets on with its closes neighbour - creates new barriers either immediately or over time, and divides single domestic markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes that comes about through gradual economic divergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes through diverging regulator regimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And sometimes through the different political and economic decisions made by separate states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is wholly natural for individual countries to adopt different regulatory regimes, to establish different insurance frameworks, and to set different interest rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are good domestic reasons to do this, but the plain fact is that these movements spell the end of integrated economies and the strength, resilience and ease of trade that comes with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take one recent example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the dissolution of Czechoslovakia in 1992 a customs union was created between the new Czech Republic and Slovakia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the creation of this customs union - just 10 years after dissolution total Czech Republic exports to Slovakia had fallen from 22% to 8% and the 42% of Slovakian exports that went to the Czech Republic had fallen to 13%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not a blip - these reduced levels remain even now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Scotland’s principle trading partners are the other nations of the United Kingdom; independence would erode the foundations on which that relationship is built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also dilute Scotland’s influence in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on legal and academic opinion, the most likely outcome in the event of Scotland leaving the UK is that the remaining UK would continue as an EU member state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, the remaining UK would be a smaller entity, shedding influence, but it would remain a comparatively large, wealthy and powerful player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland, as a new state, would be required to seek membership, on negotiated terms, with the unanimous approval of every other EU member state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means a smaller state, negotiating for influence, from a position of weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting aside the political challenge of persuading every government that Scotland, in principle, should join the club, agreeing new terms of membership would put Scotland’s economic interests - indeed Scotland’s broader interests - at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would Scotland negotiate in good faith yet stay out of the euro when the commitment to join is a legal requirement for all new member states, given explicitly by every new member since 2005, and the plainly stated intent of Iceland and Croatia as part of their ongoing application process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would Scotland opt out of Schengen membership when, again, every new member is required to join and, if we did join, how could we then avoid the need to establish a land border between Scotland and England?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how would Scotland ensure not only good deals on agricultural funds, structural funds and fisheries quota - but how would it influence the future management of these plus the regulation of Scotland’s oil, gas and financial sectors, and the EU’s priorities on trade both at the WTO and elsewhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who want Scotland to leave the UK family tell us that all of this is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But assertion is no substitute for fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is possible for a country of 5 million people to leave a country of 63 million, and seek membership of the EU on improved terms, maintaining them despite reduced clout in the European Council and reduced overall representation in the European Parliament, then we should be told how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to these questions, there have been no answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Scotland that downsizes its influence on the European platform, also downsizes its influence on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now, the United Kingdom sits at the top tables of the EU, the G20 - the G7, where the big economic decisions are taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And under the last government, the Prime Minister and Finance Minister who sat there were both Scots, and proud of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Scotland, and all of the United Kingdom, are to retain tomorrow the influence we have today on the economic direction of the world, we must stay together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Scots understand that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the usual way for nation states to shed influence voluntarily over their own destiny or reduce their influence on the international front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would be the counter-intuitive impact for Scotland in leaving the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do not believe that it is the road that Scotland will take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Scottish people are asked to vote on their future, there are many issues on which they will reflect for which I believe that they will vote to remain part of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the strength of our economy will be of vital importance to their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of our domestic market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our influence within the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our role on the global stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these is crucial to the kind of economy we want to shape and through which we can prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, they comprise the triple guarantee on the economic future for Scotland and our UK partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By standing together, the nations of the United Kingdom can exert greater influence and achieve more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I believe that Scots will vote positively to remain in the UK family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But independence wouldn’t only have an impact on trade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would also be major implications for defence and foreign policy - for Scotland, the remaining UK, and our friends and allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Special Relationship’ between the US and the UK is often mentioned with pride on both sides - and this genuine, deep friendship is truly valuable. As President Obama said in September this year, the UK is the US’ closest ally.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our shared history and priorities have seen the UK be the partner of choice for the US since World War Two leading to unparalleled military cooperation in defence of our shared global interests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the Cold War to the conflict in Afghanistan our countries and our armed forces have stood shoulder to shoulder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron said in July 2010, our mutual sacrifice in Afghanistan offers no clearer, more tangible illustration of Britain and America standing together with a shared national interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together the UK and US have worked as close allies to take tough decisions and support people across the world through key organisations including the G8, the UN and NATO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a key member of that military alliance the UK is one of the largest contributors, and reinforcing our close cooperation with the United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw this at first hand as a member of the UK’s delegation to the NATO Parliamentary Assembly between 2007 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an uncertain world, we both take our global responsibilities seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using our influence and shared values to act in concert on a whole host of strategic global issues including, for example, our cooperation in the Middle East - on Syria, Libya and Iran - which is second to none. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, our commitment to internationalism, combined with our close alliance with the US enables the UK to make a significant influence on the world stage, that extends far beyond what might be expected given our geographic size. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The motives for our action vary - for either or both domestic and international security as in the case of Afghanistan, or for the prevention of violence and promotion of human rights as in the case of Kosovo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings with it an enormous moral responsibility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do what is right by ourselves and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, mistakes are made, but for our democracies to play a central role in the twenty-first century world order is, in my view, both a duty and a privilege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my own point of view as a Scot, I believe that one United Kingdom can fulfil that role more fully and effectively by remaining as one country, working in concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some on my side of the constitutional argument who think of Scotland’s military role in terms of improved job prospects for Scottish personnel or who think primarily of the security gains for Scotland that come from being part of a large and militarily capable country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these arguments are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for me there is a bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, as Scots, we believe not just in our own security but also in the promotion of peace, democracy and human rights for others, then Scotland’s role is maximised by our place in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s capacity strengthened by the personnel and geographical facilities that Scotland contributes to our overall defence capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the United States and the broader international community has a more coherent and capable partner than it would if our country separated into its constituent parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true for other international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already touched on the value for Scotland of being part of a big EU member state that holds real influence on the range of policy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week, for example, I visited Brussels where, as a UK cabinet minister, I was able to make the case for the oil and gas industry - one of Scotland’s biggest industries ¿ right at the heart of Europe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our position within the EU combined with our special relationship with the US puts us in a unique position to help support and strengthen links between the US and the EU - to provide, as has been said before, a bridge between America and Europe, that serves all parties well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently supporting the EU-US High Level Working Group process, looking at all options to more fully integrate EU-US trade, including the establishment of a comprehensive free trade agreement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will benefit all within the EU and the US - including Scotland - but a downsizing UK within an ever-expanding EU would find that productive position harder to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is not the time to divide among ourselves and fall short of our greater potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a turbulent but inter-connected world, now is the time to stand tall, stand together, and play a role of which we can be proud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trade, defence and security, foreign affairs: the arguments that those of us who support Scotland remaining part of the United Kingdom can make - and do make - are many and varied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are winning the argument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent opinion polls show that support for independence continues to hover at around one in three; sometimes a little higher, sometimes a little lower - but always in line with historical trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amongst businesses the views are even clearer, a survey published just last week shows that almost three-quarters of all corporate decision makers in Scotland believe that independence would be bad for Scotland’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those of us who support a strong Scotland within the UK are not complacent. 
We will keep making the case and setting out the facts on behalf of our parties, our government and people in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a debate that we are determined to win, to settle once and for all Scotland’s place within the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just an issue for government, Better Together, a cross-party campaign has been established in Scotland under the leadership of former Labour Chancellor Alistair Darling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campaign allows those from all parties and none to come together to make the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland’s place within the United Kingdom is an argument of both the heart and the head. I’ve set out  my perspective on both sides of this debate here for you today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I leave you with a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is to be gained from breaking up our partnership and bailing out after 300 years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What needs could be better served by the reduction of the United Kingdom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To these questions, I am yet to hear any adequate answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We Scots have achieved so much within the United Kingdom - not in spite of it - but because of it. And there is so much more that we can continue to achieve together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can seize this future together, because we are not as divided as our politics suggests. We’re not as cynical as the pundits believe. We are greater than the sum of our individual ambitions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the concluding words of President Obama’s acceptance speech after the US elections last month. I hope you don’t mind me borrowing them..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They define what the United States of America is - but they could just as easily define the United Kingdom family in the context of the independence debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our United Kingdom - and I am confident that when Scots have their say in referendum in 2014 they will seize a future together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56836</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T11:55:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/scotland-s-future-a-family-affair--2"/>
    <title>Scotland’s future: a family affair</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore, Secretary of State for Scotland, discusses how family life will influence peoples' votes in the Scottish independence referendum.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the London base of the Scotland Office, and, before the creation of the Scottish Parliament, the Scottish Office. In a dimly lit corridor downstairs hang the portraits of my predecessors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlighting that this has been the political home of Scots in London for generations. Not only for ministers from the UK government and our Scottish government colleagues, who have rooms downstairs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…but also for countless Parliamentarians, Scottish journalists, business leaders and others who have graced the many events in these magnificent surroundings over the past century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this day it remains a ‘network hub’ for Scots in London, somewhere that we can promote all that is best about Scotland and tackle the Scottish dimensions of the major issues of the day. But for all that, it may be regarded as a slightly curious place to host a speech on Scotland, some 300 or so miles from the epicentre of the ‘great debate’ that is shaping our future as a nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as someone who is extraordinarily proud to be Scottish, it is not such a stretch. As I will hope to establish over the next 20 minutes or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-choice-before-us"&gt;The choice before us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2 years time, when Scots are faced with the choice about whether to leave the UK family or to remain within it, we want to make the decision in light of all the available facts. It is the most important collective decision people in Scotland have ever been asked to take. There are many questions to ask and answers to give on the potential impact of such a radical and irreversible move. So we’ll want to get the arguments sorted. People will want to know where Scotland would fit in a fast-moving, globalised world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What level of defence and security we would build for ourselves and use to the benefit of others. And what the economic impact would be - both the costs and the opportunities - for Scottish business, and Scotland’s families, in setting up a new and separate state. These issues - and many more - will be debated in the months and years ahead. Indeed, this ‘great debate’ is already under way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nationhood-and-statehood"&gt;Nationhood and statehood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the First Minister said something interesting back in July about the nature of the decision that we as Scots will take about our future in 2014. He said that, for him, the key driver of his support for independence was not the economy, but rather about Scotland’s sense of itself as a nation, and that nations always do better when they are independent countries. I am not convinced that the majority of Scots share this view. For many Scots - most Scots - I don’t think that their primary consideration for the future is a sense of nationhood unfulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people I speak to are more preoccupied with the daily concerns that confront individuals, families and communities throughout Scotland and, indeed, all of the UK:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is my kid’s job safe and my standard of living secure, at a time of financial turbulence? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the country generating the cash we need to pay for our schools, hospitals and roads? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are my monthly bills going to keep rising, and is my rent or mortgage affordable? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are certainly the issues that concern the people I meet and talk to and keep the UK government focussed in its day to day work. And I believe that for people throughout Scotland, these, and other aspects of the quality of their life, will be of central importance when they decide how to vote in the independence referendum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;will my family, my community, be safer, stronger, more prosperous within the United Kingdom family or outwith it? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;My own view is clear - to coin a phrase, we are better together, staying within the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the First Minister’s comments back in the summer did identify something fundamental to the thinking of those who advocate independence. For them, there is a point of principle that as a nation, separate statehood is, per se, a necessity for Scotland to reach its potential. This evening, I would like to look more closely at that claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acknowledging, as the pro-UK side of this debate must, that identity plays an important part in our argument; that this debate is a matter of the heart as well as of the head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And being clear that the emotional aspect cuts both ways and is not the reserve of nationalists alone. I want to explore this in very personal terms - not simply as a Scottish politician, privileged to be at the centre of the constitutional debate. But as a Scot with my own sense of national identity and how that shapes the Scotland where I want to live and live with my family. So this evening I will talk about what nationhood and national identity means to me. And how that informs my choice about Scotland’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-scottish-nation---who-we-are"&gt;The Scottish nation - who we are&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who are the Scots… and what is this nation of ours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question - examined by so many learned thinkers and academics down the years - is pretty tough. For some people, our nation’s identity is shaped by our land. From the standing stones in the Northern Isles, past the grandeur of our cities’ Georgian and Victorian terraces to the uplands of southern Scotland - the ‘debateable lands’, where once the writ of kings, whether in Edinburgh or London, barely ran. For others it is about our national experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Declaration of Arbroath, the Reformation, the Clearances. Stirling Bridge, Bannockburn, Flodden and Culloden. And for many more it is about the rich variety of our cultural life. The languages we use - Gaelic, Scots, English. The pipe bands and silver bands, the clarsach and fiddle, the poetry and the prose. The sporting triumphs, and more recent defeats, of our national sides at rugby, football and so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All manner of things - geography, history, politics, religion, philosophy, values, scientific invention, art, literature, music, sport and so much more - all of these meld to give us an individual and a collective sense of what it means to be a Scot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all fascinated by this sense of nation - we take it apart, explain it, rationalise it. We have the odd argument along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of Scottish life is that the ties that bind us are strong and enduring. We have a clear sense of self, of identity, and of nation. But we don’t need to be, or stay, north of the border to feel it. Or require newcomers to share every last aspect of it. To be Scottish is a fact of your life or, just as validly, a very personal choice - Scottishness is inclusive, not exclusive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many ‘new Scots’, like the former asylum seekers, who played football in a forest clearing near Selkirk, as part of this summer’s ‘Cultural Olympiad’, would attest. As would the young kids and local families, who cheered them on, some of whom might trace their family history all the way back to the Borders raiding families of the middle ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Scots one and all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="national-identity-and-independence"&gt;National identity and independence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leads me to ask, in the context of nationhood, what extra purpose independence would serve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After more than 300 hundred years within the United Kingdom, our Scottish identity has not withered. On the contrary, it has flourished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the UK family our institutions have remained - Scottish education, the Scottish legal system, the Church of Scotland. Our culture has thrived - with the advance of Scottish folk music and contributions to every musical genre, old and new. An artistic tradition that has taken in Raeburn, the Glasgow Boys and Bellany, one of whose works is on the wall behind me to the left. And a fine Scottish literary tradition spanning Burns, Scott and Grassic Gibbon through to Gray, Kelman, and of course, J K Rowling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our social and political values remain resonant in a partnership of nations. Where the Claim of Right was received with acclaim. Where the Scottish Parliament was demanded and re-established. And where the devolution settlement continues to strengthen and evolve so that the domestic issues that impact on Scots lives can be settled closer to the people. This is hardly a nation oppressed or held back. This is a nation whose identity thrives and whose sovereignty of the people has been reinforced by its 2 governments working together to make sure the referendum on independence takes place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days opponents of independence decried Scotland’s place in the world - the country was ‘too wee, too poor, too far away’. That is not the approach of this government: we are making the positive case for our partnership of nations. But there should be a symmetry here on the other side of the argument. In the old days, we could only rise and be a nation again through independence.  That, too, is an obsolete argument. And insulting to many, who are proudly Scottish. Or comfortable living in Scotland, while proud of feeling some other national identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need for anyone to feel insecure about Scotland’s identity, place or position. We don’t need Scotland to become a separate state to prove things either to ourselves or to others. But I believe that, if we did choose that path, something - something important - would be lost forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-british-nation---who-we-are"&gt;The British nation - who we are&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us north of the border say that we are Scottish first and British second. And that makes complete sense. Most people in England, Wales and Northern Ireland have their own versions of this layered, multi-dimensional identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But British identity does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;300 hundred years of history shouldn’t be worn lightly, then discarded casually. Not when so much has happened down the centuries to bind us together. Most Scots wear their British identity with comfort and ease. And it is a very good fit. We can take an historical tour to remind ourselves: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the growth of empire, which allowed generations of Scots to found businesses, forge trading links and finance the growth of Scotland’s cities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the armed forces, where, under the Union Flag and other colours, flags and pennants, Scots played their role in 2 world wars, countless other campaigns, and interventions to protect civilians from Kosovo to Afghanistan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the global platform, on which Scots have stood - as British prime ministers, chancellors, or leaders of international organisations; or as financiers, exporters, scientists and explorers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But I don’t want simply to play you ‘Britain’s Greatest Hits -  the Scottish remix’.  I want us to recognise that our identity within Britain remains strong to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-we-flourish"&gt;How we flourish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no physical border separating Scotland from the rest of the UK. There are hard-to-miss signs on the trunk roads. More subtle changes of road surface on the others. Nature plays its part - and there is no more majestic entrance to Scotland than at the Carter Bar, 10 miles south of Jedburgh. While the River Tweed does its job to mark the boundary for the last few miles on the run in to Berwick. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the dotted line on the map which separates Scotland from England is, for the most part, a conceptual rather than a real dividing line. When Hadrian ordered the creation of a physical dividing line, he didn’t just lock out the Scots, but the northern English, too. Nobody else has ever been quite as bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when it comes to the economy, cultural and social life of this country, I believe that, far from borders being built up, any remaining divisions are eroding over time. In Scotland today we export twice as many goods and services to the rest of the UK as we do to the rest of the world combined. Nearly three quarters of Scottish imports come from the rest of the UK. And companies owned elsewhere in the UK employ a fifth of all Scottish workers and contribute to about a quarter of total business turnover in Scotland. In terms of everyday cultural experience, we share so much in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the BBC we have a cherished national institution, however challenged it has been recently, with BBC Scotland and BBC Alba catering for our national and more local interests across Scotland. We have fantastic universities in Scotland, born out by 22,000 English students who choose to study at them. And Scotland had more than its Barnett share of medallists at this summer’s London 2012 Olympic Games. An occasion on which all parts of our United Kingdom jumped to their feet to cheer on Team GB. And we’ll enjoy the sporting sequel at the Commonwealth Games in Glasgow in 2014, even if our loyalties will be more divided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="family-ties"&gt;Family ties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its in the family sphere that British identity is written into our DNA. The UK is a huge family: we’ve gone from 1707 when just 3% of the Scottish population had English relatives to around 50% today. And we are a nation on the move. More than 450,000 people living in Scotland today were born in England, Wales or Northern Ireland. And more than 830,000 born in Scotland now live in other parts of the UK. And in 2011 there were nearly 7 million trips made to Scotland from the rest of the UK, compared with about 2.5 million made from overseas, reinforcing the close bonds of business, friendship and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own story is a case in point - I am a proud Scot whose family is a very British story. My parents are from Northern Ireland. I was born there but my family moved to Inverness when I was just a toddler and I have lived in Scotland ever since. My 2 younger sisters were born and raised in Scotland but now live in England. My wife was born and brought up in England but now lives happily in Scotland. My young daughter is being raised to be proud of her Scottish identity and also proud of her British heritage. I believe that this is the reality for most families and I also firmly believe that most people in Scotland are secure in our own identity and nationhood without having to leave the United Kingdom to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel I have anything to prove - and I don’t think anyone else in Scotland should either. Millions of us who consider ourselves Scots don’t need a legal frontier to establish our identity. We don’t need to leave the United Kingdom, which we help to shape, to be Scottish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are Scottish, and British, and we are proud of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And happy to enter the debate on independence on that basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56838</id>
    <published>2012-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T14:23:29+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/scottish-council-for-development-and-industry-international-awards-dinner"/>
    <title>Scottish Council for Development and Industry International Awards Dinner</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore, Secretary of State for Scotland talks to the SCDI awards dinner, celebrating their international success.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tonight is all about celebrating international success.  And who better to talk to us than Dr Madeleine Albright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The award, this year, of the Presidential Medal of Freedom, was yet another accolade to add to the many given over many years in recognition of Dr Albright’s contribution to international relations. A distinguished US ambassador to the UN, Dr Albright was later unanimously confirmed by the Senate as the first female Secretary of State in 1997, becaming the highest-ranking woman in US government history. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madeleine  - you are quoted as saying that ‘in order to be a successful negotiator you have to be able to put yourself into the other person’s shoes. Unless you can understand what is motivating them, you are never going to be able to figure out how to solve a particular problem.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During your 4-year tenure as Secretary of State you proved your ability to do this time and time again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcing US alliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promoting US trade, business and environmental standards abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But above all championing democracy and human rights across the world: most notably in Kosovo and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have said, that ‘for somebody who loves foreign policy, being Secretary is the best job in the world’, but your work didn’t stop with the end of your tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You continue to provide advice, expertise and insight. And we look forward to hearing from you today on the challenges and opportunities that you see lying ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were of course all glued to the events in the US earlier this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a firm Obama supporter, I have no doubt that this has been a nerve-wrecking but rewarding week, as you watched the results come in while here in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you will excuse us, however, if tonight here in Glasgow we focus on celebrating success a little closer to home and where better to do that than here in the Velodrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The superb Commonwealth Arena will host the Commonwealth Games in 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Olympics just a few short months ago showed the world what the United Kingdom can achieve both on and off the track. Our foremost cyclist, Sir Chris Hoy, along with countless others, made us all proud in the Summer. We are all determined that the Games here in Glasgow in 2014 will be just as successful and raise awareness of what Scotland has to offer around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising awareness of Scotland’s capabilities is just one of the reasons why working with organisations like Scottish Council for Development and Industry (&lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;) is essential - not just for government - but any company with an interest in international business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to pay tribute to the work that Robert Armour, Lesley Sawers and their colleagues do day-in, day-out to help build Scotland’s international trade and business links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt; established back in 1931 was a very different organisation to the one that we see before us today. But what has remained constant is &lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s purpose: to strengthen Scotland’s economic competitiveness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert, Lesley, you are both fantastic champions of this organisation and Scottish business. The UK government regards your work as vital, helping our companies develop the strength they need to compete globally:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I experienced &lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s expertise first hand when I led Scotland’s biggest trade mission to Brazil. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to see UK exports to Brazil double by 2015.  The trade mission allowed Scottish companies to showcase their services and establish links in this key high-growth market.  I applaud your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s work on the international stage has been hugely significant for Scottish companies down the generations and under your auspices tonight we rightly recognise the international achievements of Scottish companies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone here understands how tough the economic conditions are across the world. So, that makes the success we celebrate tonight even more impressive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a time of real international uncertainty and instability and the United Kingdom is not immune to what is going on in its biggest export markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ongoing difficulties in the Eurozone, and the wider global economy, present challenges as we attempt to rebalance our economy and our public finances, and build a better future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcome last month’s UK GDP (Gross Domestic Product) figures showing a return to growth in the third quarter of this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But weak global confidence and nervous financial markets mean that we cannot be complacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why the UK government, has made it a priority to set out an unequivocal message to our international partners:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Britain is open for business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open to innovators and entrepreneurs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open to investment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Boosting export levels for both goods and services is one part of the picture - and that’s why, in the UK, we are aiming to increase our exports to £1 trillion annually by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an ambitious target and I intend Scotland to play its full part in reaching it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[That is one of the reasons I have asked Brian Wilson, the former Trade Minister, to conduct a review of Scottish exporting as part of the work of the Scottish Business Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian is bringing his many years of business expertise to bear on considering what more we can do to ensure that Scottish businesses get the support they need to export their way to growth.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No other relationship demonstrates the power of international links than our special relationship with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts speak for themselves. Britain and the US are the largest investors in each other’s economies; enjoying the largest Foreign Direct Investment relationship in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK companies currently provide employment for around one million people in the US - roughly the same figure as American companies in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are some really encouraging examples of Scottish businesses soaring ahead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craneware, an Edinburgh healthcare technology company, now works with nearly one-quarter of US hospitals. The company has more than doubled its revenue in the US since 2005 and reported strong profits again last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weir Group, based in Glasgow, continues to expand into the US. In the past year the company has acquired two specialist oil and gas companies in Texas while posting a record order book and profits 30 per cent higher than the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not a one way relationship - there are plenty of examples of US firms investing here in Scotland, supporting not only our businesses but also investing in our future: &lt;abbr title="Scottish Council for Development and Industry"&gt;SCDI&lt;/abbr&gt;’s own Young Engineers Club active in more than 180 Scottish schools is sponsored by US Energy giant Chevron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010 alone, Scotland exported an estimated £3.5 billion of goods and services to the US, and we must continue to build on that success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe our relationship holds even greater potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scottish, UK and indeed EU wide-recovery will go hand-in-hand with that in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As free-trading, outward-looking, democratic nations our futures remain intertwined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the prospect next year of establishing a free trade agreement between the EU and the US that will build on the strong trade links that we already have between the UK and the US. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a commitment to innovation and entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we can create new jobs, business and prosperity for all our peoples. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I look forward to future award ceremonies where we will continue to recognise and reward Scotland’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that is for another day: tonight is about rewarding success in the here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been an historic week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw how the world’s most powerful nation made its democratic decision on how it wishes to be led and governed over the next four years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that time the USA and the world will face many challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way in which president Obama and his new team meet these challenges will affect us all&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in Madeleine Albright we are honoured to have someone with us who has been there before; someone who has faced those challenges, made those tough and, and at times lonely decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions that have in turn shaped our history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what her successors in the new American administration will now have to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why it is an honour to introduce her tonight for what will i am sure be a fascinating insight into the challenges the USA  and the world now face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Albright - As Secretary of State for Scotland it gives me great pleasure to welcome to Glasgow a former Secretary of State for the World and to invite you to speak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56839</id>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T14:40:54+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rural-islands-housing-association-forum-annual-conference"/>
    <title>Rural &amp; Islands Housing Association Forum: Annual Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore talks at the Annual Conference of the Rural &amp; Islands Housing Association Forum.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly delighted to be here today when you are celebrating your 25th anniversary. The association plays a vital role in making its members’ voice heard at local and national levels and I want to congratulate members past and present on your success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Borders I have built up close working relationships over many years with the Eildon, Scottish Borders, Berwickshire and Waverley Housing Associations. Their pro-active, constructive engagement with me and other parliamentarians is a model which I commend to you all. They don’t miss and hit the wall when there are difficult issues to discuss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, equally they provide me with useful, indeed invaluable, insights into policy issues beyond housing itself and I very much value the relationship. That ‘extra mile’ of engagement with elected representatives is something across party and across the country that we all appreciate - so thank you to everyone for the efforts you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that recently the Forum was successful in raising sufficient funding to enable research by the Joseph Rowntree Foundation to proceed later this year. The research which will look at a minimum income standard in Scotland’s rural areas and should provide solid empirical evidence for what we already know anecdotally - that living in a rural community is more costly than living in an urban community. I look forward to seeing the results, which I’m sure will be of interest to departments in both the UK and Scottish governments, mine included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland’s many and varied rural and island communities are vital to the life-blood of our nation. Yet they are not without their challenges. I understand those challenges. I live and breath the reality of life in rural communities in Scotland. I live in Galashiels and am proud to represent one of the largest rural constituencies in Scotland. One of the other largest rural constituencies in Scotland is represented by a certain Danny Alexander. So, I don’t think anyone could disagree when I say that the challenges of Scottish rural communities life are well understood at the heart of the UK government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have travelled tens of thousands of miles across Scotland in the past two-and-a-half years as Secretary of State, I have also valued the chance to visit housing projects in different parts of the country. Your association has witnessed enormous changes in Scotland in the last 25 years.  Devolution and the creation of the Scottish Parliament has transformed the policy-making environment in Scotland for your association and for every other part of civil Scotland. I have championed devolution all my life and I am proud to continue to champion Scottish devolution.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you look back today, it is only natural that you should also want to look forward to the next 25 years. The independence referendum will hardly have escaped your attentions. Di [Alexander] has told me that part of your discussion today will focus on the potential impact of independence on Scotland’s rural and island communities. I hope you will forgive me if I say that I do not intend to speculate on that issue today although I am happy to take questions at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that the people of Scotland will vote to retain Scotland’s place within the United Kingdom. In other words, I am confident they will vote for devolution rather than independence. In any case, it is the Scottish government which is seeking to change Scotland’s status within the UK. It is for them to set out what an independent Scotland might look like. So what I want to do today is to focus on issues closer to home. I want to focus on what the UK government is doing to address the challenges of rural and island communities in Scotland and to address the challenges which so many of you and your tenants face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move into shorter days and the winter weather, there are fewer greater challenges than rising energy costs. The recent announcements from some of the major energy suppliers are disappointing news for customers. I understand all too well that rising energy prices are hitting many households hard at a difficult time. But let me highlight a number of positive steps which the government is taking and which all of us can take too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, the easiest ways to keep energy bills down are to get people paying the lowest possible tariffs and to reduce the amount of wasted energy, by taking advantage of offers available on free or discounted home insulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would urge all consumers to shop around and check their energy deal. When they find a better deal, vote with their feet and take their business elsewhere. That is why government is working with Ofgem to make sure that households have clear information on their bills about the supplier’s cheapest tariff and the savings they could make by switching. Ofgem will have new powers to force suppliers to compensate customers if they’ve lost out as a result of a company breaching a licence condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Collective purchasing and switching’ is another great way to beat rising energy costs. We have been pushing to make it easier for people to club together to get a better deal on their energy. I would urge you to consider this option for your tenants. The government has also launched a £5 million competition for the most innovative local authority or third sector schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I understand completely that there is only so much that can be done to reduce costs by way of switching. The government is also making sure that the most vulnerable households get direct financial help from their supplier. Over 1 million pensioners will get £130 off their fuel bills this winter as part of the Warm Home Discount scheme, with the wider scheme helping around 2 million households this year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And direct from the government, all pensioner households under 79 will get £200 Winter Fuel Payment this winter and those over 80 will get £300. Annual payments for pensioners worth up to £300 have already been paid out to an estimated 12.7 million older people in more than 9 million homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also highlight one initiative which I want to praise as a great example of a rural housing association working in partnership with other government agencies for the benefit of its members and its members’ fuel bills. Berwick Housing Association is building a three-turbine community wind farm at Hoprigshiels Farm, near Cockburnspath, in what will be the first wind farm developed by a Housing Association in the UK. Uniquely, all profits will go to community or charitable projects. The wind farm will power around 4000 households and provide income for both Berwick Housing Association and Community Energy Scotland, helping to build new homes and supporting local community projects. This is a project that I commend to you all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the difficult issue of energy prices, let me touch on some wider issues affecting the rural economy. Post Offices play a vital role in our rural and island communities. That’s why I am delighted that the coalition government took the decision not to repeat the closure programmes of the previous administration. This government is investing £1.34 billion to ensure that there are no more closure programmes, and that the network remains at around its current size of at least 11,500 branches across the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the wider issue of connectivity, everyone here today will be acutely aware of the importance to rural communities of reliable, fast broadband connections, whether for business or in the home. Out of a UK-wide programme totalling £513 million for the roll out of superfast broadband in rural areas, Scotland is due to receive £100.6 million. At the same time, UK-wide investment of £150 million will improve the coverage and quality of mobile voice services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to incomes, I know from my own constituency that it’s often the case that incomes in rural areas are lower than in urban areas. That’s why I’m particularly pleased that the Coalition government has progressively raised the personal tax allowance for low earners. The increases announced to date will benefit 2.1 million Scots, and take 162,000 low income individuals out of tax from April 2013, many of whom live in rural and island communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while it’s important to help low earners, it’s equally important to help people into employment in the first place, particularly our young people, many of whom will be tenants in your properties.  Tackling this issue takes a concerted effort across Scotland’s two governments and across all delivery agencies. Let me highlight, however, the government’s Youth Contract which for the next 3 years will bring vital support for unemployed young people, helping them to prepare for work and find jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Youth Contract provides additional work experience and sector-based work academy places. There is a place for every young person who wants one before they enter the Work Programme.  Extra help from Jobcentre Plus is also available as well as wage incentives of up to £2,275 each available to employers who recruit 18 to 24 year olds from the Work Programme for at least 26 weeks.  In the same way that I would take the opportunity to encourage businesses and employers across Scotland to consider apprenticeships or internships, I would urge you to consider whether your organisations could offer work experience opportunities to young people in your communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to welfare reform, I know that members from this forum, and more widely the Scottish Federation of Housing Associations, have voiced concerns about particular policies which will affect your services and the people who use them, such as the new under-occupancy rules for housing benefit, or the switch to direct monthly payments of housing costs to tenants as part of Universal Credit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise the challenges that we face collectively, and the range of opinions on these policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I welcome your engagement with us on these issues and I would encourage you to engage in the design and implementation of welfare reform in Scotland, either directly with the Department for Work and Pensions, or through other government channels via the Scottish government or Convention of Scottish Local Authorities (COSLA). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, my colleague David Mundell will be holding a Scotland Office-sponsored roundtable with housing associations early in the new year at which I hope many of you can be represented.  The government is committed to working with you to tailor the implementation of the reforms to Scottish needs wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let me return to one constitutional policy issue which I feel the Forum should be aware of. You will be aware of the passing of the Scotland Act 2012 earlier this year, the largest transfer of fiscal power from London to Edinburgh in 300 years. We must not lose sight of the significance of that legislation as our attention starts to focus on the referendum in two years’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to one particular provision within that Act, and that’s the devolution of stamp duty.  The Scottish government recently consulted on its proposals to introduce a replacement ‘Land and Buildings Transaction Tax’. This is a matter which will be of great importance to housing associations. If you have not already done so, I would encourage delegates here today to engage in the development of that legislation to make sure that your voice is heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to sum up, what I have said today illustrates some of the supports the UK government is providing to housing associations and their tenants in Scotland. I recognise that the ‘big debate’ on Scotland’s constitutional future will be at the front of everyone’s minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s not forget that we owe it to everyone to ensure daily business - in whichever sector we work - carries on as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Scotland faces up to that big debate, I am confident that the Forum will enjoy another 25 years of working and thriving within a strong devolved Scotland which is part of a strong United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56841</id>
    <published>2012-08-30T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T15:04:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/the-uk-right-for-business-right-for-scotland"/>
    <title>The UK: right for business, right for Scotland</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore talks about building a stronger, more vibrant, more sustainable Scottish economy in which all businesses can grow.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people in this room underline how diverse the Scottish &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; (small and medium enterprise) community is - and how important you are to the health of the Scottish economy. Your businesses make up 99% of enterprises in Scotland. You provide more than half of Scotland’s jobs. And you produce more than a third of turnover in the Scottish economy. Our economy - the jobs that provide families with a home and a future, the services that make our daily lives better -  all of that relies on your hard work and dedication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the message I want to convey today is that the UK government supports you in your efforts to thrive and to grow - we are on your side. I want to take the economic issues head on and then set out where we are on Scotland’s other great challenge - our constitutional future as part of the UK or separated from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of this Convention is ‘Real Challenges, Real Solutions’. Those challenges are clear, just as those solutions are essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the financial crisis in 2008 to the cardiac arrest in the banking system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the hangover following the UK’s largest ever peacetime deficit to a succession of external shocks, including commodity price spikes and the euro crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the uncertainty in the euro area is the biggest challenge to the recovery of the UK economy today. The EU is Scotland’s biggest international export market - £9.8 billion of all Scottish exports outside the UK go to the EU. Almost half our international exports. All of these factors have been damaging to the Scottish and wider UK economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody is denying the scale of the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the government will support you in finding real solutions to those challenges, creating the conditions that allow you and your businesses to thrive. Returning the UK to sustainable, balanced growth is at the heart of why we formed the Coalition - and it remains our overriding priority. So we keep listening to businesses, large and small, across Scotland and the wider UK. We are taking decisive action to support you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="access-to-finance"&gt;Access to finance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s not duck a big issue for most of you - access to finance. Most &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; I meet raise this: it’s a matter of financial life or death for some. I get that. The government understands it. And we are taking action. We are kick-starting bank lending through the new Funding for Lending scheme to enable banks to support businesses such as yours, and families aspiring to own their own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme, which has no upper limit, reduces the funding costs of banks and building societies, allowing them to make loans less costly and less scarce. No doubt Ken Barclay will tell you more about what the Royal Bank of Scotland (&lt;abbr title="Royal Bank of Scotland"&gt;RBS&lt;/abbr&gt;) is doing. I welcome Ken’s appointment as Chair of the &lt;abbr title="Royal Bank of Scotland"&gt;RBS&lt;/abbr&gt; Scotland Board, and I look forward to working with him to ensure that &lt;abbr title="Royal Bank of Scotland"&gt;RBS&lt;/abbr&gt; is supporting &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased that &lt;abbr title="Royal Bank of Scotland"&gt;RBS&lt;/abbr&gt;, thanks to the government’s scheme, will waive fees for every &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprise"&gt;SME&lt;/abbr&gt; given a loan and reduce borrowing costs by 1% on average, or 1.6% for smaller &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt;. That is welcome - and we should expect all the banks to support this key part of the market. And not just existing players, but new entrants, too: we want a more competitive lending market and our bank reforms will deliver that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t just want the cost and availability of loans to improve; we want better terms and conditions, too. Less unilateral re-writing of terms and conditions, more genuine negotiation. Less remoteness in decision making, more interaction with knowledgeable bank managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not too much to ask. Or expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past two years we have been removing the obstacles to lending. Now we’re using the government’s balance sheet to allow an unprecedented step change in making credit available.  And we are moving ahead with radical bank reform too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tax-system"&gt;Tax system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s not all about lending. You want a better deal on tax, too. So, we are putting in place a stable, competitive tax system, which provides greater rewards for your hard work, drives investment and encourages innovation. A fair tax system which rewards wealth creators, but punishes tax-dodgers and evaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as cutting corporation tax to the lowest rate in the G7, we have cut the small profits rate to 20%, and introduced tax simplification for small businesses. We have increased tax credits for research and development for &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to 200% in 2011, and 225% in 2012, as well as providing a new patent box that means companies can pay 10% corporation tax on profits from patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have announced the new Seed Enterprise Investment Scheme, which will offer tax reliefs to investors who purchase shares in small early-stage companies. And we have introduced the Regional Employer National Insurance Contributions Holiday, to help new businesses in Scotland with the costs of employing staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="regulation"&gt;Regulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my conversations with small businesses across Scotland, one of the things that almost always comes up is regulation. We are cutting red tape. We introduced a new one-in, one-out rule, so no new domestic regulation can be brought in without regulation of an equivalent value being removed. In April last year, we introduced a 3-year moratorium on new domestic regulation affecting micro businesses and start-ups. And under our Red Tape Challenge we have committed that 50% of over 1800 regulations will be scrapped or improved - saving businesses such as yours over £350m per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a key issue for UK competitiveness, and recently Lord Heseltine, who is reviewing the public sector’s impact on competitiveness, was in Edinburgh to listen to business leaders. He asked for examples of burdensome regulation and within 48 hours we had some substantial material sent to us - if you have more ideas, please let us know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-policy-and-the-green-economy"&gt;Industrial policy and the ‘green economy’&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More broadly, we are taking action to boost investment and rebalance the economy, creating opportunities for companies to start up and grow. We made money available to the Scottish government, allowing them to introduce 4 Enterprise Areas in Scotland - with 100% capital allowances for investment in Irvine, Nigg and Dundee, and the potential to deliver 4,000 new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are revolutionising the energy market and putting Scotland at the forefront of the green economy. Introducing the world’s first Green Investment Bank, headquartered in Edinburgh, to drive forward the UK low carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exports"&gt;Exports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To promote sustainable growth, exports will be hugely important - and we want to support you in your efforts to break into new markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment (&lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt;)’s new 5-year strategy sets out programmes to link &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; to trade finance, credit insurance and venture capital, as well as work to bring high value opportunities home - bringing major supply chain opportunities for &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; across a wide range of sectors. The UK government will spend £35 million to double, from 25,000 to 50,000, the number of &lt;abbr title="Small and medium enterprises"&gt;SMEs&lt;/abbr&gt; that &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt; supports. But we are on the look out for further ideas too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why I have asked Brian Wilson, the former Trade Minister, to bring his many years of business expertise to bear on a review of support for Scottish exporting. The review will report in autumn 2013, and will consider how to ensure that Scotland’s export performance improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="priorities"&gt;Priorities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are real solutions to the real challenges we face. But if there is more we should be doing, then tell us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I repeat - we are on your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scotlands-two-governments"&gt;Scotland’s two governments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing I should stress. You rightly demand and expect much from those of us who serve in government. For my part that means Scotland’s two governments working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in efforts to promote trade, where SDI works closely with &lt;abbr title="UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment"&gt;UKTI&lt;/abbr&gt; and its network of over 150 offices in 100 markets, covering 98% of world GDP (gross domestic product).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in our consistent focus on youth unemployment where Skills Development Scotland (SDS) and Jobcentre Plus work hand in hand. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in delivering broadband fit for purpose in the 21st century. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in making sure that part of the legacy of the Olympics is a business-friendly environment for the Glasgow Commonwealth Games. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am committed to ensuring that for you in business, politics does not get in the way of your two governments serving your needs. We will continue to do everything we can to ensure that businesses within Scotland, and the UK as whole, have a prosperous future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that context, I want to talk about the importance of Scotland’s place in the UK to your businesses. And let me concede straightaway that, on this one, Scotland’s two governments don’t see eye to eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="economic-benefits-of-scotland-in-the-uk"&gt;Economic benefits of Scotland in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, as part of the UK, Scotland has a trusted currency, record low interest rates and a competitive business environment. These are the things that will help us weather the economic storm in Europe, that will put our economy back on the road to recovery and that will generate the jobs we need. All of us in Scotland, individuals and businesses alike, are better off as part of the UK. Stronger together, weaker apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me highlight 3 key areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the single market. As part of the UK, Scotland has access to a hugely successful single market with no boundaries, borders or customs, but a common currency and a single set of regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, international influence. Scotland’s influence on the international stage as part of the UK is undoubtedly greater than it would be if it spoke alone. The UK is one of the ‘big 4’ member states in the EU and a member of the G7, G20 and IMF (International Monetary Fund). In today’s global economy these are the arenas in which decisions affecting your businesses are taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the pooling of risk. If the events of recent years have taught us one thing, it is that crises and shocks will happen, and we have to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the UK, we benefit from the size and diversity of the UK economy, providing security when global or local economic conditions require the UK government to provide support. This included injecting capital in excess of the entire Scottish government budget into &lt;abbr title="Royal Bank of Scotland"&gt;RBS&lt;/abbr&gt; and HBOS during the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56842</id>
    <published>2012-06-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T16:18:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/electronic-systems-in-energy"/>
    <title>Electronic Systems in Energy</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore, Scotland's Secretary of State, delivers a Keynote address at the NMI conference 'Electronic Systems in Energy'.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are entering a very exciting time for your industry and it is great to look around the room at those who serve with great distinction across your sector. Today’s event is very timely.  With the renewables revolution well underway, we are entering a truly exciting time for the industry here in Scotland. This presents huge opportunities for the electronics sector to capitalise on this growth and explore how you can underpin our country’s energy supply and demand challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the backdrop to our discussion is the critical state of the world economy. This is a time of real international uncertainty and instability. And the United Kingdom is not immune to what is going on its biggest export markets. But within this difficult context, there are still opportunities to be seized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="global-energy-challenges"&gt;Global energy challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why are renewables proving to be such a success story? Put simply, the time is right. Global energy challenges are huge. Declining domestic production has made us increasingly exposed to risks from rising global demand. The UK became a net importer of gas in 2004. And a net importer of oil in 2006. The costs of this dependency on fossil fuels are felt in homes right across the country. This winter families faced gas prices around 40% higher than last year. We also need to meet statutory targets on climate change. Reducing our greenhouse gas emissions by 34% by 2020 and 80% by 2050. And this is within the context of a potential doubling of electricity demand by 2050.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-government-vision"&gt;UK government vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we cannot overstate the importance of the energy revolution - secure, affordable &amp;amp; clean energy is absolutely vital to our future and the government is committed to meeting those goals. In July last year we set out our aims and underlying principles in our UK Renewable Energy Roadmap. A UK-wide document, explaining our shared approach to unlocking our country’s renewable energy potential, achieving our 2020 targets and driving down costs. And crucially, it places renewables firmly within the energy mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scotlands-strengths"&gt;Scotland’s strengths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with Scotland’s potential in renewables, the prize is great. You will be well aware that there is a lot of publicity associated with the successes of the renewables industry. And there are some truly remarkable success stories. For instance, last June, SSE’s Clyde wind farm started exporting electricity to the grid. Once fully completed it will be Europe’s largest onshore wind farm, with over 150 turbines generating 350 Mega Watts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January this year, Moray Offshore Renewables announced plans for a £4.5 billion offshore wind project. If consented this will be the world’s largest offshore wind farm. And in March we heard the good news that Gamesa plan to build a major turbine manufacturing facility in Leith. The project is worth around £125 million of initial investment creating an estimated 800 new jobs with significantly more in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attracting this kind of high tech, high value manufacturing to the UK is key to realising the maximum economic potential the sector can offer. And what isn’t often recognised so publicly are the wider benefits for the supply chain for industries like yours, producing the essential technology needed to support this activity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="link-to-electronics-supply-chain"&gt;Link to electronics supply chain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your companies are at the forefront of an emerging worldwide trend of seeking to capitalise on these opportunities. [The figures speak for themselves. Globally, low carbon goods and services are worth £3.2 trillion, and employ 28 million people. It is growing by 4% a year, faster than developed world GDP (gross domestic product), and will accelerate.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite difficult economic times, the sector in Scotland is showing incredible progress. Attracting significant investment and winning significant work. Between April last year and March this year, we have seen announcements totalling 1.7 billion pounds of investment  in renewable energy in Scotland, supporting more than 4,400 jobs. And there is a potential 8 billion pounds of investment in the pipeline to support over 3,300 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So renewables aren’t just a major part of our energy mix. They are now a major part of our economy and the daily working lives of so many people directly employed in the industry and in the wider supply chain. There are immediate linkages to the electronics sector. From advanced power electronic systems to affordable high performance devices and smart energy management principles - this technology is integral to the renewable energy systems of today and the future.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-government-economic-reforms"&gt;UK government economic reforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to see big names like Alstrom and Siemens today, looking to develop their supply chain here in Scotland. And the UK government is keen to do everything we can to encourage this sort of investment and help to develop the growth of the supply chain opportunities in this sector. So what practical steps are we taking to make this happen? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, we are focussing on the economy. The global economic difficulties have a huge impact on your sector, just as they do on every other industry up and down the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning the UK to sustainable, balanced economic growth is our overriding priority. The actions we have taken to reduce the deficit and rebuild the economy have secured stability and positioned the UK as a relative safe haven.  Interest rates are at near record lows, benefitting businesses and families. The Budget in March announced wide-ranging reforms to the tax system to support growth and stimulate investment, such as reductions to corporation tax, falling from 26% to 24% from April this year, and reaching 22% in April 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-government-energy-reforms"&gt;UK government energy reforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning to the energy sector, we are looking closely at the subsidy framework and other incentives that enable the sector to compete. These are crucial reforms at the heart of the coalition’s policy priorities. In the Budget statement, the Chancellor reaffirmed our commitment to assist our world-leading renewable energy sector to thrive. An estimated £110 billion of investment is needed in electricity generation and transmission this decade alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that we send out clear and consistent messages to investors, and we are looking closely at the subsidy framework and other incentives that enable the sector to compete, through the Electricity Market Reform proposals. The Reforms will mean clear, stable and predictable revenue streams for investors across all forms of low carbon technologies and encourage long term investment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-green-investment-bank"&gt;UK Green Investment Bank&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking out innovative routes to fund green projects. Earlier this year, we announced the UK Green Investment Bank - the world’s first investment bank solely dedicated to greening the economy. Capitalised with £3 billion of UK taxpayers’ money, the UK Green Investment Bank will play a vital role in addressing market failures affecting green infrastructure projects, leveraging as much as £15 billion of private sector capital in low carbon infrastructure by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposed priority areas for the Bank include offshore wind power generation and non-domestic energy efficiency, where your expertise is needed. Following state aid approval, the Bank will be established as a standalone institution, headquartered in Edinburgh, with a view to the bank being fully operational by Autumn 2012. The Bank will be an enduring institution that will build deep expertise in financial expertise and green markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="research--development"&gt;Research &amp;amp; development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as we meet here in one of Scotland’s leading universities, it brings home the message that we need to encourage constant innovation. Your industry has to sustain skills and keep up with the cutting edge of technology to stay ahead of your competitors worldwide. So for those technologies that need additional support, we are providing dedicated funding to help them on their path to full commercialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, Scotland is leading the way. Here at the University of Strathclyde the £50 million Offshore Renewable Energy Catapult will be headquartered. This is in addition to a share of the £140m High Value Manufacturing Catapult. Linking with an operational centre at the National Renewable Energy Centre in the North East of England, the Offshore Renewable centre of excellence will draw on skills shared across the UK at the Wave Hub and Marine Energy Park in the South West of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim will be to bridge the gap between university research and full commercialisation, a period which can be especially difficult. Prof Jim McDonald is going to speak shortly on the detail of the Catapult and what we hope to achieve from this venture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting also that the Pentland Firth and Orkney Waters will soon be the UK’s second Marine Energy Park, fostering co-operation and collaboration within the marine industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="importance-of-partnership"&gt;Importance of partnership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning to that theme - cooperation and collaboration are essential to release the potential of Scotland’s renewable energy resources. Partnership across the private sector to drive growth amongst the leading players in the field and the wider supply chain and to attract investment in this competitive global marketplace. Partnership between industry and academic institutions to transfer the latest research and technological advances in pursuit of world-class innovation and to foster innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes - partnership between the UK and the Scottish governments so that we can use the economic levers at our disposal as effectively as possible to help industry to thrive - in the best interests of Scotland and right across the UK. Although at times the politicians may disagree on many things in the constitutional debate - one thing we do not disagree on is the need for Scotland to fulfil its true potential in the field of renewables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the UK government is prepared to do everything in its power to work collaboratively with the Scottish government to make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Catapult is a prime example - the UK government, through the Technology Strategy Board, is committing funding and strategic vision, but working closely with Scottish Enterprise to make the all-important links with local companies. Together we are greater than the sum of our parts. UK government relationship with electronics community&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - I would like to reinforce the message that the government is also keen to work in partnership with you. The electronics community in the UK covers a breadth of application areas and markets that few other industries can match. The nature of this sector means that it has a strong role to play in underpinning energy supply and demand challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want companies like yours - directly or through organisations such as NMI - to play an active part in our thinking on how to address the economic challenges ahead.  For example through publication of the National Strategy for Power Electronics last Autumn, produced by NMI and the Department for Business Innovation &amp;amp; Skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  look forward to the forthcoming report outlining the Challenges and Opportunities facing the wider Electronic Systems community in the UK, expected to be published this Autumn.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scotland-in-the-uk"&gt;Scotland in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I conclude I hope you will allow me to reflect on our current constitutional debate. All of our considerations about energy policy, innovation and investment occur in the context of the great debate on Scotland’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I am committed to ensuring Scotland remains in a strong and prosperous United Kingdom. Along with many other Scots that you will speak to, I believe Scotland is stronger within the UK and the UK is stronger with Scotland as an integral part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Scotland’s interests are UK interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we work together to reach places, and have influence, and win contracts that would be impossible for Scotland alone. Pooling risks and sharing resources with your neighbour - the UK is a stable home which is envied world over. We are seeking the answers to all of the questions that the proposal for independence raises. Questions that affect the lives - and the livelihoods - of everyone in this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are of fundamental importance to Scotland’s future and must be properly answered by those who argue for independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, by committing firmly to new institutions such as the UK Green Investment Bank and the Renewable Energy Catapult, we can harness our shared strengths. By continuing to work together as a strong, united country we are best placed to meet the economic and energy challenges we face. Combining our natural resources with investment in skills and infrastructure, our world-class research base and strong economic framework, Scotland is well placed to lead the world in the renewables revolution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have every confidence that your skills and ingenuity will continue to attract global investment needed to make the renewables revolution flourish here in Scotland. And this government will do all it can to make sure that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/64201</id>
    <published>2012-04-17T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T13:41:58+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/reforming-the-law-on-scottish-unincorporated-associations-and-criminal-liability-of-scottish-partnerships"/>
    <title>Reforming the law on Scottish unincorporated associations and criminal liability of Scottish partnerships</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>The proposed reform of Scots law on unincorporated associations and criminal liability of partnerships. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Secretary of State for Scotland (Michael Moore): I am publishing today a consultation paper that sets out the proposed reform of Scots law on two topics: unincorporated associations and criminal liability of partnerships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation document seeks views on 2 topics: firstly, the proposal to attribute legal personality to non-profit making unincorporated associations where they meet certain statutory criteria and secondly, reform of the law on criminal liability of dissolved Scottish partnerships and their partners, with the principle intention to address a loophole in Scots law that allows Scottish partnerships to escape prosecution for potentially serious offences by dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main proposals for unincorporated associations are that becoming a Scottish Association with Legal Personality (&lt;abbr title="Scottish Association with Legal Personality"&gt;SALP&lt;/abbr&gt;) should not be dependent on any registration requirement and that office-bearers and members will not incur any personal liability by acting as an office bearer or member. Accordingly, &lt;abbr title="Scottish Associations with Legal Personality"&gt;SALPs&lt;/abbr&gt; will have limited liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals are based on work by the Scottish Law Commission which led to a report and draft Bill in 2009 on reforming the law on unincorporated associations in Scotland and a report and draft Bill in 2011 on reforming the law on criminal liability of dissolved Scottish partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission has indicated that it supports the consultation process and will continue to work with the UK government to finalise a Bill that it is hoped will come before Parliament within its current term. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56851</id>
    <published>2011-08-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T17:11:24+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/empowering-our-nation-reaching-our-potential-the-future-of-scottish-devolution"/>
    <title>Empowering our nation, reaching our potential: the future of Scottish devolution</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore, Secretary of State for Scotland, talks to the David Hume Institute about the constitutional future of Scotland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="the-scottish-political-context"&gt;The Scottish political context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constitutional change in the United Kingdom is a live subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this area, and others, the coalition is a force for radical reform:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cutting the number of MPs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recasting the House of Lords&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening the devolution settlement in the constituent nations of the United Kingdom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Secretary of State for Scotland one of my primary tasks has been to oversee the drafting of the Scotland Bill and its progress through the Houses of Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has now completed its House of Commons stages and next week will begin its passage through the Lords for their consideration and amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Bill will further empower the Scottish Parliament, making it more accountable to the Scottish people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It constitutes the greatest single transfer of financial powers from London to Scotland since the creation of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a further milestone in the devolution of power from central government to the nations, communities and individuals who are best placed to ensure that the exercise of power serves the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I acknowledge that there is a distinct danger that the real time context in which it progresses upstages the very significant changes it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 has, after all, been a big year in Scottish politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish National Party’s outright win in May’s election means that Scotland has its first single-party majority government since the Scottish Parliament was re-established in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is historic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish National Party (&lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;) has all the Member of the Scottish Parliament (&lt;abbr title="Member of the Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSP&lt;/abbr&gt;)s it needs to set the legislative agenda at Holyrood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of Holyrood’s powers, it has the mandate to pursue its policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be churlish to deny the scale of the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s electoral achievement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And foolish to underestimate the work that will need to be done by the other parties to recover the ground that we have each lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s majority has also laid bare the constitutional position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fruitless pas-de-bas about an independence referendum in the last Scottish Parliament, the new majority government has pledged to bring forward its plans for the break-up of the United Kingdom, to establish Scotland as a separate state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been uncharacteristically shy in setting out exactly what independence would involve and what it would cost. Indeed, quite reticent about what they even mean by independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the rest of us, who believe strongly in the continuation, and development, of a modern United Kingdom, must not be complacent about making the case for Scotland’s continued presence in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, ladies and gentlemen, in this new, even heady, political climate, I hope this evening to provide an assessment of where Scotland’s constitutional position stands and how we can move it forward in a way that allows our politics, economy and society in Scotland to develop in line with our aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I want to sketch out for you the implications of the UK government’s Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not just the list of powers that we intend to devolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an accountant by training and a politician by profession, I am aware of the very real temptation to speak in terms of process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know that when people consider politics they don’t think in terms of process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They tend to think in terms of what they need and what is being delivered for them: needs, outcomes and results, if we must resort to jargon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to show the very real difference that the Scottish government and Scottish Parliament will be able to make to the lives of men, women and communities after the Scotland Bill becomes law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to take this opportunity to explore some policy options for Scotland in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I want to explore how best to consider constitutional change and to prepare the way for it. In passing, I want to contrast the legitimacy gained by patient consensus-building, as shown in the Calman process, with the uncertainties of the politics of assertion, which for now is the modus operandi of those who make the case for independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, recognising the fact that the UK and Scottish governments differ in their visions for the future of the United Kingdom, but must co-operate in Scotland’s interests, I want to be clear about our respective roles and responsibilities today. An important aspect of this is to disentangle the thorny issue of political mandate and relations between the Scottish and Westminster governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Hume made the great insight that human behaviour is based on passion and emotion rather than rationalism. He combined that with being a sceptic and an empiricist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that he could have given us all quite an insight into the current state of politics and thinking here in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the next 30 minutes, I’m afraid mine will have to suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-scotland-bill-achieving-our-potential-possibilities-for-scotland"&gt;The Scotland Bill: achieving our potential, possibilities for Scotland&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me underline an important, but rather obvious, starting point -  the UK government remains committed to the Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fundamentally based upon the work of Sir Kenneth Calman’s Commission on Scottish Devolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established in 2007 by a vote of the Scottish Parliament, with the support of the then UK government, and complemented by the work of Professor Anton Muscatelli’s independent expert panel on finance, it was tasked with assessing whether the Scottish Parliament had the powers it needed to deliver for the people of Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission included Conservative, Labour and Liberal Democrat members but was broad based, with non-partisan representatives from business, education, the wider public sector and civic Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It engaged and consulted widely with people throughout Scotland by means of public events, survey evidence and oral evidence sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing so, it drew from a spectrum of views and interests from public life and the business community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s final report in 2009 concluded that devolution was serving the Scottish people well and that it was here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also identified a number of additional powers that ought to be devolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, it highlighted the problem of a Parliament tasked with spending money, but which was unaccountable for how that money was raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Calman recommended a number of measures to address that anomaly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing directly on those ideas, the Scotland Bill will re-write the fiscal responsibilities of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will provide a package of taxation and borrowing powers that will see the Scottish Parliament become accountable for more than a third of the money it spends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will open a new chapter in Scottish devolution, whereby an empowered and accountable Scottish Parliament can innovate in new and exciting ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look back at the last twelve years, it is clear to see the difference that devolution has made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first term we had free personal care for the elderly, land reform, and the scrapping of section 2a.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second term it was fair votes for local elections, a ban on smoking in public places, and free eye and dental check ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were big, bold achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They showed Holyrood innovating and, often enough, Westminster following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have every confidence that the new powers we devolve can also be used to radical effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allow Scotland to go down new and unique policy paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because these new powers are very extensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill will create a Scottish rate of income tax by cutting 10p of every income tax rate, reducing the Scottish block grant in proportion and obliging the Scottish Parliament to set a new rate to meet its spending plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will allow the Scottish Ministers to borrow up to £500 million for current spending and a minimum of £2.2 billion in capital spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in the light of a request from the Scottish Parliament, it will make part of that capital investment available in pre-payments for approved projects by 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also devolve landfill tax, stamp duty, and the power to create new taxes - with air passenger duty and the aggregates levy to follow in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill will phase in these powers up to 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want you to think about the policy levers that will be at the disposal of the Scottish government elected that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to picture the kind of changes that &lt;abbr title="Members of the Scottish Parliament"&gt;MSPs&lt;/abbr&gt; will be empowered to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to endorse any vision or policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear for everyone - especially for the journalists in the room - that I am not advocating what should be done, but rather showing what could be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the range of options is extensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new capital borrowing powers, the Scottish government could be far into the construction process of a new Southern General hospital in Glasgow, or a Borders railway, or a new Forth Crossing by 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with pre-payments, the preparations for that work could begin as soon as next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new tax powers the Scottish government could stimulate the construction sector and boost the housing market by cutting stamp duty by 5% at a cost of £25 million to the Scottish budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could ensure that Scotland competes to be the greenest country in Europe by proposing innovative new green taxes - offset by other tax cuts - to ensure that Scotland moves the tax burden from people to pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could use the new Scottish Income Tax to raise investment in public services higher still than that in other parts of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a 2p rise raising £208 million or the equivalent of the combined budgets for alcohol misuse, tobacco control, health protection, specialist children’s services, research, clean hospitals, MRSA screening, and mental health services&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could do just the opposite, cutting the rate to attract the bright and ambitious to Scotland and reduce the brain drain from within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a 2p cut putting £350 back in the pocket of the average earning Scot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These options - these alternatives - show the extent and range of powers on offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this freedom to innovate - these possibilities for Scotland - will ensure that future administrations can take our country in new directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if they simply maintain the status quo, there will be more debate and greater accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scottish public services funded by money raised through taxes levied here in Scotland, not at Westminster. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate will be sharper and will ensure that every Scottish government is answerable to the Scottish people for the money they raise and the decisions they take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the balance that the Scotland Bill strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-political-legitimacy-of-constitutional-change"&gt;The political legitimacy of constitutional change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is the UK coalition’s Scotland Bill that will bring about the next phase of Scottish devolution, we have not acted alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me now reflect on how we have approached this constitutional change and established its legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the expert, cross-sector Calman Commission, supported by all three of the Conservatives, Labour and the Liberal Democrats, we would not have proceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we would not have achieved the political consensus or wider buy-in that is critical to constitutional reform in this county.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a comparatively short period of time, the UK has developed a convention by which significant constitutional change is agreed either by consensus, or direct democracy - and, where appropriate, both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s membership of the European Economic Community was reaffirmed in the 1975 referendum, which featured cross-party campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals for devolution in Scotland and Wales also resulted in cross-party camps and a popular vote in 1979 that saw devolution rejected outright in Wales and supported in Scotland albeit by fewer votes than the then required threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, after support for devolution resurged in the 1980s and 1990s, the 1997 referendum campaigns were once again fought by broad yes and no groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this second occasion, with a much happier conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resounding yes vote in Scotland owed much to the years of consensus-building that led up to the ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish Constitutional Convention brought together the Labour Party and the Liberal Democrats alongside representatives from academia, business, the trade unions, the churches and wider Scottish society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, they reached a consensus, they drew up the blueprint, they defined the settled will of the Scottish people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is from consensus or direct democracy that constitutional change derives its legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, in politics, momentum matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the fortunes of political parties wax and wane, the constitutional settlement - the delineated borders of devolved and central government - ought not to be bent or blurred in reaction to a singular election result nor at the will of one party or government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For countries with written constitutions, there are established legal safeguards against that possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, for example, an amendment to the Constitution requires a two-thirds majority in Congress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the United Kingdom, there is no codified constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The division of power between Westminster and the nation states can be changed with a parliamentary majority of just one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But much of the legal space occupied in other countries by constitutional law is filled in this country by constitutional convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the boundaries of devolution have become one of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is also with the current Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the powers we are devolving do not mark as great a constitutional shift as the re-establishment of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that reason there is no discernible appetite for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the provisions of the bill are based on a great deal of work and consensus-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just through the Calman Commission, but also in the passage of the Bill itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been subject to public consultation, scrutiny by Scotland Bill committees at both Holyrood and Westminster, and the legislative procedures themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also established a high level implementation group of outside experts that meets regularly with me, my Ministerial colleagues and government officials to ensure that we hear informed, outside opinions about the Bill and its future implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Bill has already been approved in draft by an overwhelming vote of the last Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it becomes law the amended Bill will go back to Holyrood for its approval once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout this process we have been clear that while the Bill is based primarily on the Calman Commission’s consensus, we are open to amendments that improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for any amendment to be acceptable - wherever it comes from - it must meet three key tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it must be a detailed proposal that materially strengthens the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it must maintain the broad consensus on which the Bill is based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And third, it must be without detriment to the UK as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not random tests designed to fail any new proposal - indeed we have already changed the Bill to reflect ideas put forward by the previous Scottish Parliament and others in Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tests reflect the standard that the Calman proposals themselves achieved - thorough, detailed plans based on arguments that were developed to secure consensus and always in the context of the broader common interests of the United Kingdom as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Scottish National Party’s re-election in May, they have pushed hard for the UK government to make a series of further amendments to our Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have prioritised 6 areas in which they want to see further devolution of power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;borrowing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;corporation tax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EU representation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;excise duty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;broadcasting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Crown Estates Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have perfectly reasonably asked that the proposals should match the Calman standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have asked for detailed information from the Scottish government on each of these proposals and we will give a serious and considered response to each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the right and reasonable thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds are not closed, but we are crystal clear that those three tests would need to be met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish government has now submitted papers on four of its demands, plus a consultation document on corporation tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have yet to receive anything at all on excise duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fair to say that there are still very significant questions outstanding in each of these areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of corporation tax, I am pleased that the Scottish government has now at least acknowledged in its consultation paper that there are real issues to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the UK government’s announcement that the Crown Estate will fund a UK-wide coastal communities fund, from which Scotland will benefit disproportionately, has clear significance for the discussion of changes to its structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will keep talking to the Scottish government about these proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But stepping back for a moment, I am bound to say that their latest strategic move - the so-called ‘Six Demands’ - has come rather late in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only last year that they sought to turn the cross-party Scotland Bill into a vehicle for delivering the ambition of ‘fiscal autonomy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A loosely-defined notion of devolving all tax-powers, based on one academic paper, which left key questions unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Fiscal autonomy’ has never been spelt out in detail, there is certainly no consensus about it and it would have major implications for the UK which have not been explored, so it clearly failed the three tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than develop the arguments, the Scottish government has shifted ground and put forward its new agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not this is a scaling back or not is a matter for the Scottish government to answer, but the new approach has to be subjected to the same scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The politics of assertion will not be enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot is at stake and time is tight for the Scottish government to get the details of their ‘Six Demands’ sorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is at least agreement on the need to provide more powers as speedily as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I pointed out earlier, the Scotland Bill has already left the Commons and gone to the Lords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it were not passed by the end of this Parliamentary session, it would fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not something we are willing to contemplate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own view is that the manner of the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s last minute approach is further evidence of the need for broad engagement at the start of a constitutional process rather than towards the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had the Nationalists agreed to be part of the Calman process when it began, or even articulated their thinking in a parallel process, they could have made the case for their Six Demands or indeed for fiscal autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They chose not to, for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, much of our current thinking now focuses on the prospect of a referendum on independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independence has been debated for decades, and amongst the politicians it now has a much sharper focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But among the Scottish people, independence remains very much a minority pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1999, the Scottish Social Attitudes Survey showed that 27% of Scots wanted Scotland to separate from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, that percentage was unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no opinion poll before or since has shown a majority of Scots in favour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same survey shows that in both 1999 and 2009 support for a devolved Scotland within the UK hovered at around 60%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever factors played a part in May’s election result, it was not a rise in support for Scottish independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say we should ignore the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, we should take it on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when the Scottish government does come forward with its referendum proposals, there will need to be proper scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From politicians yes - but also from business, from civil society, from all groups and individuals with an interest in Scotland’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What question will they ask?  How many questions will there be?  How will the campaign be conducted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is important that they are asked fairly and without an inherent bias designed to deliver the referendum result that the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those are only the organisational aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They must also answer the substantive questions about what they mean by independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish government has unbounded enthusiasm for talking about its Six Demands of the Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here are just six of the many questions for them on what an independent Scotland would look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six specific questions, in six areas of key importance, that the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; must answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What regulation would be applied to our banks and financial services and who would enforce it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which currency would Scotland adopt and how could entry and influence be guaranteed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would membership of international organisations - including the EU - be assured?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would be our defence posture and the configuration of our armed forces?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many billions would we inherit in pension liabilities and who would pay for future pensions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And above all, how much would independence cost: what is the bottom line?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, that’s more than six questions in truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once you start, it’s hard to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the questions keep coming, the implications keep emerging and the imperative to answer keeps growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these are fundamental to the notion of an independent Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And given that independence is the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s key article of faith - and that a referendum was a core policy pledge - we are all, as Scots, entitled to know what the answers are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because here in Scotland we benefit massively from our position in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of economic strength, international standing and so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And until the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; sets things out, the Scottish people are being asked to take a punt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, our future cannot be taken on trust; it’s just too important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we adapt the three tests of the Scotland Bill to independence and we ask -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it a detailed proposal that will materially strengthen Scotland?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has it generated consensus across Scotland?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will it be without detriment to the UK as a whole?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then what we have is a proposition that fails three times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The politics of assertion won’t pass the tests - we need and deserve the detailed arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real risk for Scotland is that the uncertainty caused by delay undermines public confidence in the Scottish government’s intentions and saps investor confidence when it comes to deciding where - that is in which country - jobs should be based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we can say with certainty is that whenever a referendum is held, this government will fight for a secure Scotland within a strong and prosperous UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will make what the Prime Minister calls the ‘big, optimistic case’ for the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am confident that we will win the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="governments-2-mandates"&gt;2 governments, 2 mandates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have already said, the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt;’s victory in May was a very significant achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is important, three months on, to be clear about the nature of their mandate and the responsibilities it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me therefore, finally, turn my attention to the mandates each of the governments hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard it said - not least by Nationalists themselves - that May’s result changes everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication is that the Scottish government is now alone in understanding and representing Scotland’s interests and beyond challenge in interpreting where they lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new world their interlocutors - including the UK government - must give ground where disagreements arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whether by accident or design, this approach feeds an insidious narrative in which the Scottish government is standing up for Scotland’s interests any time it is in dispute with the UK government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me be very clear about something which UK Ministers have been perhaps too slow - or considered it unnecessary - to point out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland has 2 governments - distinct, elected and legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each takes decisions in the interests of Scotland, in light of their respective powers and their democratic mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, after all, worth noting that in the 2010 election the coalition parties, taken together, won more votes than the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; got on the party list in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that either government has a greater mandate than the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is simply to state that these are 2 separate and legitimate governments, each of which is responsible for taking decisions in Scotland’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a member of the UK government - as Secretary of State for Scotland - I can assure you that we are doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By restoring the pensions-earnings link to benefit one million Scottish pensioners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking 91,000 low paid Scots out of income tax altogether by April of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By ending the scandal of child detention at Dungavel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by making record investment in superfast broadband, cutting the price of fuel in our most rural communities, and agreeing to defer the first year of spending cuts in Scotland because we responded to the specific circumstances and needs of the Scottish economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions we make - against the backdrop of the worst finances in modern history - are decisions taken to get the best for Scotland in the hardest of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Scottish government need not worry about the motives of the UK government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scottish Ministers, after all, have plenty to be getting on with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Scottish government, supported by a majority in the Parliament, does have an enhanced mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it has that within the context of devolved government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of the 1998 Scotland Act - supported overwhelmingly by the Scottish people in a referendum - the Scottish Parliament has defined and extensive powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, written into the Act, is the assumption that all power is devolved other than that which is specifically reserved - rather than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are powers that cover the bread and butter policy issues that matter to the Scottish people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schools where we send our children, the hospitals where we treat our sick, the police forces that protect our communities, the transport systems that get us from A to B, the local authorities that provide the services on which we all rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these fall within the remit of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As does economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish government already has its hands on a great many economic levers, particularly with relation to economic development:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through our schools, colleges and universities it has the power to ensure that our workforce has the capabilities, skills and qualifications it needd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through Scottish Enterprise, VisitScotland, and Skills Development Scotland, to think of just 3 bodies, it has the capacity to nurture talent and attract jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through council tax, local business rates and what would have been a 3p income tax varying power, had the Scottish government maintained it, they also have powers to vary public revenue and public spending levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On education, on health, on the economy - the Scottish people’s priorities - the Scottish government already has the powers it keeps claiming that it needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They should get on with the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of us - as Scottish voters like millions of others - have every right to expect them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, all too often, their minds appear to be focused on other things - particularly if those things are happening south of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macroeconomic policy, Corporation Tax, constitutional change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are of vital importance to Scotland, and it is unrealistic to expect the &lt;abbr title="Scottish National Party"&gt;SNP&lt;/abbr&gt; to have no view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these are issues reserved to Scotland’s government at Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Scottish government’s concentration on them leaves the impression that Scottish Ministers lack interest in the powers they do have while being obsessed with powers they don’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than get on with developing a radical and effective economic strategy using powers at their disposal, they have instead committed themselves to undermining the UK government’s economic policy, albeit with the flimsiest of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government has taken the hard decisions needed to bring our economy back from the brink, drive down the deficit and rebalance our national finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, we are determined to rebuild and rebalance our lop-sided economy and ensure that Scotland is a place of opportunity with a sustainable jobs market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is for this purpose that we are cutting corporation tax to the lowest rate in the G7, reforming national insurance contributions and keeping interest rates low to reduce the cost of borrowing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Scottish government has attacked our policy consistently, and made much of their case for a Plan B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On publication, that case amounted to 2 sides of A4, with the policy content confined to just one page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its relaunch a week later it had grown to five and a half pages, with the addition of charts and graphs but not much extra detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not a plan, it’s a stunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now is not the time for stunts and blame-shifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a majority comes the opportunity to innovate and the responsibility to govern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Salmond should seize those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to the First Minister’s statement next week on the Scottish government’s programme for the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that it will map out a serious course of action, using the Scottish Parliament’s current powers to improve the lives of people throughout our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there will always be areas of genuine policy overlap and disagreements that arise between the 2 governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But where the latter arises, effective mechanisms already exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joint Ministerial Council - or &lt;abbr title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;JMC&lt;/abbr&gt; - plenary including the Prime Minister, the Deputy Prime Minister and the Secretaries of State and First Ministers for Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland meets annually to discuss issues of mutual importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;JMC&lt;/abbr&gt; domestic and &lt;abbr title="Joint Ministerial Council"&gt;JMC&lt;/abbr&gt; Europe meet several times a year with relevant ministers from each country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Finance Quadrilateral brings together finance ministers on an increasingly regular basis to discuss economic issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition there are bilateral relationships between departments and Ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish and UK governments are, for example, in the process of establishing a Joint Exchequer Committee to plan and coordinate the devolution of the tax and borrowing powers outlined in the Scotland Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on a more personal note, since May 2010 Scotland’s First Minister has had face-to-face meetings with the Prime Minister, the Deputy Prime Minister, the Chancellor and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diplomacy prevents me from saying how often Mr Salmond met with the last occupant of No 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is about more than meetings: it is about trust and respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the coalition took office last May, the Prime Minister made an early trip to Scotland and made clear his commitment to a respect agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He meant it - we meant it - and we still do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to be clear that respect is a 2 way process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to be clear that the respect agenda is in fact a mutual respect agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scotland’s 2 governments should acknowledge one another’s legitimacy, respect one another’s mandates, and ensure that they fulfil those mandates to the best of their abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottish people expect nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, Scotland’s constitutional settlement sits in a well-established framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within that framework our laws are made, our politics is conducted and our economy is shaped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore in the interests of all of us to get that settlement right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure that it serves the people of Scotland in line with their desires and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 years after the aspiration for a Scottish Parliament was met there is no going back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devolution is embedded in national life and national consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate is about how to take it forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be assured that the coalition at Westminster is committed to creating a successful future for Scotland of which we can all be proud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56991</id>
    <published>2011-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-07T17:46:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/scotland-bill-the-second-reading"/>
    <title>Scotland Bill: the second reading</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>The second reading of the Scotland Bill in Parliament. The Bill will begin a new phase of devolution in Scotland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, I beg to move that the Bill be read a second time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, the devolution of power and decision making from this Parliament to the Assemblies of Wales and Northern Ireland, and to the Parliament in Scotland, has transformed the constitutional arrangements of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this Bill we begin a new phase of devolution in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A phase we enter with cross party support and the support of individuals and organisations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill is, of course, an important step in the coalition government’s programme to modernise and reform the United Kingdom’s constitution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its origins lie in the Scottish Parliament itself and in the support given by the previous government, which I am happy to acknowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, this Scotland Bill will further empower the Scottish Parliament and make it more accountable to those who elect it. In doing so, it will strengthen Scotland’s position within the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us reflect on how we got here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late Donald Dewar famously said, whilst quoting from the first line of the Scotland Act 1998:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There shall be a Scottish Parliament”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I like that’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His sentiments were, and continue to be, widely shared in this House, and throughout Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is important to pay tribute to Donald Dewar for his historic role in shaping modern Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was a true statesman, serving both as Secretary of State for Scotland and Scotland’s original First Minister. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the creation of the Scottish Parliament he has a fine legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he would be the first to insist on recognition for the countless others, across different parties, and, crucially, from many different backgrounds in Scotland - who patiently built the case for devolution over many years, indeed decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we should acknowledge those in this place, in the Scottish Parliament and beyond who supported the early years of the devolved institutions, building their capacity and establishing their credibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we build on that work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When taking the original Scotland Bill through this place in 1998, Donald Dewar said that the creation of a Scottish Parliament was not just for Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor was it just routine tinkering with the detail of our political system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, it was a fundamental, radical reform of the UK’s constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After more than a decade of devolution, the Scottish Parliament is firmly established as part of the fabric of Scottish life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than that, devolution - not just in Scotland, but right across the United Kingdom - is now part of our national life too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliament was established to bring power closer to the people of Scotland. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make government more responsive to their needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put their priorities at the heart of Scottish governance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has succeeded: decision-making, on education, health, the environment, among many things, is closer to the people those decisions affect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of Scottish devolution has changed the terms of the debate. Few would seriously now argue that there should be no Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, the Bill that we debate today builds on the achievements of the original Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It builds on the experience of devolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it further strengthens Scotland’s place within the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just six months after being elected, we introduced the Scotland Bill on St Andrew’s Day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, we made good our formal pledge, in our Programme for government, and in the Queen’s Speech, to implement the recommendations of the Commission on Scottish Devolution, the Calman Commission as it is more commonly known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this was not our commitment alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party opposite also pledged in its manifesto to implement the recommendations of the Calman Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I welcome their ongoing support - without in any way seeking to compromise the important role they will perform in scrutinising the detail of the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, however, the measures brought forward to this House, on a major piece of Scottish constitutional legislation, are founded on support from across this Chamber and within Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, after the first decade of devolution, it was right to review the Scotland Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assess how devolution was working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that the Scottish Parliament had the right powers to deliver for people in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2007, the Commission on Scottish Devolution was established by vote in the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaired by Professor Sir Kenneth Calman, the Commission included Conservative, Labour and Liberal Democrat representatives: but it was independent of any political party. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it embraced representatives from business, education, the wider public sector and across civic Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission gathered evidence from a wide-range of sources and engaged directly with people in Scotland and elsewhere in the United Kingdom - through detailed consultation, public engagement events, oral evidence from a spectrum of interests in Scottish public and business life, and survey evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me record my thanks to Professor Sir Kenneth Calman and his Commissioners for their thorough, inclusive and well-evidenced work. I would also like to acknowledge the impressive and detailed work of Professor Anton Muscatelli and the Independent Expert Group on Finance, which supported the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Final Report of the Commission was submitted jointly to the Scottish Parliament and the UK government in June 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was widely welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based firmly on the Commission’s findings, the Scotland Bill seeks to implement its key recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s first and overarching conclusion was that devolution has been a real success; that it is here to stay: and that the balance between reserved and devolved policy powers and functions is, broadly, in the right place.       &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also concluded that there is a shortcoming in terms of the way the Parliament is funded - and specifically in terms of accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, at the centre of the Commission’s Report and of this Bill are measures to improve the financial accountability of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a Parliament in Scotland that can determine policy on a wide range of subjects. It can determine how and where money is spent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at present it cannot be held effectively to account for raising the money it spends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission recognised this imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill addresses that imbalance by providing a package of taxation and borrowing powers that will see the Scottish Parliament become accountable for over a third of the money it spends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, the Bill represents the largest transfer of fiscal powers from central government since the creation of the United Kingdom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a radical but responsible step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most significantly, we will create a Scottish income tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will create that tax by cutting 10 pence off the basic, higher and 50 pence tax rates for Scottish taxpayers, adjusting the block grant in proportion, and allowing the Scottish Parliament - indeed, obliging it - to apply a Scottish Income tax at a level of its choosing to meet its spending plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give Scottish Ministers and the Scottish Parliament a much more significant stake in the performance of the Scottish economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of the Scottish rate will be Scotland’s to decide. And those who set the rates will answer directly to those affected by them. Power will rest with the Scottish people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to income tax, the Scotland Bill will devolve to the Scottish Parliament responsibility for stamp duty land tax, and landfill tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will complement its policy responsibilities for housing, planning and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill will also allow the Scottish Parliament to propose new devolved taxes, to sit alongside its other powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fiscal powers are not limited to tax. They extend to borrowing powers, too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill will allow Scottish Ministers to borrow up to £500 million for current spending where tax receipts fall short of those forecast. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the other end of the scale, we will provide for a Scottish Cash Reserve so that they can bank and save money where tax receipts exceed those expected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These provisions will allow for effective financial management to deal with fluctuations in its new revenue stream of tax receipts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also set out in the Bill a brand new capital borrowing power, of up to £2.2billion.  This will provide the Scottish government with new means to invest in major infrastructure and other projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be for Scottish Ministers and the Scottish Parliament to decide whether to borrow, and if so for what purpose - a new Forth crossing, or new hospitals, or new schools. Maybe even a railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will be for them to account to the Scottish people for those choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of increasing the financial freedom and accountability of the Scottish Parliament to raise its own revenues, there will be a reduction to the existing block grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant will continue to make up the remainder of the Scottish budget.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will ensure financial stability. It will ensure continuity of public service provision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will maintain the economic union that is so central to our United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that views differ, both in this House and further afield, on the broad issue of the block grant, and specifically on the Barnett formula that underpins it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not expect those differences to be resolved today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the funding formula is not part of the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has set out its position on the Barnett formula in its Programme for Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst recognising the need to review the arrangements in time, our overriding priority is to tackle the deficit and we will not consider a review until the public finances are returned to good health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me be very clear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing in this Bill prejudges future changes to the funding formula. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, the effect of the Bill will be to make the Scottish Parliament more reliant on its own revenues, and less reliant on the block grant, to fund public spending in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is another set of financial arguments which has been put forward as an alternative to the measures in the Bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent months, there has been some discussion in the Scottish Parliament and the Scottish press about other approaches to fiscal devolution - and specifically about the idea of ‘fiscal autonomy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, its proponents have failed to come up with any credible proposals - indeed, any detailed proposals at all while the economic arguments advanced in support of ‘fiscal autonomy’ lack any firm evidence to support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals in this Bill are the only practical and sensible way forward for Scotland and for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than taking a leap into the unknown, our proposals introduce significant changes which build on established practice from elsewhere in the world. I look forward to the scrutiny they will receive here and the continuing scrutiny from the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, implementing these new financial arrangements will require detailed work by the UK government, the Scottish government and a range of other stakeholders. We will approach the task in a carefully planned and phased way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bill provides the overall framework for the new arrangements: but more than legislation alone will be needed to give effect to the measures set out there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Command Paper published alongside the Bill sets out the key stages in this process, with milestones, so that the full package of powers is in place in time for the tax year 2016-17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bill and the Command Paper are not just about finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Calman Commission examined the whole of the devolution arrangements and found that the division of policy responsibilities in the original Scotland Act worked well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did, however, make recommendations to improve it further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are reflected in the Bill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of justice, we will give the Scottish Parliament the power to legislate on air weapons. And give Scottish Ministers the power to set the drink-drive limit and a Scottish national speed limit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of health, we will give Scottish Ministers the power to decide which doctors in Scotland should be able to use drugs for the treatment of addiction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will give the Scottish government a formal role in key appointments to the BBC Trust and the Crown Estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we will give the Scottish Parliament more powers over the administration of its own elections, and its own processes and procedures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also some areas where, for good and practical reasons, the Calman Commission recommended re-reservation of powers to Westminster. These too are included in our Bill - for example, the regulation of healthcare professions and corporate insolvency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have taken the opportunity to address the question of the official title of the devolved administration - the ‘Scottish Executive’ or the ‘Scottish government’. The term ‘Scottish government’ has now become broadly recognised. We propose to make that official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every proposal from Calman is set out in this Bill. In some cases, legislation is not required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Commission recommended much closer co-operation and communication between administrations and between Parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the proposals require change to working practices - change to which this government, for its part, is committed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know, Mr Speaker, that you, the Lords Speaker and the Presiding Officer will determine the appropriate basis on which to develop relationships between our Parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fulfilling our commitment to implement the Calman recommendations there are some cases where we have deviated from the precise recommendations because the policy context at UK level has changed - for example, in relation to air passenger duty, which this government is reviewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, however, we have gone further than the Commission - building and strengthening its recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Speaker, this is the first time since the creation of devolution that a government has brought forward legislation with such wide-ranging effect on the current settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, this Bill will fundamentally change the powers and responsibilities of the Scottish Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that reason, this government will only proceed with this Bill with the formal and explicit consent of the Scottish Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is right and proper that the Scottish Parliament should examine the measures that we set out in the Scotland Bill. I welcome the thorough way in which it is going about its business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I look forward to returning to discuss the provisions with the Bill committee in the Scottish Parliament next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion
Mr Speaker,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devolution breathed new life into Scottish politics and Scottish society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It brought government closer to the Scottish people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it shaped a more confident Scotland in a more secure United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scotland Bill extends that settlement for the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter of devolution began with the Scotland Act 1998. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second chapter opened on St Andrew’s Day when we published the Scotland Bill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Bill reflects the work of many across this chamber and in Holyrood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that we have undertaken together, with consensus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strengthening Scotland’s future within the United Kingdom.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend it to the House. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56996</id>
    <published>2010-10-07T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-08T09:34:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/oil-and-gas-uk-decommissioning-conference"/>
    <title>Oil and Gas UK Decommissioning Conference</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Michael Moore MP, Secretary of State for Scotland, discusses decommissioning and the globally renowned reputation of our oil and gas industry.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to start by thanking Oil and Gas UK and Decom North Sea for inviting me here to today’s conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past two weeks I have travelled extensively across Scotland, and I have seen many energy related projects. From the Dounreay site in Caithness to Sullom Voe in Shetland, down to Cruachan Power station in Argyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy was, is and will continue to be a pivotal sector in Scotland’s economy. Whether we are talking about renewable, nuclear or the oil and gas industry, there are real challenges and massive opportunities ahead of us. You know that. That is why you are here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference has been about getting ahead. Getting ahead of the game in offshore decommissioning and securing the benefits arising from this expanding sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first time that I have attended a Decommissioning event; although I met a few of you at the Subsea UK Parliamentary Reception I attended a couple of months ago at Westminster. I was interested to hear some of your views on the future of decommissioning and encouraged by your ambition to make the most of your opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am very pleased to be here with you today. It is also a rare chance, to be talking to an audience about something other than deficit reduction, vital though that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to share some thoughts with you this afternoon about two key areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, decommissioning challenges and opportunities;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And second, the importance and globally renowned reputation of our oil and gas industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the outset though, let me acknowledge the tragic recent events in the Gulf of Mexico which are still very much on our minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gunther Newcombe’s [BP] points on safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK Government continues to monitor events and will look at any lessons which need to be learned. The work of the Oil Spill Prevention and Response Advisory Group (&lt;abbr title="Oil Spill Prevention and Response Advisory Group"&gt;OSPRAG&lt;/abbr&gt;) is of great value in this respect and I recognise the significant industry expertise which this embodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are together determined to ensure the best outcome for future safety in our waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As industry experts have emphasised, our offshore regulatory regime must always be robust and fit for purpose. The increased number of inspections implemented in the North Sea is indicative of proper engagement and a proper response to the events in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some quarters, there have been calls for sterner measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Commissioner Oettinger has made clear his support for a moratorium on deep sea drilling. I can assure you that his view is not ours.  Work will not stop: It will go on, safely and purposefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does stop, at the point where our resources are exhausted, new challenges face us, which are, of course, your main focus here today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="decommissioning"&gt;Decommissioning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of decommissioning offshore oil and gas facilities is of course complex. It calls for sophisticated management, planning, coordination and control of a wide range of skills, resources, facilities, technologies, equipment, services and consultancies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decommissioning of offshore oil and gas platforms will soon start to speed up. Around 260 UK Continental Shelf (&lt;abbr title="UK Continental Shelf"&gt;UKCS&lt;/abbr&gt;) fields will have to be wholly or partially removed from UK waters by 2040.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our preparations, there is a need for continued investment in technologies both old and new which will take time. I heart your concerns about how regulation can affect this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge is to ready ourselves, to work with the North Sea supply chain for what is a multi-billion pound opportunity. It is estimated there will be around £25 billion of work in the &lt;abbr title="UK Continental Shelf"&gt;UKCS&lt;/abbr&gt; over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again Gunther’s point about collaboration within sector and with government is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This a fresh opportunity for Scottish firms to lead in the world. Decommissioning is an emerging market which offers Scottish businesses with the right expertise, decades of work, not just in the North Sea but right across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole supply chain will need to work together to provide reliable, safe and cost-effective solutions to the challenges which decommissioning poses. As a government we are committed to working with you on this as key partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Scotland the industry is making headway with the Shetland Decommissioning Consortium and with a partnership between the Lerwick Port Authority and AF Decom. And I know that other companies and other organisations in Scotland are keen to follow Shetland’s lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already seeing firms like Shell making plans to decommission the Brent Area with work  awarded to Production Services Network. This is encouraging. I hope the work of Decom North Sea will help develop British expertise so that British companies make the most of British opportunities. After all a number of further fields are expected to follow suit in the not too distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also take Gunther’s points that we are learning across the sectors, for example with nuclear, and there are environmental challenges, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Secretary of State for Scotland I am a member of PILOT and I look forward to attending my first meeting. It has proved to be a very effective forum which has been instrumental in delivering a number of important and game changing initiatives. As the North Sea matures there is much more that can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that PILOT has reached its 10th  birthday, my Coalition colleague, the Energy Minister Charles Hendry, is working with the industry to assess  how it should evolve. Decommissioning is of course one of the key energy issues that PILOT will tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-north-sea-oil-and-gas"&gt;The Importance of North Sea Oil and Gas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond decommissioning, I would also like to underline the importance we attach to the oil and gas sector as a Government and celebrate the globally renowned reputation of our oil and gas industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Sea oil and gas has been a key part of Scottish life and the Scottish economy throughout my adult life. It has always been a source of prosperity and political debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an industry which has a story like no other. A rollercoaster of inspiration, excitement and tragedy at different times. A story which this audience more than any other knows so very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extracting oil and gas from the uniquely challenging North Sea involved unprecedented feats of civil engineering. It has never been easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be fair to say in the second decade of the 21st century that North Sea oil and gas is a mature sector. But it remains hugely important for Scotland, our energy supply and energy security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pioneering spirit which once involved 80,000 men and rigs sited halfway to Scandinavia has never been extinguished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it burns on. It is right here in the skills and expertise of a workforce whose talents are sought around the world. People from the UK’s oil and gas sector are already working in every oil producing basin in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry also has an excellent track record when it comes to overcoming hurdles. I appreciate that some of the technologies we now take for granted were once ground-breaking ideas. Easy oil wasn’t easy at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we know the challenges will become increasingly complex. To overcome them it is vital that the sector continues to attract the brightest and most talented young people to supplement its already substantial workforce. It is imperative for the North Sea to maintain its skills base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course that means that the industry must be free to prosper. Government cannot grow the energy sector. But it can create the environment in which that growth can take place. We are committed to do all we can to make Scotland and the UK an attractive place to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition is committed to creating an environment in which investment grows and business prospers. This is a government with an agenda pledged to simplify tax and to cut red tape too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phased reduction in Corporation Tax - to 24p in the pound by the end of this Parliament - will give the UK the lowest rate among G7 states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, our changes to Employer National Insurance contributions, raising thresholds for established companies and partially exempting new enterprises, are geared to help business prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private sector led growth in a rebalanced economy is the only route to a sustainable recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident you will be a strong part of that and that in decommissioning we have new opportunities for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my message here today is this: In this government, your industry has a champion and a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We support your desire for collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exciting opportunity to exploit the decommissioning needs of our country: To grow the industry, to develop the skills, to continue to lead in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish you every success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
