<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/mike-penning</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/mike-penning.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Mike Penning MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/15036</id>
    <published>2012-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/red-ensign-flies-for-merchant-navy-day"/>
    <title>Red Ensign flies for Merchant Navy Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Red Ensign flag will fly over the headquarters of the Department for Transport to mark the UK’s thirteenth Merchant Navy Day on Monday 3 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its introduction in 2000, Merchant Navy Day has provided an opportunity to remember the sacrifices of the seafarers of the past, to show appreciation for British shipping today and to look ahead to our future as a maritime nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipping Minister Mike Penning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Merchant Navy Day is an opportunity to not only remember seafarers of the past, but to look to a bright future for UK shipping. More than 20,000 merchant seafarers lost their lives in the Second World War alone, while working to provide this country with the means to survive. We owe those brave seafarers a debt of gratitude for their sacrifices and the contribution they made to our national wellbeing.
&amp;gt;More recently, it has been encouraging to see a real revival in UK shipping and in the number of young people seeking a career at sea. The British maritime sector, while facing the challenge of competition from abroad, still has a great reputation. The vast majority of goods arriving or departing the UK do so by sea, so we look forward to a future where the UK continues to be a significant and successful maritime nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Red Ensign is the official flag of the commercial shipping fleet of the UK and its Crown Dependencies and Overseas Territories. It will fly over the headquarters of the Department for Transport - Great Minster House in Horseferry Road, London SW1 - on Monday 3 September. The significance of the date is that it is the anniversary of the sinking of the SS Athenia, the first British merchant vessel lost during World War II.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since January 2002 the UK registered trading fleet has increased from 5.03 to 16.64 million gross tons, an increase of over 230% over the past decade. The UK has the thirteenth largest Merchant Fleet in the world and the fifth largest in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The increase in tonnage on the UK shipping register has been achieved without compromising quality standards. The Maritime &amp;amp; Coastguard Agency (MCA) have appointed dedicated Customer Account Managers to assist with enquiries throughout the registration process. This - and removing excess regulation - has made the UK flag more attractive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tonnage tax was introduced in the Finance Act 2000. Shipping companies can opt into tonnage tax, or stay in the current corporate tax regime. Tonnage tax applies normal corporation tax to notional profits determined by the tonnage of the ships operated. It brings certainty and clarity about tax liabilities and is used by a number of other EEA countries, including Germany, the Netherlands, Greece and Norway. The tonnage tax is enabling British shipping to be more internationally competitive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A feature of the UK tonnage tax is the minimum training obligation. This normally requires each shipping company in the tax to recruit and train one officer trainee each year for every 15 officer posts in its fleet, and to give consideration to employment and training opportunities for ratings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Support for Maritime Training (SMarT) scheme has been running since April 1998 and provides financial support for courses approved by the Merchant Navy Training Board (MNTB) and the MCA for the training of officers and ratings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14204</id>
    <published>2012-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/alan-cook-reappointed-non-executive-chairman-of-highways-agency"/>
    <title>Alan Cook reappointed non-executive chairman of Highways Agency</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alan Cook has been reappointed by Transport Secretary Justine Greening as non-executive chairman of the Highways Agency Board for a further 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook, who was first appointed in January 2011, will focus on supporting the Transport Secretary’s ambitious programme for reforming the strategic road network while ensuring that the Agency continues to deliver its business against tough efficiency targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Penning, Minister for Roads said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a challenging time for the Highways Agency but I am confident that Alan Cook is the right person to work with Ministers towards achieving the Agency’s transformation into a more efficient, business-like and commercially-focused operator, which crucially does much more to listen and respond to the needs of road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His extensive experience will also help support the Agency in taking forward my roads reform agenda to improve how we operate, maintain and enhance our major roads which are the backbone of Britain, getting people to and from work, powering the economy and keeping families connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, the Transport Secretary published her response to Alan Cook’s independent review of the strategic road network. The Transport Secretary also set out ambitious plans to increase the quality and efficiency of the network, offering a better service to motorists and business users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook’s role will see him providing advice to senior staff and making sure the Agency delivers on changes identified in his independent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He will also offer advice on organisational change and provide views on alternative operating models which are currently being developed as part of a feasibility study announced by the Prime Minister in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cook said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I welcome the opportunity to continue in the role of chairman for a further 12 months in order to both assist with the crucially important feasibility study and also help the Agency mobilise its own change programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This programme will deliver the changes identified in the government’s response to my independent review with the aim of the Highways Agency becoming a best-in-class executive agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20110110/"&gt;press release announcing Alan Cook’s appointment as the first ever non-executive chairman of the Highways Agency&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Transport Secretary’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dft-press-20120524c"&gt;strategic road network reform announcement in May&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/publications/strategic-roads-network"&gt;Alan Cook’s report ‘A Fresh start for the Strategic Road Network’&lt;/a&gt; is available on both the Department’s and the Agency’s websites. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14243</id>
    <published>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/vehicle-identity-check-vic-scheme"/>
    <title>Vehicle Identity Check (VIC) scheme</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department has today published a consultation paper on the future of the Vehicle Identity Check (&lt;abbr title="Vehicle Identity Check"&gt;VIC&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the &lt;abbr title="Vehicle Identity Check"&gt;VIC&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme is to deter the crime of vehicle ringing. Typically, this involves the theft of a car often of significant value, which is then given the identity of a similar car (make, model, colour etc) which has been the subject of an insurance write-off. The written-off car is obtained cheaply; its identity (VIN and registration numbers) is then transferred to a higher value stolen car which, now apparently genuine, can be sold at market price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the introduction of the &lt;abbr title="Vehicle Identity Check"&gt;VIC&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme in April 2003, around 717,000 checks have been undertaken and 38 confirmed ‘ringers’ detected, at a cost of around £30 million to the motorist. About 75% of the checks were undertaken on cars which were 7 years or older, written-off because the cost of even small repairs was greater than the very low market value of the vehicle, often meaning that the cost of the check fell on the less well-off members of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is felt that the scheme has become, unintentionally, an unnecessary burden to many honest motorists, the police feel that it is still the only deterrent to ‘ringers’. The scheme also enables vehicle purchasers to be aware that the vehicle they are considering purchasing has previously been a write-off and confirms that the vehicle identity has been checked and therefore provides some protection against purchasing a stolen vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to consult on whether to retain, re-scope or abolish the scope of the &lt;abbr title="Vehicle Identity Check"&gt;VIC&lt;/abbr&gt; scheme in a move to explore whether fewer vehicles can be checked in the future in order to remove unnecessary burden on law-abiding citizens, without jeopardising prevention of vehicle ringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation documents can be found on the department’s website. An electronic copy has been lodged with the house library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="download-documents"&gt;Download documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-33/"&gt;Future of the Vehicle Identity Check (&lt;abbr title="Vehicle Identity Check"&gt;VIC&lt;/abbr&gt;) scheme, 17 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14899</id>
    <published>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/driver-and-vehicle-licensing-agency-dvla--4"/>
    <title>Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was an inadvertent error in the answer to the Parliamentary Question from Charles Kennedy on 9 July [115811], official report, column 69W. The answer indicated that Bangor, Beverley, Chester, Dundee, Exeter, Inverness, Maidstone, Peterborough, Sidcup, Theale, Truro, and Worcester local offices would close on 30 November 2012. The date should have read 30 November 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-links"&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dvla.gov.uk/"&gt;DVLA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16357</id>
    <published>2012-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/driver-and-vehicle-licensing-agency-dvla--5"/>
    <title>Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency (DVLA)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In December 2011, I launched a &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/dvla/consultations/response_to_transformation.aspx"&gt;full consultation around a programme of work to transform the way that the &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; delivers&lt;/a&gt; its services to customers. The consultation recognised the need to modernise the way these services are delivered and to respond to the growing demand for more flexible public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am announcing that &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will press ahead with its proposals to modernise its services. As a result of this decision the &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will centralise its enforcement operations by March 2013 and will close its 39 local offices by the end of 2013. While I recognise that a large number of respondents expressed concerns, I believe that many of these concerns can be mitigated and I am confident that this programme will result in modern, effective services delivering savings of £26 million each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also announcing that &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will work to ensure that customers in Northern Ireland have access to the full range of vehicle services available to the rest of the UK. This will include on-line taxing of vehicles and introducing additional benefits such as retaining registration marks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will build on its successes in electronic delivery by providing more transactions online. Local businesses will act as intermediaries to offer motorists more convenient access to certain &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; services through at least 4000 outlets nationwide compared to the current 39 &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; local offices. The &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will ensure that alternative service channels will be available before offices close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the concerns arising from the consultation related to issues around potential degradation of services and uncertainty over the alternative channels. The &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; has developed its proposals to address these concerns. Discussions with stakeholders have helped shape these proposals, which will provide the motor trade and individual motorists with a more efficient and effective service through a greater number of convenient, accessible channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to all those who engaged in the consultation process as their views have helped to develop the proposals in a way that can ensure customer needs are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I am publishing a package of documents, including an impact assessment and a formal response to the consultation. These documents provide more detail of the future services and will be available on the &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; website and in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am committed to maintaining or enhancing current service levels for all motorists and the &lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt; will continue to work with stakeholders to support their transition onto new channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-information"&gt;Related information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/dvla/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driver and Vehicle Licensing Agency"&gt;DVLA&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14831</id>
    <published>2012-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/local-authorities-given-further-support-to-make-roads-safer"/>
    <title>Local authorities given further support to make roads safer</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Updated speed limit guidance to help local authorities improve safety on their roads was published for consultation today by Road Safety Minister Mike Penning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance provides up-to-date advice to aid greater consistency of speed limits on local roads across England. It incorporates recent changes that have increased flexibility for local authorities to implement 20mph limits and zones where it can be shown that they benefit road safety and quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gives authorities more information about the new speed limit appraisal web tool which will help authorities fully assess the impact of any change to a speed limit in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is vital that speed limits are suitable for local conditions and councils are best placed to determine what these limits are, based on local knowledge and the views of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help, we are publishing updated guidance for consultation. This includes a number of initiatives we have introduced to improve road safety, including making it easier for local authorities and communities to put in place 20 mph schemes, or use common-sense measures such as variable speed limits outside schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Road safety is a top priority and the guidance - along with the speed limit appraisal web tool - will help councils make evidence based decisions to introduce local speed limits that reflect the needs of all road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revision of the guidance and the introduction of an economic tool to help authorities assess the full costs and benefits of any proposed schemes were a commitment in the Department for ‘Transport’s Strategic Framework for Road Safety’ published last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance is aimed at local authorities in England. The consultation document can be found here &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-32"&gt;http://www.dft.gov.uk/consultations/dft-2012-32&lt;/a&gt;. The final guidance is expected to be published by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web tool, also to be launched later this year, is being developed with input from road safety groups and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This guidance is to be used for setting all local speed limits on single and dual carriageway roads in both urban and rural areas. Local traffic authorities are responsible for determining speed limits on the local road network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The objectives of this guidance are: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the provision of up-to-date and consistent advice to traffic authorities;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;improved clarity which will aid greater consistency of speed limits across the country;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enabling the setting of more appropriate local speed limits, including lower or higher limits where conditions dictate;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;achieving local speed limits that better reflect the needs of all road users, not just motorised vehicles;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ensuring improved quality of life for local communities and a better balance between road safety, accessibility and environmental objectives, especially in rural communities;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;improved recognition and understanding by road users of the risks involved on different types of road, the speed limits that apply, and the reasons why;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;improved respect for speed limits, and in turn improved compliance; and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;continued reductions in the number of road traffic collisions, injuries and deaths in which excessive or inappropriate speed is a contributory factor.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The key factors that are taken into account in any decisions on local speed limits are: 
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;history of collisions, including frequency, severity, types and causes;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;road geometry and engineering (e.g. bends, junctions, barriers);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;presence of vulnerable road users;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;road function;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;existing traffic speeds; and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;road environment, including level of road-side development and possible impacts on residents (e.g. severance, noise, or air quality).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are not seeking views in this consultation on the national limits of 30mph on street lit roads, 60mph on single carriageway roads and 70mph on dual carriageways and motorways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14420</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/taking-testing-to-the-customer"/>
    <title>Taking testing to the customer</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year I asked the Driving Standards Agency (DSA) to consider arrangements for delivering practical car driving tests from premises other than traditional driving test centres such as local authority buildings or leisure centres to provide a more local service for candidates. On 27 March 2012 I announced to the House the next steps of that programme. I also informed the House that we would be seeking public and private organisations to work in partnership with the DSA to identify and provide locations from which the practical car test could be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to report that real progress has been made and there are proposals being developed for partnerships with Halfords Group PLC and Mantra Learning Limited. Subject to working agreements being finalised and suitable premises with driving test routes being identified, driving tests should be delivered, in the locations I have already announced, from premises of these organisations in the near future. These will be non exclusive arrangements and DSA may, in future, consider other partnering agreements to provide premises, which meet its criteria. Local agreements with the fire and rescue service, particularly in areas not otherwise covered, are also being explored and there have also been discussions with several universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Significantly this use of property will be provided at no cost to DSA. Tests will continue to be conducted by DSA examiners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSA will evaluate the success of these arrangements and I will keep the House informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/press-releases/dsa-press-20120710a"&gt;Driving tests brought closer to home with partnership deal, press release, 10 July 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13319</id>
    <published>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/driving-tests-brought-closer-to-home-with-partnership-deal"/>
    <title>Driving tests brought closer to home with partnership deal</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as using traditional driving test centres, the Driving Standards Agency (&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;) is looking at working with public and private sector partners to provide driving test premises in selected areas that don’t already have a local test centre. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; began exploring a new approach to test delivery last year, offering tests from premises such as local authority buildings and leisure centres. In March this year the agency announced plans to extend the scheme to 21 more locations, and invited proposals from businesses and other organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; has now selected Halfords plc as a preferred partner, and is also exploring partnerships with the Fire and Rescue Service and several universities. In one location the agency also expects to sign an agreement with training company Mantra Learning Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partners will allow the use of their premises at no cost to &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and tests will continue to be conducted by &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; examiners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Penning, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is vital that public services are as open and accessible as possible. This initiative is a great example of how working with partners in the public and private sectors can help to ensure that we offer people the best possible service wherever they live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim is to provide all driving test candidates with a local service that is convenient as well as being cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Wild, Halfords CEO, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We want to help motorists wherever we can, so we look forward to working in partnership with &lt;abbr title="Driving Standards Agency"&gt;DSA&lt;/abbr&gt; to provide a first class service for drivers taking their tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme focuses on 21 locations, centred around 5 different areas across the country (Glasgow, Kettering, Manchester, Watford and Worcestershire). Testing from partner premises in these locations is expected to start from the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These arrangements apply to practical car tests; other types of test and theory test centres will not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14178</id>
    <published>2012-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/15m-boost-to-improve-cycle-accident-hotspots"/>
    <title>£15m boost to improve cycle accident hotspots</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A further £15m funding to tackle dangerous junctions for cyclists across the country was &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/news/statements/baker-20120626a"&gt;announced today by Transport Ministers Norman Baker and Mike Penning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment - for use by English local authorities outside London - is in addition to the £15m awarded to Transport for London in March to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured. This has already delivered improvements at a number of sites in the capital with other junctions set to benefit over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities will need to submit bids to the Department for Transport for a share of the latest fund. We will also be looking to the local authorities themselves to contribute further money, in order to maximise the work that can be undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am delighted to be able to provide today a further £15m to improve cycle safety, by enabling local authorities to tackle proven dangerous junctions. This investment - alongside a number of other initiatives we have progressed - will make our roads a safer place for everyone using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a fantastic way of getting fit, reducing congestion and improving the environment, and cyclist safety matters hugely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the new fund were being outlined today to the department’s Cycling Forum, which includes cycling, motoring, and road safety groups, who have been working together to find ways to improve cycle safety. The department will now work in partnership with local authorities and the forum to identify the most important junctions to have safety improvements. This process will use analysis of accident data to highlight potential sites for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions on how the money will be allocated are likely to be announced in the Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment is the latest government action to improve cycling safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department is already giving £1.8 billion of funding to local councils enabling them to design solutions appropriate to their local transport challenges, including improving their road infrastructure to encourage and support cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the vast majority of projects being funded under the department’s £560 million Local Sustainable Transport Fund contain a cycling element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers recently announced a new allocation of £15 million for better cycle routes and facilities across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department has also made it simpler for councils to put in place 20mph zones and limits, and install Trixi mirrors to improve the visibility of cyclists at junctions, by reducing bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Members of the Cycling Forum’s Safety Group include: Association of Chief Police Officers, Bike Right!, British Cycling, Campaign to Protect Rural England (CPRE), CTC - the UK’s national cyclists’ organisation, Cyclenation, Department for Transport, Freight Transport Association, Institute of Advanced Motorists, London Cycling Campaign, Mineral Products Association, Parliamentary Advisory Council for Transport Safety (PACTS), Road Haulage Association, Transport for London and Sustrans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/13320</id>
    <published>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-to-protect-learner-drivers"/>
    <title>New powers to protect learner drivers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the current legislation, it takes a minimum of 45 days to prevent an instructor from continuing to give paid driving instruction. However, from 13 July, the Registrar of Approved Driving Instructors will have the power to immediately suspend the registration or trainee licence of an instructor who presents a significant danger to the safety of the public. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road Safety Minister Mike Penning said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Driving instructors play a vital role in helping to ensure Britain’s roads remain among the safest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The vast majority of instructors meet the extremely high standards we require of them, but in the very rare cases where an instructor presents a significant danger to the public, it is right that we take prompt and effective action to protect learners and other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The registrar is likely to exercise the suspension power in cases where instructors have been convicted of a violent or sexual offence or are delivering tuition of a dangerously low standard, while the formal removal or revocation processes are being completed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="right-of-appeal"&gt;Right of appeal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructors retain the right of appeal against a decision to remove them from the register of approved driving instructors or to revoke their trainee licence. The instructor will be able to apply for compensation in respect of the period of suspension if they are not subsequently removed from the register.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?r.i=1097573028&amp;amp;r.l1=1081597476&amp;amp;r.l2=1082103262&amp;amp;r.l3=1084755704&amp;amp;r.l4=1082104385&amp;amp;r.l5=1097571587&amp;amp;r.s=m&amp;amp;r.t=RESOURCES&amp;amp;topicId=1097571587"&gt;Being suspended as an approved driving instructor (&lt;abbr title="Approved driving instructor"&gt;ADI&lt;/abbr&gt;): Business Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
