<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/nick-boles</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/nick-boles.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Nick Boles MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65293</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T10:27:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T10:27:38+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/communities-to-receive-cash-boost-for-choosing-development"/>
    <title>Communities to receive cash boost for choosing development</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles announces new cash incentives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communities that tackle the legacy of inadequate house-building and choose to accept new housing will benefit directly from new generous cash incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods that take a proactive approach by drawing up a neighbourhood development plan, and securing the consent of local people in a referendum, will receive 25% of the revenues from the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; arising from the development that they choose to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cash boost will be paid directly to parish and town councils and can be used to back the community’s priorities for example to re-roof a village hall, refurbish a municipal pool or take over a community pub. Neighbourhoods without a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood development plan&lt;/a&gt; but where the levy is still charged will still receive a capped 15% share of the levy revenue arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities without a parish or town council will still benefit from this incentive, with the local planning authority retaining it and spending it in accordance with the wishes of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of hectoring people and forcing development on communities, the government believes that we need to persuade communities that development is in everyone’s interest. Incentives are key to getting the homes built that we both need for today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital this country increases the number of homes it builds to meet the needs of its increasing population. The failure of previous administrations to build enough homes, latterly despite the credit boom, led to a severe housing shortage that has been made worse by the rapid increase in the number of households. The number of people living alone has rocketed, and immigration has led to an influx of 1.7 million people into England in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to tackle this housing shortage and make best use of what we already have the government has invested £160 million to deal with the 250,000 homes empty for more than 6 months - 50,000 fewer then in 2009. This money combined with a share of £300 million announced in September’s housing growth package, will help put more than 15,000 empty homes back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has also made clear that planning should encourage the effective use of land, including brownfield land that is not of high environmental value. The majority of all new homes - 76% of those completed in 2010 - were built on brownfield land. But this will not be enough and some undeveloped land will need to be made available for house-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have a simple choice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. We can shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or we can accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land and resolve that we will make these decisions locally and build beautiful places like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This government is determined to persuade communities to accept more house-building by giving them a tangible share of the benefits it brings. By undertaking a neighbourhood plan that makes space for new development, communities can secure revenues to make the community more attractive for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neighbourhood planning is an important way to make sure that development has the backing of the community. It is right that the areas that have organised themselves to bring forward a neighbourhood plan and have taken the plan through all the stages of the neighbourhood planning (including a successful examination and referendum) should be rewarded for their positive, pro-active approach to delivering growth. This is why they are entitled to an extra 10% of the levy arising from development in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy amount passed to neighbourhoods reflects the rates the local planning authority set for the levy. These charge a rate or different rates for development in the local area in pounds per square metre. The neighbourhood funding element will be calculated based on the levy receipts from the relevant development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The levy’s charges will become due from the date that a chargeable development is commenced. The neighbourhood funding element will be passed to parish or community councils in accordance with a timetable agreed between the local planning authority and the local council.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the money is transferred to a parish council (in England) or a community council (in Wales) they will decide how the money will be spent - although they will be expected to work with the local planning authority. Where the money stays with the local planning authority (in areas without a parish or community council) the local planning authority will engage with the communities where the development has happened to agree how best to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In areas that have not been subject to neighbourhood planning there will be a cap of £100 per council tax dwelling on the neighbourhood funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We aim to have these incentives in place from Spring 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We previously &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;consulted&lt;/a&gt; on allowing councils the choice whether to spend their levy receipts on affordable housing but given other ongoing policies to support housing, we are not proposing to make this change at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also going to enable a mayoral development corporation to impose a Community Infrastructure Levy charge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65346</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T16:27:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/housing-the-next-generation"/>
    <title>Housing the next generation</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>Speech by Planning Minister Nick Boles at an event hosted by Policy Exchange.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;[This version of the speech excludes party political content].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last September, the Prime Minister declared that our mission is “to build an ‘aspiration nation’”, in which we “get behind people who want to get on in life.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s what’s always made our hearts beat faster,” he said. “It’s not just an economic mission” - but “a moral one” too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to that speech as one of David Cameron’s newest and most junior ministers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, though I find the Prime Minister’s message inspiring, implicit in it was a challenge that keeps me awake at night. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No aspiration is more deeply embedded in the British psyche than the desire to own your own home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the prospect of doing so has been slipping ever further out of the reach of millions of hard-working people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a result of our decades-long failure to build enough houses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the root cause of that is our decades-long refusal to release enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are other problems affecting the housing market in the short term: most of all, the lack of finance for buyers and developers since the credit crunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These the government is already tackling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/helping-people-to-buy-a-home/supporting-pages/help-for-first-time-buyers"&gt;FirstBuy&lt;/a&gt;, which helps reduce the deposit first-time buyers need to find to just 5% of the price of their new home, will invest £460 million, matched by housebuilders, to help 27,000 people by 2014. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/newbuy-guarantee-scheme"&gt;NewBuy&lt;/a&gt; enables other households to access 95% mortgages for new build homes, and the Prime Minister announced on Monday that we will bring forward further measures to increase the availability of affordable mortgages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my colleague, Mark Prisk, is deploying £570 million in the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/get-britain-building"&gt;Get Britain Building fund&lt;/a&gt; to get building going on sites that already have planning permission, and using the £225 million fund that the Deputy Prime Minister announced to accelerate the delivery of housing on large sites like Cranbrook in Devon and Ebbsfleet in Kent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the long term, the original source of our housing crisis is the failure of past governments to provide enough land for development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As planning minister, it is my job to persuade local authorities to make more land available so that more homes can be built and the price of new homes comes down - and thereby reverse the trend that has been heading in the wrong direction for decades. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now can you understand why I sleep a little uneasily?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2011 census revealed that, in the ‘noughties’, home ownership in England fell, for the first time in 60 years: from 68% to 63%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because houses became too expensive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homelessness charity, Shelter, has shown that if the price of food had risen as fast as the price of housing in the last 30 years, a supermarket chicken would now cost £47 - and a jar of instant coffee would cost £20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, the average person setting aside 5% of their income each week could save up for a deposit on a house after 8 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it would take the same person 47 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some say that this trend is inevitable, given a growing population, rising incomes and a finite supply of land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Germany real house prices have remained constant since 2000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the Netherlands, which has shared the UK’s rapid growth in population, real house prices rose by a little bit more than a fifth in the same decade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did they nearly double in the UK? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve built too few houses to keep up with the rapid increase in the number of households needing a place to live, especially the dizzying increase in the number of people living on their own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons for this growth in the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some we should celebrate - like the fact that people are living longer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others we should regret - like the high rate of divorce or the immigration policies that led to a net influx of 1.7 million people into England in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of these changes have happened and all of the people concerned have the right to a decent home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, Shelter estimated that we would need to build 240,000 new homes a year in England to cater for all of these new households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2012, Alan Holmans from the Cambridge Centre for Housing and Planning Research updated these estimates using my department’s publication of new projections of the number of households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concluded, that, to keep pace with this trend, we now need to build 270,000 new homes a year, leading to a net increase of 250,000 a year as 20,000 of them would replace existing homes that have to be demolished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether Mr Holman’s projections will prove accurate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do know that the house-building that took place during the ‘noughties’ fell woefully short of what was necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a decade of easy credit and an explicit target to build 213,000 new homes a year in England, an annual average of only 147,000 new homes were completed between 2000 and 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same period the population went up by 3.4 million and, from 1998 to 2008, the number of households went up by 1.7 million. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, in each year of the ‘noughties’, the Netherlands built over 4.4 new homes for every 1,000 inhabitants and the French built over 5.6 for every 1,000 inhabitants. In England, we built just 2.9. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in spite the fact that, between 2000 and 2010, total mortgage debt in the UK more than doubled - from £500 billion to £1.2 trillion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because this debt just fuelled a massive boom in prices - and did little to boost the supply of new homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those homes that were built got smaller and smaller, as land prices went up and up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2001 to 2003 the new houses we built in England were smaller than the ones we’ve already got - and 30% smaller than the new houses being built in the Netherlands, a country that is more densely populated than ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For housing, as in so many areas of our national life, the ‘noughties’ were a wasted decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loads of money sloshing around, lots of top-down targets, but very little to show for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we have to build even more houses to make up the ground lost and to keep pace with future growth in the number of households needing homes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s assuming we continue to tighten our grip on immigration so that net migration falls below 100,000 a year by 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I do really understand why the idea of a lot more house-building makes people nervous. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I certainly don’t want to see more open land developed than is absolutely necessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately there is no painless way to make homes affordable for working people earning ordinary wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the empty homes?” people ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they are certainly right to suggest that we should make full use of our &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/empty-homes"&gt;existing housing stock&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most empty homes are only empty for short periods while they change hands or are renovated or are caught up in probate after the last owner’s death. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are around 259,000 houses that have been empty for more than 6 months, 50,000 fewer than in 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has already invested £160 million and that, together with a share of the £300 million additional spending announced in September’s &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/plan-to-boost-british-housebuilding-jobs-and-the-economy"&gt;Housing Growth Package&lt;/a&gt;, should help put over 15,000 empty properties back into use by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to see good homes standing empty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can’t make more than a marginal contribution to the hundreds of thousands of new homes that we need every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What about all the brownfield land?” people then ask - and they point to the Campaign to Protect Rural England (&lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt;) estimate that England has enough brownfield land to support 1.5 million homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to maximise the number of homes we build on previously developed land - not least because such land tends to benefit from existing links to our road and rail networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even the &lt;abbr title="Campaign to Protect Rural England"&gt;CPRE&lt;/abbr&gt; admitted that we would only get 450,000 new homes out of brownfield sites in those parts of the country where most of the new homes are needed - London, the South East and the South West. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And achieving that number would require us to build on every scrap of brownfield land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that we are already building most new homes on brownfield land: 76% of all the homes completed in 2010 as against 56% in 1997. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simply can’t squeeze much more out of brownfield sites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To restrict new house-building to brownfield land would leave us a long way short of the number of new homes we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So “what about the developers’ land banks?” people then ask. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, I do understand why it riles people that their local councils have to find new sites for development, when the major house-builders are sitting on land with permission to build hundreds of thousands of new homes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m afraid this concern is also misplaced, resting on a misunderstanding about how the British house-building industry works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of September 2012, on sites of 10 or more units, there were 487,000 units with detailed planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 246,000 of them were on sites where no building has even started - and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; that I am taking through Parliament with colleagues will make it easier for developers to renegotiate the unaffordable Section 106 agreements that have made many of these schemes unviable and caused them to stall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most sites with planning permission are for schemes of 150 units or more which developers generally build out over 3 to 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are going to have any prospect of getting our current house-builders to build the number of new homes we need, we need them to have a pipeline of sites representing 3 to 5 years’ supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s over a million units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with developers’ land banks is not that they exist - but that they are currently much too small to feed the level of house-building that we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am afraid that we have a simple choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can decide to ignore the misery of young families forced to grow up in tiny flats with no outside space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can pass by on the other side while working men and women in their twenties and thirties have to live with their parents or share bedrooms with friends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can turn a blind eye while the dream of a property-owning democracy shrivels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shrug our shoulders as home ownership reverts to what it was in the 19th Century: a privilege, the exclusive preserve of people with large incomes or wealthy parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t believe that anyone really wants to go down that road. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we believe in anything, we believe in the power of home ownership to motivate people to work hard, raise strong families and build healthy communities, to put down roots, take responsibility for their surroundings and look out for their neighbours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Cameron said, “We get behind people who want to get on in life, the young people who dream of their first pay-cheque, their first car, their first home - and are ready and willing to work hard to get those things.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to accept that we are going to have to build on previously undeveloped land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to resolve that we will make these decisions locally, and that we will build beautiful places like we used to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That way England can remain the green and pleasant land we all love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start from a good position. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, contrary to media myth, we’ve got plenty of undistinguished, undeveloped land to spare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By overlaying satellite imagery onto Ordnance Survey maps, the Centre for Ecology and Hydrology’s 2007 Land Cover Map shows that 8.9% of England is built up or developed as gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that over 90% is not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty together account for around 30% - more than 3 times the amount that is built on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we include the green belts that stop our cities sprawling without limit then that goes up to around 40% of England is protected from development - more than 4 times the area that is built on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are ancient woodlands and other irreplaceable habitats which are protected by the National Planning Policy Framework, and other important sites which lie outside the official designations, that are rightly championed by organisations like the &lt;abbr title="Royal Society for the Protection of Birds"&gt;RSPB&lt;/abbr&gt; and the Woodland Trust. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is high quality agricultural land which all of us want to see used for the essential purpose of growing food. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are much loved open spaces in villages and towns, which local people understandably want to keep intact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done will undermine the protection of National Parks, Sites of Special Scientific Interest, Areas of Outstanding Natural Beauty and the green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or stop good agricultural land being used for farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or prevent councils from identifying ancient woodland and green spaces that local people want them to protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And nothing that I have said and nothing that this government has done involves telling communities how many new houses they should accept or where they should be built. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional top-down housing targets caused enormous resentment and as we have seen failed to deliver the goods - house-building has fallen to its lowest peacetime level since the 1920s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have already revoked the regional strategy for the East of England. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, having considered the responses to the consultation on the environmental report, I can announce today that I have decided to revoke the equivalent edict for Yorkshire and the Humber while saving the policies to protect York’s green belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making decisions about the other regional strategies in due course, once the consultations on &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-communities-and-local-government/series/strategic-environmental-assessments"&gt;other environmental reports&lt;/a&gt; have closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the localism that Eric Pickles has unleashed is not and never has been a one-way street. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has always said, with power comes responsibility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/making-the-planning-system-work-more-efficiently-and-effectively/supporting-pages/national-planning-policy-framework"&gt;National Planning Policy Framework&lt;/a&gt; spells it out very clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they draw up their local plans, councils must assess their local housing need in an objective way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they must identify immediately developable sites sufficient to supply all of the new homes that are needed over the next 5 years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, many councils are embracing this duty with energy and imagination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some are dragging their feet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a few are looking for ways to evade their responsibilities - or slough them off onto their neighbours because the politics of house-building is just too difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is not acceptable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils which do not produce credible plans to meet local housing need will find that the presumption in favour of sustainable development will trump local decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they will have to explain to local residents why their failure to produce a robust local plan exposed their communities to speculative development in places where it is not welcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not defend and the government will not support those local councils who abdicate their responsibility to meet their fair share of our common housing needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to pretend that it will be easy for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillors will have to find a way to persuade the people who elect them that substantial further house-building is in the interest of the whole community, including those who are living there now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are giving them the tools they need to go about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that people want is input into the plans for development in their neighbourhood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not just perfunctory consultation that is acknowledged but then ignored. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But real involvement and a vote on the outcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve created the option of a &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;neighbourhood plan&lt;/a&gt;, which is drawn up by representatives of a defined community and subject to a referendum of all their neighbours, before it can be adopted and form part of the statutory plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;300 localities are already pursuing a neighbourhood plan - from Thame in South Oxfordshire to St James’ ward in central Exeter to central Milton Keynes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailblazer is Upper Eden in Cumbria, where I was on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their neighbourhood plan will be the first to be put to the test in a local referendum in March of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing people want, aside from local input and local control, is a share in the benefits that new development can bring, whether that takes the form of a boost in the local authority’s tax revenues or an investment in new community facilities or better infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s why we’ve introduced the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/increasing-the-number-of-available-homes/supporting-pages/new-homes-bonus"&gt;New Homes Bonus&lt;/a&gt; that gives local councils over £8,000 over 6 years for every new Council Tax Band D home that gets built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils received £430 million in New Homes Bonus in 2012 to 2013 and are provisionally set to receive £660 million in 2013 to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need incentives, as Policy Exchange has pointed out, that are even more local - so that the people who have to live with new housing developments get a direct benefit from them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I am pleased to be able to announce that in areas that charge the new &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-communities-more-power-in-planning-local-development/supporting-pages/community-infrastructure-levy"&gt;Community Infrastructure Levy&lt;/a&gt; neighbourhoods which accept new development will get 15% of the revenues from the Levy (up to a maximum of £100 per existing household).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because I believe, and this government believes, that neighbourhood plans are the key to unlocking more house-building, those communities that draw up a neighbourhood plan and have it approved by local people in a referendum will receive 25% of these revenues with no upper limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to re-roof your village hall, build a permanent home for your community shop, refurbish the municipal swimming pool, implement a new landscape design in your local park or save your local pub, look no further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jump on the bandwagon and get yourself a neighbourhood plan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government believes in localism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that if you give people power, they will use it responsibly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you explain to them what their community and their country needs, they will do their bit to make sure it is provided. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you give them a stake in a future in which beautifully designed homes with easy access to green space are, once again affordable for working people on ordinary wages, they will do what it takes to bring that future about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my perch on the lower branches at the Department for Communities and Local Government, I look around the great wood that is the British government and I see other ministers battering away at the barriers that hold people back with gusto and grit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iain Duncan Smith reforming the benefits system to ensure that work always pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gove giving schools control over their own destinies while ramping up expectations of the standards that they will achieve for their students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are an inspiration and a goad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inspiration because they are ministers who have identified a shocking injustice in the way our society works and are fearless in their determination to “spread the privilege” of a good education and a decent job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A goad because we are more than half way through this Parliament, and it’s now up to me to make sure that our reformed planning system provides enough land to build the houses that England’s next generation so desperately needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it does, I’m sure I will have no problem sleeping at nights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60950</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T13:56:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-practice-guidance-should-be-simpler"/>
    <title>Planning practice guidance should be simpler</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An external review of planning practice guidance has recommended rationalising advice and making it easier to use.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review group, led by Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; practice guidance that explains statutory provisions, planning and the planning system but did not review planning policy. They were not tasked with revaluating green belt policy or other countryside protections, which continue to be safeguarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that the existing guidance is unwieldy in its current form and recommends that it be shorter but retain key elements, and be more accessible to be useful to everyone using the planning system. They stated that guidance is important to ensuring planning decisions are properly informed but should not place undue burdens on users of the planning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group found that a vast range of materials are being considered guidance, and that ‘living documents’ intended to be updated on a regular basis had not been amended since publication.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;consultation&lt;/a&gt; to consider the group’s recommendations was launched today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Taylor said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is very clear that the old way of doing things is no longer fit for purpose. We have made recommendations for a modern web-based resource that is clear, up-to-date, coherent and easily usable, not just by planners and developers, but the public too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very grateful to the group for all the work they have done on this. We will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and I would urge other users of the planning system to have their say by responding to the consultation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review group consists of Simon Marsh, Andrew Whitaker, Trudi Elliott and Councillor Mike Jones. They are sitting as individuals and not representatives of their respective organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/external-review-of-government-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;External review of government planning practice guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/review-of-planning-practice-guidance"&gt;Review of planning practice guidance - consultation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew Taylor, Lord Taylor of Goss Moor, was author of the Taylor Review of Planning (Rural Economy and Affordable Housing - Living Working Countryside, 2008). He is chairman of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.housing.org.uk/"&gt;National Housing Federation&lt;/a&gt; which represents 1,100 housing associations across England, chairman of the St Austell Eco-Town Strategic Partnership and was, until recently, founder Chair of the Rural Coalition (representing 14 national organisations interested in the sustainable development of rural communities). He was MP for Truro and St Austell for 24 years from 1987, until he stood down at the 2010 general election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Marsh from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rspb.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Society for the Protection of Birds&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew Whitaker from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hbf.co.uk/"&gt;Home Builders Federation&lt;/a&gt;, Trudi Elliott from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.rtpi.org.uk/"&gt;Royal Town Planning Institute&lt;/a&gt; and Councillor Mike Jones, Leader of &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.cheshirewestandchester.gov.uk/"&gt;Cheshire West and Chester Council&lt;/a&gt; are sitting independently and not representing their organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57133</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T14:24:21+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-cash-backing-more-communities-to-put-neighbourhood-plans-together"/>
    <title>New cash backing more communities to put neighbourhood plans together</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning Minister Nick Boles has announced a new multi-million pound cash boost to help more communities.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash will help more communities take centre stage in planning the shape, look and feel of their local area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/giving-people-more-power-over-what-happens-in-their-neighbourhood/supporting-pages/neighbourhood-planning"&gt;Neighbourhood planning&lt;/a&gt; gives people a major say in shaping development in their area. It gives communities the power to help decide where development should go including the type and design of development that they want to allow planning permission for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 2 years local planning authorities will benefit from up to £17 million to help communities turn the vision for the future of their local area into a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January local planning authorities will be able to claim grants of up to £50,000 to help up to 10 communities get going with their neighbourhood plans. From April this will be extended even further making £100,000 available to kick start up to 20 plans in the area. Authorities will then receive a further £25,000 for every neighbourhood plan that gets through a successful examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 300 communities are already using the new powers introduced in the Localism Act to work up plans for neighbourhood areas that decide, for example, the location of new homes or what green spaces communities to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning Minister Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Communities across the country are showing real enthusiasm for neighbourhood planning and taking up the powers we gave them to get directly involved in making - this is in stark contrast to the top down only decisions we saw before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The new financial support we are making available today to councils will enable them to open up neighbourhood planning so that even more communities can turn paper plans into the realities of prospering neighborhoods that are growing and developing in the ways they want to see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From 2 January local planning authorities are able to claim up to a maximum of £50,000 (up from £20,000) for area designations this financial year up to a maximum of 10. There is an overall limit of £1.5 million on designation payments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes from 1 April 2013 -  local planning authorities will be able to claim for up to 20 designations (£100,000) in the financial year 2013 to 2014. The overall limit for designation payments in 2013 to 2014 has been set at £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, local planning authorities can claim up to £30,000 for each neighbourhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first payment of £5,000 will be made following designation of a neighbourhood area recognising the officer time supporting and advising the community in taking forward a neighbourhood plan. The second payment of £5,000 will be made when the local planning authority publicises the neighbourhood plan prior to examination. The third payment of £20,000 will be made on successful completion of the neighbourhood planning examination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This money recognises the duties that local authorities have in relation to neighbourhood planning. These are to: provide advice and assistance; to hold an examination; and to make arrangements for a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about neighbourhood planning visit the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://mycommunityrights.org.uk/neighborhood-planning/" title="My Community Rights"&gt;My Community Rights website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/56622</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T15:13:20+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/guidance-will-help-support-development-and-get-infrastructure-built"/>
    <title>Guidance will help support development and get infrastructure built</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Updated guidance will ensure the Community Infrastructure Levy is effective in supporting development and getting key infrastructure built. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidance has been revised with the active participation of councils and developers to provide certainty on key issues. It has been updated to reflect reforms to the planning system and will help councils looking to introduce the levy, as well as providing clarity to those paying the levy about how it works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/community-infrastructure-levy-guidance"&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; ensures there is no double charging to developers by clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidance reflects existing best practice and ensures councils in the process of developing proposals do not need to start their levy setting process from the beginning. Support will be available to councils who choose to review their levy as a result of the new guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ensures a robust evidence base is used for assessing levy rates and provides advice on the 2012 regulations that improve the operation of the levy. The guidance also makes clear that there is no obligation for councils to charge the levy, and that they can set a low or zero rate if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Government has worked actively with councils and developers to get this guidance right and make clear how we expect the levy to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The guidance ensures that councils who have already adopted their levy will not need to do anything new and only councils developing levy rates will need to consider this new guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government will continue to listen to issues being raised, such as the need for greater clarity at an earlier stage on how the levy will be spent. We will also be considering the suggestion to move the 2014 date when councils will be limited in their use of pooled Section 106 planning obligations for infrastructure that can be funded by the levy. The government expects to consult on further regulatory changes in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community Infrastructure Levy has the potential to raise an estimated £1 billion a year of funding by 2016 to support growth locally. It gives councils more choice and flexibility in how they fund the infrastructure that their communities want and need, and provides developers with much more ‘up front’ certainty about the amount of money they will be expected to contribute for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Peace from the British Property Federation said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The development industry has raised a number of concerns about the Community Infrastructure Levy. We have been closely involved in the development of this document and are pleased that it clearly sets out what local authorities must do when they are looking to charge the levy. These revisions should help support development by ensuring the levy is being implemented effectively. We look forward to continuing our work with the department on other Community Infrastructure Levy issues next year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councillor Mike Jones, Leader, Cheshire West and Chester Council said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Councils are keen to continue work with the development industry in a positive and productive way that enables much needed development to take place in a way that is fair and equitable to developers and to local people. Discussions on the Community Infrastructure Levy have been conducted in this spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home Builders Federation Executive Chairman Stewart Baseley said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have been closely involved in the process to improve the Community Infrastructure Levy guidance. We are pleased that it assists in clarifying the relationship between the levy and Section 106 planning obligations and sets out the importance of robust evidence and transparency when deciding on levy rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="further-information"&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government recently introduced changes to ensure planning applicants no longer face the threat of being double charged the Community Infrastructure Levy. Applicants will be able to amend planning conditions on existing consents (via a Section 73 planning application) without having to pay another levy on the same development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17243</id>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-29T12:33:36+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/town-and-country-planning-association-conference-speech"/>
    <title>Town and Country Planning Association conference speech</title>
    <category>Speech</category>
    <summary>This is a speech delivered by Planning Minister Nick Boles about beautiful urban landscapes and affordable homes.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;England is famous for the beauty of its landscapes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Yorkshire Dales to the South Hams, from the Weald of Kent to the Cumbrian Lakes, England glories in countryside of which generations of man and nature are joint authors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes - together with the greater drama of their Celtic cousins - that draw visitors to these islands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is these landscapes that our most popular institution and your sister organisation, the National Trust, was set up to preserve in perpetuity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of England is its finest asset and, for each of us, our most precious inheritance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative in both name and spirit, as a West Country boy and a Lincolnshire MP, as the son of a former director general of the National Trust and the brother of 1 of its conservation managers, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that nothing would do more to improve the health and happiness of the British people than if more of them got to spend more of their lives surrounded by beauty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty lifts, calms, excites, inspires.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more intoxicating than any narcotic, more soothing than any therapy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Britain becomes more prosperous, we must insist that it becomes more beautiful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the beauty we seek, and the landscapes we treasure, are not only to be found in our open spaces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the loveliest scenery in Britain is to be found in our villages, cities and towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take you on a journey, which starts in my constituency.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, the river Welland has snaked its way through the low contours of Lincolnshire from its source in Northamptonshire’s Hothorpe Hills.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enters Lincolnshire at the point where 4 counties meet and passes through countryside that is pleasant but hardly memorable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wandering painter or poet would not give this stretch of the Welland valley a second look, were it not for the landscape of Lincolnshire limestone that is the town of Stamford.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is not just 1 of England’s most beautiful towns; it is 1 of its finest bits of scenery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man-made. Built from stone and timber frames and slate.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the aesthetic equal of our most splendid hills, lakes and rivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did this landscape come from?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it spring fully formed from the mind of some 17th century master planner, the brainchild of a Lincolnshire Haussman?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford is, as the Royal Commission for Historic Monuments pronounced, ‘a town of discrete buildings’, each 1 unique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earls of Exeter from nearby Burghley House provided long leases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the local community of wool, leather, cloth and hemp merchants, apothecaries and solicitors indulged themselves with a great variety of stone window surrounds, doorways, eaves, corner and chimney details.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did so within a broad set of rules set out in the London manuals of Rome educated James Gibbs but almost always used local architects and builders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stamford was the spontaneous product of human initiative, haphazardly executed and totally unplanned, motivated by the desire for profit, the love of God and that age-old urge that keeps makeover shows in business, the desire to make your house nicer than your neighbours’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop is north of the border, in Great Britain’s first New Town.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by contrast, was an example of municipal town planning at its boldest and most inspired.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the economic stagnation into which Edinburgh had slipped after the Act of Union, in 1752 the Provost, George Drummond, launched an architectural competition to design a new cityscape of wide streets, crescents and squares, featuring symmetrical terraces of town-houses as well as purpose-built shops and public gardens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-six year old James Craig won the competition and, in 4 stages between the 1760s and the 1850s, he, Robert Adam, William Chambers and William Playfair all stayed loyal to the original vision and developed their own variations on a Greek revival theme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In building their New Town, Edinburgh’s town councillors not only restored commercial and cultural vigour to Scotland’s capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also created 1 of the most beautiful landscapes in the British Isles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who can resist the melancholy charm of a walk in the rain around Charlotte Square and through Ainslie Place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would wager that the Facebook pages of recent visitors to Scotland contain at least as many photographs of Bute House and Moray Place as they do of Loch Lomond or Glencoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Stamford in the early 1600s, and in Edinburgh 150 later, beauty came about as a result of the natural human urge to get together with one’s neighbours to build a place in which it would be a pleasure to live and work, to raise a family and do business.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the same generous set of instincts that, another hundred and fifty years later, inspired Ebenezer Howard to build Letchworth Garden City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I am skating on very thin ice telling members of the Town and Country Planning Association anything about the Garden City movement, when your association was founded to promote just that.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do want take a moment, as a layman, lacking all planning qualifications, to say why, like the Prime Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister, I believe that we have so much to learn from Ebenezer Howard and his garden cities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genius of Letchworth, like so many of the most appealing towns and cities, lies as much in the spaces between the buildings as in the buildings themselves.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By resisting the temptation to cram as many houses as possible onto the available land and adopting their golden rule of twelve houses to the acre, Letchworth’s architects, Barry Parker and Raymond Unwin allowed room for the organic intermingling of nature and architecture.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buildings are buttressed by front and back gardens, the roads are lined with broad verges and trees, the town is criss-crossed with footpaths and patchworked with allotments and parks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ebenezer Howard himself put it, “Parks and gardens, orchards and woods, are being planted in the midst of the busy life of the people, so that they can be enjoyed in the fullest measure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letchworth and the other garden cities work as living, breathing urban communities because, as an Ebenezer Howard put it, they combine “the advantages of the most energetic and active town life, with all the beauty and delight of the country.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the way most English people want to live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to find a way to build places like this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has been holding us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only been planning minister for a few months but I have observed the debate about housing and planning for over ten years and I think I know what is wrong.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trapped in a vicious circle.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at the new housing estates that have been bolted on to their towns and villages in recent decades and observe that few of them are beautiful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not to put too fine a point on it, many of them are pig-ugly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Harrisons Wharf in Purfleet that I visited last week.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure the flats inside are nice enough but they occupy an overbearing and unbroken slab of dismal brickwork that is an insult to the community it borders, cutting it off from a stretch of the River Thames which, in Victorian times, attracted day-trippers from London keen to take a pleasant walk along banks of the river.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since new housing estates are all too often soulless and formulaic, and those who will inhabit them will add to the pressure on local roads, primary school places and doctor’s appointments, existing residents oppose any proposal to build new houses on green field sites, even when the land is of low environmental quality.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities respond to the wishes of local voters by putting too few sites into their local plans. And this drives the cost of development land up to stratospheric levels (roughly £3 million an hectare in the South East and East of England by 2010.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers respond by stuffing as many units as they can onto any site and, in an attempt to make the properties affordable, skimp on room size, architectural features, vernacular materials, communal spaces and landscape design.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, because we don’t build beautifully, people don’t let us build much. And because we don’t build much, we can’t afford to build beautifully. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the coalition, and my personal mission as planning minister, is to help us break out of this vicious circle once and for all.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get back on to that confident, progressive path, which created Stamford, Edinburgh New Town and Letchworth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to build beautiful and affordable places once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have we done to bring this about? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Pickles’ first step, in June 2010, was to scrap John Prescott’s blanket density target of 30 dwellings per hectare and to stop the garden grabbing that was destroying the precious green spaces that make Britain’s cities so pleasant to live in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government then embarked on a root and branch reform of the planning system and the creation of the National Planning Policy Framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mammoth task which had to be masterminded by a minister with a mammoth brain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my predecessor, Greg Clark, is blessed with exactly that - as well as the unfailing patience and politeness required to bring the good ship Reform to dock with most of those interested in planning and development still on board.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Framework establishes a few clear principles, which it is now my job to drive through.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That local councils should take charge of development in their areas by drawing up local plans.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that alongside the power to plan comes the responsibility to provide new houses to meet people’s aspirations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through their local plans, councils must bring forward enough land to meet the objectively assessed housing needs of their area over the next 5 years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they do so, they will be able to protect precious open spaces against speculative development.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Secretary of State and I will back them to the hilt.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if they fail to take their responsibilities seriously, the presumption in favour of sustainable development will fill the vacuum and make the vital decisions that they are ducking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Framework, Grant Shapps introduced the New Homes Bonus, which gives local councils additional money for every new home for which they give planning permission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in what I believe will turn out to be our most revolutionary step, the government launched neighbourhood planning through which villages, parishes and other neighbourhoods can take control of their future and decide for themselves how and where development should take place.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be talking more about our ambitions for neighbourhood plans after the Autumn Statement.
So the government has acted to ensure that more land is brought forward for development and that local communities have an incentive to welcome new housing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now for planners, architects and developers, large and small, to seize the opportunity we have created and start designing beautiful places, which local people will welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, on the edge of Bishops Castle in Shropshire, Bob Tomlinson and Carole Salmon set out to create a new, contemporary village, a friendly place that people would want to live.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was The Wintles, 1 of the most exciting and enchanting collection of new houses anywhere in England.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses are all different.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are unashamedly contemporary but incorporate vernacular features in a bold and imaginative way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a wide range of both natural and manufactured materials and make a priority of the spaces between the buildings (both private and communal) and the planting of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wintles did not get everything right first time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which experiment ever does?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not as integrated into the rest of Bishops Castle as some long-standing residents would like. And, to replicate it on a large scale, one would need to find a way to build houses that are just as beautiful and just as sustainable but cost less to build.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Bishops Castle I believe that the Living Village Trust created a model for our future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which Ebenezer Howard would be proud.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which, once again, we build beautiful new urban landscapes full of affordable houses surrounded by green spaces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be our goal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16956</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T13:39:14+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/measures-to-reduce-bureaucratic-barriers-to-growth-and-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Measures to reduce bureaucratic barriers to growth and infrastructure</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>An expansion of the ‘one-stop-shop’ approach for considering nationally significant infrastructure projects will help boost growth and jobs.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt;, currently being considered in Parliament, will help the country compete on the global stage by introducing a comprehensive series of practical reforms that will reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposals in the Bill include reducing the number of different consents infrastructure developers require. The government is also consulting on a new streamlined ‘one-stop-shop’ service and on reducing the number of bodies developers need to consult on every application. The proposed reforms will deliver a swifter, more efficient planning process while ensuring interested parties can continue to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforms will also open up the fast-track planning process used for nationally significant infrastructure projects to additional types of nationally significant development. It will be open for the first time to business and commercial projects that are important to delivering growth and prosperity and boosting the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new types of developments that could be considered under the nationally significant infrastructure system include: manufacturing and major tourism and leisure proposals, office development such as research and development facilities, and warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers would be allowed to request that their application for these nationally significant business projects be determined through the infrastructure planning system which ensures decisions are made within 12 months from the beginning of examination. Existing requirements to consult local communities are retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations on these two proposed reforms to the major infrastructure planning process were issued today. (See &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-extending-the-regime-to-business-and-commercial-projects" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: extending the regime to business and commercial projects"&gt;extending the regime to business and commercial projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/nationally-significant-infrastructure-planning-expanding-and-improving-the-one-stop-shop-approach-for-consents" title="Nationally significant infrastructure planning: expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents"&gt;expanding and improving the ‘one stop shop’ approach for consents&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is vital we secure investment in new nationally significant infrastructure and commercial development, and that quicker and better planning decisions are made, if we are to help boost the economy and create the new jobs we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning delays help no one. They bring uncertainty for local people and local firms and can deter new investment all together. By streamlining the planning process to make it quicker and easier for these national significant projects to be decided we can ensure sustainable development gets underway without delay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reforms have already given significant additional powers to councils and communities so they can decide on the scale and location of development in their areas. With this power comes a responsibility to ensure that local planning decisions are efficient and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth and Infrastructure Bill will also give planning applicants the ability to apply directly to the Planning Inspectorate where there is clear evidence that a council’s planning service is performing very poorly and failing to administer a proper service for both applicants and local residents.  A consultation recently published sets out how these proposals would work, including the basis for assessing performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16487</id>
    <published>2012-11-19T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-19T13:59:47+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/nick-boles-attends-launch-of-national-business-competition"/>
    <title>Nick Boles attends launch of national business competition</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Communities Minister sees young people being inspired through business at the launch of this year’s Mosaic Enterprise Challenge competition.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting Westminster City School, Nick Boles spoke to the winners of last year’s competition and saw the how they invented a winning product by taking part in an online business game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="image embedded"&gt;&lt;div class="img"&gt;&lt;img alt=" Nick Boles with students" src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/1125/mosaicwinners2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Nick Boles speaking to students from Southfields Community College, winners of last year’s competition&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;School teams are supported by specialist business mentors to compete through the game, which places them into a realistic business situation in which they must develop and market a new product and respond to simulated business competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The competition aims to promote entrepreneurship and inspire knowledge and enthusiasm about business among young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.mosaicnetwork.co.uk/en_gb/portal/enterprise-challenge"&gt;Enterprise Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the department, will this year involve over 3,000 students in 80 schools who will be supported by more than 300 mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Apax-Mosaic Enterprise Challenge is an excellent way of enabling pupils to learn practical business skills such as sales, marketing and finance from within the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was fantastic to speak to last year’s competition winners and hear how they have benefited from taking part and how much they enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted that the Department is supporting this for another year and wish everyone taking part the best of luck.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos of the event are available from the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/communitiesuk/sets/72157632046112497/"&gt;DCLG Flickr channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/14370</id>
    <published>2012-11-12T13:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T10:36:04+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-powers-for-homeowners-and-businesses-to-improve-their-properties"/>
    <title>New powers for homeowners and businesses to improve their properties</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Proposed new powers will make it easier for hard working families to make home improvements.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new powers will make it easier for for homeowners to make improvements in a way that also protects neighbours’ amenities, says Planning Minister Nick Boles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reforms would, for a time limited period, slash planning red tape, sweep away unnecessary rules and bureaucracy and help tens of thousands of homeowners and companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the 200,000 homeowner applications submitted each year are uncontroversial. Almost 90% are approved but still have to go through an application process that is often costly and creates delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases the current system adds little value yet forces homeowners wishing to extend their home more than a few metres from the property’s rear wall to fill in complicated application forms that can take 8 weeks or longer for the council to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/consultations/extending-permitted-development-rights-for-homeowners-and-businesses-technical-consultation" title="Extending permitted development rights for homeowners and businesses: technical consultation"&gt;consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; published today proposes making it quicker, easier and cheaper to build small-scale single-storey extensions and conservatories by extending permitted development rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minister made clear that safeguards will remain to ensure any impact on neighbours and communities is acceptable. The new rights will not apply in protected areas such as national parks, conservation areas, areas of outstanding natural beauty and sites of special scientific interest and do not remove the requirement for separate listed building consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permitted development only covers the planning aspects of development and does not remove requirements under other regimes, such as building regulations, the Party Wall Act or environmental legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These proposed reforms will make it easier for thousands of hard working families to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or to build a conservatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Homeowners and businesses must be allowed to meet their aspirations for improving their homes and premises but this won’t be at the expense of neighbours, communities and protected areas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that up to 40,000 families a year wishing to build straightforward extensions will benefit from the proposals, and will be able to undertake home improvements to cater for a growing family or look after an elderly relative without unnecessary costs and bureaucracy. Some 160,000 homeowner applications will continue to be considered through the planning system as at present, including all the larger, more complex and controversial cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposals will save householders £150 in planning application fees along with many indirect savings on transaction costs such as professional fees, production of scaled drawings and time spent compiling and presenting information. The estimated total savings on the planning application process is up to £2,470 depending on the level of information required to support the application. If the requirement to seek planning permission were removed these costs would no longer be incurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16040</id>
    <published>2012-10-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-14T12:41:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/planning-inspectorate-essential-to-new-planning-measures"/>
    <title>Planning Inspectorate essential to new planning measures</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Planning minister sees first hand how the Planning Inspectorate is playing a vital role in new reforms and improvements of the planning system.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government recently announced a number of new measures in the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/growthandinfrastructure.html"&gt;Growth and Infrastructure Bill&lt;/a&gt; to reduce confusing and overlapping red tape that delays and discourages business investment, new infrastructure and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Boles said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New planning measures will put the Planning Inspectorate centre stage in ensuring we have a swift and effective planning system that helps boost local economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By expanding permitted development rights, cutting red tape and streamlining the planning process we can save householders money and help businesses create jobs and compete.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his first visit to the Inspectorate in Bristol on Thursday, the minister discussed the work of planning inspectors with Inspectorate Chief Executive Sir Michael Pitt and toured the National Infrastructure Division and Planning Appeals Division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
