<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/nick-clegg</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/nick-clegg.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Nick Clegg MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:37+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18369</id>
    <published>2012-04-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-support-for-business-access-to-alternative-finance"/>
    <title>Government support for business access to alternative finance</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg highlights Government action this year to help businesses across Britain make greater use of non-bank finance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the Institute of Directors, the Deputy Prime Minister outlined plans for the £1.2billion Business Finance Partnership (BFP). The BFP is part of the Government’s package of credit easing that also includes £20bn through the National Loan Guarantee Scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government is currently considering proposals for the BFP, including allocating finance to senior loan funds. £100million has already been earmarked to support non-bank lending channels such as peer-to-peer lending and mezzanine finance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIS will distribute this £100million portion of the BFP. It aims to increase the supply of capital through non-bank lending channels. This should also stimulate the development of a deeper and more diversified non-bank lending market for those businesses in the UK with a turnover of less than £500m. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As announced at Budget, a request for proposals will be issued at the end of May to invite finance providers to bid for these £100m. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said: We need to break open the market here in the UK, with more competition within the sector as well as more alternative sources of finance, outside of it.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Coalition is going to invest directly in non-bank finance as part of our £1.2 billion Business Finance Partnership - £700 million will be invested through up to seven fund managers who will lend directly to British firms. There will be additional investment from the private sector with our share eventually returned to government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That still leaves half a billion, £100 million of which will be invested in banking alternatives for SMEs. And, if we see quick take-off, I will certainly want us to invest the remainder as quickly as we can. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Investments will be made over the coming months, to precisely the kinds of schemes I’ve described and I’m issuing a call to all of you today - tell us your ideal way to bypass the banks to unlock new channels of capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to reshape the UK’s finance landscape to better serve the needs of ordinary businesses, helping more companies find the support they need to start and grow.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/businessfinance"&gt;Non-Bank Lending Taskforce to boost finance options for businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/fin_sector_banking_business_lending.htm"&gt;HM Treasury: lending to business and credit easing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//news/topstories/2011/Dec/taskforce-to-boost-finance-options-for-business"&gt;More finance options for business: announcement of the Non-Bank Lending Taskforce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18342</id>
    <published>2012-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:33+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1-billion-growth-fund-open-for-business--2"/>
    <title>£1 billion growth fund open for business</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Government's announces an extra £1 billion for businesses seeking support at the National Manufacturing Summit.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funding is part of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;/a&gt; and takes the total to £2.4 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be available to businesses and public / private partnerships with ambitions to create new jobs and make a significant impact on their local economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg will make the announcement at the Government’s National Manufacturing Summit being held at the Bristol &amp;amp; Bath Science Park today.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He will also confirm that 48 of the successful firms from the first two rounds of the fund have completed their legal checks and have access to the Government fund.  Speaking ahead of the summit, he said;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Fund is already having a huge impact across the UK. So far there have been over 170 successful bids to the fund, leveraging around £7.5 billion of private sector investment and set to create and protect 330,000 jobs. I want to see more businesses that are confident they can create jobs and get Britain building and making things again, coming forward - making sure their hats are in the ring.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Funding from rounds one and two has gone to some extraordinarily promising manufacturing projects. From Pirelli Tyres in Carlisle who’ll use the money to develop a new range of carbon-cutting tyres; to a Portsmouth based company which hopes to use theirs to create a cutting edge boat building college.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These are the kinds of projects that will lead their communities into brighter times, helping put industry at the heart of the UK’s economy. Businesses have until June to apply for a share of this extra £1 billion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="manufacturing-industry-urged-to-bid-for-extra-growth-funding"&gt;Manufacturing industry urged to bid for extra growth funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Manufacturing Summit brings together Government and key industry leaders to discuss and debate progress, the upcoming challenges and next steps for the sector as the Government continues to put manufacturing at the heart of its Growth Programme. There will also be further announcements for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://discuss.bis.gov.uk/seeinsidemanufacturing/"&gt;See Inside Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;, and 23 new ‘Industry Champions’ for &lt;a rel="external" href="http://makeitingreatbritain.bis.gov.uk/"&gt;Make it in Great Britain.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the summit, the Deputy Prime Minister will be joined by Business Secretary Vince Cable at GKN Aerospace, Bristol to open the company’s new £150 million advanced composites manufacturing centre. This is site where the 27 metre long Airbus A350 wing is being made. When operating at full production, the facility will provide employment for 250 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Minister Mark Prisk, attending the conference later today, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Worth approximately £130bn a year and employing 2.5m people, the manufacturing industry’s contribution to our economy cannot be under estimated.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Government remains committed to manufacturing, which is why we have placed it at the heart of our Growth Programme. Equally so, showcasing manufacturing as a worthwhile career choice for young people in modern Britain is another goal of Government, which Make it in Great Britain and See Inside Manufacturing are helping to lead for the long term prosperity of the industry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=423400&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;Regional Growth Fund&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/27266</id>
    <published>2012-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:19:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/deputy-prime-minister-s-discussion-with-his-excellency-abdelilah-benkirane-head-of-government-morocco"/>
    <title>Deputy Prime Minister’s discussion with his Excellency Abdelilah Benkirane, Head of Government, Morocco</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg spoke to Abdelilah Benkirane, Head of Government in Morocco, to express his support for the newly elected government.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The last twelve months have witnessed unprecedented change in North Africa.  Today I spoke to Abdelilah Benkirane to discuss Morocco’s internal reforms and the opportunities and challenges faced by the newly elected government.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made clear the UK’s support, both bilaterally and through the  EU, for Morocco’s plans for political and economic reform,  as well as underlining the UK’s support for the implementation of constitutional reform and its application to minority rights.  Through the Arab Partnership Fund, we are assisting the Moroccan government in their efforts to increase rates of political participation and target corruption in public life.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discussed the ongoing unrest throughout the Middle East and North Africa region including the situation in Syria as well as the importance the UK attaches to a more integrated North Africa for the long-term security and prosperity of the region.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18278</id>
    <published>2011-07-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/judging-starts-on-regional-growth-fund-bids"/>
    <title>Judging starts on Regional Growth Fund bids</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>BIS has received more than 490 bids competing for a share of £950 million from round 2 of the Regional Growth Fund.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These bids were received in response to the second round of the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk/policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund"&gt;£1.4 billion fund,&lt;/a&gt; which is designed to encourage enterprise, growth and jobs in the private sector and support regions that are dependent on the public sector. The bids will compete for a share of £950 million. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.bis.gov.uk//policies/economic-development/regional-growth-fund/successful-projects-list"&gt;Further details on regional spread and total value of the bids&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 492 bids, asking for £3.3 billion, are being assessed by the Independent Advisory Board, chaired by Lord Heseltine, over the summer. The board will then make recommendations to a board of ministers, led by Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg, which will make the final decisions as to which proposals should receive funding. It is expected that the successful bidders will be announced in the autumn.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 140 bids received for the North West - the highest of all the regions, which account for 28 per cent of all the bids received. More than 330 of the total number of bids received are bidding for between £1 million and £5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister, Nick Clegg, said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This vital regional fund uses government investment and multiplies it to give a real boost to local businesses. Round one is already helping local economies across the country and has attracted £2.5 billion of private sector investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This will directly create or protect over 27,000 jobs, and secure around a further 100,000 jobs on related supply chains and in local economies. We welcome the bids received for the second round, and hope we can do even more this time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allocation of funding each successful proposal will receive will be the minimum amount the proposal needs to get off the ground. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each bid must also demonstrate it is bringing in private sources of funding as well. The public investment in the first 50 successful bids is expected to secure a further £2.5 billion of private investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Heseltine said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We knew from the road shows there was going to be a huge amount of interest in the second round of the Regional Growth Fund, and we have been overwhelmed by the volume of bids submitted.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is clearly a hunger for public support which will allow new and exciting projects to deliver jobs and growth in their local communities to get off the ground, and I’m pleased to see so many people wanting to be a part of this. We now face the difficult task of assessing each of these bids; we have a busy summer ahead of us!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=420634&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;Press Notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/26257</id>
    <published>2011-03-31T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:16:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-us-talks-in-washington"/>
    <title>UK-US talks in Washington</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg visited Washington, DC yesterday to meet with senior US officials and take part in a UK-US seminar on social mobility.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister and Vice President discussed UK, US and allied cooperation in Libya and Afghanistan at the White House on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a brief visit to the US capital, the Deputy Prime Minister made a call on Vice President Joe Biden at the White House. The two leaders discussed the international community’s efforts to protect the Libyan people in accordance with UN Security Council Resolutions 1970 and 1973. The Deputy Prime Minister and Vice President also reaffirmed UK and US commitment to the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan, and discussed progress in transitioning to an Afghan security lead.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, the Deputy Prime Minister met with Senator John Kerry, Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister concluded his visit by participating in a discussion on social mobility with President Obama’s Middle Class Task Force at the Economic Policy Institute. Social Mobility is a priority for the Coalition Government and the seminar was a useful opportunity to share best practice.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the Deputy Prime Minister’s second visit to Washington, DC since taking office in May of 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="search-the-news-archive"&gt;Search the news archive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28090</id>
    <published>2011-03-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/deputy-prime-minister-nick-clegg-meets-mexican-president-felipe-calderon"/>
    <title>Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg meets Mexican President Felipe Calderón</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK Deputy Prime Minister Clegg and President Calderón underlined their wish to see increased cooperation in the fields of trade, investment, science, technology and education</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The visit to Mexico by Deputy Prime Minister Nicholas Clegg is a signal of the close state of relations between Mexico and the United Kingdom. These are built on the basis of shared values, such as democracy, the rule of law, promotion of economic growth and prosperity, the fight against organised crime and climate change, as well as recognition of the links between development, peace, security and human rights. Today’s visit, following on from President Calderon’s State Visit to the UK in 2009, is a valuable opportunity to reinvigorate co-operation and build a natural partnership across a much wider range of areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a working breakfast, President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg underlined their wish to see increased cooperation in the fields of trade, investment, science, technology and education. Both recognised the important links between economic stability, development and investment, as well as the need for continued economic reform to achieve sustained development. They welcomed the 30% increase in bilateral trade in goods between 2009 and 2010, and the strengthened contacts between business leaders from both countries. They also agreed to work towards doubling bilateral trade by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They agreed on the need to make multilateral institutions more representative, transparent and efficient. Both welcomed the close cooperation between our two countries in international fora, such as the G20 and the UN system, including the Human Rights Council. They agreed on the need for further close collaboration on the issues of sustainable development, climate change and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg reaffirmed the commitment of Mexico and the United Kingdom to co-operate on the promotion of international security and stability, international humanitarian law and the protection of citizens. Both welcomed the willingness of the international community to ensure the protection of the people of Libya, as set out in the United Nations Security Council Resolutions 1970 and 1973.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Deputy Prime Minister welcomed Mexico’s Presidency of the G20 next year. Both committed to work closely together towards achieving the G20’s goal of reaching strong, sustainable and balanced global growth, and the reform of the global financial and economic system. They agreed to continue working on green growth initiatives and towards a successful conclusion of the Doha Round negotiations in 2011, which both countries believe is more important than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg reiterated their commitment to fighting poverty and exclusion; achieving the Millennium Development Goals; their shared responsibility in the fight against transnational organised crime, including strengthening cooperation on e-crime ; the promotion of international peace and security, and greater educational, cultural and tourist exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg both welcomed the launching of the British Council in Mexico as a self-standing social enterprise, which will lead to increased engagement in areas such as English language training, education and the arts. Last week’s visit to the United Kingdom of Minister Alonso Lujambio and this week’s visit from Deputy Prime Minister Clegg have led to important outcomes for developing further collaboration to improve economic competitiveness and development through education and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg agreed that adoption of the Cancun Agreements was a key step forward in the development and consolidation of the United Nations’ climate regime. They expressed their determination to pursue their implementation and to work for progress in the international negotiations consistent with the goal of limiting global temperature increases to two degrees celsius, as well as actions at home, using both countries’ leadership to pursue a low carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, they welcomed the Memorandum of Understanding for Securing a Sustainable and Low Carbon Development to be signed today by the Mexican Secretary of Environment and Natural Resources, Juan Rafael Elvira and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg, covering co-operation at both the national and local levels to increase further this partnership. They stressed the need to maintain cooperation with climate stakeholders such as parliamentarians, civil society organizations and the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Calderon and Deputy Prime Minister Clegg agreed on the importance of maintaining frequent bilateral contact, to expand and deepen bilateral relations further. They agreed that Mr. Clegg’s visit to Mexico opened up new opportunities for cooperation between both countries and governments, and they look forward to a visit of Prime Minister David Cameron to Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28091</id>
    <published>2011-03-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-and-mexico-reveal-joint-target-to-double-trade-to-4-2-billion-by-2015"/>
    <title>UK and Mexico reveal joint target to double trade to £4.2 billion by 2015</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg is in Mexico today, leading a delegation of more than 20 of Britain’s companies.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These include top engineering, construction and design firms as well as universities  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister and Mexican President have agreed to set up a new UK-Mexico business forum, which will bring together key business leaders from both countries to help reach the ambitious trade target. They have agreed to set up a Mexican Chamber of Commerce in London to increase trade and investment flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The UK Government is committed to strengthening our trade and investment links with the fastest growing economies of the world, including Mexico. During this visit, we have not only agreed to double trade, but we have set up ways to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As Mexico’s economy continues to grow it provides huge opportunities for UK firms, particularly in infrastructure energy, education and retail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And as we set out in last week’s Budget, Britain is open for business and we welcome investment from Mexico. The UK is one of the easiest places in the world to invest and do business and we are committed to making it ever better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister is accompanied by Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne, and Universities Minister David Willetts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later today, the Deputy Prime Minister and Mexican President Felipe Calderon, chaired a business round table to discuss trade relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK trade with the Latin American region increased by 30 per cent last year and bilateral trade in goods to Mexico, over the same period, went up by a third.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 350 British companies and 900 with British capital are already operating in Mexico and UK Trade &amp;amp; Investment has identified opportunities for UK companies in sectors such as infrastructure, energy, retail, advanced engineering, and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mexico’s National Infrastructure Plan, set up in 2007, set out an investment programme worth £140 billion. Part of this work involves building nearly 1,500 kilometres of railroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the UK businesses already based in Mexico are: HSBC, Invensys, Thomas Pink, Essential Nails, and Currie &amp;amp; Brown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="facts"&gt;Facts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The UK is the fifth largest investor in Mexico over the past ten years, with nearly US $7.4 billion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 350 British companies and 900 with British capital are operating in Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mexico is the UK’s second largest trading nation in Latin America after Brazil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2010, UK exports increased by 28% compared to 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2010, bilateral trade in goods between the UK and Mexico also increased by a third - totalling almost £1.9 billion.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28092</id>
    <published>2011-03-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/deputy-prime-minister-gives-speech-on-foreign-policy"/>
    <title>Deputy Prime Minister gives speech on foreign policy</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg described new “axis of openness” in global affairs in speech at Chapultepec Castle in Mexico City.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Just as 1989 and 2001 marked sharp breaks with the past, so 2011 could prove to be a turning point in international affairs: the third critical moment in recent history.                 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many of the received wisdoms of the last decade have tumbled like dominoes. Against the predictions of most of the experts in foreign ministries around the world, the last nine months have seen a rising tide of democracy and openness, and a resuscitation of the ideals of multilateralism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There has been real progress on climate change here in Mexico, at the Cancun Summit last year. I’d like to congratulate the Mexican government and the Mexican people for helping make the Cancun Summit such a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The rising democratic tide in North Africa and the Middle East, led by middle-class secular forces, with a movement for openness in societies across the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A swift and decisive response by the United Nations to the dangers posed to those fighting for freedom in Libya. A response strongly supported by many emerging economies and with a significant and encouraging new role played by China, Russia and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And the reaction of the world to the tragedy in Japan. It has long been a cliche to say that the world is becoming smaller. But I believe that in terms of compassion and ethics, the case is now proven beyond doubt. When citizens in war-torn Afghanistan are sending money to Japan, it is possible see ourselves as citizens not only of our own nations, but also of that wider country, the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking on the day of the Libya Conference in London, he added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is a good deal of concern in the UK, and I know here in Mexico too, about the military action. The sight of coalition warplanes in action in North Africa is a stark reminder of earlier conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like most of you, I was a strong opponent of the war in Iraq. It was wrong. But the action being taken in Libya today is right. It would be a terrible tragedy if the mistakes of Iraq led to a retreat from the principle of liberal interventionism, from the principle that we have a collective responsibility to support freedom and protect human rights around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The lesson of Iraq is not that intervention in support of liberal aims is always wrong. The lesson of Iraq is that any such action must only - and must always - be multilaterally sanctioned and driven by humanitarian concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Liberal vigilantism is dead. Law-abiding liberal interventionism is not.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/28089</id>
    <published>2011-03-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:21:28+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-deputy-prime-minister-nick-clegg-visits-mexico"/>
    <title>UK Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg visits Mexico</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>UK Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg will be in Mexico from 28 to 30 March.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He will be most senior British government minister to visit Mexico on bilateral business for more than a decade.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Deputy Prime Minister will be accompanied by Minister of State for Universities and Science David Willets, Foreign Office Minister Jeremy Browne and a high-level delegation of UK business leaders, representing a wide range of sectors including financial services, health care, energy, construction, consultancy and consumer goods. The delegation will be joined by top level UK university representatives from Aberdeen, Southampton, Sheffield and Strathclyde.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit to Mexico, the Deputy Prime Minister will meet President Calderon, promote British business and educational links, and deliver a keynote foreign policy speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking ahead of his visit, Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to visit Mexico. It marks the beginning of a major push in 2011 to renew the UK’s ties to Latin America. This is a commitment from the whole of the UK Government, supported by UK business and education leaders.  I will be travelling with top business representatives from the UK so we can explore how we can maximise our trade and investment relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that there is a huge amount of unrealised potential for further trade between our two nations. With our world-class expertise in green technology and financial services, the UK is a good fit for Mexico’s future economic development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our two countries are natural partners on the global stage, cooperating closely on climate change, the G20 and in the UN. I am looking forward to discussing the full range of international issues, including developments in the Middle East, during my trip.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18204</id>
    <published>2011-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T16:25:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/flexible-parental-leave"/>
    <title>Flexible parental leave</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>The Government has today announced more detail on its plans for a new system of flexible parental leave to help parents balance their work and family commitments.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Department for Business will be launching a consultation soon which will explore proposals for the design of a more flexible system of parental leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consultation will also consider how best to extend the right to request flexible working to all employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/parenting-speech"&gt;Speaking at an event&lt;/a&gt; on contemporary parenting, the Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg set out principles that the Government wants the changes to embody:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any new arrangement must absolutely maintain women’s guaranteed right to time off in the first months after birth, paid as it is now; and must protect the rights of lone mothers. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The reforms must transform the opportunities for fathers to take time off to care for their children. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It must be possible for mother and fathers to share part of their leave, splitting it between them, in whatever way suits them best. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new system must take into account the needs of employers and it must be simple to administer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Right now, most parents simply do not have flexibility they need. Despite the fact fathers can request flexible working, many feel reluctant to do so. There is still a stigma attached. And, when a child is born, men are still only entitled to a paltry two weeks of paternity leave. These rules patronize women and marginalise men.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They’re based on a view of life in which mothers stay at home and fathers are the only breadwinners. So in the coming weeks we will be launching a consultation on a new properly flexible system of shared parental leave, that we aim to introduce in 2015.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Secretary Vince Cable said:   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We want to help parents juggle work and family life and create a fairer and more family friendly society.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We will consult fully with businesses on how best to proceed and we are conscious of the concerns of some companies, particularly SMEs - but I hope they will embrace our plans. More and more businesses are appreciating that family friendly workplaces are motivated and productive workplaces.”   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://news.bis.gov.uk/content/detail.aspx?NewsAreaId=2&amp;amp;ReleaseID=417453&amp;amp;SubjectId=2"&gt;BIS press notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dpm.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/news/parenting-speech"&gt;Deputy Prime Minister’s speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.businesslink.gov.uk/bdotg/action/layer?lang=en&amp;amp;r.l1=1073858787&amp;amp;r.s=tl&amp;amp;topicId=1080898061"&gt;Business Link: Maternity, paternity and adoption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/Parents/Moneyandworkentitlements/WorkAndFamilies/index.htm"&gt;Directgov: Parental leave and flexible working&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
