<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/norman-baker</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/norman-baker.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - Norman Baker MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60281</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-secures-free-travel-for-london-midland-passengers"/>
    <title>Government secures free travel for London Midland passengers</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers who suffered cancelled services and delays last year will receive free travel passes and cheap tickets thanks to tough action taken by the government, Transport Minister Norman Baker announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Midland season ticket holders will be given 5 days worth of free travel passes under a £7 million package of benefits. The government has also secured 500,000 additional cheap advance tickets for passengers on key network routes serving London, Birmingham, Northampton, Crewe and Liverpool and a commitment to invest in infrastructure improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“London Midland has cancelled or delayed hundreds of services in recent months. On repeated occasions, they were not able to provide enough drivers and some services had to be cancelled, with severe delays to services, and they have fallen short both of everyone’s expectations and their franchise obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Securing these benefits for passengers represents a firm yellow-card for London Midland and some financial benefit for those who have been hardest hit by their poor performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am confident London Midland has now rectified their driver shortage but the company need to be clear that we will continue to monitor their performance closely and take firmer action if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free tickets will be available to all monthly and annual season ticket holders, as well as to weekly ticket holders who have been affected by disruption, while the additional Advance tickets will be available over the next two years to passengers planning to travel on key London Midland routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal that has been struck will also confirm the end date of the franchise as September 2015, ensuring that London Midland is given sufficient time to resolve these problems on a permanent basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London Midland will also spend millions of pounds improving the resilience of their trains and will invest at least £2.25 million on a range of measures to benefit passengers - primarily in the West Midlands, where the worst disruption was experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government is taking this action because London Midland were responsible for the cancellation of a high number of services, particularly at weekends and during the half-term period, due to a shortage of drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The free 5-day passes will enable annual and monthly season ticket holders to make additional journeys outside of their regular commute, or as an extension to existing season tickets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 500,000 additional cheaper advance tickets will be issued over and above those issued in the last year and will be for travel during 2013 and 2014. The tickets will be available on key routes including London-Birmingham, London-Crewe, London-Northampton and Birmingham-Liverpool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57512</id>
    <published>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:02:07+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/operators-urged-to-tackle-crowding-on-busiest-services"/>
    <title>Operators urged to tackle crowding on busiest services</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker has urged train operators to continue work to tackle congestion on their services following the publication today of the top 10 most crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London is served by some of the busiest trains in the country according to the list of crowded trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Climbing on a crowded train where there is little space can often be an unpleasant experience and I sympathise with passengers who have to travel on these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The operators on the list are aware of the crowding problems on these particular services. I will be monitoring these services closely, and others which have not made the top 10 list, and urging train companies to reduce crowding on the busiest services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rail has experienced unprecedented growth in recent years. That is why we are investing in more carriages, longer trains and better services and funding major projects like HS2, Crossrail and Thameslink, all of which will significantly boost capacity on our rail network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is an important tool to give increased transparency to passengers and help the industry act to improve journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list, compiled from data collected in Autumn 2011, shows that the following services were the busiest in England and Wales (in descending order): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington – load factor 180%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:32am service from Woking to London Waterloo – load factor 164%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:13pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 162%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4:48pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 160%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington – load factor 158%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon – load factor 157%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough – load factor 155%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6:17pm service from London Liverpool Street to Shenfield – load factor 154%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7:14am service from Alton to London Waterloo – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5:46pm service from London Euston to Birmingham New Street – load factor 152%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport (DfT) collects rail passenger counts from train operating companies to monitor train crowding levels. All franchises let by DfT require the train operator to address crowding and to plan their timetables in such a way as to ensure, as far as possible, that crowding is not unduly concentrated on any particular route or individual service. The table included in this paper shows the 10 most overcrowded peak services in the autumn 2011 passenger counts data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘top 10’ list is determined based on ‘load factor’, which is the number of standard class passengers on a service expressed as a percentage of the standard class passenger capacity for that service. For example, a train which has the same passenger load as the passenger capacity would have a load factor of 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Great Western has recently strengthened the 7:44am service from Henley on Thames to London Paddington by adding an additional carriage, so that the number of standard class seats has increased to 340.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From December 2012 London Midland is providing three Class 350/2 ‘high density’ units for the 6:13pm service from London to Birmingham New Street to maximise the number of seats. In the long term, London Midland has 10 new 4 car trains on order that will allow them to operate additional trains on this route from 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From September 2012, the 6:30am service from Banbury to London Paddington has started from Oxford not Banbury, leaving Oxford at 7:00am. It is now operated by a different type of rolling stock which provides a higher standard class seating capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More recent counts on the 7:55am service from Stourbridge Junction to Stratford-upon-Avon suggest much lower loadings on this service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the long term, from the May 2014 timetable period, it is planned to introduce a fifth train per hour between Manchester and Leeds which should relieve capacity on the 6:23am service from Manchester Airport to Middlesbrough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 10 list can be accessed on the &lt;a href="/government/publications/top-10-overcrowded-train-services-england-and-wales"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55970</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T11:36:09+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/transport-for-everyone"/>
    <title>Transport for everyone </title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker is calling on operators and local authorities to work with government to put accessibility and equality front and centre when delivering services for the travelling public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help them to do this, the Department for Transport has published 2 action plans which set out priorities, as well as highlighting areas where action is in the pipeline or already underway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Transport for everyone’ outlines how operators, local councils and the Department can help to make it easier for people using public transport – particularly those with disabilities - to get to where they need to go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action plan builds on the success achieved in improving accessibility on public transport during the Olympics and Paralympics. At the heart of the plan is the importance of improving door-to-door journeys rather than addressing issues in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The department’s equality action plan looks at how we can encourage a more inclusive transport network and underlines the importance of ensuring that policy makers at all levels are alive to the particular needs and concerns of different groups in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include affordability issues for young people and pensioners and the ability for all people to travel in safety and free from harassment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Minister Norman Baker said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A good transport system allows people to access jobs, opportunities and vital services - it needs to work for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We recognise the concerns that specific groups of people have about public transport and so we have pulled together ideas from across the transport sector on how these concerns can be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The action plans will help policy makers, as well as transport operators, to tackle problems head on and - more importantly - to level the playing field for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz Sayce OBE, Disability Rights UK Chief Executive, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An accessible transport infrastructure is essential for what Disability Rights UK wants to achieve – disabled people playing a full and equal part in society. Over the past 20 years we have come a long way as our practical guide ‘Doing transport differently’ shows but there are still too many attitudinal, communication and physical barriers facing disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Action plan’ is a step change towards making further progress. We welcome the commitment that the Department for Transport will continue to work in partnership with disabled people and our organisations to ensure the most effective steps are taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ‘Accessibility action plan’ builds on the transport successes of the Olympic and Paralympic Games and aims to create a long lasting legacy of improved access and information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Olympic and Paralympic Games, public transport operators carried thousands of spectators with disabilities and work was done to ensure that the travelling public had easy access to information. One of the aims of the ‘Accessibility action plan’ will be to build on the Games Spectator Journey Planner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new planner would cover a wider geographical area and more types of transport as well as being made accessible to people with visual impairments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other measures outlined in the plan include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considering where £100 million of extra funding might be best spent in the long term to improve accessibility of railway stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible further amendments to the Blue Badge scheme to tackle abuse and fraud in this area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building on guidance for mobility scooters and powered wheelchairs to encourage training for those using this equipment &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘Equality action plan’ sets out in one place what the department is doing to ensure people from all parts of society have the option to use public transport. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points addressed in the plan include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accessibility to public transport for young people, older people and those living in rural areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;safety and personal security for women travellers, particularly at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tackling hate crime and bullying on buses and other public transport &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promoting employment of under-represented groups within the transport industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both documents include lists of issues and the actions that have been, or will be, taken to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Accessibility action plan’&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;‘Equality action plan’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the interests of transparency and to enable as many people as possible to have their say, the ‘Equality action plan’ will be open for comment until 15 February. These will feed in to a final version of the document which will be published in due course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/55866</id>
    <published>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/accessibility-action-plan-and-equality-action-plan"/>
    <title>Accessibility action plan and equality action plan</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am today pleased to be publishing the department’s accessibility action plan &lt;a href="/government/publications/accessibility-action-plan"&gt;‘Transport for Everyone: an action plan to improve accessibility for all’&lt;/a&gt;, and, for comment, a draft &lt;a href="/government/publications/equality-action-plan"&gt;equality action plan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has already been achieved in making transport more accessible, and the accessibility action plan seeks to address the challenges that remain. In doing so, we also want to draw on the success of the Olympic and Paralympic Games which demonstrated what can be done to provide those using our public transport system with a positive experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility action plan focuses not only on improving physical accessibility, but also on providing better information for the traveller, and on improving attitudes and behaviour, especially towards disabled passengers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying our priorities in the action plan, we have worked with a large number of representative organisations, individuals, transport operators and local authorities. I am grateful for the support and input that they have provided.  We want transport to be accessible by all and the plan moves us further towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equality action plan presents some of the activities we are undertaking to meet our duties under the equalities legislation, and provides an initial set of priorities for promoting equality and well-being, based on the evidence we have gathered and the engagement we have already had with transport organisations and other interested parties. We are seeking comments on this initial draft and will publish a final version following further engagement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/50194</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T11:49:08+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/19-5-million-to-kick-start-regeneration-in-portsmouth"/>
    <title>£19.5 million to kick start regeneration in Portsmouth</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work to kick-start the regeneration of the 22 hectare Tipner site in Portsmouth can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will see Portsmouth City Council deliver extensive improvements including a new access road to the site from the M275 and a new Park &amp;amp; Ride scheme. As well as improving access to the regeneration site at Tipner, the scheme will relieve traffic and congestion on local residential roads around the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This important scheme will encourage regeneration of the Tipner site by opening up access to the area for businesses and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new junction on the M275 and the new park and ride scheme will be a huge boost for the area - helping to deliver new homes and new jobs as well as reducing congestion and encouraging visitors to the city. Having visited Portsmouth to see for myself, I am in no doubt that this is a good scheme and a sensible use of taxpayers money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £19.5 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will deliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new motorway junction on the M275 at Tipner providing access to the development site and greatly reduce the impact of construction traffic on local roads - at present the only access to the site is via existing narrow Victorian streets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new additional bus priority lane on the M275 heading south from the new interchange - this is intended to improve public transport between Tipner and central Portsmouth and improve bus reliability, this will be an additional lane and would not remove any capacity for general traffic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a park and ride site accessed via the new motorway junction, with bus every 10 minutes to the city centre/Gunwharf Quays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tipner scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the spending review process. Work can now start on the construction with the project scheduled to complete in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Tipner scheme enabling work to begin.The department will provide a maximum of £19.5 million towards the full scheme cost of £28.19 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066 &lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292 &lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/48843</id>
    <published>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/office-of-rail-regulation"/>
    <title>Office of Rail Regulation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank-you ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great pleasure to join you today for this important conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here to talk about ‘transparency’ – one of those modern buzzwords that we hear all the time in politics, business, and the media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by giving you my own perspective on transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transparency-for-the-customer"&gt;Transparency for the customer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speak as a rail minister…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a regular user of the rail network…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a Liberal Democrat…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have campaigned for transparency ever since I was first elected in 1997.  The first bill I presented to Parliament was on the release of public records and I was the first person to submit a &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; request of MPs’ expenses, with all the ramifications that led to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you won’t be surprised that I’m a passionate believer in transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something we need to see more of from every powerful institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud of the progress we have made to open up government and the wider public sector in this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I will say this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about building the respect, trust and confidence of the people who use and fund the network - passengers, freight customers, and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true measure of transparency comes not from those who claim to practise it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes from those on the outside who stand to benefit from it… the passengers and the public who provide the patronage and pounds sterling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This must be a shared agenda, while we have made big strides over the past few years, we still have some way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Laidlaw report&lt;/a&gt; last week made a specific criticism of the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; when it said the department wasn’t transparent enough with bidders about the franchise process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are correcting that and we will be more transparent in future, but you have to do your bit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rail-transparency"&gt;Rail transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me put rail transparency in some sort of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.openpublicservices.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/"&gt;Open Public Services White Paper&lt;/a&gt; last year set the scene for the government’s transparency agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was followed this year by another White Paper and the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.data.gov.uk/library/dft-open-data-strategy"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s Open Data Strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental to these programmes are public services which are responsive to the people they serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations which can be held to account by citizens and elected representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open data is crucial to this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our rail reform programme highlighted 3 specific areas for transparency: rail finances; network performance and open access to information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so much has already been achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we are now publishing a great deal of performance data, from right time and passenger complaints to statistics on overcrowding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; has set out the costs of supporting the network by &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt;; subsidies per mile; and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Rail has separated accounts by route. And new information about &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt; finances will be published next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And passengers have much better access to timetables and real time service information than they had in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, data produced by Network Rail is allowing developers to generate phone and computer apps for passengers on how trains are running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a private-sector, not-for-dividend, company limited by guarantee, Network Rail is not currently subject to the Freedom of Information Act. Nonetheless, as a regulated provider of public services, in receipt of public subsidy, the company wisely recognises the demand for more of its information and data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, it began a programme to publish more of its information and data on its website, including an on-line form allowing members of the public to make suggestions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government welcomes these steps, which will improve the organisation’s accountability to passengers and taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I welcome the excellent news from the last &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dft-transport-sector-transparency-board"&gt;Transport Transparency Board&lt;/a&gt; that the fares database will be released as open data during the first quarter of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="olympics"&gt;Olympics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these transparency measures are designed for long-term dissemination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Olympic Games earlier this year set the industry a more immediate challenge around the provision of transport data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key part of the programme was to provide businesses and the public with information about the transport network, and which stations were likely to be busiest at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Transport for London"&gt;TfL&lt;/abbr&gt;, Network Rail, &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt; and train operators worked with organisers to produce ‘hotspot’ data which was published on the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.getaheadofthegames.com/"&gt;Get Ahead of the Games&lt;/a&gt; website – together with journey planners and interactive tools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site had over 16 million page views and 4 million unique users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it played a key role in what was an enormously successful operation to manage transport demand during the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience was invaluable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It showed just what can be achieved by planning ahead and communicating information to users of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was also a lesson in how to deliver data effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information is of little use if it’s too complicated or inaccessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to be carefully managed, targeted and presented to meet the needs and expectations of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely what was achieved by the team who delivered the Olympics transport plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fares-and-ticketing"&gt;Fares and ticketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the government re-shuffle back in September, the new &lt;a href="/government/people/patrick-mcloughlin"&gt;Secretary of State&lt;/a&gt; asked me to lead the &lt;a href="/government/consultations/rail-fares-and-ticketing-review"&gt;fares and ticketing review&lt;/a&gt; in the department.  You will appreciate that this is a hugely labyrinthine process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I am concerned, transparency is key to the review.  I want an outcome where the passenger can easily access the right information to enable them to buy the right ticket for their journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while many do, many don’t.  Indeed, there appears to be some confusion even at the highest levels, judging by &lt;abbr title="Association of Train Operating Companies"&gt;ATOC&lt;/abbr&gt;’s comments in the metro last week blaming the government for the rise in unregulated fares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now turn to the issue of right-time information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="right-time"&gt;Right-time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will know, I have been pushing for the release of right-time – the number of trains arriving within 59 seconds of the advertised arrival time - for some time now, actually for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first raised this formally at the Performance Delivery Group which I chair on 20 July 2011 and I am to be honest disappointed that it has taken this long to get where we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make it clear that it is not the intention of the government to replace &lt;abbr title="Public Performance Measure"&gt;PPM&lt;/abbr&gt; with right-time for performance benchmarking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may together conclude that the correct benchmark is whether a long-distance service arrives within 9 minutes and 59 seconds, but it is close to dishonest to suggest that a train arriving 9 minutes and 59 seconds after its stated arrival time is on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public are entitled to know the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I recognise, and indeed sympathise, that there is a concern within the industry that if this information is published, you will be attacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observe at this point that ScotRail recently released its right-time data and the world has not ended north of the border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that releasing information to the public can be uncomfortable – just look at the hundreds of &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; requests we have to deal with in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; each month.  But actually the free availability of information is a key tool to driving up performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry will be releasing right-time data by &lt;abbr title="Terms and conditions"&gt;TOC&lt;/abbr&gt; on 20 December, even if the timing means it won’t be getting much coverage, I will be making a lot of noise about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be making comments saying what a good showing this is from the industry.  In terms of both performance and transparency we’re ahead of our European competitors so this staging post is welcome, but we need to go further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commuter on the 6:40 from Aylesbury, the student on the 8:32 to Brighton and the occasional traveller on the 10:15 to Nuneaton have a right to know whether their train is regularly on time or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look fwd to these passengers having the data they need when we make a further right-time release in the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This information is held by the ORR and, as such, it is available under the &lt;abbr title="Freedom of Information"&gt;FOI&lt;/abbr&gt; laws.  It is in my view far better for the industry to be on the front-foot with this rather than have it extracted by someone hostile to the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-transport-sectors"&gt;Other transport sectors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that the rail industry is doing pretty well in punctuality.  Both in comparisons with other countries, and in this country when compared with other modes.  Why hide your light under a bushel as if there is a guilty secret?  Those of you who have been to my office will have heard me reference the poster in my office which champions the railway against the clogged road network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am determined the same level of transparency should apply to other transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Highways Agency, for example, has released a wide range of statistics about roadworks and real-time traffic conditions, and over 80% local authorities have opened up their roadwork data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working with the Agency to improve reliability data for the motorway network, and hope to publish information on the wider road network next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus industry has released its national database of services across Britain, with access to real time information from all 350,000 bus stops… &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple but enormously effective improvement for passengers, particularly during these winter months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the aviation industry is also embracing transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) is already publishing monthly punctuality data by route and airline for 10 UK airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our Civil Aviation Bill will enshrine further powers to collect and publish data to help the consumer. Specifically, it will require the industry to provide information that the CAA considers appropriate to help passengers understand and compare different services and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Aviation Bill has completed its passage through Parliament and now awaits Royal Assent.  We anticipate that this will be before Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s more the aviation industry could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, we would like the airlines to provide clearer information about the ticket price their customers should expect to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in reality, you have a good story to tell.  Some of you, however, are mindlessly trying to cover it up.  This is 1950s thinking and frankly, it won’t wash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me conclude by first of all recognising and congratulating the industry for the strides it has made towards greater transparency in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an industry that received £3 billion of public subsidy in 2010/11, the public has a right to clearer and more open information on costs, performance and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is what you are delivering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also urge you – wherever possible – to press ahead with further transparency in the future so it becomes embedded in the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe that whatever helps the passenger will ultimately help the railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17108</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"/>
    <title>Cash boost to get England cycling</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cities, towns and villages across England are set to benefit from an extra £20 million for cycle infrastructure.  The new funding was announced today by Transport Minister Norman Baker, at a conference in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new funding will help people take to two wheels.  Projects could include better cycle facilities at railway stations, improved cycle links, or projects to improve the layout of road junctions to make them more cycle-friendly. Previous investment has seen some great projects making a real difference in communities, including better cycle routes from residential areas to schools to encourage the next generation of cyclists to cycle more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s conference in Leicester, attended by Public Health Minister Anna Soubry and Norman Baker, explores how councils’ health and transport officials can work better together to deliver better options for cycling and walking in their local areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is great for your health, the economy, and for the environment so we are determined to make it easier for people to cycle whether for leisure, getting to the shops or as part of their commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following the success of the Olympics, there is a huge appetite for more cycling provision from the travelling public and we need to capitalise on this enthusiasm at local and national level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are investing £20 million in cycling infrastructure and getting councils to bring an end to silo working in their offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public Health Minister Anna Soubry said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being active helps us stay healthy and protects against life threatening conditions such as heart disease, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cycling is a great way for adults to get their recommended 150 minutes of physical activity each week and this funding will help encourage more people to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £20 million announced today is in addition to £30 million already announced for similar projects this year which drew in an additional £15 million in matched funding from local sources.  The projects to be funded will be announced later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"&gt;written statement&lt;/a&gt; was laid in Parliament this morning &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence today also published new &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.nice.org.uk/"&gt;guidance on public health for local authorities&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17109</id>
    <published>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/additional-funding-for-cycling-infrastructure"/>
    <title>Additional funding for cycling infrastructure</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coalition Government has today made available an additional £20m for our existing infrastructure projects to support cycling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funding will increase the total available for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Community Linking Places Fund (in addition to the £15m announced on 7 February 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving cycle safety at junctions (in addition to the £15m announced on 26 June 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Community Linking Places Fund is primarily for improvements to cycling and walking infrastructure, facilities and links. This includes improving access to the rail network by bicycle. In addition the fund aims to support jobs, enhance access to employment and encourage greater use of more environmentally friendly transport.   Projects currently being supported were announced on 6 March 2012. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investment in junctions - for use by English local authorities outside London - will help to tackle accident hotspots where cyclists have been killed or seriously injured, or are deemed to be at greater risk.  Local authorities are currently submitting bids for funding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand from local authorities, Sustrans and train operating companies, who are delivering the infrastructure, has been high.  An increase of £20m to the total funding available will allow the Government to support more high quality proposals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of the projects to be supported under the additional funding will be published early next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/cash-boost-to-get-england-cycling--2"&gt;Cash boost to get England cycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/17271</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/transport-scotland-high-speed-rail-summit"/>
    <title>Transport Scotland high speed rail summit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2gEnT-LreI&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU8mgf88hO4bbrfta9bcgZuA"&gt;Transport Scotland high speed rail summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="transcript"&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello and thank you for the opportunity to put on record coalition government’s commitment to high speed rail, and its determination that all parts of our country, including of course Scotland, should benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing demand for inter-city rail travel is putting increasing pressure on existing infrastructure. Without planning for additional capacity, passengers face the prospect of increasingly crowded and more unreliable services. To be clear, the primary, though not the only, justification for &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a clear need for extra capacity north to south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plans for a high speed rail network from London to the West Midlands and on to Leeds and Manchester will be the backbone of a new transport system for the 21st century.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2026, Phase 1 of High Speed 2 will link London and Birmingham. Comfortable trains travelling at 225 miles per hour will cut the journey time to just 45 minutes, compared to the 84 minutes it currently takes. Importantly for Scotland, the first phase of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will provide connections to the existing network at Birmingham, and also link &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; to &lt;abbr title="High Speed 1"&gt;HS1&lt;/abbr&gt;, opening up the opportunities for through trains to run from Scotland to Paris and Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completion of the Y network to Leeds and Manchester will further spread the benefits of high speed rail across the country, increasing capacity and enhancing connectivity all the way to Scotland by relieving pressure on the most congested southern end of the line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition agreement makes it clear that our ultimate goal is a genuinely national network, with high speed services from London to the Midlands and the north, including Scotland. We see phases one and two of the High Speed 2 project as the best way to make progress towards that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department for Transport ministerial team is very much engaged in the question of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; as it affects and, indeed, benefits Scotland. I visited Glasgow last year, the former Secretary of State went in March this year, and the current Secretary of State intends to visit later this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last month we announced the launch of a study on ways to get fast journeys further north and to Scotland, making sure that the north-east benefits too. The aim is to fully understand and articulate transport needs in Scotland and the north of England, setting out the remit for any future work, using completion of the ‘Y’ network as a starting point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study won’t start with any preconceptions but will be open to all options that offer good value for money to the taxpayer. This may include a full high speed solution, upgrades to existing infrastructure, or a combination of the two.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands today the network is expected to deliver up to £50 billion of business benefits alone and that will be felt very much in Scotland and the north of England as well as the South. The claim by some opponents of &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; that better and faster transport links between north and south will see economic activity pulled into London and away from the UK’s other great cities is defeatist and misguided, and out of line with public opinion. The further north you go, the louder are the voices in support of high speed rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing Edinburgh and Glasgow closer to London as well as the cities of the midlands and the north of England will undoubtedly boost growth across all of our major conurbations. That confidence is based on the evidence from our European neighbours, who began their high speed rail journey a generation before we had even started arguing about our first 67 mile stretch of high speed track from the channel tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With passengers enjoying faster journeys, there has been more extensive modal shift between rail and air as the train becomes the mode of choice for more travellers. High speed rail is already greener than flying and the gap between the two modes will widen as we make progress in decarbonising the sources of our electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; will benefit every type of traveller, not just on the new network, but on existing lines too, freeing up more space and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, not only will high speed rail help boost the Scottish economy and support thousands of jobs in Scotland and throughout the UK, it gives us a once-in-a-generation opportunity to reshape the economic geography of the whole country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever way you look at it, &lt;abbr title="High Speed 2"&gt;HS2&lt;/abbr&gt; is a national scheme in the national interest driven by a national government. Realising the full benefits of high speed rail for Scotland is crucial to the economic wellbeing of the whole country, and I can assure you we will continue to work very closely with our partners in Scotland to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/16957</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-11-26T11:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/green-light-for-weston-transport-improvements"/>
    <title>Green light for Weston transport improvements</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on a new package of public transport and road improvement measures in Weston-super-Mare can now start after receiving final approval from Local Transport Minister Norman Baker today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme will support economic growth in Weston-super-Mare and reduce congestion in the town centre. The work will also improve links between local roads and the M5 motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheme includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvements to increase capacity of the M5 Junction 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new link road for buses to access Worle railway station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bus priority measures at junctions and bus only sections to improve bus access to the south of Worle Station, linking it with regeneration areas at Weston Airfield and Locking Parklands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a new 320 space car park with a bus interchange, drop-off and cycle facilities together with improvements to the north-side car park at Worle Station&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increased capacity between the town centre and the regeneration areas through road widening and new routes for pedestrians and cyclists as well as bus priority measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norman Baker said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a great scheme that will support employment, reduce congestion and make it easier for people using public transport in and around Weston-super-Mare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The £10.4 million we are putting into this scheme shows that the coalition government is serious about investing in the infrastructure the country and the region needs to drive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Weston package scheme was one of the schemes given funding approval last year as part of the Spending Review process.  Work is currently planned to start in March 2013 with the package scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today’s announcement grants full (final) approval to the Weston package scheme enabling work to begin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The package of measures, promoted by North Somerset Council, is scheduled to open in April 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
