<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/patrick-mcloughlin</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/patrick-mcloughlin.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government - The Rt Hon Patrick McLoughlin MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65304</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:44:17+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"/>
    <title>Government's rail strategy receives independent endorsement</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent review of the government’s rail franchising strategy, following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition, has backed the overall policy while delivering advice for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Richard Brown, Chairman of Eurostar, to conduct a thorough investigation into how the government should manage its franchising programme following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast competition last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key conclusions from the Brown review stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the rail industry works, and that there is no credible case for major structural change (paragraph 1.4, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;passenger numbers have grown by 92% since privatisation… punctuality and passenger satisfaction are running at much improved levels… it is highly unlikely that these successes could have been delivered if franchising was fundamentally flawed (paragraph 1.5, p3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have now had nearly two decades’ experience of franchising and therefore a good idea as to what has worked and what still needs to be addressed (paragraph 1.6, p4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown’s report, published by the department today, recommends that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the department’s capability should be strengthened to manage future franchising programmes (paragraph 1.12, p8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise should be strengthened and simplified (paragraph 3.13, p23)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plans should be put in place to devolve more English franchises to the relevant authorities (paragraph 5.5, p37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Brown said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In carrying out this review I have come to the conclusion that the franchising system is not broken, but rather it has made a major contribution to Britain’s increasingly successful rail network. It is therefore essential for both passengers and the wider rail market that the franchising programme is restarted as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To achieve this goal, my review has identified a series of practical proposals and recommendations which, if implemented, will result in a stronger and more effective approach to franchising. In addition, I have provided the department with three broad options for them to consider where a strengthened franchising organisation might be located. As set out in both my review and the Laidlaw Report, the department must look to strengthen its franchising capability as a top priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Passengers cannot wait whilst theoretical discussions are held about the structure of railways. It is essential to get on with the franchising programme in order to maintain the momentum of investment in increasing capacity and improving services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The review has confirmed that government’s approach to rail franchising system is still the best way to secure the rail services for tax payers and fare payers alike. It has identified a number of detailed improvements, which I will carefully consider before publishing a further statement regarding the government’s franchising policy in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any delays to the franchising programme will not affect services for rail passengers and they will continue to receive the services they depend upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brown review was launched by the Department for Transport in October and follows work conducted by Sam Laidlaw, Chief Executive of Centrica and a non-executive DfT board member into what went wrong with the West Coast competition directly. His report was published in December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has recommended that by February the government should publish its plans for the Essex Thameside; Great Western; and the Thameslink, Southern and Great Northern franchise competitions which were put on hold last October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government considers that, until those plans had been agreed, it would be inappropriate to publish the specific recommendations about these three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government is planning to set out a programme for future franchise competitions in the spring alongside a further statement of franchising policy in light of the Brown Review and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"&gt;Rail franchising written statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 10 January 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department for Transport press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;br&gt;
Brown inquiry team press enquiries: 07584 115 270 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/65306</id>
    <published>2013-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-10T11:03:44+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--15"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Richard Brown’s review of the rail franchising programme.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I took the decision last October to cancel the competition for the InterCity West Coast rail franchise and to put the wider franchising process on hold, I commissioned two independent reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am today laying before the House the second of these, by Richard Brown, the Chairman of Eurostar and a highly respected industry figure. His report sets out his recommendations on how best to get the franchising programme back on course. I welcome this report, and am grateful to Mr Brown and his team for their swift and thorough consideration of the issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown concludes that franchising is a fundamentally sound approach for securing the passenger railway services on which so many people rely.  He has identified a number of detailed recommendations for improving the way that franchises are specified and franchise competitions are run. The issues he has identified deserve, and will get, very careful consideration. His recommendations include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that the franchising programme should be restarted as soon as possible, but at a pace that both the department and the industry can sustain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that franchise term should be determined by the circumstances and size of each individual franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals to strengthen and simplify the bidding and evaluation process for each franchise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposals for the financial and contractual structure of future franchises, including in relation to risk allocation and capital requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that the government should plan to devolve responsibility for further English franchises to the relevant authorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also makes recommendations on how to strengthen my department’s capability to manage the future franchising programme, echoing the findings of Sam Laidlaw’s independent inquiry into the lessons to be learnt from the InterCity West Coast competition.  My department has already published a response to Mr Laidlaw’s report, setting out a series of actions that will allow it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible.  The Permanent Secretary has now appointed a single director-general with responsibility for rail, including franchising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review recommends that the government should determine, by February, our plans for the three franchise competitions which I put on hold last October.  I accept that recommendation, and I will update the House when I have determined those plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, however, I consider that it would be inappropriate to publish Mr Brown’s specific recommendations about these three franchise competitions because of their stock market sensitivity, and so I have redacted the relevant paragraphs from the version of the report I have published today.  I will publish the redacted paragraphs once I have decided the way forward for those three competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Brown also recommends that we should set out a clear programme for future franchise competitions.  I will do so in the Spring, alongside a further statement of the government’s rail franchising policy in light of Mr Brown’s recommendations and the Transport Select Committee’s &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/transport-committee/inquiries/parliament-2010/rail-2020/"&gt;Rail 2020&lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="related-documents"&gt;Related documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/the-brown-review-of-the-rail-franchising-programme"&gt;The Brown review of the rail franchising programme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/governments-rail-strategy-receives-independent-endorsement"&gt;Government’s rail strategy receives independent endorsement press notice, 10 January 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Response to the report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Report of the Laidlaw inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/publications/letter-from-the-secretary-of-state-to-richard-brown"&gt;Letter from the Secretary of State to Richard Brown, 15 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/news/west-coast-main-line-franchise-competition-cancelled"&gt;West Coast Main Line franchise competition cancelled press notice, 3 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/government/speeches/statement-on-west-coast-main-line-and-franchising"&gt;West Coast Main Line and franchising oral statement by the Secretary of State for Transport, 29 October 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/61008</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T10:41:37+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-to-tackle-local-pinch-points"/>
    <title>Cash boost to tackle local pinch points </title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Councils are invited to apply for a share of the £170 million Local Pinch Point Fund to remove bottlenecks on the highway network.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advice for local councils wanting to apply for a share of a £170 million fund to remove bottlenecks on the local highway network and support growth-enhancing development was published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funding forms part of an additional £1.5 billion of government investment, announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement, to improve the road network and reduce congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Local Pinch Point Fund will tackle obstacles on the local transport network that restrict growth by limiting the movement of goods, employees and customers. The investment will build on the success of the Highways Agency’s Pinch Point Fund for the strategic road network, which received an extra £100 million in the Autumn Statement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tackling congestion and making the most of our infrastructure is essential for economic growth.  We have already provided significant funding to local authorities to promote growth but more can be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That is why we are providing this additional £170 million to help councils free up key bottlenecks on the highway network. This funding will unlock development sites to help local businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment will fund improvements which have an immediate impact on growth with the aim that all schemes will be delivered as quickly as possible - funding will be available until March 2015. The schemes delivered as part of this programme will help create additional jobs and housing and could include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving existing local roads to ease congestion bottlenecks, speed up journey times and improving reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provision of new roads, junctions or roundabouts to improve access to business or housing development sites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strengthening or repairing of bridges or retaining walls which would otherwise lead to traffic restrictions and cause delays for traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement on the 5 December 2012 announced the allocation of £170 million for a Local Pinch Point Fund to help address congestion on the local road network in England, which are acting as an impediment to economic growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fund is available to local highway and transport authorities in England - Transport for London will be able to bid for up to £10 million of the fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.highways.gov.uk/news/press-releases/170m-road-boost-for-local-economies/"&gt;Highways Agency Pinch Point Programme&lt;/a&gt; was announced on 8 October 2012 - investment from earlier rounds of the Highways Agency’s programme is removing bottlenecks and keeping traffic moving on England’s motorways and major A roads, with a potential to deliver more than 300,000 new jobs and 150,000 new homes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the guidance for the application process for local authorities is available on the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-transport/series/local-pinch-point-fund"&gt;GOV.UK website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60967</id>
    <published>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-03T09:31:25+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/end-of-the-road-for-over-9-000-traffic-signs"/>
    <title>End of the road for over 9,000 traffic signs</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>As unnecessary signs are removed from our roads the Secretary of State calls for local authorities to continue the cull.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of traffic signs are being brought down across the country as part of a government drive to rid our streets of clutter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin today urged local authorities to continue the cull. He has also unveiled a new document called ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ that provides guidance to local authorities on how to remove unnecessary traffic signs as cost-effectively as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In London alone 8,000 repeater signs and 4,000 poles installed on the capital’s roads in the early 1990s have been ripped out. Laid out side by side these would stretch almost 2.5 miles. In Hampshire 200 traffic signs have been taken away along a 12 mile stretch of the A32 while Somerset has also done away with a further 1,000 signs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transport Secretary is encouraging other local authorities across the country to follow suit. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are too many unnecessary signs blotting the landscapes of our towns and cities. That is why I have published new guidance, to help encourage local authorities to make old, confusing and ugly signs a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate London, Hampshire and Somerset councils for leading the way and getting rid of sign clutter. They are a fantastic example and I urge other councils to think about where traffic signs are placed and whether they are needed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dana Skelley, Director of Roads at Transport for London (TfL), said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary street clutter can make the journeys of all road users awkward, regardless whether they are motorists, cyclists or pedestrians, and can dissuade people from visiting local areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By identifying and removing unnecessary poles, signs and other street furniture, we can make our road network more accessible and help transform our city environment into one that people can enjoy working, shopping and socialising in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaun Spiers, Chief Executive of Campaign to Protect Rural England, said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individual signs may be added with the best intentions but before long can sprout into a forest of clutter that degrades our countryside and distracts drivers.  Rather than being hectored by health and safety signs alerting of any possible risk, people driving on rural roads should be encouraged to expect to share minor rural roads with a range of other road users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope many local authorities will take heed of the Secretary of State’s call and make a spring clean of clutter one of their New Year’s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new traffic signs advisory document provides local authorities with various hints and tips to help get them started in removing pointless signs. It also encourages authorities to think about: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improving the streetscape by identifying and removing unnecessary, damaged and worn-out signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping to ensure signs are provided only where they are needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minimising the environmental impact, particularly in rural settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reducing costs, not just of the signs themselves but maintenance and energy costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the ‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/reducing-sign-clutter"&gt;Reducing sign clutter&lt;/a&gt;’ traffic advisory leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The signs removed in London are red repeater signs. They reinforce the meaning of the restriction imposed by the double red lines – ‘no stopping’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research carried out by the department on the traffic signs policy review, showed that people already have a clear understanding of the red route marking, without the need for the upright signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For new signs, the aim should be to make sure there is no clutter from the start. The advice challenges sign designers to use their knowledge and judgement to place traffic signs only where there is a clear need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/signing-the-way-traffic-signs-policy-review"&gt;Signing the way&lt;/a&gt;’ was published in October 2011 and set out the conclusions of the traffic signs policy review. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Department for Transport is currently revising the ‘&lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2002/3113/contents/made"&gt;Traffic Signs Regulations and General Directions&lt;/a&gt;’ with the aim of giving councils more discretion in how and where they place traffic signs. We are aiming to have the new regulations in force by 2014. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60283</id>
    <published>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/department-for-transports-boost-to-train-builders"/>
    <title>Department for Transport's boost to train builders</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>New train carriages procured by Southern Railway. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train builders have received a year-end boost as the government announces its backing for two new train orders, Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin announced today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of government support, Southern Railway has now procured 40 new carriages from Bombardier based in Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the 40 carriages, the government is also supporting Southern’s tendering process for 116 new electric carriages with the option for a further 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our support for Southern will not only boost capacity but help secure British jobs. The deal for the 40 new carriages, helped along by my department, demonstrates the government’s ongoing commitment to invest in Britain’s railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My officials are working with Southern to accelerate their procurement process for up to 256 carriages because our ambitious electrification plans requires additional rolling stock on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2011 Southern Railway, with government support, announced its plans to buy 130 carriages from Bombardier to run on services in south London, Surrey, Sussex and Kent. Southern expects these will be in service by December 2013. As part of this deal Southern had the option to buy the additional 40 carriages at a later stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July the government announced the biggest programme of rail modernisation since the Victorian era. At the heart of the scheme was the electrification of the Midland Main Line, from London to Sheffield, with additional spurs linking it to the Great Western Main Line and the Port of Southampton.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Southern progresses with the procurement, these 116 new vehicles, and potentially 140 more, could initially be used on the Thameslink routes. Once the expected new Thameslink trains are operational these carriages will be moved to the newly electrified routes, which could include the Midland Main Line to Corby and North Transpennine Routes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/60121</id>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:48:26+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/rail-franchising--14"/>
    <title>Rail franchising</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Compensation package for passengers agreed with London Midland.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would today like to give an update on the situation in relation to franchised train operator London Midland (&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passengers who use &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; trains may be aware that the operator has been experiencing difficulties recently, with a number of services being cancelled due to a shortage of driving staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation has caused inconvenience and disruption, particularly to passengers in the West Midlands, many of whom have expressed their dissatisfaction to me. I very much share their disappointment that they have not had the reliable service that they rightly expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although the recent levels of performance have been extremely disappointing, I am pleased to say that the measures that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; have put in place are beginning to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has implemented increases to driver efficiency to enable drivers to operate an increased number of routes during existing shifts, improved driver training processes, provided additional incentives for drivers to work overtime and put in place new measures that allow for drivers to cover shifts on other parts of the network where there are shortages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in addition to the ongoing training programme that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; is undertaking to ensure that new drivers enter productive service as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;’s performance has been of such a level that they are now in breach of their contractual obligations. We have made London Midland aware that they must now take action to compensate passengers for the disruption caused. We have, therefore, agreed with &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; that they will provide a substantial package of passenger benefits by way of compensation for the inconvenience that has been caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has agreed to spend an additional £4 million over the remainder of the franchise to put in place measures to ensure that these problems do not happen again. In addition, the package of passenger benefits includes the issue of 5 free rail day passes to London Midland season ticket holders, with an expected value of up to £3.5 million. We have also agreed that London Midland will invest a further £2.25 million in infrastructure improvement projects. We have required London Midland to discuss with Centro, the West Midlands Passenger Transport Executive, how the majority of this money will be invested for the benefit of those passengers who have experienced the worst disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this consultation, &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; has agreed that most of this money should be directed towards measures such as improvements to safety and security at stations and improving the reliability and efficiency of &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we have also agreed with &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; that they must make available an additional 500,000 Advance tickets on key routes on the &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; network, giving a net benefit of around £1.9 million to passengers who will be able to take advantage of these cheaper fares over the next two years of the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; will be able to remain the operator of this franchise for the remainder of its contract - to September 2015. But London Midland will continue to work to challenging performance benchmarks for the remainder of the franchise, and we will take further action (including ending the franchise early and re-tendering it, if appropriate) in the event of any recurrence of performance problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the package of passenger benefits, we have agreed to revise the profile of performance benchmarks for the next year, to include additional measures that can penalise &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; financially in the event of further poor performance. We have also agreed financial measures to ensure that the reduction in revenue as a result of the free and discounted tickets is borne by &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt;, and not by the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that this package, on balance, represents a good deal for passengers and taxpayers, and sends a message to the industry that this level of cancellations is unsatisfactory. I hope that &lt;abbr title="London Midland"&gt;LM&lt;/abbr&gt; can now put this period behind it, and continue to operate a good service for its passengers for the remainder of its franchise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/57030</id>
    <published>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-18T10:38:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/cash-boost-for-local-roads"/>
    <title>Cash boost for local roads</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Extra £215 million to local authorities for road maintenance.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Councils can plan how to spend their share of a £215 million fund for local road maintenance after funding allocations were published today by Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £215 million is part of a £333 million fund announced in the Chancellor’s Autumn Statement for essential maintenance to renew, repair and extend the life of roads in England.  This funding is in addition to the £3 billion the government is already providing for councils in England between 2011 and 2015 for highways maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This maintenance funding could be used for improvements such as road resurfacing, maintenance to bridges or repairing damage to highway infrastructure caused by severe weather events, such as the recent flooding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This extra money will support economic growth and development by helping local authorities to get the best out of their local road networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This funding can be spent on measures to bring smoother, safer and more reliable journeys to the travelling public whether they are commuting to work or taking the children to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help local residents see where this money has been spent it will be a condition of the funding that local authorities commit to publishing a short statement on their websites at the end of each financial year setting out what and where this additional funding has been spent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local authorities are also encouraged to look at the information published by the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep"&gt;Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme&lt;/a&gt; which is leading the way by bringing together the public and private sectors to develop good practice and reduce costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne announced in the Autumn Statement on 5 December additional funding of £333 million for highways maintenance for both the motorway and trunk road and local road network. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;£215 million additional capital funding will be provided to local highway authorities, including London, to help renew and repair the network in England. £140 million will come in 2013 to 2014, with the remaining £75 million following in 2014 to 2015. The funds will be distributed on the basis of the department’s existing highways maintenance capital funding formula. A &lt;a href="/government/publications/local-transport-capital-block-funding"&gt;full list of the allocations by region and local authority&lt;/a&gt; is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be eligible for this additional funding and to promote greater transparency and accountability, the department will require local highway authorities to publish a brief note on their website by the end of each financial year (end of April 2014 and end of April 2015) on where (in terms of location) and how this additional funding was spent on highways maintenance. This is so local communities are able to see how this extra funding has been spent. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Highways Maintenance Efficiency Programme (HMEP) is a sector-led programme designed to maximise returns from highways investment and deliver efficient and effective services.  HMEP provides practical guidance on highway maintenance efficiencies for local authorities, supplier organisations and representative bodies in the form of toolkits, case studies and good practice.  The most recent of these, launched on 29 November, are the &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/standard-spec.php"&gt;standard specification&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a rel="external" href="http://www.dft.gov.uk/hmep/efficiency/asset-management.php"&gt;asset management toolkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries: 020 7944 3066&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18821</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T11:50:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T11:50:22+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/west-coast-main-line-final-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"/>
    <title>West Coast Main Line: Final report of the Laidlaw inquiry</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Final report of the Laidlaw inquiry released.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The independent inquiry into the cancelled West Coast Main Line franchise competition has concluded that the project failed because of an accumulation of significant errors related to inadequate planning and preparation, complex organisational structure, and a weak governance framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport Secretary Patrick McLoughlin asked Sam Laidlaw, the chief executive of Centrica and a non-executive &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; board member, to conduct an urgent investigation following the discovery of unacceptable flaws in the procurement process that led to the competition being cancelled on October 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;final report&lt;/a&gt;, published today by the Department for Transport, finds that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; used flawed and inconsistent methodology when guiding bidders on the amount of risk capital (known as the Subordinated Loan Facility) they would need to offer to guarantee their franchise against default (Inquiry report paragraph 4.31, p22)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Subordinated Loan Facility figures resulting from the flawed methodology were then varied in a way that contravened franchise competition rules (3.4, p11)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ministers made the original August 14 provisional contract award without being told about the critical flaws (2.12, p8) and having been given “inaccurate reports” (3.8, p12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the Laidlaw Inquiry also concluded that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the report’s recommendations to strengthen accountability and governance structures “if acted upon quickly and effectively, will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement” (paragraph 8.6, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;while there were inconsistencies in the way First Group and Virgin Trains Ltd were treated during the franchise process, the report finds that there is no evidence of a culture of bias against Virgin at the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; (paragraph 2.6, p7)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is nothing in the report to suggest that the flaws discovered in this franchise competition exist in any other &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; procurements (paragraph 8.3, p79)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; is today publishing its formal response to the report which commits the department to implementing swiftly a series of actions that will enable it to resume the franchising programme, with the confidence of the rail industry, as soon as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring future franchise competitions are delivered at a good pace based on sound planning, a clear timeline, rigorous management, and the right quality assurance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a simpler and clearer structure and governance process for rail franchise competitions, including the appointment of a single director general with responsibility for all rail policy and franchising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring we have the right mix of professional skills, in-house, and where necessary from professional external advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Building upon and confirming the conclusions from my initial findings, the final report provides an in-depth analysis of the events that led to the flaws whereby the InterCity West Coast competition was cancelled. Alongside this I have also made a series of recommendations for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have explained in detail the technical nature of certain errors, specifically around modelling flaws and the Subordinated Loan Facility sizing process. In addition, the report outlines an accumulation of contributory causes including a lack of transparency, inadequate planning and preparation, as well as a complex and confusing organisational structure with weak quality assurance and insufficient governance oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While it is clear that a number of serious and regrettable errors have occurred, I believe that if acted upon quickly and effectively, my recommendations will help to restore confidence in the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;’s ability to conduct effective rail franchising and procurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The final report from the Laidlaw inquiry makes extremely uncomfortable reading for the department. It has identified precisely what went wrong, revealing serious failures, as well as offering us a number of sensible recommendations to put things right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will not allow these mistakes to be made again and the department is determined to ensure all future franchise competitions are conducted on the basis of sound planning, the rigorous identification and oversight of risk, and the right quality assurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He added: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sam Laidlaw has delivered an uncompromising report that offers us a way to face up to a number of shortcomings and I would like to thank him and his team for producing these findings with such diligence and speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; Permanent Secretary Philip Rutnam said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no question that this has been a serious blow for the department and I am determined that we learn everything we can from this episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will implement all of Mr Laidlaw’s recommendations, and go further, to ensure we have the right set of skills, support and training to ensure failures like this do not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-to-editors"&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;Laidlaw inquiry final report to the Transport Secretary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/response-to-the-report-of-the-laidlaw-inquiry"&gt;department’s response to the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report&lt;/a&gt;, setting out the actions being taken immediately to resolve the report recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/laidlaw-inquiry-final-report"&gt;Transport Secretary’s oral statement to the House of Commons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Laidlaw inquiry’s final report is only part of the work the department is doing to review its rail franchising policy. It will also take into account the forthcoming &lt;abbr title="National Audit Office"&gt;NAO&lt;/abbr&gt; report into the lessons from the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise and the conclusions of Richard Brown’s review of the future of the rail franchising programme, due to be submitted to the Secretary of State by the end of December&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Department for Transport press office: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of hours: 020 7944 4292  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press enquiries to the Laidlaw inquiry team: 020 7861 2410&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public enquiries: 0300 330 3000  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18775</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T07:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/virgin-trains-to-run-improved-west-coast-services"/>
    <title>Virgin Trains to run improved west coast services</title>
    <category>News article</category>
    <summary>Virgin Trains to continue operating rail services on the West Coast Main Line for up to 23 months.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rail passengers will experience better services including 28,000 more seats a day under an agreement announced today for Virgin Trains to continue operating rail services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new franchise agreement will run for up to 23 months after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It coincides with the early completion of a government-backed deal to roll out 106 new Pendolino carriages, providing passengers with four new 11-carriage trains and lengthening 31 existing trains from nine carriages to 11. A new hourly service between London and Glasgow will also be introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick McLoughlin said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are determined to ensure not only that passengers continue to experience the same levels of service they have in the past, but that services improve. There will be a new hourly service linking Glasgow and London and we will also work with Virgin Trains to explore other service improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am also extremely pleased that passengers will benefit from up to 28,000 more seats daily thanks to the delivery of 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line which has happened on budget and ahead of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passengers travelling on Virgin Trains will also find it easier to claim compensation if their train is severely delayed thanks to plans for Virgin Trains to introduce an improved passenger’s charter incorporating a delay repay scheme from 1 April 2013, subject to agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="notes-for-editors"&gt;Notes for editors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 23 month franchise will run from 9 December 2012 until 9 November 2014 after which the West Coast Main Line will be let under a long-term franchise. The Department for Transport (&lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;) will be able to shorten this period by up to six months if a subsequent franchise can be let on a shorter timescale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The franchise will operate as a management contract with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;. In return Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;) will receive a margin of 1% on revenue for operating services. The franchise also makes a provision for the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 106 Pendolino carriages project has been delivered on budget and ahead of schedule and has resulted from a successful collaboration between the &lt;abbr title="Department for Transport"&gt;DfT&lt;/abbr&gt;, Virgin Trains, Alstom, Angel Trains and Network Rail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Enquiries: 020 7944 3108&lt;br&gt;
Out of Hours: 020 7944 4292&lt;br&gt;
Public Enquiries: 0300 330 3000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18789</id>
    <published>2012-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-12-06T09:32:19+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/intercity-west-coast-franchise"/>
    <title>InterCity West Coast franchise</title>
    <category>Statement to parliament</category>
    <summary>Virgin Trains to continue to operate services on the West Coast Main Line. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 15 October 2012 I announced to the House that following the cancellation of the InterCity West Coast franchise competition the Department for Transport was commencing negotiations with Virgin Rail Group (&lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can today announce that negotiations have concluded successfully and that Virgin Trains will continue to operate services on the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After careful consideration I believe taxpayers, rail passengers and the wider rail industry will be better served by moving directly from this agreement with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to a longer term franchise on the West Coast Main Line. Doing so will provide greater certainty for passengers, minimise disruption for all stakeholders and enable us to maximise the benefits for taxpayers and West Coast passengers. For this reason the new franchise with &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will be for up to 23 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also pleased to announce that passengers will not only experience the same levels of service they have previously enjoyed but will also benefit from improvements to previous levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition this agreement coincides with the successful completion today, on budget and ahead of schedule, of a project to deliver 106 new Pendolino carriages onto the West Coast Main Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new carriages, which will see up to 28,000 extra seats provided each day, are being introduced with £1.5 billion of government support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new franchise agreement, there will also be a new hourly service between London and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This franchise will operate as a management contract, with both revenue and cost risk being borne by the government. In return &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; will receive a margin of 1% on revenue. The contract also makes a provision for the department and &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; to agree revised commercial terms that would see &lt;abbr title="Virgin Rail Group"&gt;VRG&lt;/abbr&gt; take greater revenue and cost risk in the period to 9 November 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
