<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-GB" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:/government/people/peter-luff</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/people/peter-luff.atom"/>
  <title>Inside government -  Peter Luff MP</title>
  <subtitle>Latest</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>HM Government</name>
  </author>
  <updated>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45364</id>
    <published>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-12-ssafa-fund-raising-dinner-ads-event-as-part-of-farnborough-2012"/>
    <title>2012/07/12 - SSAFA Fund Raising Dinner (ADS event as part of Farnborough 2012)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Sir Stephen [CAS].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you to the ADS team for hosting tonight’s dinner.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on a very successful Farnborough 2012, and to all the sponsors and donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you are laying plans for an equally successful Farnborough 2014, and a show within a show - the Unmanned Aerial Systems Expo. This is a really important area for us and the UK needs to demonstrate leadership. This initiative is therefore doubly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks to Robin for his remarks, and to you in the aerospace industries for recognising so  generously the support from ministers across government at this year’s show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of government representation is certainly a far cry from the days when you were lucky to be able to secure just one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we do value the aerospace sector - civil and defence - and we understand the role of government in supporting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting it with words and deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words with real intent. And tangible deeds that count. Such as the Chancellor highlighting the aerospace sector in his Budget speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the old cliche has it, “actions speak louder then words.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visit companies, not just defence companies, I always wait for that moment when they give me the well worn line about people being their greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It too is a cliche - but it happens to be true, as all good cliches are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret in business is to mean it, and to be able to demonstrate a genuine commitment to it. Not just to say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s not a company going through the motions and just paying lip service to this maxim which impresses me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really impresses me is a company proving that the men and women who work for them really are their greatest resource&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because people matter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s my theme tonight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know for a fact, for example, that SSAFA Forces Help does demonstrate that commitment and support in a very practical way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA knows that people are at the heart of defence and that what they do when they serve Queen and country demands a generous response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a week when the platforms have taken centre stage, it’s worth reminding ourselves that for Defence people really are our greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That stunning display from Typhoon was only possible because of the skills of the pilot - Scott,  the people in the engineering crew on the ground, the people in industry who support the plane, the people in four nations who make it and the brilliant people who designed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People, always people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I know he’s not here so I can say nice things about him behind his back, that link is personified in the work of your chairman, General Sir Kevin O’Donoghue, who moved from platforms to people when he moved from CDM to SSAFA. MOD’s loss was SSAFA’s gain.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have emotions, ambitions, skills, hopes and fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it turns out there are even those in the defence industry who have emotions too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - let me just say for the record that I’ve always found Robin Southwell to be a business like chap, a matter of fact kind of guy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His role as ADS President is to fight your corner, champion your interests and act as an advocate for industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his job in EADS is to sell me anything he can. And he does a good job in both roles, in a robust kind of way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he is a man who says what he thinks. I think “shooting from the lip” is the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was still rather taken aback when I opened the Financial Times  earlier this year - Friday 24 February to be precise - and saw a piece about the defence industry’s relationship with Government which read - and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love,” says Robin Southwell, head of the UK arm of EADS, the pan-European defence contractor and president of ADS, the industry’s biggest trade group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was - as you can imagine, because I do like to think of myself as emotionally aware and sensitive man - most concerned by this heartfelt plea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the next time that I met Robin I went out of my way to ensure that he did feel sufficiently cherished. That he got the love he craved.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember engulfing him in a fond embrace in the street outside Portcullis House in the Palace of Westminster. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, Robin did seem rather taken aback.  I like to think he was probably just carried away by the sheer emotion of the moment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, though, he was reacting to my comment that this demonstration of love discharged all MoD’s financial obligations to EADS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, “We don’t want money, all we want is love.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tribute-to-industry"&gt;Tribute to industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do hope that everyone here this evening from industry appreciates that we do recognise the vital contribution you are making to our defence effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular your responsiveness in recent years when it has come to our operations in Libya and Afghanistan in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, thanks to your efforts, our forces today are better equipped than ever before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know that because of the universally positive feedback I get from one very discerning focus group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People whose lives very often depend on the way we deliver  acquisition and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking here of course about our servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meet them regularly on my visits to theatre and here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They speak in glowing terms about the quality and availability of their equipment.  The protection and cutting edge, battle winning capability of the equipment you produce and we provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your contribution is likely to grow as we develop the Total Support Force concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you will make that contribution with people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their talent and dedication will enable our Armed Forces to keep the nation safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one major obstacle - and I’ll be talking about this in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have heard what the Prime Minister said on Monday about the Aerospace Growth Partnership and the beginning of a similar dialogue with the defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the approach set out in the Aerospace Growth Partnership  and the National Security through Technology White Paper, we will now begin a dialogue with you to see what we can do to create an environment in which you are strong and can flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope it will put paid, once and for all, to some of the speculative debate about our real intent our the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper may be tough love Robin, but it is love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, though, we can also start looking forward and talking about the wider context. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be much to talk about. Challenges and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the top of the agenda I believe will be the obstacle I referred to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the whole issue of skills.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any business needs the right people to succeed. Your companies are no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - of course you need a healthy order book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But without skilled engineers in particular you simply won’t be able to develop and integrate the equipment, to write the software, to understand and interpret our requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these people we cannot safeguard our operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know you can’t find them. At all levels of engineering and in all disciplines there seems to be a shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met one engineering company a few months ago who’ve given up looking for engineers in the UK and are recruiting from Spain, Portugal and Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smaller defence companies I meet complain about all kinds of things, and understandably so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But top of their list is skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked about these issues endlessly as a nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers just aren’t valued sufficiently highly in this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an urban myth that this country doesn’t make anything anymore. And that manufacturing is dead or dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So schools don’t encourage bright young people into science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And anyway they’re often too focussed on university and not enough on technical vocational options for their pupils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities offer too many general courses that don’t produce the technical, specialist skills you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am absolutely passionate about the need to do more about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not making specific suggestions here tonight to address it, but I certainly hope it will be a major theme of the dialogue the Prime Minister announced on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the only one, but perhaps the most important one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people are indeed our most important asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s show is of course a great chance to enthuse and inspire future generations of engineers and scientists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you’ll be doing that at tomorrow’s dedicated Futures Day when you should have 7,500 young people there from schools and universities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets hope their visit to Farnborough tomorrow will inspire some of these young people to pursue a career in science and engineering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of initiative I warmly commend - it’s definitely the way forward for our science and technology sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the Bloodhound world land speed record project which is doing excellent work to inspire school pupils with the massive excitement of technical innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus tonight has been on people and I have spoken about the needs of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is also the case in Defence, that people in industry serve the people in our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask a lot of these servicemen and women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we also ask a lot of their families.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We owe them all a huge debt of gratitude for the sacrifices they make on our behalf. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the work of SSAFA is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why the money you raise this evening will make a real difference to the lives of thousands of men, women and children. Serving personnel, families and veterans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSAFA promises a lifetime of support - and it delivers just that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our oldest service charities, it works tirelessly to provide a wealth of practical, hands on support and guidance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its people include many experts and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to health and social work, for example, and running the SSAFA Norton Homes which provide accommodation for families visiting injured personnel recovering at Birmingham and Headley Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is also a huge pool of committed volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of men and women who give up their time to work in communities, bases, units and garrisons up and down the country, as well as overseas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money you pledge tonight will ensure SSAFA Forces Help has the money it needs to continue this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Defence Minister I have the huge privilege of working with and for the United Kingdom’s Armed Forces - quite simply the  bravest, most committed people it is possible to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are our nation’s greatest asset, and tonight our generosity can demonstrate our understanding of that vital truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45370</id>
    <published>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-07-02-motorsport-industry-association"/>
    <title>2012/07/02 - Motorsport Industry Association</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Alistair [Fergusson, Managing Director of Alcon Components] for that introduction. It is a pleasure to see you all here this evening and I am grateful to Chris [Aylett, Chief Executive Officer of the Motorsport Industry Association] for inviting me to say a few words. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorsport is one of the few, perhaps the only, high tech industry where the UK is comprehensively world beating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technological advantage born in the UK continues to deliver race wins and championships around the world, season after season, under the flag of almost every nationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It supports tens of thousands of high value jobs here in the UK and puts billions of pounds into the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will forgive me for reminding you that, as a former chairman of the Business, Innovation and Skills Committee, I published a report that recognised your industry as one of national importance and a crown jewel of UK manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I think that was one of my own recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely stand by that conclusion. And from my office in the Ministry of Defence, I can see that you are in fact even more important than that report said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Armed Forces, technological advantage is - quite literally - a matter of life or death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be the case, that where the military led the civilian world followed. But more than ever this is a trend that is reversing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yours is a sector more responsible for this than most. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to say that Defence is harnessing the technological strides being made in your industry like never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One person more than any other is to thank for the blossoming of this relationship - and not just for being our host tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Drayson [Rt Hon Lord Drayson of Kensington], when he was sat in my place at the MOD, led the establishment of the first formal dialogue between your industry and the Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His other great gift to Defence was the Centre for Defence Enterprise - but that’s a subject of another occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He, of course, has quite a motor-racing pedigree himself - I’ve been following his Tweets from Goodwood over the weekend - so it is no surprise that he had the foresight to recognise the benefits that your industry could bring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, while success has many fathers, he should be justly proud of our biggest collaborative achievement so far, the delivery of the first Foxhound patrol vehicles to Afghanistan only last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound is a UK design and 90% of the companies involved in its production are UK based. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is only possible because British companies like you enable us to exploit state of the art technologies in areas such as machining and composites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound is an amazingly agile piece of kit, with an engine which can be removed and replaced in just 30 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been designed to withstand a direct strike from an Improvised Explosive Device and, not only keep those inside safe, but be able to drive away on just three wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Ricardo who was responsible for the original concept and has been instrumental in its design and manufacture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it was an ex-Formula One design engineer who was responsible for the vehicle pod, using materials more commonly found on the Grand Prix circuit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, Lifeline Fire &amp;amp; Safety Systems provide the innovative fire suppression systems to the engine and internal compartment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also had similar success with other MIA members on important projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, you have already heard from Alistair of Alcon Components, who have used their extensive motorsport experience to provide brakes for an upgraded Jackal armoured vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NAR group have drawn on their Paris-Dakar experience to design a new dust proof cooling system for the Panther, Mastiff and Ridgeback vehicles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorsport has made many other contributions to Defence - in airframes and radars for example. You should be proud of these achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are making a very real difference to our personnel in Afghanistan today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may have already noted that the Army has a penchant for naming their vehicles after dogs. Foxhound, Mastiff, Husky, Jackal, Ridgeback, Wolfhound, Springer…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now we have adopted another canine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was at Millbrook driving Foxhound, I was asked by Richard Noble to be an engineering champion for the Bloodhound project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to propel the land speed record beyond a thousand miles per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you will know, the Royal Air Force and the Army are already deeply involved supporting the construction of the vehicle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will also be supporting the record attempts themselves in 2013 and 2014 in South Africa. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed the driver, Andy Green, is himself a serving officer in RAF, with the very ordinary job of Tornado pilot when he is not off breaking records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared access to leading edge, high performance engineering will, I have no doubt, bring direct benefit back into Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the project - just like the broader motorsport industry - is energising interest in science, technology, engineering and mathematics in our young people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sparking the imagination of the next generation of engineers and scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them will, in future, be responsible for winning championships, and boosting our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of them will be responsible for winning wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of winning, we come to the award…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Peter Luff MP then presented the award for Outstanding Contribution to the Motorsport Industry to John Surtees, OBE] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45368</id>
    <published>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-28-the-defence-industrial-base-a-critical-component-of-military-capability"/>
    <title>2012/06/28 - The Defence Industrial Base - A Critical Component of Military Capability</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It really is a pleasure to be at RUSI once again and to have the opportunity of discussing such an important issue and at such an appropriate moment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, to those from industry, I’m very glad that this event is focusing on you, and your businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the challenges - and opportunities - you will be encountering as Defence becomes more streamlined. More challenging. And more disciplined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an appropriate moment for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is published, the defence budget is balanced, defence transformation continues apace, we are near reaching conclusions on the future of DE&amp;amp;S and the National Audit Office is considering our equipment plan prior to its publication. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s clearly the right moment to clarify some of the issues affecting defence companies. I also say that because I was somewhat baffled by elements of the pre-conference papers for this event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There appear to be a number of misunderstandings - which I suspect may be more widely shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m aware that some of these misunderstandings could be down to us. Perhaps we in MOD have not been sufficiently clear when it comes to explaining the principles, rationale and implications of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months on we’re now busy taking the White Paper forward. Have we, though, successfully concluded the whole communication process with industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked hard - and continue to do so - to make sure that the logic and implications of our White Paper are fully understood within the MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing a mindset has taken time even within our own organisation, never mind across industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think I may need to bang the drum a bit louder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take SMEs - Small and Medium-sized enterprises.  I was more than a little surprised when I saw that there was no mention at all of SMEs in those pre-conference papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s because they are the life blood of any industry and are therefore something I highlight in every speech and meeting. Today will be no exception. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, repeating new truths doesn’t necessarily mean we think all the old ones have all lost their validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if I talk up SMEs and don’t say so much about Primes, it’s not because I don’t value both. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s because I think we all - the Armed Forces, MOD, DE&amp;amp;S and the Primes - need to value SMEs much more than we have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I welcome today as an opportunity to set the record straight on a number of fronts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on I’ll be exploring the whole ‘off the shelf’ principle, and our commitment to exports. As well as clarifying our stance on sovereign requirements.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, though, I want you from industry to be in no doubt whatsoever that you are a critical component of military capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your people, your products, your services equip, transport, protect, clothe, feed, support our Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Secretary of State has made clear, the defence of our nation is a team effort. Defence contractors, civilians and the Armed Forces themselves are the three essential pillars of the whole force concept which delivers modern defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are hundreds of you, of every size - primes, medium and small, even micro enterprises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you have a global presence - others are smaller firms based just here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are involved in a range of activities and would not brand yourselves as defence-centric companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of you have been involved in the provision of UORs in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I speak there are around five thousand contractors out in theatre, supporting our Armed Forces in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the honour of presenting medals to a number of them whose work has been crucial to our effectiveness there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year industry also did a magnificent job in support of the Libya campaign, and - for the record - there’s a dedicated case study on their contribution to Operation Ellamy on page 24 of the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact I also wrote letters of thanks and appreciation to some twenty companies of all sizes who played a crucial role in Op Ellamy. I could easily have written ten times that number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take just one example - Typhoon, and the way industry optimised its capability for that operation. Of course, the excellence of the aircraft played its part too, but it was private sector companies and their staff that kept it flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, thanks to your innovation - and strong partnership working with organisations like DSTL - our Forces have superb kit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it is the best they have ever had. And as good as can be found anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your part in that remarkable achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be a cliche, but it is true - necessity is the mother of invention. That has certainly been the case in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And significant parts of that defence innovation, as is so often the case, are being transferred across to the civilian world.&lt;br&gt;
I’m thinking here in particular of the advances in battlefield medicine which are also driving forward changes in the NHS. &lt;br&gt;
So - you are a vital part, all of you, of our defence effort. You make defence happen.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s this - I don’t actually agree with the title for this conference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not because you aren’t a critical component of military capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, it’s the first three words of the conference theme that worry me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was Voltaire who wrote that the Holy Roman Empire was neither holy, nor Roman, nor an empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is with the “defence industrial base”, a term that makes my heart sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, it’s not just about defence, because of the increasing overlap with Security - a major theme of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about industry but technology. More about that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not about a narrowly defined base when so many of our key suppliers have supply chains that reach around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the phrase defence industrial base summons up visions of some giant monolith - shielded from the market forces that are always the driver of efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faceless, intransigent - and unaccountable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful symbol of the problems that have faced defence acquisition in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete antithesis of the way we intend to run our whole defence equipment and support programme.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look specifically at that third word; ‘base.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a problem with the very idea that we have - or indeed should have - a ‘defence industrial base’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly, it’s more complicated that that. In fact, I’m not sure it’s even factually correct these days to refer to a ‘defence industry’ as a collective concept. Your diversity is your strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality - as I said earlier - is that defence equipment and support covers a huge and diverse range of activity, and companies of just about every size, with varying degrees of dependence on the MOD budget.  And they are all important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From primes to start-ups. Providing everything from syringes to submarines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their services and products often cover a range of sectors. They certainly don’t want to get pigeon holed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is driving fundamental change in our supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And those smaller companies are so often the ones who are proving to be innovative and agile - and sensitive to the customer’s needs in these times of austerity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are out there winning international business in today’s tough global environment - and not waiting for the MOD to make up its mind about what it will buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we are looking for greater SME involvement in our procurement strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not for altruistic reasons - but because we are determined to drive in innovation and responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we will also hard-wire this approach into the reformed DE&amp;amp;S and its harder-edged relationship with the MOD customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are defence industries. But as I said earlier, their supply chain spreads around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are industries which contribute to defence but which have their origins, or the majority of their business, in other sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are industries that may not yet be on our radar which should be - and which must be encouraged to make their contribution to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in Defence value you highly, but you are not a united industrial base as such.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also striving to increase the proportion of the equipment and support solutions that we buy in open competition. More of that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we do understand the limits on competition in defence acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all on this issue, our security depends on us being able to protect our sovereign requirements for operational advantage and freedom of action. And we will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is where the misunderstandings between us -  between the MOD and industry - most urgently need to be addressed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These concepts were, after all, an important feature of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old phrase “sovereign capability” trips easily off the tongue. But it can lead to some pretty woolly thinking.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence Industrial Strategy of 2005 listed the capabilities industry had.  And then said what Government would do to protect them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed everybody and anybody to claim that their capability was essential and that, implicitly, the MOD would have to fund it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An approach that proved to be unaffordable - and downright illogical in an age of rapid change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the White Paper “National Security Through Technology” does what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets out an approach that starts with what the State needs for its security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it looks at the different ways of achieving it, establishing affordability, what it will acquire, and how it will acquire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now embedding this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper implementation team is looking now at exactly how best to embed these concepts - and that of exportability - in both Main Building and the Front Line Commands. And how to take account of the views of industry and DE&amp;amp;S.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process we will follow is much more subtle and nuanced than some commentators seem to have understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will buy equipment using the route most appropriate for that equipment bearing in mind its nature and our need for operational advantage and freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will seek exemptions from EU procurement rules to sustain our technological advantage where we need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important, however, that you recognise and understand that we’re not going back to producing a long list of specific sovereign capabilities - effectively owned by specific companies - that we will protect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is changing too fast, and money is too tight - as indeed they both probably always were - to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future lies in open systems - as we see in the Land Open Systems Architecture approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognise this means big change for many larger firms in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the gains for Defence as a whole are real. And I believe greater competitiveness will help the big companies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, be very clear, the skills and resources to deliver operational advantage and freedom of action will be safeguarded when we must do so to protect the nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the White Paper we set out the broad circumstances where this will apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real challenge we all face is not new acquisition processes but constrained acquisition budgets here and, indeed around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be skills the UK needs to safeguard and with development money for new projects constrained, some of them may be at risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would have faced the challenge of how to deal with in any event, White Paper or no White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having operational advantage and freedom of action in the future depends investment in the future of the right technologies now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we are constantly assessing what we believe are critical technologies - and why our decision to protect the Science and Technology budget from further cuts is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently announced a billion pound investment in the Rolls Royce core production capability at Derby. Here is a clear example of a technology and skill set we know we do need to sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the announcement at the end of last year of additional funding for research into next generation of highly capable air systems - a £40 million four-year research contract with BAE Systems to explore critical technologies and key systems integration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be other such examples and we will take careful note of the views of industry as we identify and address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it will be for the Government to determine how best to sustain the technology - perhaps, for example, by collaboration with one of our most trusted allies rather than by maintaining a single UK source.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is a national business - but it is not an industry of the state. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state has its defence requirements, and they are being met by an increasingly diverse range of suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of you realise that Hewlett Packard is our fourth biggest supplier? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that SMEs now win over 42 per cent of all the contracts we let? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the overall value of those contracts is lower, at 13 per cent of our spending. But it is a very significant amount given that the sheer scale of many of our programmes mean they are outside the scope of SMEs, at least as prime contractors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, the beguiling argument that spending money on Defence will create more jobs for UK PLC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in essence, defence is in some way special in its capacity to generate employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does have an academic term: ‘Military Keynesianism’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, John Maynard Keynes himself didn’t approve of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Keynes wrote an open letter to President Franklin Roosevelt. In that letter he said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”… a war has always caused intense industrial activity. In the past orthodox finance has regarded a war as the only legitimate excuse for creating employment by governmental expenditure. You, Mr President, having cast off such fetters, are free to engage in the interests of peace and prosperity the technique which hitherto has only been allowed to serve the purposes of war and destruction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I agree with Keynes - up to a point. There are many ways to stimulate an economy other than by investing in Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We buy defence equipment and support that equipment because we need it to secure our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the duty of the MOD to buy what we need to do that and to protect our sovereignty - no more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the consequences of the acquisition decisions we take in the MOD have implications for the responsibilities of other Government departments - or vice versa - the White Paper established a ministerial committee to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a sub-set of full-blown military Keynesianism that asserts we should always try to buy defence equipment in our own country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a “red in tooth and claw” capitalist to believe in capitalism’s principal tenets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that the greatest long-term good is served when competition is allowed to work. That means efficient markets and real wealth creation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it’s good when British-based companies win UK defence contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often our needs will mean buying British from single sources; 40 percent of our defence equipment and support budget is spent that way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And much of the remaining 60 per cent is also won by British companies too because you are so good at what you do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look through the announcements we have made recently - on Sea Ceptor, Sea Viper, the Core Production Capability, the refit of HMS Vengeance, maintaining Hercules, the Warrior Capability Sustainment Programme, Foxhound, Scout - the list goes on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of highly skilled jobs secured by our acquisition and support decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course buying defence equipment creates jobs. But so does investing in the arts, in hospitals, in schools, in roads, in housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to justify defence spending by its potential for job creation, others in Government would raise their eyebrows and offer a rather incredulous response along the lines of: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh really? More jobs than funding research in the civil aerospace technology? Or rolling out Broadband across the UK?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK defence companies do make an important contribution to our economy. I celebrate that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the only reasons for the MOD to go out of its way to protect their technologies are operational advantage and freedom of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlie Blakemore of BAE Systems told it like it was when he announced last month the loss of jobs at their munitions factory in Monmouthshire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said - and I’m quoting here from the BBC: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to adapt to very challenging market conditions, and further reduce our overheads to drive better value for our customers and increase our competitiveness in the export market.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words capture the kind of hard headed realism companies across the spectrum need to adopt if they are to succeed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are new opportunities for industry too. Not just in equipment acquisition, but also in support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means a new appreciation and understanding of what support means. And the number of services and capabilities it actually covers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly as we roll out the Total Support Force concept, which will include a sizeable number of contractors doing jobs we always thought were done by people in uniform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are real new commercial opportunities here for you. I appreciate the work being done by industry to help us drive this agenda forward to our mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake. We do want you to thrive and prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the White Paper clearly spelt out earlier this year, it is in our interests to have successful - and competitive - defence industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you heard from Susanna Mason, this is a Government committed to promoting an environment conducive to responsible defence exports. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her appointment as MOD lead for exports is a tangible sign of our commitment to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our real challenges in implementing the White Paper is driving exportability into our requirement setting process from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realise that even a simple term like ‘exportability’ means different things to different people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, in this context it does not simply mean “capable of being exported within the constraints of the export licensing regime”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are proud of our responsible and tough regime - although I know it could often work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, fundamentally it means, from the very beginning of a project, making defence equipment that the UK requires attractive to potential overseas customers. That brings benefits to us and to you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring this issue is fully addressed as we devolve responsibility to the front line commands is a major White Paper implementation task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, on the subject of international acquisition policies, I often hear it said that the White Paper does not address industrial participation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s simply not the case. I refer you to page 48, paragraph 154 of the White Paper for a clear summary of our new policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new approach towards engagement with overseas suppliers aims to encourage these companies to invest in the UK supply chain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance as a prime location to engage in research and development investment and technology transfer;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, these activities will also underpin the promotion of the UK’s defence and security exports, exploring what assistance can be provided to help UK exporters meet their global offset obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s precisely because we want you to succeed, and to deliver our operational advantage and freedom of action into the foreseeable future that I have - for the first time - put a floor under the science budget. To ensure that we as a nation we can remain at the forefront of cutting edge, battle-winning technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our national security depends on that. And that means a lot of opportunities for you.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of contractors have told me they consider the White Paper to be pragmatic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the policy it articulates is in fact a continuation of what had been the Department’s direction of travel for several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that the White Paper spells it out in black and white. And provides industry with the clarity - and honesty - you have been asking for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the commitments to science, to exports, and to SMEs are new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a change from the 2005 Defence Industrial Strategy which this year’s White Paper replaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also agree wholeheartedly with John Maynard Keynes when he said, or at least is believed to have said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When the facts change, I change my mind. What do you do, sir?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well here are some of the facts - the realities - which I believe have changed or become more prominent over the last seven years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A global network of alliances with whom we intend to cooperate more deeply:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The international distribution of manufacturing:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Massive civil sector investment in R&amp;amp;D that increasingly spins in to Defence: &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rapidly advancing, often disruptive technology (some increasingly expensive, other parts of which become ever lower-cost):&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And increasing financial challenge and austerity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what do these facts - these new realities - mean in practice? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they mean working more closely with our allies on acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On very large programmes like JSF with the US and a wide range of international partners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On specific much smaller-scale programmes such as aspects of counter- IED technology with the Germans - as I saw at DVD last week when I met MineWolf Abacot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or across a wide portfolio of programmes in the framework of the wide-ranging Franco-British agreement. Here we are working on complex weapons, unmanned combat systems, support for A400M, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then again, there are occasions when addressing this new world means single source non-competitive contracts to build nuclear powered submarines, to develop unmanned combat air systems, to build complex warships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it means mutual commitment like the one in the complex weapon pipeline arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinction between the old approach and the new one is this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policy will, more often than in the past, lead the Government to open up our defence contracts to international competition -  just, indeed, as the last Government judged it right to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, don’t forget that, as the EU takes more steps to enforce the Defence Procurement Directive, more and more European opportunities will open to British companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are competitive here, you will succeed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recent history shows us that there is absolutely no reason why UK companies should not win MOD business. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at Foxhound. An excellent example of an agile and versatile vehicle - a contract competed for and won by British companies, Force Protection Europe and Ricardo, sustaining around 750 highly-skilled jobs across the UK.  And with huge export potential too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the Warrior Capability and Sustainment Programme - a contract which will create and sustain around 600 British jobs -    was won by Lockheed Martin UK in a competitive process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also the case that big contracts awarded overseas will also help to open up those international markets to British companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MARS tankers are a case in point. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of British companies took part in the international competition - which was quite rightly initiated by the previous Government because they recognised, as tankers, they were not “warlike stores”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, no British company submitted a final bid for the build contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes - of course I would have preferred it if there had been a competitive British bid. But in the end there wasn’t any British bid at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build contract has been awarded to Daewoo Shipbuilding and Marine Engineering of South Korea, but the ships are designed by a British company, BMT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there will be up to £150 million of associated contracts for the MARS project, many of them offering opportunities for SMEs here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MARS means UK companies have the chance to show their potential to one of the world’s largest shipyards and for DSME to get first hand experience of the services and products that can be provided cost-effectively from UK companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Korea at DSME’s hugely impressive yard on Monday. I heard of the close working relationship developing between DSME and BMT. It looks very likely to lead to further ships, based on the successful MARS design, being developed and sold to third countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means additional opportunities for the British marine engineering industry.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of equal significance is the potential of opening up the Korean defence market for other UK companies as the strategic relationships created through MARS develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early and encouraging sign is the significant breakthrough into the Korean naval propulsion market made by Rolls Royce. I was delighted to hear that contract announced on Tuesday in Seoul alongside representatives of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came back from South Korea yesterday and at the airport I met a Royal Navy team going in to discuss naval cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many similar challenges and shared understandings, the potential for ever deeper collaboration and partnership is very real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do agree with the pre-conference papers that MOD is adopting the ‘tough love’ approach when it comes to our relationship with industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re being equally as tough on ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recognised that we’ve got to change - and drive forward a new culture across the MOD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means changes ahead at DE&amp;amp;S and in the way we do business. You will be aware of Bernard Gray’s Materiel Strategy and the Defence Transformation agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is still underway as decisions are being made and you will hear more about our thinking as soon as we are ready. However, we are determined that the MOD will be a better informed and more demanding customer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I draw all this to a conclusion, I would like, briefly, to reflect on the overarching theme of this conference, “Defence, Industries and Society”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’d all agree that today the nation - quite rightly - holds our Armed Forces in very high regard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Armed Forces Day on Saturday, we will see this high regard turned into practical support up and down the country. I’m looking forward to events in my own constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thousands of men, women and children who line the streets up and down the country for homecoming parades show that support and admiration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public also recognises - in very tangible ways - the sacrifices the Armed Forces and their families make. Just look at the success of a charity like Help for Heroes which has raised £100 million in its first four years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to recognise that defence spending is in competition with all the other things that taxpayers’ expect the  Government to spend their money on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, there appears to be a greater willingness in the UK to fund Defence than in most Western nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the British people have seen the news, they read the newspapers. They know that the MOD has been culpable of gross financial mismanagement and - let’s be frank here -  squandering their money. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two years of the Coalition Government have been spent dealing with the horrendous national deficit. But MOD Ministers have had this challenge compounded by Defence’s own broken finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both were real security risks in their own right. A country cannot be strong unless its finances are strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a Government department cannot do its job unless it manages its finances well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case that is best summarised as “It’s only by looking after the bottom line that we can really look after the front line.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that balancing the MOD’s books has been a tough and time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - we’re there. We’ve balanced the budget. We will be announcing an audited 10-year equipment programme as soon as the National Audit Office completes its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result we will be spending a lot of taxpayers’ money on equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over ten years that will be £160 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - in contrast to the unfunded aspirations of the past, this is real money - including around £4 billion of contingency on the committed programme and £8 billion of headroom to fund additional projects from our Single Integrated Priority List.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, that all gives defence companies a lot more certainty than most businesses ever have about their customer’s requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this happy state is to endure it will take a lot of discipline from all of us - and especially from the MOD - officials, front line commands and politicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The balanced budget, the Yellow Book review (something there wasn’t time to talk about today incidentally), the Materiel Strategy, Defence Transformation and the White Paper are all essential building blocks of a new more confident, sustainable, effective Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the moment of maximum pain. But it’s also the moment when the light at the end of the tunnel may actually be precisely that, and not the light of another train bearing down upon us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the messages of the White Paper must be understood properly both within and outside the MOD and the Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must think more about defence and security as a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must think more about technology, the way it is changing and what we need to protect the State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we must nurture the growing diversity of what once saw itself as a defence industrial base but is now a complex supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the habits of a lifetime is never easy, but that is what I am inviting those of you who have not already done so to do now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have to be competitive. Growth will be hard won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will only be able to export something if it is competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we get there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We build in exportability;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We support UK companies in export campaigns;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invest in the right technologies;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We allow SMEs the space to flourish;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We protect our operational advantage and freedom of action;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We focus on building and retaining competitive advantage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collaborate more with our closest partners;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And crucially, we always remember affordability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach may be driven by austerity but just happens to be intellectually right too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective should not be to protect a defence industrial base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should rather be to create the right incentives to grow thriving, vibrant companies that can compete globally and supply Defence in the UK with what we need, when we need it, at a price that the taxpayer can afford.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45357</id>
    <published>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-06-21-defence-vehicles-dynamics-dvd"/>
    <title>2012/06/21 - Defence Vehicles Dynamics (DVD)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be back here at Millbrook. Having the chance to see world class land systems being put through their paces is fascinating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this event is also a reminder that equipping and supporting our forces is a wide-ranging effort. I’m delighted to see so many companies - primes and SMEs - here from a range of sectors who contribute to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a number of contractors are also represented. Your role in facilitating and supporting operations will become ever more prominent as the Total Support Force concept is driven though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the last DVD event back in 2010 very well. I have to say it was a somewhat less soggy occasion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had just taken up my post as Minister for Defence Equipment and Support, and this was one of my first engagements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-time-of-change"&gt;A time of change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge amount has happened in the intervening two years. I’d like to highlight just three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the 2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review - the SDSR - has provided the strategic direction which was so urgently required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Defence transformation - the vital reforms needed to ensure delivery of Future Force 2020 - is underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - and these are words I wondered if I would ever be able to say - we’ve balanced the Defence budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the winds of change continue to blow across every area of defence, and I know that these are uncertain times for the Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will certainly be challenges ahead, for example, devolving control of the acquisition process down to the Front Line Commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pr12---bringing-certainty"&gt;PR12 - bringing certainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the announcement of PR12 means we can all now plan for the future with a certainty that we just couldn’t before as we continued to wrestle with a huge deficit and the legacy of financial over-commitment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Army in particular paid a very high price for this overheated equipment programme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and again your projects were shelved simply because they had relatively shorter lead times and it was easy to cancel, postpone or reduce them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to say that our careful planning will put an end to this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the Army will be one of the primary beneficiaries of PR12.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="funding-in-place-for-the-armoured-vehicle-programme"&gt;Funding in place for the Armoured Vehicle Programme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balancing the books has enabled us to move forward to plan and deliver an Armoured Vehicle Programme over the next decade which will deliver a fleet of state of the art, high tech and easily deployable fighting vehicles.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£5.5 billion pipeline, funding has been secured for Armoured Fighting Vehicles. This sum guarantees funding for:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An Upgrade for Warrior and the Challenger Life Extension&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new fleet of Utility vehicles to come on stream from the mid 2020s as a replacement for Bulldog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support costs for Foxhound beyond operations in Afghanistan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And, of course, the Scout programme - a new family of reconnaissance vehicles. The programme is now well into its demonstration phase and is on display here today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Scout, we will first need to reset the programme in order to remain within the pipeline profile. We will then drive hard to a Main Gate 2, at which point production numbers will be finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these fleets are now all lined up and accounted for in the Armoured Vehicle Pipeline - a highly disciplined approach which will enable us to keep firm control every step of the way when it comes to costs, numbers, performance and sequencing.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And across the board this approach exemplifies a new financial rigour which will run through the equipment programme.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot, and will not, allow Defence acquisition and support to lapse back into chaos, mismanagement and fiscal incompetence.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="land-open-systems-architecture"&gt;Land Open Systems Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of this Armoured Vehicle Programme will be the development of a Land Open Systems Architecture - or LOSA -  which I’m delighted to see is the central theme of this year’s conference.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open systems - and the flexibility they provide - are a central principle of the White Paper we published earlier this year.  It means that from day one modularity, interoperability and the ability to upgrade are key factors of the design process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="foxhound"&gt;Foxhound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound - which, as we announced at the weekend, has already begun to arrive in Afghanistan - is a great example of this new generic architecture structure.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s extraordinarily agile, exploits state of the art technology from the UK’s world-leading motorsport industry, and has an engine which can be removed and replaced in half an hour.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And its UK designed and built - with 90% of the companies involved in its production UK based. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foxhound’s arrival in theatre has been highly anticipated and I’m not in the least bit surprised. I  have driven it. I know just how good it is. And just how easy it is to drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress is also being made on Terrier. Initial production vehicles are undertaking acceptance trials and training at a bespoke facility has commenced. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Terrier is likely to be the last in a long and illustrious line of armoured vehicles built in Newcastle, where a great workforce has made a fine contribution to Defence over many a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that must be a matter for regret, I am encouraged that this contribution is now being made around the UK - in South Wales, on the South Coast, in Coventry and elsewhere, by primes, SMEs and newcomers to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uors---driving-forward-innovation"&gt;UORS - driving forward innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Land equipment has been transformed in recent years. I think its fair to say that we have learnt more in this domain than any other sector.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to thank those of you here from industry for your responsiveness on the UOR front - you really have done a magnificent job in recent years in getting essential kit our to our troops in theatre.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UOR process in particular has been a driver of innovation. Great strides have been made when it comes to high tech adaptation and integration.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs have a particular role to play in this. Companies like Formaplex which has a background in luxury cars and Formula One vehicles, and which are currently producing the Foxhound vehicle pods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re a good example of a company with no previous track record of working in defence who are bringing their expertise to a defence UOR.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are exactly the kind of projects which will help to develop and sustain our skills base here in this country.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exports"&gt;Exports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will of course be challenges for the Land sector as our requirements change with our return to contingency operations after Afghanistan and the bringing of some UOR vehicles into core.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are also opportunities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just reiterate what I said back here at DVD 2010 about our commitment to reinvigorating our agenda for responsible British defence exports. And how keen I was to ensure this was taken forward.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years on, and the more I see of our defence industries the more convinced I am by just how much they have to offer the global market.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m delighted that there’s real impetus behind supporting exports.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UKTI is energised. We have appointed Susanna Mason as MOD Director for exports. And promoting defence exports is now a central effort of our defence diplomacy drive, and the way we engage with international partners.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defence industries are - and I am confident will remain -  vibrant and successful here in the UK.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are changes ahead.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our core mission will remain - to deliver military success on operations. And to ensure that we have the ability to project power and protect our national security.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the heart of this effort is the essential requirement - that together we are meeting so well - to ensure our troops have the equipment they need, when they need it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You here today have made a very important contribution to that requirement in the past, are doing so as we speak, and will - I know - do so in the months and years ahead.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/45351</id>
    <published>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-24-qinetiq-70th-anniversary-dinner"/>
    <title>2012/05/24 - Qinetiq 70th Anniversary Dinner</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good evening &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Headmaster. [Headmaster of Malvern - Antony Clark]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a privilege to be here in the peaceful and glorious surroundings of Malvern College. In the middle of what I call God’s own country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although of course as a local Member of Parliament - like Harriet Baldwin - with the privilege of representing this county I’m aware that I say that with a certain partiality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headmaster - thank you for your hospitality this evening. And I am delighted to see that we are also joined by Malvern staff, pupils and brilliant physicists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Adam (Adam Palser - QinetiQ Group Plc) if you’re the custodian of Malvern then I suppose that I am the paymaster - so together we make a great team.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tre---the-move-to-malvern"&gt;TRE - the move to Malvern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we gather here this evening we look back 70 years ago to a very different time and place.  To the dark and terrible days of a nation -indeed a world - at War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was also a war that shaped the present day - and a lot of the changes we now take for granted. The move of aircraft manufacturers to the North West of England from London, for example, to take them  beyond the range of German bombers. Now the North-West is the centre of advanced aerospace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And May 1942 saw the Headmaster of this College, all his staff and pupils, pack their bags and de-camp to Harrow School at the express instruction of the Prime Minister himself, Winston Churchill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Malvern is a centre of scientific excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One wonders, looking back, exactly why Harrow - a London school was chosen. I wonder if the fact that Churchill himself was an old boy had something to do with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently it was quite ok to evict Malvern pupils at just one week’s notice to the risky environs of North London as long as scientists had somewhere safe to carry on their important work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if today’s Malvern parents would be quite so understanding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was of course a fact that German air attacks posed a very real threat to the essential work of the Training Research Establishment - or TRE as it was known - based on the cliffs of Worth Matravers in Dorset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Churchill was absolutely adamant that TRE - and the RAF Radar Research and Development Establishment -  be immediately relocated to Malvern. The fact that we had just raided the equivalent German facility also had a lot to do with it, as Adam (Palser) has just explained. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes said that the War was won on the playing fields of Malvern. I am sure that there is a great deal of truth in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of radar is complex and like so many personal endeavours - particularly in the field of human achievement - is the cumulative work of inventors, scientists and engineers from a number of countries over many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there can be no doubt that the work on the magnetron taken forward by the men and women working at Malvern - some of the great brains of their generation, and known affectionately by the RAF as ‘the boffins’ - was ground breaking and changed the direction of the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That scientific legacy was carried forward across the generations.  And so Malvern developed that reputation as a hub of scientific endeavour which - thanks to Qinetiq - continues to this day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dera---qinetiq-and-dstl"&gt;DERA - Qinetiq and DSTL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years the research facility here at Malvern  evolved over time to become the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency. The process of invention continued along the way, and a number of vital technologies were developed. Liquid Crystal Display - how many local people know that came from here? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a number of you here this evening worked for the Agency, and that today has been a great opportunity for some happy reminiscing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency then went on to be split into two separate organisations back in 2001. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was Qinetiq. The other, the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory. Still part of MOD and more commonly known as DSTL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qinetiq is now a global brand, and your scientists and engineers help some of the world’s top manufacturers push the boundaries of technology in aviation, energy, IT and space exploration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - 70 years on you are still here in Malvern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your strong and enduring links with Defence do of course continue.  Take just one, radar, as an  example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The establishment of Radar at Malvern was in part to protect the development of the ground imaging radar called H2S. And to be clear, that’s quite different to the high speed rail link HS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, airborne radar imaging is performed daily in Afghanistan using Synthetic Aperture Radar from Sentinel R1 surveillance aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The performance of that vital capability Sentinel is due to world leading focussing algorithms developed at Malvern by scientists now working for Qinetiq.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Watson-Watt - a great pioneer of radar technology - was very clear about the importance of effective collaboration between the military and the scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back many years later he said, and I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I believe that our success in radar depended fundamentally on…the intimacy and complete confidence between the operational user and the scientific and technical researcher and developer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a unique relationship which continues to this day. Today our servicemen and women look to British scientists  for this special expertise and support.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the operational tempo of recent years in Iraq, Afghanistan and Libya have seen more scientists and operational analysts on the front line than at any time since the Second World War. Defence scientists today are certainly no back room boffins. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commanders look to them for expert scientific advice and rapid technical solutions to very specific threats and issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our scientists have a 24 hour reach back to colleagues  here in the UK and to our intellectual network in industry and universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure our people are well equipped and supported with the battle winning capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="innovation-and-the-uor-process"&gt;Innovation and the UOR process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was already very clear back in May 1942 was that technology was going to play a deciding role in the conflict and that electronic supremacy - what Churchill called ‘The Wizard War’ - would be a deciding factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in today’s fast moving operational environment the imperative to be able to exploit new and emerging technologies is just as pressing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is precisely what we did when it came to developing Foxhound - the next generation of light protected patrol vehicle for our forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re looking for the ability to remove and replace an engine in  just 30 minutes, and for that vehicle to be able to drive away from an ambush on only three wheels necessary - then you go to the very best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why Foxhound was devised by engineers from, among other areas,  the World Rally Championship, McLaren F1 and BMW and incorporates Formula One racing technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="technology-at-heart-of-defence"&gt;Technology at heart of Defence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology has an absolutely fundamental role in providing Defence and security to this country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="help-for-heroes"&gt;Help for Heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Defence is really about people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ‘well done’ to that hardy bunch from Qinetiq who have just recreated the journey taken by all those scientists from Worth Matravers in Dorset here to Malvern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That journey today was on two wheels in aid of Help for Heroes -well done on the £3,000. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of Help For Heroes is clear evidence of the tremendous respect and affection of the British people have for  our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="my-role-as-minister-for-defence-equipment-support-and-technology"&gt;My role as Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Minister for Defence Equipment, Support and Technology it’s my job - my duty - to ensure that these courageous and committed men and women have what they need to do their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best battle winning capability and the best support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is a mission the importance of which I am reminded whenever I meet our Armed Forces.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visit Afghanistan and meet the amazing men and women who work on the MERT - or Medical Emergency Response Teams. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And have the opportunity to see for myself at first hand the ground breaking technologies saving lives today on today’s front line. Technologies which owe so much to British scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I go to see our equipment in action and talk to the service personnel who use it - and whose lives depend on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days our forces are giving an unequivocal ‘thumbs up’ to the excellent range of kit and equipment now at their disposal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigadier Patrick Sanders, for example, who last year commanded 20th Armoured Brigade in Afghanistan has described the equipment his troops had - and I quote: “second to none” and “the best that I’ve experienced in 27 years.” And a lot of that is down to science. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="courage-and-sacrifice-of-our-service-personnel"&gt;Courage and sacrifice of our service personnel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course I’m also reminded of the importance of what we all do to support our Armed Forces when I meet our serving personnel back here at home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I was talking to personnel from the Navy and RAF who took part in last year’s Libya campaign, and were attending a reception at the House of Commons held in their honour to celebrate their courage and heroism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a junior rating who talked about what it was like to be working in the Ops Room of HMS Liverpool when it came under missile attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the deck hands of HMS Ocean who got the Apache helicopters off and safely home. They spoke of black helicopters on a black night on a black sea.  Not an easy job with whirling blades, weapons loaded and adrenalin pumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also spoke to the Typhoon and Tornado pilots who flew 16 hour missions,  and struck again and again with such deadly precision against the Qadhafi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own county regiment - The 2nd Mercians, who I still think of by the way as the Worcestershire and Sherwood Foresters -   have of course served with tremendous valour in recent times. Some have tragically lost their lives, and some have been very seriously injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RSM of the Second Mercians said something very perceptive about the young men and women he recently commanded in Helmand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you here may have seen an article last month in the Worcester News in which RSM Martyn Chatterley described them as “absolutely exceptional”, and wrote the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“People talk about the ‘Play Station’ generation, and how the youth of today are not up to anything , but this is just not the case.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of soldiering, Afghanistan brings together everything you are trained for and learn - every single aspect of what makes the modern professional soldier.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these guys have proven they have what it takes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbling words. And a reminder that today’s Armed Forces are just as brave, and just as resourceful, as those sailors, soldiers and airmen of 1942.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A readiness to explore new boundaries and exploit technology was critical then - and is just as critical today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I note that the Malvern College motto is: ‘Sapiens Qui Prospicit’ or ‘Wise is the person who looks ahead’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually - perhaps we should adopt it as a motto for the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do hope, Headmaster, that you heed this clarion call - I know this is a school with an excellent reputation for promoting and recognising scientific achievement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you and your teaching staff encourage pupils to look ahead, to realise their potential  and pursue careers in these fields. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This country needs our scientists and engineers. And a lot more of them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry is crying out for them. Our national security demands them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, as I look ahead, I can say with absolute confidence that this country’s independence - and our contribution to a better and safer world - will continue to depend on our scientific wizards. Many of whom are here with us tonight.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wizards of the present, and I hope, of the future too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, Qinetiq, on your first 70 years at Malvern. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your work is carrying forward the legacy of those early pioneers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprising men and women who worked so tirelessly to push forward the boundaries of scientific endeavour. And to whom we owe so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18769</id>
    <published>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-23-the-strategic-challenges-of-defence-acquisition"/>
    <title>2012/05/23 - The Strategic Challenges of Defence Acquisition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week the Defence Secretary spoke about PR12 marking a new chapter in the long history of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s absolutely right. Balancing the budget is a key part of transforming Defence and making sure we have a Defence Equipment Programme based on firm foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m well aware there may be some here who may be sceptical that this vast programme of change - the root and branch reform of something as large and complex as defence - will succeed. Or indeed actually happen at all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should it work this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well - there are four reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of these is the economic imperative, and a series of events which have led us to this moment. In the foreword to the SDSR the Prime Minister said that bringing the defence budget back to balance is a vital part of how we tackle the  national deficit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you aren’t convinced by that, just think for a moment about the implications of the gathering storm over the Eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is political will - a determination and commitment which comes from the very top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third - this is a process which is gathering momentum on a daily basis. The winds of change are blowing across Defence and across the Armed Forces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And fourth, there is a growing recognition that everyone has a part to play in this process. And a universal wish - in fact , a real drive - to succeed and see MOD taken off ‘special measures’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now see a general recognition that there is no turning back. Top down meets bottom up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No return to the so called good old days with MOD merrily pushing out fantasy budgets, whipping out a blank cheque book and starting ill-tested projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects which hadn’t a hope of seeing the light of day because, actually, there was no funding in place to ever pay for them.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few deluded dissidents, including in industry, seem to yearn for the best forgotten past, but must understand that there will be a heavy price to pay if we don’t grasp this opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A failure to act now would mean a toxic legacy for the future. And wwould threaten both the security and prosperity of our nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a burden which would be shared by future generations of servicemen and women who won’t have the best high tech cutting edge capabilities and solutions. Because we just couldn’t - or wouldn’t - get our act together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indulge me for a moment here in one of my other passions. And let me cite the words of one man who puts this a lot better than I ever could. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shakespeare’s Julius Caesar is one of my favourite plays. It encapsulates so much about life’s dilemmas, conflict and the human condition. About politics, and indeed war.  Albeit a civil one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Act 4 Brutus and Cassius are discussing the final phase of their civil war with the forces of Octavian and Marcus Antonius. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cassius says they should group their forces and take advantage of the secure location to catch their breath. Brutus urges that no - they must act immediately while they have the advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brutus says:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a tide in the affairs of men.&lt;br&gt;
Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune; &lt;br&gt;
Omitted, all the voyage of their life&lt;br&gt;
Is bound in shallows and in miseries.&lt;br&gt;
On such a full sea are we now afloat,&lt;br&gt;
And we must take the current when it serves,&lt;br&gt;
Or lose our ventures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circumstances have created just such a tide and all of us are now afloat on a full sea. But unlike Brutus we will succeed.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper-pr12-defence-transformation-materiel-strategy--equipment-plan"&gt;White Paper, PR12, Defence Transformation, Materiel Strategy &amp;amp; Equipment Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we are to ensure success, more needs to be done. We have the advantage - but we need to do more to maintain it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the  building blocks are in place.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One. The White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has set out our principles on an open approach to procurement.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means buying off the shelf where possible, a commitment to opening up more business to SMEs, building in exportability at an early stage. And strong support for exports, as well as a floor in the MOD’s annual Science and Technology budget.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two. PR12 means we can now plan for the future with a certainty that we just couldn’t before as we continued to wrestle with a huge deficit and legacy of overspend.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you are aware, our announcement last week guaranteed the delivery of a number of projects for the Navy, Army and RAF.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted also be able to confirm the establishment of an Armoured Vehicle Pipeline, which provides significant funding for the Warrior Upgrade, Challenger Life Extension, a Utility Vehicle and the Scout programme which is now well into its Demonstration Phase.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pipeline approach enables us to keep a firm control of costs,  numbers, performance and sequencing in order to remain within the allocated profile. The Army, as the end user, will be intimately involved in this process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the Scout, a world-class family of reconnaissance vehicles to which we are now committed, we will first need to reset the programme in order to remain within the pipeline profile. We will then drive hard to a Main Gate 2, when we will finalise production numbers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves the final three building blocks of success. Defence Transformation, The Materiel Strategy and the publication of the Equipment Plan.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Levene’s  Defence Reform recommended devolving most capability planning and resourcing to Front Line Commands -  FLCs - and in turn  a smaller, more strategic and stronger Head Office.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less of the long screwdriver from Head Office - and a lot more giving the FLCs a real opportunity to control their own destinies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant change like this won’t happen overnight. We expect to roll out these changes gradually with an initial operating capability for this model in place for the 2013/14 financial year.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embed this new approach I’d ask industry to work closely with the Front Line Commands during this crucial transition process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles of the White Paper will also apply to Front Line Commands:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance they must ask themselves what are the capabilities where we require operational advantage and freedom of action?-  what steps should we take to protect these elements?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we embed open systems and exportability into our procurement processes; and   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we make sure SMEs get access to defence opportunities at an early stage?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am under no illusion that this represents a considerable  challenge for the FLCs - not least to ensure they have the right skills in place as they take on this new responsibility, and accountability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have heard just now from Chris Deverell about ongoing work on the Materiel Strategy, the fourth component of success.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you here from industry will be aware that we intend to be a more demanding customer - improving skills and processes at Abbey Wood will ensure we are able to deliver on that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And 2012 will see us announce our 10 Year Equipment Plan after careful scrutiny from the NAO - all funded and accounted for, not just in terms of acquisition but also support costs.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fifth component of success will give industry the transparency which they quite understandably, have been pressing for.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that comparisons are still being made with the Defence Industrial Strategy of 2005 - and its much heralded announcement at the time of a 10 year equipment plan.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know this plan never materialised, for the simple fact that, like the Strategy itself, there was no funding plan behind it.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we are now in very different place.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a balanced budget and a core equipment programme of £152 billion over 10 years, against a total planned spend of almost £160 billion. That £152 billion includes, for the first time, a centrally held contingency of over £4 billion.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme also includes an additional £8 billion of funding over the next ten years which is unallocated. This means that the budget will have guaranteed headroom which can be allocated to projects as military priorities change.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will open up opportunities to suppliers who are agile, and able to respond with mature products and services as these new opportunities arise.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think , by the way, that we know what we are likely to spend this headroom on. But - it wouldn’t surprise me if we look back in ten years time and discover that changing priorities and technologies had led to very different outcomes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all set to go. Or are we? What are the factors which might hold us back?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know there are a lot of institutional, governmental and political challenges.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is one main challenge relevant to this audience as far as I am concerned and that is a failure by industry to recognise -  and possibly seize - the opportunities coming your way.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france"&gt;UK-France&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take UK-France collaboration.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portfolio of Franco-British programmes sets out to deliver a wide range of capabilities. There’s now real momentum behind this relationship. To some extent we are drawing on each others strengths. And aiming to avoid duplicating capabilities where we don’t need to.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10 year strategic plan for the British and French Complex Weapons Industries encapsulates this.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are real benefits here from our common position on this sector when it comes to budgets, as well as similar military and industry requirements.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the two most capable military powers in Europe, we will look to strengthening our ties with the new French administration to address common security challenges facing both countries.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a relationship which has developed around a change of administration here in the UK.  And it is a relationship which will continue to deepen after the recent change in France.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all changes there are risks and opportunities that we will need to address.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will do our bit - but we do need industry to engage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK/France Critical Technologies Study is a case in point where we need you to present a consolidated view. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the White Paper makes clear, we need to focus investment on the ‘critical outcomes’ of what science and technology should achieve, rather than a list of ‘critical technologies’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There needs to be a methodology to do this so we can identify, assess and prioritise as criticalities emerge - and we need industry to contribute to this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve seen - and it’s certainly become very clear in the UK/France High Level Working Group which I co - chair  - is that  French companies are being very proactive when it comes to  getting involved in UK-France equipment collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaboration is an important principle of the White Paper because it’s essentially about mutual benefit. There are just as many opportunities for our own industrial base.  But you really do have to seize the initiative on this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many of you think that our industrial policy is radically different from that of France. Well, perhaps it is. But I believe that collaboration will only evolve if it can be seen to bring benefits to both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I need your views and ideas on potential opportunities that you see would benefit UK plc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-offset-and-smes"&gt;Industrial offset and SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking about opportunities, I want to say a word here about the issue of offset, and how it impacts on British industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an issue that’s been raised with me on a number of occasions recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offset is a significant challenge to UK exporters, particularly SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while there is limited scope for Government to provide practical help, we will do what we can and work with industry to try and identify measures which help to ease the offset burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reverse of this was, as some of you will be aware, our Industrial Participation Policy which we comprehensively reviewed last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done in the lead up to the publication of the White Paper in February, and was undertaken in liaison with industry members from the UK Offset Strategy Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review factored in the changes that have been going on in the global offset market place in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the review has resulted in a new Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy which remains compatible with our obligations under EU law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this encourages our overseas based suppliers to continue investing in the UK’s defence and security sectors, and to extend opportunities for UK companies to become part of their supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means we will encourage our overseas based suppliers to engage with SMEs in these activities, as they did through our industrial participation policy. And the evidence so far is that they are more than willing to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies such as Boeing are engaging with hundreds of UK suppliers where SMEs are found at every level of the supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boeing has over 350 UK suppliers providing parts, services and technology to platforms such as the Chinook and 787. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="supply-chain-and-smes"&gt;Supply Chain and SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you’re all pretty aware by now that I’m a determined champion of SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are definitely the innovators of the Defence supply chain, and the life blood of any successful industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up more opportunities for them is one of the deliverables of the White Paper. And a key challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very heartened by the way some of the Primes are engaging with these smaller businesses in such a creative way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I visited General Dynamic in Wales where they have a dedicated technical facility known as The Edge, which searches out new ideas from across the supply chain and academia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just a couple of weeks ago I attended a ‘Meet The Technologist’ event at UKTI, a kind of speed dating event organised by Lockheed Martin who flew over some of their leading experts from the States to hook up with SMEs back here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rather telling that it’s Primes from overseas who seem to be energised when it comes to exploiting this innovation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder - is there any reason why our domestic primes don’t seem to be showing the same leadership and commitment? Perhaps they are - and they’re just not telling me about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is - and this is my challenge to you - that one of the ways I’ll be evaluating companies will be on the quality of their engagement with the SME supply chain, because to me that flag ups innovation and value for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find very interesting about many of these smaller companies is the way SMEs are increasingly establishing themselves by selling to the export market and then marketing themselves back here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re hungry, they’re aggressive and they’re not afraid to get out there and pitch for the business. It’s the key to success and I relish their enthusaism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked today about a new chapter for Defence. And about the challenges for industry in this new era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new era in which Defence is a tougher and more pragmatic customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And also a time when Defence will have to be a more informed and intelligent customer. And we’ve just been hearing about the changes needed to take forward the Materiel Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="total-support-force"&gt;Total Support Force&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing a lot more today about the nature of this challenge. And it will be very interesting to get the perspective of the Front Line Commands themselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course transformation and changing the way we do things also brings other opportunities for industry. And there’s one in particular that will now demand greater attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total Support Force - TSF - with contractors having a crucial role to play as part of a fully integrated force structure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re very keen that they’re involved at the earliest opportunity in Op Herrick drawdown and other capability regeneration plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD, in close liaison with Industry, has continued to build upon the success of Contractor Support to Operations. In fact, there are currently over 5,000 contractors directly supporting operations in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very encouraging that Industry is taking an active and positive role in the development of the Total Support Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The services, together with other areas of Defence, have been working to identify a number of identified a number of potential Total Support Force initiatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’re engaging with industry - directly, and through ADS -   in the work to decide what will be brought to market and how. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas under consideration include equipment support activities currently largely delivered by the REME, as well as some new ideas on airfield support activities, possibly allied to Project Future Brize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that balancing the books has not been easy. It has - quite rightly - been a forensic process and it has taken some time. It’s taken the SDSR, two planning rounds, a three month exercise and then some. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although I enjoyed the comment, the Daily Telegraph wasn’t quite right when it said that we had fed the 5000, cleared the Agean stable and solved the Schleswig-Holstein question all in a single day; it has actually taken two years.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to get Defence back onto a firm footing so that we could look to the future and get on with the job. And there is more work to do to ensure the footing is really secure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must also remember that the job of delivering military success on operations, which is , after all what Defence is all about. And which remains our number one priority. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the money, and how we use it, matters. As Chris Deverell’s presentation makes clear, only by looking after the bottom line can we make sure we’re achieving our real objective of looking after the front line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18765</id>
    <published>2012-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-05-01-helicopter-capability-industry-briefing-day"/>
    <title>2012/05/01 - Helicopter Capability Industry Briefing Day</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you, for that kind welcome from Paul and his team here in Yeovilton. [Paul Chivers CO Yeovilton]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thank you to [Kevin and] ADS for organising this event with Wayne’s team in the MOD. [Commodore Wayne Keble, Head of Air Littoral Manoeuvre Capability] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADS does a great job championing this sector, and playing an active role in both the Suppliers Forum as well as the SME Forum. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that ADS - and indeed many others here - have contributed to the Defence Rotary Wing Capability Study which you’ll be hearing more about later on from Wayne and his team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also most grateful to Agusta Westland, Rockwell Collins and Lockheed Martin for their kind sponsorship of today’s event - today wouldn’t be possible without you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally I would of course be speaking to you here today in a post PR12 world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very aware that many of you are waiting for this level of direction to inform your planning and decision making in the months ahead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s regrettable that our discussions today won’t be able to have that level of detail. I can assure you though that we are nearly there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is plenty to talk about when it comes to this sector. And I’m confident that our White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has provided clarity on MOD’s approach to acquisition and support. More about that later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="helicopter-availability-in-theatre---tribute-to-industry"&gt;Helicopter availability in theatre - tribute to industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago ‘helicopter availability’ was a pretty loaded term. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopters were very definitely a bad news story for defence -back in 2009 it seemed that barely a day went by without gloomy media headlines denouncing a lack of helicopters in Afghanistan, and claims that this shortage was undermining our operational effectiveness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years on and I’m delighted to say that we’re now looking at a very different picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Afghanistan earlier this year visiting Lashkhar Gar and Bastion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to travel on a range of helicopters, (including by the way an Osprey, if an Osprey is really a helicopter) to talk to the crews, and visit Joint Helicopter Force there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was impressed - and very heartened - by the availability and capability of UK airframes.  And this was also borne out by Commanders I spoke to on the ground.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work being done by the Chinooks responding to medical emergencies, for example, is just incredibly humbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the workhorses of the skies being flown by incredibly courageous crews. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we have enough of these vital assets performing at  an optimum level on a daily basis is - I believe - a testimony to the improved and effective partnership working of defence and industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week on the Terrace of the House of Commons I met members of the Royal Navy and RAF who had been involved in Op Ellamy over and near Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among them were the deck hands of HMS Ocean who got the Apache helicopters off and safely home - black helicopters on a black deck on a black night on a black sea.  Not an easy job with blades whirling, weapons loaded and adrenalin pumping. But what a job those Apaches did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their story really brought home to me once again just how critical rotary power is for our operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s delivering freedom of movement and logistic support, or providing close combat support and an evacuation capability.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability of our fleet to operate in these hostile and dangerous environments is - I believe - in very large part due to the hard work and commitment of the companies here in this room today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can still do more, and it is your technological innovation that is helping us to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you will be aware of the very successful cooperation between DSTL, Ferranti, Elbit and Agusta Westland to develop a product to help crews during brown-out landings, which remain one of the biggest risks to helicopter operations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that others are actively pursuing solutions in this area too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cooperative investigation has been very successful so far and I very much hope that we will be able to build on this research to provide our pilots with a solution in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industry-support-to-uors"&gt;Industry support to UORs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your responsiveness has been particularly striking on the UOR front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agusta Westland’s upgraded Lynx Mk9a has been a real success. We now have a vastly more capable airframe able to cope with the demanding environment of Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 helicopters delivered to the front line in just 18 months was an enormous achievement - and the now fully converted fleet is continuing to turn in a star performance in theatre with over 4,000 hours flown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked to some of the air crew in person when I was in Bastion. They raved about it. And they can’t wait for Wildcat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not all UORs are on this scale, but they are just as important - the kind of emergency practical stuff that’s so essential for keeping our fleet airworthy and effective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protective floor covering on Chinook and Merlin used on the Medical Emergency Response Team flights, for example, took just 10 weeks to be fitted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s 10 weeks, by the way, from initial concept and drawing board stage to deployment in theatre. A terrific achievement , and one that is helping ensure this life saving capability is maintained. A match indeed for Brunel’s mobile theatre for the Crimea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="rotary-wing-capability-study"&gt;Rotary Wing Capability Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotary power is an absolutely critical component of combat power. That’s why the Defence Rotary Wing Capability Study - or Derrick as I believe it’s known colloquially - is so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know the study was initiated by VCDS in the wake of the Strategic Defence and Security Review. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially the study has been looking at capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And taking a long hard look at issues such as basing, force structures, command and control - and of course military helicopter flying training from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, you’ll be hearing more about the conclusions and recommendations of the study from Wayne and his team today -  particularly on areas such as training and simulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that many of you here today will have been personally involved in the study so I’ve no doubt there will be a lot to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am confident that the study will help to provide industry with direction and clarity.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-white-paper"&gt;Defence White Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hope that our White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ also provides insight into how MOD sees the future, and the changes we need to make to ensure we have a balanced and affordable equipment programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, this means we’ll be adopting an Open Procurement policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means buying off the shelf wherever possible and when appropriate. Where we need technological advantage for security we will maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means collaboration with friends and allies wherever possible. The UK-France Defence Co-operation Treaty is a tangible example of that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a partnership which continues to mature and develop, and the consolidation of the Complex Weapons programme under MBDA is a demonstration that we’re definitely in this for the long term. And it’s a partnership that must bring benefit to both sides. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Procurement also means a commitment to opening up more MOD business to SMEs - organisations which bring innovation and agility to our equipment programme, and which are already winning a sizeable proportion of defence contracts. Changing technology makes this commitment ever more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies are already making an important contribution to this sector - I’m thinking here of companies like Wallop Defence Industries, involved in providing the flares we use to counter MANPADS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper has been described as ‘pragmatic’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is. It was meant to be and it has to be. We have to get the right solution for the Armed Forces at the best possible price for the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yes this means it’s sometimes better to do work outside of the UK - elements of the Puma life extension programme are being undertaken in Romania and France rather than on these shores. And actually that was a decision taken by the last government and one I am entirely comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why, for example, we took the decision to build our 14 new Chinooks on Boeing’s Philadelphia production line. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there are those of you in the audience that would have liked to have seen these built right here in Somerset. And you made a strong argument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I visited the Boeing factory last year I was left in no doubt that the scale of the operation already in place means that best value for money and lowest risk can only be delivered from there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the realities of Defence procurement in 2012. Of course I would love every penny Defence has to stay in the UK, but apart from anything else, if we want the world to buy our products and services - which we do - we have to be prepared to use theirs when it is right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="defence-industrial-engagement---and-the-defence-industrial-strategy-2005"&gt;Defence Industrial engagement - and the Defence Industrial Strategy (2005)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But has it not ever been so? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…it is important to be clear that we will continue to look to the vibrant and competitive global market place to satisfy our future helicopter requirement…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds rather 2012, white paper in the age of austerity, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it’s anything but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this text is lifted from page 94 of Lord Drayson’s 2005 Defence Industrial Strategy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DIS contained many commendable aspirations. Most of them were, however, unfunded, which meant it was always going to be something of a wish list - and certainly became one as economic realities unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it had a pretty clear and realistic position on helicopters reflected in the reality of Wildcats assembled just down the road in Yeovil, Pumas modified in mainland Europe and Chinooks being built in America. And, as I saw yesterday at RAF Benson, increasingly effective support for the Merlin fleet in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand you want clarity on industrial engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hope you’ll agree that actually when it comes to this sector, there has been an enduring policy in place for a number of years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see no enduring reason why a competitive British defence industry shouldn’t win business in this sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making you, the Defence industry, more competitive is a central theme of the White paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Government committed without reservation to building an environment conducive to responsible Defence exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s why we are doing so much to support the SME base, where innovation and flexibility offer us a dynamic that the Primes cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s why I have for the first time put a floor under the science budget, to ensure that as a nation we remain at the forefront of cutting edge, battle-winning technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper is realistic, but it is deliverable. And I firmly believe it should give you more - not less - confidence in the Department as we go forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="industrial-base---the-offset-issue"&gt;Industrial base - the offset issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And staying on the industrial theme, I want to say a word here about the issue of what was once known as industrial offset, and the challenge this poses for UK SMEs when exporting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an issue that’s been raised with me on a number of occasions recently - and quite seriously misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of you here will be aware, the MOD conducted a comprehensive review of our previous Industrial Participation policy last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done in the lead up to the publication of the White Paper in February, and was undertaken in liaison with industry members from the UK Offset Strategy Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review factored in the changes that have been going on in the global offset market place in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also acknowledged the challenges faced by UK exporters who are increasingly being asked to fulfil stringent offset obligations, particularly in new and emerging defence markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the review has resulted in a new Defence and Security Industrial Engagement Policy which remains compatible with our obligations under EU law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this encourages our overseas based suppliers to continue investing in the UK’s defence and security sectors, and extending opportunities for UK companies to become part of their supply chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also means we will encourage our overseas based suppliers to engage with SMEs in these activities. And the evidence so far is that they are more than willing to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Boeing are sourcing key components for the 14 new Chinooks from UK SMEs and will be basing through life support work in the UK - which will provide further opportunities through the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="looking-ahead---our-helicopter-fleet"&gt;Looking ahead - our helicopter fleet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSR clearly set out our long term plans for a helicopter fleet based on four core platforms from 2025 - the post Herrick era as I’ve heard it referred to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are already part of the rotary lexicon: Apache, Merlin, Chinook and Wildcat. I am pleased to say that we have recently secured the release to service for the first Wildcat to start Army training - I look forward to seeing this aircraft this afternoon. And we are looking at options to upgrade the Merlin Mk3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will still need Puma until the future changes can be made and that is why we committed to complete the Life Extension Plan in SDSR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that of course means that there is currently no medium term MOD requirement for a new UK developed airframe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are opportunities here in the civilian market and BIS are taking a very active role in helping the sector in that diversification process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year BIS announced £32 million of government investment in helicopter production, research and development which will provide an important boost to Agusta Westland, for instance in the introduction of the civil AW169 aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that, when it comes to future defence work, the opportunities for many of you here will lie in support and training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the Wildcat flying should sustain hundreds of engineering and technical jobs at Agusta Westland and here in Yeovilton over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And looking ahead there will be opportunities for industry to contribute to our Total Force Support concept which will include a sizeable number of contractors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know there’s more you can be doing when it comes to providing expert support on the ground - in fact this sector is already leading the way, with Vector Aerospace and Boeing UK deploying engineers in theatre doing vital work keeping our Chinooks airborne. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the best way to sustain jobs in the long term will be to widen your customer base. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why supporting exports is another principle of the White Paper, and why we’ve also appointed Susana Mason to co-ordinate exports on the MOD side. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re providing Ministerial support across Government for rotary wing opportunities - particularly the AW101 and AW159 Wildcat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are worldwide export opportunities for Wildcat, with specific interest from other Lynx operating nations such as Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the word pragmatic earlier on to describe our approach to making sure we have a balanced and affordable equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s an approach I would also commend to all of you in this sector as your companies plan and invest for the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, while defence here in the UK may be a shrinking market, there are plenty of other opportunities out there - in the civilian sector as well as overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversification will be the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve covered quite a lot of ground here this morning - and I hope I’ve addressed some of the issues that I know those of you here from industry have been seeking clarity on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18762</id>
    <published>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-28-editorial-intelligence-comment-conference-the-manufacturing-economy"/>
    <title>2012/03/28 - Editorial Intelligence Comment Conference ‘The Manufacturing Economy’</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an economist with a passion for engineering I welcome Editorial Intelligence’s initiative in organising today’s event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a truism but it needs to be said - especially by ministers. The role and contribution of manufacturing in today’s global economy is central to us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this morning’s session has centred on the producer’s view - the industry perspective - of the manufacturing economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the challenges and opportunities companies face in a globalised and technological age. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-manufacturing"&gt;The importance of manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you’ve also discussed the challenge of inspiring young people to get involved in production and manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I feel passionately about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply can’t understand the constant hand wringing in this country about the state of our manufacturing industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gloomy assertions that we don’t - and can’t - make anything any more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the endless claims that in any event the whole process of manufacturing somehow ‘doesn’t count’, and is irrelevant to our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes my blood boil, because all this unhelpful armchair criticism just doesn’t reflect the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if anyone here saw Evan Davies’s excellent TV programme last year on UK manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did a great job in exploding the urban myth that Britain is no longer an industrial nation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain - he correctly argued - could not actually survive without its vital manufacturing industries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is, in fact, still a manufacturing powerhouse with upwards of four million people still making everything from high-tech aircraft to supercars. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are people employed in a sector which is - in economic terms - twice as big as financial services. In fact, manufacturing accounts for half UK exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be talking later about the role of the defence industry in our manufacturing industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What concerns me about this endless talking ourselves down and the gloomy media headlines is that it all becomes something of a self fulfilling prophesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - worryingly - acts as a disincentive to young people who might otherwise consider working in industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a real problem. And I see it all the time in the defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a huge demand in this country for well qualified people with the right engineering, scientific and technical skills. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand is there - but the people aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are subjects which just haven’t been popular options in recent years. And of course there continues to be a noticeable lack of women working in these roles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons behind the recent decision to allow women to serve in Royal Navy submarines is the possibility that we can attract people from the widest pool of talent and skills into the Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies I deal with tell me that these skills shortages are having a direct impact on their growth and productivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got to take steps to reverse this process of decline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And make sure that being an engineer is an attractive proposition. And that it’s a career choice which carries the same status as being a doctor or a lawyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just an issue for Government or industry. The manufacturing sector matters to our wider economy, to our communities. And to our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, nurturing and developing this talent at an early stage is one particularly effective way of developing our skills base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOD runs a range of civilian craft and technician apprenticeships across the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Armed Forces as a whole are the largest providers of apprenticeships across the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BAE Systems, one of today’s sponsors, are particularly successful in this area when it comes to development. They are renowned for their huge pull through of apprenticeships to senior management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’re all in agreement that developing our skills base is going to be an essential driver of our economy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have also been talking this morning about the need for growth. And how innovation is central to this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here to talk about the manufacturing economy from the perspective of one of its major customers. The Ministry of Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be outlining some of the changes we’re making in our approach to buying equipment - in particular our commitment to making the MOD more accessible for SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about our determination to become a more intelligent and demanding customer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-defence-industry---a-vibrant-sector"&gt;The Defence industry - A vibrant sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defence industry is one of the UK’s most vibrant sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts speak for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an industry currently supporting around 300,000 jobs in this country - many of them in advanced engineering, an area in which this country has such a distinguished tradition and strong track record. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take aerospace for example - a great example of an R&amp;amp;D intensive, high tech industry with technological spin offs to the rest of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has the largest aerospace industry in Europe, and the second largest in the world after the USA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK aerospace has a turnover of £23 billion. Defence accounts for just over half of that - 52% to be precise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this country is the second largest defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of annual sales and a 22% share of the global market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, with the fourth biggest defence budget in the world, the Ministry of Defence is - even in these straitened times - a customer with a lot of spending power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a government department we are also a customer that is accountable to the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making sure defence has an equipment programme which is balanced and affordable is important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an age of both national and defence austerity it’s absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="materiel-strategy"&gt;Materiel Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this government inherited a Ministry of Defence with a gaping deficit - and an equipment programme in financial freefall. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programme based on the kind of fantasy budgets that I know many of you here from the corporate sector would find it pretty hard to countenance. Or even imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working hard to balance the books. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully it will not be long before we can announce our plans for PR12, and the equipment plan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting a grip of this gaping deficit - and we have - has meant, and will mean, driving forward change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It calls for a new mindset. And a very different approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means defence has to become a more intelligent and demanding customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means taking a long hard look at our processes, and the way we do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upping our game when it comes to having the right skills in areas like financial and project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it calls for significant changes in Defence Equipment and Support - DE&amp;amp;S as it is known - the organisation outside Bristol which heads up our acquisition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Materiel Strategy, as it’s being called, aims to transform DE&amp;amp;S. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure it has the relationships, structures, management and skills it needs to provide the right equipment to our Armed Forces. At the right time and at the right cost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have looked at a number of options and we have pretty well already ruled out the status quo. I have already said in public that there have been three options judged most appropriate for further consideration: Trading Fund, Executive Non-Departmental Body and a Government-Owned Contractor-Operated organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already have extensive experience of running Trading Funds - for example the Met Office and DSTL- and so the DE &amp;amp; S has now begun a soft market testing exercise to obtain further information from the private sector about the other options to help inform our decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just stress here that no decisions have yet been taken on this, although we intend to have a clear idea later this year on the best option to take forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper"&gt;White Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be changing our processes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re already changing our approach to acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s necessary for us - and it’s essential for industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s because the defence industry - any industry in fact -  has to be competitive if it’s to thrive in today’s global economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re making sure this change happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month we launched our White Paper - ‘National Security Through Technology’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plan of action for defence which commits us to adopting a new, open procurement approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, pretty much what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we’ll be seeking to fulfill defence requirements through open competition in the domestic and global market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means buying off the shelf if that represents the best value for money - which it often will. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why a competitive British defence industry shouldn’t win that business. Recent history - for example the Foxhound protected mobility vehicle or the Sea Ceptor missile system - shows it generally does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also thinking here of a company like Mabey Bridge Company, which is based in South Wales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mabey is a world leader when it comes to pre-fabricated bridge systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have won a number of contracts to supply logistic support bridging to our Forces in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when British Army engineers took on construction of a 140 tonne bridge to connect two Afghan communities in Helmand -  the biggest bridge our soldiers have built since World War 2 - it was Mabey who won the contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And “modified off the shelf” - buying a platform that’s freely available on the British or international market and then integrating it with, say, electronic counter measures or communication equipment here in the UK - ensures vital system skills are maintained in our domestic manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open procurement means actively looking for ways to collaborate, preferably bilaterally, with other countries because this will often offer economies of scale, and benefits such as longer production runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries such as the US, which is our major bilateral partner and where collaboration allows us access to cutting-edge research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course France with whom we’re now co-operating on a range of defence programmes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together the UK and France account for half of Europe’s defence expenditure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We led last year’s operations in Libya. And we’re now working to develop a Combined Joint Expeditionary Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both countries collaboration means our money goes further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means we can maintain a critical mass of demand for skills and industries we might otherwise lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - very importantly - it ensures we can operate our combined forces effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our open approach can best be summed up by the word ‘pragmatic’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that most certainly does not mean any compromise when it comes to this country’s national security and  capability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology at the heart of the equipment programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper puts Technology at the heart of our equipment programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of business, technological advantage - quite properly - means making money and increasing your market share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For defence it’s now absolutely crucial to our modus operandi, and  making sure we have operational advantage over potential adversaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to invest in technology to be able to meet an increasingly capable and diverse range of threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why it was so extraordinarily short sighted of the previous Government to more than halve the MOD’s Science and Technology budget between 1997 - 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m determined this process of decline is immediately stopped. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it has been. The proportion of spending on Science and Technology is now baselined at its current level of 1.2% of the overall defence budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment that’s around £400 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A commitment to technology and open procurement also means opening up defence to providers with agility, innovation and the ability to exploit new and emerging technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means making defence a lot more accessible to SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key principle of the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="smes"&gt;SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMEs are the lifeblood of any successful industry today. And it’s certainly the case in defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, when its agility and innovation we’re looking for - and that’s certainly been the case in recent years when it comes to getting urgent operational requirements out to our forces in Afghanistan - we have found its these smaller organisations which have proved time and again that they can - and will -  deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re determined to open up more of our business to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re already making progress on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, SMEs are currently winning 42% of MOD’s equipment contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In financial terms that’s around £1 billion of new business a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many more SMEs are contributing to defence and security programmes as sub contractors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening up our business of course also means that we have to be a lot more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means making sure - for example - that there’s an emphasis on open systems factored in to our requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And scope for these smaller companies to offer the kind of modular systems which enhance major weapons and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cde---helping-smes"&gt;CDE - helping SMEs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And making us more accessible of course also means that we need to make sure SMEs know about our requirements - and are able to put forward their ideas and make sure they’re properly assessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the Centre for Defence Enterprise - CDE - comes in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in Harwell it acts as an entry point for new science and technology providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And unlocks the potential of SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE gives practical help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By sending out themed calls for proposals on a range of issues, for example,  and organising ‘one to one’ surgeries providing guidance on how best to pitch an idea to the MOD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE cuts through a lot of the red tape which often seems to engulf an organisation as big as ours.  Companies can get advice from the CDE team in Harwell, submit their research proposal online and track its progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that proposal is generally assessed within 25 working days -although it can take as little as 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE was originally launched as a pilot scheme back in 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now time to take it to the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why yesterday I announced an expansion of its role -additional activities which will provide a dedicated focus to SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities such as market place events for SMEs to showcase their projects to defence primes and the venture capital investment community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open engagement events to increase awareness of opportunities within the defence industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a with a small dedicated team from CDE and our Defence, Equipment and Support organisation who will now act as mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be additional annual funding of up to £2 million through the Small Business Research Initiative - or SBRI as it’s more commonly known. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is money which will be directly used to progress successful CDE projects which show the most potential for defence purposes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s our commitment to sourcing these new providers, and opening up our business, which means that I was particularly intrigued to see that the next session will be debating the role of UK brands in the global market place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, of course, the whole issue of branding can be a bit misleading.  In the old days there was just one label: ‘Made in’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today that same product could probably have a number of different labels to show its provenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such as ‘designed in’; ‘manufactured in’ or ‘developed in’. The global supply chain is a complex one - and that’s as true for defence as any other industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could of course be argued that the individual UK Armed Forces are in themselves a brand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British Army. The Royal Navy. The Royal Air Force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say these names is to hear their power - as fighting forces and as names that inspire loyalty, affection, respect, trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s probably true that if they are using a particular piece of kit then that’s the kind of endorsement a lot of companies are very keen indeed to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However - the fact is that defence as a customer has no interest whatsoever in brands. We have no ‘brand awareness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just not a factor when we’re deciding what equipment to buy -and how to support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a proposal is innovative, sound and good value it makes no difference to us whether it comes from a household name. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or an up and coming SME. A behemoth or a brash upstart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not dazzled by shiny logos. And we’re not interested in flashy marketing campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not equate familiarity with excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brand - for us - is no substitute for a hard earned corporate reputation for project management, for example. That reputation could belong to an SME just as much as a Prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe me, when I visit our forces in Afghanistan the last thing they’re worried about is who made the equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they want to know is: “Does this work? Will it give me and the people I work with the right support and battle winning capability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us the value of manufacturing is about focusing on the end user. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about ‘who makes the equipment, or piece of kit?’ but rather ‘who will be using it’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Defence that answer will be - our servicemen and women. People whose lives will very often depend on it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, indeed, all of you whose liberty could depend on it too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18761</id>
    <published>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-27-cde-showcase"/>
    <title>2012/03/27 - CDE Showcase</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for that kind introduction Mark. [Mark Fulop, a Director in the DSTL programme office]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I greatly appreciate it and I’m delighted to be here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministers and politicians often start speeches saying something like that, but today I really, really mean it. I am genuinely delighted to be here, to celebrate CDE’s success and that of its clients - and to announce some changes that should make the organisation even more effective in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE is entering a new phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology’ has already announced that CDE will have an extended remit to cover the UK’s fast growing UK security sector, which is one of the most diverse and technically advanced in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’ll be talking about the organisations which are the real drivers of innovation for defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations which most benefit - indeed really need - the practical support and expertise of the CDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course these organisations are Small and Medium Enterprises, or SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE will be focusing a lot more on SMEs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical ways. Such as organising SME friendly events and engagement programmes. As well as undertaking a mentoring role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be additional funding available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be going into more detail on this later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking about the additional resources, and funding, CDE will get to deliver more support to SMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking around this morning’s exhibition I’ve again been struck by the range and inventiveness of the ideas on show, and I sometimes feel I’m in a parallel universe where the MoD can do no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the modular robotic systems by Robosynthesis, to the extraordinary e-textile developed by Intelligent Textiles which distributes electrical power and data without the need for cables -I’m pleased to see they’ve solved their connector problem from last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m told, by the way, it currently holds the Guinness World Record for being the world’s most advanced soldier system uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting our people is about making sure they are well equipped with these future battle winning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also about making sure we provide them with the very best medical care and rehabilitation support if they are injured in the line of duty. These will be of particular interest to my ministerial colleague Nick Harvey who is here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another important strand of CDE’s work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frazer-Nash adaptive bike on display here today is the prototype of a design, with the final version now in use and proving a huge success at Headley Court. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be able to see all this kit first hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on a personal level it’s also been a very welcome opportunity to meet the men and women who are the brains behind these innovative solutions to challenging questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are individuals who come from a range of backgrounds and disciplines, a number of whom had never had any contact with Defence until they started working with CDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s really important. I want CDE to reach out beyond the “usual suspects” to bring fresh thinking to Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they will all share, however, is a passion for innovation. And a determination to see their ideas developed and out there helping our Armed Forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all our exhibitors here today I’d just like to say ‘Thank you’ for bringing your ideas to Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your solutions are already making a vital contribution to our defence effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am determined we should not rest on our laurels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="role-and-value-of-cde"&gt;Role and value of CDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I want to talk about why the work of the CDE is so important. And about our plans to take it forward on to the next phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen today, Defence is a sector with a lot of potential for people and companies with a talent for invention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE unlocks that potential. It acts as the entry point for new science and technology providers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a hub and first point of contact for SMEs, academics and others who want to know how to pitch an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does the CDE add value for MOD?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer’s simple - it gives us reach into areas of fast moving technical innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an area such as maritime innovation, for example, which CDE launched as an open call at the end of January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE held a briefing on a range of technical challenges - from improving navigation capability of unmanned underwater vehicles to next generation submarine sensors and improving the security of data on submarines. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or how best to take forward new ISTAR solutions. Recent conflicts have shown us just how important this issue is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguarding our nation and our nation’s interest covers a huge spectrum of activity and effort. The work of CDE reflects that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nearly four years ago - May 2008 to be exact - since the CDE was launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was originally the brainchild of Paul Drayson - a former Minister for Defence Equipment under the previous Government.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to take this opportunity to pay tribute to Paul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an engineer and entrepreneur he had a deep rooted understanding of just how vital innovation was when it came to delivering cutting edge solutions for defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He played a major role in raising the profile of science and technology across the MOD. Although he must have been disappointed to see S&amp;amp;T fall as a share of MoD’s spending -  something I hope we’ve now put right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul was instrumental in the setting up of CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He knew that if Defence was to be able to exploit new and emerging technologies - which it had to, to meet the challenges it faced - the department would need to be proactively reaching out to people with the ideas.  The sort of people who very often weren’t aware that their ideas could help Defence..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do so it would need to be more accessible - and to be seen to be more accessible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Drayson was absolutely right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why the CDE was set up with three main aims:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To provide visibility of the MOD’s requirements &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To inform and support new supply networks &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And above all to widen the MOD’s supplier base&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think we would all agree that this is an organisation which has more than lived up to these founding principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch the CDE has established a reputation for reaching out across a very wide spectrum of the engineering and scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a dynamic hub, running open and themed calls on key sectors, as well as seminars and workshops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it holds regular surgeries - ‘one to ones’ - where individuals and companies can get personalised guidance on what the MoD is looking for, and practical help on how to pitch an idea to us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results show that this approach has worked - to date over 3,000 proposals have been received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research contracts awarded to date are worth a total of over £23.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today marks the award of the 500th contract - to ITSUS,  an SME based in Wales who I was talking to just before I came in here, which is working to improve network capacity for military operations where bandwidth is a scarce and valuable commodity. This is one of the Holy Grails of Defence - a really central challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract, worth £104,000, is on top of a previous £50,000 CDE contract. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ITSUS will be using the funds to look at how existing systems can be used more efficiently, and give our forces an enhanced tactical advantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing shortly from Jonathan Byrne. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan, as Head of CDE  I understand that you often advise companies when they’re pitching to MOD that they need to make sure their solutions focus on  ‘explicit deliverables’ and ‘compelling outputs’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend this practical and no-nonsense approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned that pretty well encapsulates the urgency and relevance of what we’re looking for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE successfully cuts through a lot of the red tape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in very practical ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies can get advice from the CDE team in Harwell, submit their research proposal online and track its progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also - and this is particularly important for SMEs - a proposal can be assessed in around 25 days, though on occasion it will take as little as 15 days. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDE demonstrates that Defence is open for business - and hungry for ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="white-paper---smes-and-boosting-the-role-of-cde"&gt;White Paper - SMEs and boosting the role of CDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I want to build on the significant achievements of the CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And see even more of these ideas and concepts becoming mature products which contribute to battle winning capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why boosting the role of CDE is one of the deliverables of our recent White Paper ‘National Security Through Technology.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Paper places technology at the heart of our Defence Equipment and Support effort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to. Exploiting new and emerging technologies is central to making sure our Armed Forces have the battle-winning capabilities they need. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the SMEs have the agility and innovation required to deliver these solutions. And at the best possible price for the taxpayer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rapidly changing technologies, we will often find solutions to our challenges not among the big beasts of the defence jungle, but among the smaller, more agile businesses that think quicker and react more immediately to change, challenge and opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why opening up more of our business to SMEs is another commitment from the White Paper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just because we agree with the wider governmental growth agenda. It’s because we in defence absolutely need SMEs to deliver our outputs. To solve our problems. To keep our people safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are making progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, SMEs are currently winning around 42% of MOD’s equipment contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In financial terms that’s around £1 billion of new business a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And many more SMEs are contributing to Defence and Security programmes as sub-contractors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is more we can do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, that is why we’ll be taking what we call an Open Procurement approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach will focus on ensuring there’s an emphasis on ‘open systems’ factored in to our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will mean there’s scope for SMEs to offer the kind of modular systems which enhance major weapons and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will also maximise the opportunities for SMEs at Prime and Sub-contract level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a focus on exportability across our equipment programme will open up new markets for your products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s essential that SMEs - whose issues are often very different from those of Primes - have their own platform within the defence industry to engage with the Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I have established a dedicated SME Forum which addresses the concerns of smaller companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chair these meetings personally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are a really useful way of getting together with industry to address the kind of challenges some of you here may be facing - on issues such as IPR for example. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify issues that MoD needs to address and which the SMEs themselves need to think about too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADS are members of the Forum and I know we’ll be hearing from you later on; Rees I look forward to that speech very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="taking-cde-to-the-next-level---smes-and-active-engagement"&gt;Taking CDE to the next level - SMES and active engagement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Championing SMEs requires us to go out of our way to encourage and champion greater pull through of innovative ideas into applications and contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why the White Paper highlights the need to - and I quote: ‘enhance the role of the CDE, such that it works more closely with the SMEs that it funds, including the facilitation of opportunities to engage with prime contractors to increase the likelihood of exploitation of the most innovative outputs.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means as I’ve already said, taking CDE to the next level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In broadening the reach of CDE to address both defence and security markets, as well as deepening its support to new entrants into the defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, in the words of the White Paper again, ‘enhancing exploitation mechanisms between CDE and our suppliers.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will do this with an active focus on SMEs, and on implementing an active “SME friendly” engagement programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three parts to this initiative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what they all boil down to is this - CDE will be focussing much more clearly on SMEs in its future work through a series of SME initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part one. I talked about CDE’s role as an entry point to Defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it also has another function - as a bridge linking the SMEs and the main defence suppliers, as well as investors and wider Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The added value CDE brings here is in facilitating networks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later this year CDE will be launching a series of market place events. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will be designed for SMEs to showcase their project outputs to Defence Primes; the venture capital investment community and innovation initiatives across government within other government departments such as the Technology Strategy Board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of this SME initiative will be the introduction of nine new ‘Open Engagement’ events to increase awareness of opportunities within the Defence research and development market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these will be working jointly with industry bodies and knowledge transfer networks, as well as specific industry sectors - such as Transport and Healthcare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, we’ve used Formula 1 technology, as you’ll probably know, in the latest of our armoured vehicles - the Foxhound -which we’ll soon be deploying in Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And part three of the SME initiative will involve CDE mentoring SMEs - in order to guide and help their approach to maximise opportunities for exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE will be a promoter - giving SMEs the opportunity to present their innovations to leading defence and other suppliers and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the MOD - in common with the rest of the public sector - is heavily constrained when it comes to resources, I have arranged that CDE and DE&amp;amp;S will each be bringing extra focus on supporting SME engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of CDE’s strengths is its fleetness of foot, born of a small, unbureaucratic structure. I don’t want this to change. But I do want to see CDE’s clients access the acquisition programmes of MoD much more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So both organisations, CDE and DE&amp;amp;S, will be devoting a handful of staff - probably four each - to this effort. They will be the Sherpas who help make good ideas real. Who ensure CDE’s clients can reach the summit of their ambition. And so help solve more of MoD’s equipment challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise roles and locations of the staff are yet to be decided, but my key message is that we are committed to SME engagement, we are already delivering against it and we’re going to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be hearing about all of this in more detail from Jonathan Byrne. Jonathan heads up CDE and he and his team will be taking this work forward in the months ahead. And I’ll be keeping a very close eye on it, so make it work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="funding"&gt;Funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also announce that there will be additional funding for the CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under present arrangements, the CDE, which is part of the Defence Science and Technology Laboratory, or DSTL as it’s more commonly known, is funded by the defence research programme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sum has also been boosted by another funding route - through the Technology Strategy Board’s support for the Small Business Research Initiative - or SBRI as it’s more commonly known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SBRI already provides funding of up to £1.5 million a year on Phase 1 - the innovation, or new ideas stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m pleased to be able to confirm that the SBRI will also now be providing additional funding to the CDE at the Phase 2 level. This funding will be up to a maximum of £2 million a year, to be used to  progress successful projects which show the most potential for Defence purposes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sum will complement MOD funding, and expands the work Defence can gain from our Science and Technology Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also enables the Technology Strategy Board to support more technology SMEs at vital times in their development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of Government departments working together for the good of UK business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And delivering innovation for our Armed Forces. And I’m very grateful to the TSB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also be exploring with my BIS colleagues how the good ideas brought to CDE that don’t neatly suit defence and security demands but have clear potential elsewhere in government or industry can be encouraged into reality too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cde-providing-greater-visibility-of-activity---and-contracts"&gt;CDE providing greater visibility of activity - and contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke earlier about visibility as a founding principle of the CDE when it came to the MOD providing clarity of our requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry across the board - Primes and SMEs - have now told us that they would welcome much more visibility as to who has been awarded which contract by CDE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have also requested more advance notice of CDE plans to issue themed calls so that they are able to plan ahead and be prepared. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies and organisations have told us this is important because it will allow all sectors to start scoping opportunities at an early stage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s what we’re going to do. CDE tell me that from today they will publish and maintain on their website their programme of events with a minimum 6 month horizon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from the autumn details of contract awards will also be accessible from the CDE website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this addresses the entirely reasonable concerns of industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDE started off as pilot scheme. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years on it’s a going concern - and about to enter an exciting new phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is a direct reflection of Defence as a vibrant sector here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a nation with the fourth largest defence budget in the world. And we’re the second largest Defence exporter in the world, with £6 billion of sales and 22% of the market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts, as they say, speak for themselves. Defence is most definitely a sector of opportunity. And especially innovative smaller businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.gov.uk,2005:AnnouncementPresenter/18759</id>
    <published>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/2012-03-21-franco-british-council-2012-defence-conference"/>
    <title>2012/03/21 - Franco-British Council 2012 Defence Conference</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="govspeak"&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je vous remercie pour l’opportunite d’assister a cette reunion du Conseil et d’avoir l’occasion de vous presenter une ou deux de mes pensees a propos de la cooperation franco-britannique dans le domaine de la defense. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je suis toujours enchantes de visiter Paris et je suis particulierement content d’etre ici dans un contexte pareil; le succes de notre cooperation en Libye, le succes du Sommet le mois dernier, l’arrive d’un nouveau Ambassadeur et surtout l’approfondissement rapide de la cooperation entre nos armees et dans le domaine des equipements depuis la signature du Traite en 2010 [deux mille dix].  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m delighted to be here in the year that the Franco-British Council celebrates its 40th Anniversary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an organisation which has grown in influence and stature over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a well established reputation for exploring the issues of the day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to see that Defence is recognised as an integral part of this ongoing dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I see you also have your own web page on the Franco-British Council site - [www.francobritishdefence.org] which acts as a really useful information hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to take this opportunity to thank the President D’Honneur, Madame Chairman and Council Members for their work in supporting - and promoting - this defence relationship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must also thank our Ambassador, (H.M. Ambassador Peter Ricketts) for so kindly hosting our conference. Given his previous role as our National Security Advisor, I am confident that deepening of our Franco-British Defence relationship will be a priority for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uk-france---the-importance-of-our-defence-relationship"&gt;UK-France - the importance of our Defence relationship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defence is central to the values the UK and France share. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about our Defence relationship, and why it is important to seize this historic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About why it is important to drive forward this process of collaboration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how we are doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let me start with looking at why co-operation makes sense for lots of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Excellency Bernard Emie, in a recent speech to the British defence community cited Professor Robert Tombs - the noted Cambridge academic - who I think summed it up pretty well. He said: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Franco British relations over the two centuries since Waterloo could be seen as a transformation from enmity to alliance and finally partnership…Today they are the only European states that maintain ambitions for a world role. Conceivably, both might prefer other partners, but in the world of the 2010s the reality is that we have only each other’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This eloquently defines the strategic necessity for our  bilateral relationship.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A partnership which makes sense because: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are both outward-looking nations, with experience and knowledge of almost every-part of the globe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We recognise we live a dangerous and uncertain world in which taking shelter behind some mythical Fortress Europe just isn’t an option&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We both understand the importance of a strong defence - not only to ensure that our territory is secure - but to contribute to international security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We invest in Defence and meet our NATO responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have battle winning capabilities and highly trained and effective Armed Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And crucially - we share the political will to act - and have the deployable defence capabilities to do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone who doubted that by the way only has to look at Libya. President Sarkozy was absolutely right when he described the UK and France as the ‘heavy lifters’ of European defence  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We share the same responsibilities on the international stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As permanent members of the UN Security Council - as nuclear powers -as leading members of the G8, the EU and NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a similar world view, we share the same geographic space, we are of similar size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With us there is no grand frere et petit frere - although the way our respective media portray our relationship you would think we are more like quarrelling siblings..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, this is a collaboration of logic and sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forces that pull us together are far more powerful than the forces that seek to drive us apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="libya-and-nato"&gt;Libya and NATO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya was a real turning point and an affirmation that forging a new and stronger partnership was the right thing to do.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libya campaign was assisted by operating in a NATO framework.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATO provided legitimacy, a Headquarters; as well as a common language and set of procedures.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is established, proven and based on shared values. It is a uniquely capable organisation as Libya - and indeed Afghanistan - have demonstrated.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need NATO to become stronger.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Libya showed us, there were a number of capability gaps which were highlighted by the Libya campaign.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We - the UK and France are now prioritising our joint work in light of lessons identified in areas such as Command and Control; Information Systems and targeting and reconnaissance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course across the Alliance it is ever more essential to ensure nations give priority those capabilities NATO needs. I commend the NATO Smart Defence Initiative. The UK is a keen supporter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="co-operation-in-austerity"&gt;Co-operation in Austerity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our economies and defence budgets are under pressure, the rationale for co-operation in these times of Defence austerity becomes ever stronger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense, for example, to develop our Combined Joint Expeditionary Force. We hope the CJEF will be up and running by 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French and British units and ships have been undertaking reciprocal training exercises as we continue to develop the new force. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m told our forces - like the true professionals they are - operate very well together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there does appear to be some friendly rivalry over who has the best ration packs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the UK, collaboration is an important principle of our approach to Defence equipment and support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an efficient way of delivering a balanced and affordable equipment programme. It means we can look to exploit economies of scale when it  comes to harmonising British and French requirements and sharing overhead costs.. It also helps to boost export opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows us to maximise our capabilities - particularly when it comes to sharing technologies, and it allows us to spread the cost - and the risk - of research and acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course in the case of the UK-France partnership all of these factors also support interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with France is not detrimental to our national sovereignty, provided that we retain operational advantage and freedom of action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our view is that it can help to consolidate our equipment programme and sustain aspects of our operational advantage and freedom of action.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we spend around 40% of the nation’s defence budget every year - a figure of around £13 billion - on equipment acquisition, support and technology.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By getting together we can make this money - and indeed both our budgets - go further.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we do have the spending power - together the UK and France account for around 50% of European spending on defence.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense for us to collaborate. Work together and plan together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we have to look ahead, horizon scan and develop capabilities to meet future challenges… &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why Research and Technology is an area where investment is absolutely key. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our commitment to an annual target of 50 million Euros each from the UK and France on joint research shows we’re serious about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in particular when it comes to critical technologies where the market, civil or defence, may not be sufficiently strong to meet UK and France defence needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be looking to industry to work with us on this - we need their expertise when it comes to identifying vulnerabilities. As well as spotting opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya and Afghanistan demonstrated the usefulness of Unmanned Air Systems, more commonly known as drones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month’s UK-France summit committed us to taking forward our planned cooperation on UAS.  In the longer term these will develop into unmanned combat air systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint funding and interdependence should help sustain industrial capability and deliver cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another programme is A400M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France is taking delivery of this transport aircraft in 2013 and we in the UK get ours in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re developing a common support plan - including spare parts for our future fleets of these aircraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK-France project is a mature cooperation between democratic nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore we can be open about areas of disagreement and where we have different agendas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the UK has preferred to look to NATO first and then the EU, whereas France has leaned towards the EU. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were delighted when France rejoined the NATO military structures in 2009 and became a full player in that vital organisation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been significant convergence between our national positions over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the French preparatory work for their next Livre Blanc shows a balance between multi-lateral engagement with the EU and NATO, and bilateral engagement with key partners such as the UK. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the publication of that document in the month after the elections will set the strategic direction for France on a whole range of issues.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bigger challenge for European nations is not should our forces work under NATO or the EU but how do we maintain capable forces? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will no doubt be the subject of some lively debate for those taking part in this morning’s workshop .    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="making-it-work"&gt;Making it Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK we have changed our institutional architecture to support the deepening of our bilateral relationship with France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our International Policy France team in the Ministry of Defence provides us with a central hub covering a range of activity - from equipment and procurement to political and military cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yesterday evening it was my pleasure to announce that the defence staff in our embassy here in Paris now have a new name: British Defence Staff-France.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a move which acknowledges the  increase in the Exchange and Liaison Footprint in France, as well as the Defence Section here in Paris. &lt;br&gt;
This is a highly symbolic move.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one other British Embassy across the world which has been accorded similar status, and that is our Defence presence in Washington - known as British Defence Staff - US.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new organisation recognises this change in dynamic and will be a ‘one shop’ stop, co-ordinating the expanding areas of activity and development across our partnership.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will include taking forward our portfolio of co-operative equipment programmes.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a significant move, and reflects the UK’s commitment to a partnership which is dynamic, and rapidly gathering pace.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill said that ‘difficulties mastered are opportunities won’.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that ethos is - I believe - what our defence relationship - is all about.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about working together on the challenges we face.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding and exploiting opportunities in more areas where we can work together in a smarter, more cost effective way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may always be differences in our styles or our methods.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is invariably true of any successful partnership.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These differences will often play to the particular strengths of each country. To the way we complement; balance and develop our defence capabilities.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is going to be very important - and what I know we can achieve - is harmonisation of approach. Three areas in particular are vital to ensuring that we work successfully together over the longer term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political commitment: we will continue to signal the importance that both Governments attach to the defence relationship;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-operation between our Armed Forces; a combined Joint Expeditionary Force is a sign of progress but co-operation needs to be embedded throughout the two organisations and in military doctrine;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joint investment in research and technology; this is essential in creating the future capabilities for fighting together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conference is a really useful chance to stocktake, challenge some of our assumptions and assess progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I for one am looking forward to ‘having my feet held to the fire’ this morning when I chair the  workshop which I see has the  slightly ominous title of ‘Franco-British Defence Co-operation: the balance sheet’.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. And now, the floor is yours - any questions?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
